<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between Town of East Hartford And CSEA Local 2001</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No. 2010-A-0800</p>
<p>Award Date: October 20, 2016.</p>
<h4 align="left">ISSUE</h4>
<p>Whether the Town of East Hartford violated the collective bargaining agreement when it suspended Mr. Sevetz. If so, what shall be the remedy?</p>
<h4 align="left">RELEVANT CONTRACT LANGUAGE</h4>
<p class="continued">3,8,a: Employees shall not be disciplined without just cause. The following shall be sufficient causes for reprimand, suspension, or discharge though such action may be for causes other than those enumerated:&hellip;2. Incompetence or inefficiency in the performance of the duties of the position to which the employee has been appointed.</p>
<h4 align="left">RELEVANT STATE BUILDING CODE SECTIONS</h4>
<p class="continued">R105.1 Required. Any owner or authorized agent who intends to construct, enlarge, alter, repair, move, demolish, or change the occupancy of a building or structure, or to erect, install, enlarge, alter, repair, remove, convert or replace any electrical, gas, mechanical, or plumbing system, the installation of which is regulated by this code, or to cause any work to be done, shall first make application to the building official and obtain the required permit.</p>
<p class="continued">R105.2 Work exempt from the permit&hellip;Plumbing: 1. The stopping of leaks in drains, water, soil, waste or vent pipe; provided, however, that if any concealed trap, drainpipe, water, soil, waste or vent pipe becomes defective and it becomes necessary to remove and replace the same with new material, such work shall be considered as new work and a permit shall be obtained and inspection made as provided in Sections R105 and R109 of this code.</p>
<p class="continued">R109.5 Notification of inspection results. Notification as to passage or failure, in whole or in part, of any required inspection shall be made in writing by the building official or by his duly authorized representative and shall be left at the job site or delivered to the permit holder. It shall be the duty of the permit holder to ascertain the results or required inspections.</p>
<h4 align="left">FACTS</h4>
<p>This arbitration concerns a suspension imposed by the town on its assistant building official Mark Sevetz in 2010. A five day suspension was imposed by the town's director of inspections and permits Bonnie Nichols citing various violations of the state building code. The contact's grievance procedure resulted in a reduction of the suspension to three days by the town's interim director of human resources Ronald Savitski on the basis of violations of R105.1 and R109.5. The contract's grievance procedure resulted in this proceeding upon the union's filing for arbitration.</p>
<p>The town determined that the grievant Sevetz failed to comply with R109.5 because he failed to provide written documentation of the results of an inspection that he conducted at 108 Herbert Drive in January 2010. The town personnel familiar with this grievance no longer work for the town and did not testify at the hearing. The town's records state that no written documentation was provided as required by the building code and the failure of the grievant's mobile printer at the site was not an adequate excuse due to other means of providing documentation. Grievant testified at the hearing that although he did not leave written documentation at the time of the inspection, he recalls mailing the results.</p>
<p>The town also determined that grievant failed to comply with R105.1 because he approved of underground plumbing work with no permit application or permit approval for the work. The work was done at 108 Herbert Drive in November 2009. The work consisted of the repair of an exposed and leaking sanitary sewer pipe. Grievant conceded that he approved of the work without a permit. Yet, grievant testified that he considered the work to be in the nature of a repair that does not require a permit for approval.</p>
<p>Grievant had a poor working relationship with Nichols. Grievant claims that his suspension was imposed by Nichols due to his bias toward him.</p>
<p>Grievant's employment history with the town prior to the suspension includes both discipline and public letters of commendation. Grievant was given a letter of reprimand regarding unprofessional conduct in October 2009. The discipline was prompted by a public complaint. Letters from two different homeowners were also sent to the town in 2007and 2009 thanking grievant for his work.</p>
<h4 align="left">POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</h4>
<p>The town maintains that the evidence including grievant's employment history supports the three day suspension. The union's bias claim is without merit.</p>
<p>The union maintains that the evidence does not support either code violation. Grievant was suspended due to Nichols' bias.</p>
<h4 align="left">DISCUSSION</h4>
<p>The language of the building code does support a violation of R109.5. The building code requires that notification of inspection results be left at the job site or delivered to the permit holder. It is conceded that grievant did not leave the notification at the job site. The building code does not authorize notification by mail. The building code addresses the responsibilities of the building official and requires delivery to the permit holder. The plain meaning of the word &ldquo;deliver&rdquo; required grievant to take and hand over the notification to the permit holder.</p>
<p>The language of the building code does not support the R105.1 violation. R105.1 requires a permit for repair work, yet, R105.2 provides for an exception in the event of stopping plumbing leaks. Grievant approved of the repair of an exposed and leaking sanitary sewer pipe. The grievant's assertion that a permit was not required for the repair is consistent with the building code exception.</p>
<p>The claim that grievant was suspended due to bias is without merit. Grievant claims that the suspension resulted due to Nichols' bias. Yet, the three day suspension at issue was imposed by Savitski. Savitski rejected two of the four building code violations found by Nichols and his ruling as to the remaining two violations is supported as to one of the violations.</p>
<p>The building code violation combined with grievant's prior written warning reasonably support a one day suspension.</p>
<h4 align="left">AWARD</h4>
<p>The Town of East Hartford violated the collective bargaining agreement when it suspended Mr. Sevetz. Mr. Sevetz' three day suspension is reduced to a one day suspension and he shall be made whole for the two day period restored..</p>
<h4 align="left">STATE BOARD OF MEDIATION AND ARBITRATION</h4>
<p class="continued">By: <fill character="baseline-rule" width="5"/></p>
<p class="continued">Thadd A. Gnocchi, Esq.</p>
<p class="continued">Panel Chair</p>
<p class="continued">Alternate Public Member</p>
<p class="continued">By: <fill character="baseline-rule" width="5"/></p>
<p class="continued">Raymond D. Shea</p>
<p class="continued">Labor Member</p>
<p class="continued">By: <fill character="baseline-rule" width="5"/></p>
<p class="continued">David A. Ryan</p>
<p class="continued">Management Member</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>