<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>Washington Hospital Center Employer and SEIU Local 722 Union</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case Number: FMCS 16-53482-A</p>
<p>December 12, 2016.</p>
<p>Stephen Crable, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>I. <i>STATEMENT OF THE CASE</i></b></h4>
<p>Washington Hospital Center (&ldquo;Employer&rdquo; or &ldquo;Hospital&rdquo;) terminated employee Malah Brima (&ldquo;Grievant&rdquo;) on August 20, 2015, for poor performance by failing to follow a work assignment directive from the Charge Nurse. SEIU Local 722 (&ldquo;Union&rdquo; or &ldquo;Local 722&rdquo;) timely grieved the termination pursuant to the applicable Collective Bargaining Agreement (&ldquo;Agreement&rdquo;) between the Employer and the Union. The parties processed the dispute to arbitration and utilized the offices of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service to select the undersigned Arbitrator to resolve the dispute. The Arbitrator held a hearing on September 16, 2016, in Washington, DC. During the hearing, both parties presented witnesses, offered exhibits and made arguments. A certified shorthand reporter transcribed the testimony at the hearing, and the parties submitted written briefs on November 11, 2016.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>II. <i>STATEMENT OF THE ISSUE</i></b></h4>
<p>Whether the Employer terminated the Grievant for just cause, and, if not what shall be the appropriate remedy?</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>III. <i>POSITION OF THE PARTIES</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. <i>Hospital</i></b></h4>
<p>The Hospital argues it terminated the Grievant for just cause pursuant to Section 3.1 and 3.2(a) of the Agreement. In the view of the Employer, it properly severed the Grievant's employment for poor performance and unauthorized absence from her work area when Grievant failed to follow a reasonable work directive. The Grievant's termination was appropriate because she was at the third and final step of progressive discipline, having previously received a formal written warning and, separately, a 3-day disciplinary suspension for performance problems like the problems that triggered her termination.</p>
<p>Under such circumstances, Section 3.2(a) of the Agreement outlines the progressive discipline process which the Hospital must follow. The progression includes only 3 steps: a written warning, a disciplinary suspension and termination. The Employer notes the Grievant had received, in the previous 18 months, a written warning and a three-day suspension for poor job performance and failure to follow instructions. On August 16, 2015, when Grievant repeatedly failed to follow proper job assignment instructions from the Charge Nurse and the Nursing Supervisor, the Hospital justifiably terminated her.</p>
<p>In supporting it decision to discharge the Grievant, the Hospital argues that the timing and description of events by the Charge Nurse and the Nursing Supervisor are credible and stand in sharp contrast to the confusing, contradictory and internally inconsistent testimony of the Grievant and fellow employee Ojeyinka. According to the testimony of the Charge Nurse and Nursing Supervisor, both long term employees of the Hospital, the Grievant ignored repeated directions to leave Unit 4F and to report to Unit 4NW. Despite 3 direct orders from either the Charge Nurse or the Nursing Supervisor, Grievant did not report to Unit 4NW for nearly 2 hours after first being directed to do so. And then, she only complied with the order when the Nursing Supervisor personally escorted her to Unit 4NW. Considering Grievant's previous discipline, the Hospital terminated the Grievant for just cause. Nothing in the confusing and contradictory testimony of the Union's witnesses effectively undermines the testimony of the Employer's witnesses.</p>
<p>The Hospital has the responsibility to ensure adequate patient care. Depending upon the availability of staff and competing patient care demands in various Hospital Units, the Central Staffing Office regularly reassigns staff from one Hospital Unit to a different Unit. The Staffing Office relies upon the Charge Nurse to implement any reassignments necessary. When the Central Staffing Office notified Grievant's Charge Nurse in Unit 4F of the need to send a Patient Care Tech to Unit 4NW, the Charge Nurse determined Grievant should &ldquo;float&rdquo; to Unit 4NW. The Charge Nurse made this assignment after consulting the list for &ldquo;floating&rdquo; on Unit 4F and finding Grievant's name was next on the list. The Hospital cannot allow individual employees to ignore a reassignment order or repeatedly drag their feet, as Grievant did in this case, without potentially jeopardizing patient care needs throughout the Hospital.</p>
<p>The Employer asserts that the Arbitrator has no authority to vary the progressive discipline steps contained in the Agreement. The clear, negotiated language of the Agreement and past practice establish that the 3 steps of progressive discipline in the Agreement are the only steps required. If the Arbitrator concludes the performance lapse(s) alleged by the Employer have occurred, the Agreement requires the Arbitrator to adhere to the 3-step progression. The Employer asserts the Arbitrator has no authority to substitute his judgment regarding the discipline penalty assessed by adding additional steps to the progressive discipline sequence once the charges have been proven.</p>
<p>The Hospital acknowledges that there is some precedent, in two limited circumstances, for varying the 3-step progression contained in the Agreement. If an employee is extremely senior, meaning 25-30 years of service, or there is a lengthy gap between the first two steps of progressive discipline and the third performance lapse, then the Employer may add an additional step in the process. In Grievant's case, she had a short record of employment and the performance lapse triggering her termination followed on the heels of Grievant's 3-day disciplinary suspension for job performance issues. Accordingly, there is no reason for the Arbitrator to exercise clemency and overturn the Grievant's termination.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. <i>UNION</i></b></h4>
<p>According to the Union, the Hospital did not have just cause under Sections 3.1 and 3.2 of the Agreement to terminate the Grievant. The Employer has the burden of proving the Grievant refused a work assignment, but the record evidence does not support this conclusion. The Union concedes that there may have been miscommunication, misperception, and a misunderstanding about Grievant's work assignment on August 16, 2015, but she did not intend to refuse the assignment. Grievant began her shift at 7:00 pm on August 16 working in Unit 4. Grievant completed her shift on the morning of August 17 working in Unit 4NW. Rather than refusing the assignment, as a point of fact, she actually accepted and performed the assignment given to her by the Charge Nurse.</p>
<p>The Union asserts the Grievant credibly described the considerable confusion over which employee should be assigned to Unit 4NW during the evening hours of August 16. Considering this confusion, Grievant asked for clarification from the Charge Nurse and Grievant took her 30-minute lunch break pending the clarification. The Union argues that the Charge Nurse held animus toward the Grievant, triggered by two instances during the early evening hours of August 16. In these two instances, the Charge Nurse believed Grievant improperly left or prolonged her absence from Unit 4. While the Hospital did not charge Grievant with improper absence from her duty station for either of these instances, these suspected absences colored the Charge Nurse's view of subsequent events on the evening of August 16. This unwarranted animus toward Grievant caused the Charge Nurse to overreact to Grievant's request for clarification of her work assignment. The Union concludes that Grievant's description of the timing and substance of events on August 16-17 is credible and supported by the statement and testimony of fellow employee Ojeyvinka. Ojeyvinka, a nurse at the Hospital, corroborated Grievant's version of events and should be credited because she had no reason to be untruthful.</p>
<p>The Union argues the Hospital's investigation of the circumstances surrounding Grievant's termination was a travesty and amounted to no investigation at all. The Grievant suggested to the investigating official for the Hospital that several employees could corroborate Grievant's version of events. The investigating official did not contact these employees, and took no other steps to determine what may have occurred on August 16. In effect, the investigating official had already made up her mind that Grievant should be terminated before the investigation even began. Had the Hospital conducted a fair investigation, it would have been forced to conclude that Grievant did not refuse a work assignment.</p>
<p>In light of the foregoing arguments, the Union requests that the Grievant be reinstated to her job with back pay. Alternatively, if the Arbitrator finds some basis for discipline, the Union argues that the Grievant simply should be returned to her job.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>IV. <i>RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF THE AGREEMENT</i></b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><b>2.1 Management Rights:</b> All management functions, rights and responsibilities which the Hospital has not modified or restricted by a specific provision of this Agreement are retained and vested exclusively in the Hospital. Such functions, rights and responsibilities of management include, but are not limited to, the right to make or change Hospital rules, regulations, policies and practices not inconsistent with the terms of the Agreement and to promulgate, modify, distribute and enforce reasonable rules of employee conduct and manuals of operating procedures&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>3.1 Causes for Discharge and/or Discipline:</b> The Hospital shall have the right to discharge, suspend or discipline any employee for just cause. Discipline will be administered within ten (10) working days of the date on which the immediate supervisor became aware &hellip; of the conduct upon which the discipline is based &hellip;. In the event of a suspension or discharge, the Hospital shall also provide the employee with a written notification of the reasons for the suspension or discharge within forty-eight (48) hours of the notification to the employee of the disciplinary action. Nothing in this 3.11 shall preclude the Hospital from utilizing (either at any stage of the grievance procedure or at arbitration) any evidence of misconduct other than given pursuant to this 3.1, provided, however, that all reasons for the disciplinary action taken against an employee shall be made known in writing to the Union no later than fifteen (15) calendar days prior to the scheduled date of arbitration.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>3.2(a) Progressive Discipline:</b> Except for offenses enumerated below or offenses constituting gross misconduct, the Hospital shall follow a system of progressive discipline as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">First offense: written warning</p>
<p class="continued">Second offense: suspension</p>
<p class="continued">Third offense: discharge</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Progressive discipline does not relate solely to each particular offense but includes progressive discipline for any combination of offenses. In other words, a second offense shall subject the employee to suspension, whether or not it is for the same offense as the first violation; similarly, a third offense shall subject the employee to discharge, whether or not it is for the same or a different offense as the first or second violations.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued">The Hospital shall not be required to follow a system of progressive discipline for any offense that constitutes gross misconduct or for any of the following offenses: &hellip; repeated refusal to follow a supervisor's reasonable instructions&hellip;.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued">A discharge, suspension or disciplinary action based upon any of the above enumerated conduct shall be subject to grievance and arbitration for the purpose of determining whether or not an employee actually committed the act cited or whether the punishment applied was appropriate in light of the facts of the case. The arbitrator shall not consider the failure of a patient, visitor or employee witness to appear at a hearing as prejudicial.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>10.2 Authority of the Arbitrator:</b> The arbitrator shall have the authority to apply the provisions of this Agreement and to render a decision on any grievance properly coming before him but he shall not have the authority to amend or modify the Agreement or to establish any terms or conditions of the Agreement. Further, he shall have the authority to apply and interpret the provisions of this Agreement only insofar as may be necessary to the determination of such grievance. Awards may or may not be retroactive, depending upon the determination of the equities of each case. In the event any arbitral award is issued providing for back wages or other retroactive relief, the employees involved shall never be entitled to an amount exceeding one-hundred fifty (150) days of pay or other retroactive relief, provided however that, with respect to a grievance concerning a termination, the 6-month limitation will not apply if the Hospital refuses to meet within ten business days of grievance filing or fails to respond to the grievance within ten (10) business days after such meeting. Arbitration awards are final and binding on both parties.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>V. <i>BACKGROUND</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. <i>Preliminary Considerations and Article 3 of the Agreement</i></b></h4>
<p>The Hospital is in the business of providing a full range of health care services for patients who have health care needs. The Hospital is a large employer, with approximately 1,900-2,000 associates who are represented by SEIU Local 722; 1,900 who are represented by the National Nurses United; and 2,500 associates who are unrepresented. The Employer has had a bargaining relationship with the SEIU since the late 1970's.</p>
<p>The parties have bargained over and included provisions in the Agreement limiting the Hospital's right to discipline employees. Article 3 of the Agreement permits the Employer to discharge, suspend or discipline an Employee only when the Hospital has just cause for the discipline assessed. Article 3.2(a) of the Agreement allows immediate termination of an Employee for acts of gross misconduct, but Article 3.2(a) also requires the Employer to use progressive discipline for lesser offenses. The 3-step sequence for progressive discipline contained in Article 3.2(a) are: Written Warning, Suspension, and Termination. According to a Hospital witness, an employee moves from one step of progressive discipline to the next step even if the alleged rules violation at each step are different in nature. However, a past disciplinary step can be removed from an employee's record after 18 months without an infraction.</p>
<p>Evidence introduced by the Hospital suggests the Hospital typically does not add disciplinary steps beyond the three steps listed in the Agreement. Kathleen Chapman, the Employer's Assistant Vice President of Human Resources, testified that the Hospital regularly follows this three-step discipline process and only varies the steps in two situations. The first exception is when the discipline involves an Employee with 25-30 years of tenure. The second exception is when the first two steps of discipline occurred very close in time, and then there was a long period of sustained improvement before another issue arose. For example, if two instances of tardiness occurred back-to-back and then 14 month of a clean record followed, the Employer would not necessarily terminate the third instance of tardiness.</p>
<p>On August 16, 2015, Grievant was scheduled to begin work in the 4F Unit at 7pm and end her shift at 7am on August 17, 2015. After the Grievant reported for work on August 16, the Hospital's evidence of what occurred differed substantially from the Union's evidence.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. <i>Hospital evidence concerning events of August 16-17.</i></b></h4>
<p>The Hospital's patient care services are divided into a series of departments and units. On August 16, 2015, Lisa McGuire was the Charge Nurse responsible for overseeing patient care in Unit 4F. She had been employed at the Hospital as a nurse for 33 years. She is member of the union representing the Hospital's nurses, and she is not a member of the Employer management team. As the Charge Nurse, McGuire was responsible for the smooth operation of the entire Unit, including handling patient transfers, helping with emergencies on the Unit, and assigning work responsibilities to nurses and PCT staff. As patients were admitted to Unit 4F, McGuire assigned the patients to one of the multiple nurses who worked in the Unit. She also assigned Patient Care Technicians to groups of rooms to assist the nurses caring for the patients in those rooms. While most of the nurses in the Unit were assigned 5 patients, McGuire typically had only two patients considering her additional responsibilities as the Charge Nurse.</p>
<p>On August 16, 2015, McGuire was the Charge Nurse responsible for assigning Grievant work. McGuire initially assigned Grievant to assist nurses with the 16 patients in the front rooms of the Unit. McGuire assigned the Unit's other PCT, who was named Maria, to the patients in the back rooms of the Unit. According to McGuire, the first situation involving the Grievant that caused McGuire concern occurred about 9:00 pm. A patient was being discharged from the Unit to go home, and the patient's family called the Unit and spoke to Ms. McGuire about check-out procedures. The family said that they were about five minutes away from the Hospital, and the family asked if the patient could be brought to the front door of the Hospital. Since the patient was in one of the rooms assigned to the Grievant, McGuire asked Grievant to take the patient to the front door of the Hospital for pick-up. Grievant left the Unit with the patient at 9:10 pm. McGuire noted the time because of past instances, previously discussed with Grievant, when the Grievant left the Unit and did not return for lengthy periods. When Grievant had not returned to the Unit by 9:50 pm, McGuire called Grievant's cell phone to ask her to return to the Unit. Grievant returned about five minutes later, but she again disappeared from the Unit around 10:00 pm. On this occasion, McGuire s looked for Grievant and found her talking with co-workers on Unit 4E. McGuire knew that Grievant had no work responsibilities on Unit 4E, and she instructed Grievant to return to Unit 4F.</p>
<p>Around 11:30 pm, Ms. McGuire received a call from the Hospital's Staffing Office telling her that the Unit's resources were being re-allocated and that McGuire needed to send a PCT to Unit 4NW. The Hospital Staffing Office is responsible for coordinating nurse and PCT coverage on the various Units and making certain that patient care needs throughout the Hospital are met by the Hospital's nursing and PCT staff. On a day-to-day basis, Charge Nurses coordinate with the Staffing Office about their Unit's staffing and patient status. In situations of staffing imbalance, irrespective of the reason, the Staffing Office re-balances the staffing among Units by sending an employee from one Unit to another. That process was called &ldquo;floating&rdquo; to a different Unit. Floating or staff rebalancing occurred frequently enough that there was a formal procedure in place for determining which particular PCT or nurse would be selected to float. Each Unit maintains a book which tracks floating, and the Charge Nurse assigns the PCT or nurse on the list whose turn is next up.</p>
<p>When Charge Nurse McGuire checked the float list in Unit 4F on August 16, she determined that it was Grievant's turn to float. McGuire found Grievant in the Unit's nursing station no later than 11:45 pm and explained to her that she needed to float to Unit 4NW. According to McGuire, Grievant seemed upset by and grumbled about the assignment. Grievant asked if she could take her lunch break before going to 4NW, and McGuire agreed. Lunch breaks are 30 minutes, so Ms. McGuire expected Grievant toreport to 4NW by about 12:15 am.</p>
<p>At 12:30 am on August 17, the Charge Nurse from Unit 4NW called Charge Nurse McGuire and reported that the floating PCT had not arrived in 4NW. Ms. McGuire explained that she had made the assignment and that the PCT should already be in Unit 4NW. McGuire hung up the telephone and went looking for Grievant, but McGuire could not find her in the Unit. About 30 minutes later, at approximately 1:00 am, McGuire saw Grievant in the nurse's station in 4F. McGuire asked Grievant why she had not yet reported to Unit 4NW. Grievant ignored McGuire and walked past her to a nearby conference room. When McGuire continued to ask why Grievant had not reported to 4NW, Grievant would not answer her and would not make eye contact with McGuire.</p>
<p>McGuire next contacted Nursing Supervisor Gina Morales for assistance. McGuire explained the situation to Morales. Morales, who was one of 4 nursing supervisors on duty for the entire Hospital, arrived at Unit 4F approximately five minutes later and went to the conference room in Unit 4F. Grievant was still in the conference room, not doing any work, when Ms. Morales entered the room. Morales introduced herself and explained that she was there because she had received a report that Grievant was ignoring an assignment by Charge Nurse McGuire to float to Unit 4NW. In response, Grievant complained about a past experience in floating to 4NW when all the work fell to her since the shift had already started. Morales reiterated that Grievant was expected to float and that she needed to do so. Morales suggested that Grievant could tell the Charge Nurse at 4NW about her concerns related to the last time she floated, but Morales told Grievant she could not ignore McGuire's assignment to 4NW. Morales then left the conference room after directing the Grievant to report to Unit 4NW. Morales testified that there was another nurse in the conference room but the nurse did not participate in the conversation between Morales and the Grievant. After talking to the Grievant, Morales joined McGuire in the nursing station where they discussed other issues related to Unit 4F. After 5 minutes passed and Grievant had not left the conference room, Morales re-entered the conference room and said, &ldquo;You're going over to 4NW now, correct?&rdquo; and physically escorted the Grievant part of the way to Unit 4NW. Grievant arrived at Unit 4NW between 1:30 and 2:00 am on August 17.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>C. <i>Union evidence concerning events of August 16-17.</i></b></h4>
<p>The Union's evidence consisted of the Grievant's testimony supplemented by the testimony of Nurse Ojeyinka. Per the Grievant, two PCT's normally are scheduled in Unit 4F. On August 16, Grievant was one of the PCT's and Maria (last name not identified) was the other PCT. Grievant was assigned to work the front half of the Unit and Maria was assigned to the back half of the Unit. Grievant was responsible for approximately 16 patients. In addition to the Grievant and Maria, another PCT, Ms. Carlene Martin-Thomas, was assigned on the Unit as a sitter. A sitter is a PCT who sits in the room with a patient having specific health care concerns.</p>
<p>At some point during her shift, Grievant was informed that she may have to relieve Ms. Martin Thomas as a sitter for her break. The 4NW unit was understaffed and had requested from the Nursing office that a PCT be sent to their unit. Subsequently, Charge Nurse McGuire requested Grievant to report to the Unit 4NW. Although Grievant was uncertain of the time this request occurred, she indicated that it might have been as early as 11:00 pm. Grievant questioned McGuire about the assignment and requested McGuire to check the assignment book to see if she was the PCT to be floated to another Unit.</p>
<p>After Charge Nurse McGuire confirmed the assignment, Grievant asked McGuire if Grievant could complete her break of thirty minutes (30) before reporting to 4NW. McGuire later approached Grievant to determine if Grievant had finished her break and to question why Grievant had not reported to the 4NW Unit. A short time after McGuire's inquiry, Nursing Supervisor Morales contacted Grievant, instructed Grievant to finish what she was doing, and directed her to report to 4NW. Grievant subsequently reported to the 4NW Unit.</p>
<p>In addition to the Grievant's testimony, nurse Ojevinka testified that she was present in the conference room on August 16-17 for the conversation between Morales and the Grievant. At Grievant's request, Ojevinka gave Grievant an undated written statement composed sometime after August 17. In the written statement and her testimony Ojevinka asserted that Nursing Supervisor Morales spoke twice with the Grievant after 1:07 am on August 17. In Ojevinka's written statement she quoted Morales as saying &ldquo;I am sorry for the misunderstanding and miscommunication about you floating tonight but take your time, when you finished what you are doing here then you can go to floor.&rdquo; Ojevinka testified Morales returned to the conference room minutes later and said, &ldquo;Come on sunshine let's go&rdquo;. Grievant then left the room, accompanied by Morales.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>D. <i>Investigation and Termination of Grievant</i></b></h4>
<p>After Charge Nurse McGuire finished her shift on August 17, she sent an e-mail to Nursing Director Claudette LaMothe describing the problems she had experienced with Grievant on August 16 and 17. As Nursing Director, LaMothe had 24-hour responsibility for nursing operations in her Units., and her duties include hiring employees, ensuring patient safety and administering coaching/discipline for employees in her units. LaMothe supervised Grievant for more than four years, having spoken with Grievant on a number of occasions about various performance concerns, including Grievant's Written Warning and Suspension Notice.</p>
<p>LaMothe responded to the email from Charge Nurse McGuire by contacting both McGuire and Nursing Supervisor Gina Morales to obtain additional information and to understand the events reported in McGuire's email. LaMothe was particularly concerned by the report because of the possible impact on patient care that Grievant's actions might have caused. LaMothe also reviewed Grievant's personnel file, and she was reminded of the two prior disciplinary steps (a written warning and a suspension) that were still active. Absent an acceptable explanation by the Grievant, LaMothe knew that the next step of the discipline process could be termination of employment.</p>
<p>On August 20, 2016, LaMothe called the Grievant to her office. LaMothe offered the Grievant the opportunity to contact the Union. Although LaMothe and the Grievant gave differing accounts of this offer and the events that followed, both testified that Grievant agreed to proceed without a Union representative rather than delay the meeting. Grievant explained she had travel plans the following day and wanted to continue with the investigation that day. LaMothe began the meeting by reading the charges against her and asked Grievant for her comment.</p>
<p>Grievant asserted that the problem began when she first arrived for her shift at 7:00 pm. The other PCT on the shift, Maria, told Grievant that she, that is Maria, was going to be assigned to sit with a patient that day but that the sitter assignment did not happen because an ICU PCT from a different unit was covering the assignment. Grievant acknowledged that Charge Nurse McGuire told Grievant to float to Unit 4NW, but, in the Grievant's opinion, it was more appropriate for McGuire to move the ICU PCT to 4NW rather than assign Grievant to float to 4NW. When asked about the instructions that she had received from McGuire and Nursing Supervisor Morales, Grievant confirmed that she had been told by both McGuire and Morales to float to Unit 4NW. Although McGuire had given her permission to take her lunch break before going to 4NW, Grievant stated she had not gone to 4NW. She admitted she did not go there until Morales twice told her to do so. Grievant recalled she did not arrive at Unit 4NW until 2:00 am. Grievant claimed that Maria could confirm some of her statements, but Grievant did not mention that nurse Ojevinka was a witness to part of the conversation between Grievant and Morales.</p>
<p>After listening to Grievant's version of events, LaMothe concluded that there was no need for additional investigation since the Grievant did not deny having repeatedly refused to follow the reasonable instructions of two supervisors concerning their assignment that she float to 4NW. In view of Grievant's prior steps of progressive discipline, LaMothe concluded Grievant should be terminated for poor performance and unauthorized absence from a work area. LaMothe gave Grievant a termination notice and offered Grievant the chance to include her version of events in the notice. Grievant declined.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>VI. <i>DISCUSSION AND OPINION</i></b></h4>
<p>Despite numerous contradictions, inconsistencies and variations between the testimony of the Grievant regarding the events of August 16-17 and the testimony of Company witnesses McGuire and Morales regarding the same events, most of these inconsistencies and contradictions are irrelevant to the decision in this case.</p>
<p>The following facts are largely undisputed and drawn from the testimony of all three of these witnesses. On August 16, 2015, between 11:00 pm (according to the Grievant) and 11:45 pm (according to McGuire), Charge Nurse McGuire assigned Grievant to float to Unit 4NW. Grievant understood the assignment, but she was unhappy with the assignment. She questioned the assignment because she believed another PCT should cover the work. The Grievant ultimately reported to Unit 4NW between 1:30 and 2:00 am on August 17. During this 2-3 hour window, Grievant permissibly took a 30-minute lunch break, but there is no evidence of any other authorized work she completed during this window.</p>
<p>What the record does show is that the following events occurred between 11:00 pm and 2:00 am on August 16 and 17: Charge Nurse McGuire directed Grievant to report to 4NW multiple times. Grievant did not report to 4NW and questioned the assignment. McGuire checked the floating list, confirmed Grievant was the next PSC to float. McGuire ordered Grievant to report to 4NW about 11:45 pm, but she did authorize Grievant to take 30-minute lunch break before she reported to 4NW. After her lunch break, Grievant did not report to 4NW. The Charge Nurse in 4NW called Charge Nurse McGuire about 12:30 am and told McGuire that no PSC had arrived in 4NW. McGuire checked the Unit 4F and could not find Grievant in Unit 4F either. Later, sometime before 1:00 am, Charge Nurse McGuire found that Grievant had returned to Unit 4F. McGuire approached Grievant to learn why Grievant was still in 4F rather than 4NW. The Grievant ignored McGuire. In response to Grievant's actions, McGuire called Nursing Supervisor Morales for assistance. Morales promptly came to the Unit, met with Grievant in a conference room, instructed her to report to Unit 4NW, and left the conference room. Morales returned to the conference room about 5 minutes later when Grievant did not leave Unit 4F. Nursing Supervisor Morales again ordered Grievant to report to Unit 4NW. Grievant finally complied with the order but not before Morales escorted Grievant part of the way to Unit 4NW.</p>
<p>Article 3.2(a) of the Agreement allows immediate termination of an Employee for acts of gross misconduct, but Article 3.2(a) requires the Employer to utilize progressive discipline for lesser offenses. Rather than treating Grievant's conduct as insubordination and charging her with gross misconduct under the Agreement, the Hospital handled the Grievant's conduct as a progressive discipline offense. Ultimately, the Hospital charged Grievant with, and terminated her for, poor performance in failing to follow a reasonable work directive and unauthorized absence from her work area.</p>
<p>Article 3.2(a) establishes a three-step progression for discipline: Written Warning, Suspension, Termination. As of August 2015, Grievant had two active disciplines in her personnel file. The first was a Written Warning for failing to follow a nurse's instruction about taking vital signs from a patient and for insubordination when the Grievant confronted the nurse over Grievant's failure to follow instructions. The second discipline was a Three-Day Suspension for failing to provide patient care as instructed by the nursing staff. Those disciplinary measures moved Grievant to the third step of the progressive discipline process, which meant she could be terminated for any further infractions.</p>
<p>Based on the facts as summarized above, the Grievant repeatedly resisted and ignored a reasonable work assignment to Unit 4NW. She also absented herself from 4NW, without authorization, for an hour to an hour and a half. Even if Grievant initially believed that the work assignment was not proper, no later than 11:45 she understood that the assignment was proper. Yet it required at least 4 directives from a Charge Nurse and a Nursing Supervisor, took approximately 2 hours or longer, and required a personal escort before she complied with the work assignment. These actions clearly warranted discipline. Given that Grievant already had an active written warning and a disciplinary suspension on her record, the Employer acted properly when it terminated the Grievant for these most recent incidents of poor performance.</p>
<p>The Union argues that since the Grievant ultimately reported to Unit 4NW, the Employer failed to prove the Grievant refused the work assignment. If this were a gross misconduct/insubordination case, the Union's assertion might be true. It is not. Grievant's behavior in passively resisting the assignment and requiring the repeated intervention of the Charge Nurse and the Nursing Supervisor to effectuate a simple job reassignment is not acceptable conduct by the Grievant. The Hospital terminated the Grievant for poor performance and unauthorized absence from her work area. The record supports the charges against Grievant and termination was the proper step under the progressive discipline provisions of the Agreement.</p>
<p>The Union also argues that the Arbitrator is not limited to the 3 discipline steps outlined in the Agreement and could add another step, in effect, another suspension or a &ldquo;last chance&rdquo; reinstatement even if the Employer proved its case. The Hospital vigorously argues that adding steps to the progressive discipline process is beyond the Arbitrator's jurisdiction. The Arbitrator need not resolve this disagreement. Assuming arguendo that the Arbitrator had jurisdiction to add an additional step, the facts of this case do not warrant a different result. Grievant had a relatively short employment history and 3 disciplinary events in under 18 months. Moreover, none of the considerations that the Hospital concedes might warrant an additional step in the disciplinary progression are present in this case.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>VII. <i>AWARD</i></b></h4>
<p>The Company terminated the Grievant for just cause. The grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>