<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between: CENTURYLINK, Company, and CWA, LOCAL 6300, Union.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Grievant: Kevin Clemens FMCS&num; 16-00696-8</p>
<p>September 29, 2016.</p>
<p>George L. Fitzsimmons, J.D., NAA, Arbitrator</p>
<table width="585" columns="1">
<caption><i>TABLE OF CONTENTS</i></caption>
<tr>
<td width="5%"><p></p></td>
<td width="5%"><p></p></td>
<td width="80%"><p></p></td>
<td width="10%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>I.</p></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>BACKGROUND <fill/></p></td>
<td align="right" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>II.</p></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>ISSUE <fill/></p></td>
<td align="right" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>II.</p></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>RELEVANT DOCUMENTS <fill/></p></td>
<td align="right" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>IV.</p></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>SUMMARY POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES <fill/></p></td>
<td align="right" valign="top"><p>4</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>A.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>COMPANY <fill/></p></td>
<td align="right" valign="top"><p>4</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>B.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>UNION <fill/></p></td>
<td align="right" valign="top"><p>5</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>V.</p></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE <fill/></p></td>
<td align="right" valign="top"><p>5</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>VI.</p></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>DISCUSSION AND DECISION <fill/></p></td>
<td align="right" valign="top"><p>10</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>VII.</p></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>AWARD <fill/></p></td>
<td align="right" valign="top"><p>17</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>I. BACKGROUND</b></i></h4>
<p>CenturyLink (hereinafter &ldquo;Company&rdquo;) is a provider of high speed internet, phone and television services. The CWA, Local 6300 (hereinafter &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) represents bargaining unit members including Grievant Kevin Clemens. The Company and Union entered into a Collective Bargaining Agreement (hereinafter &ldquo;Contract&rdquo;) which was in full force and effect at all relevant times herein (Jt. Ex. 1). This dispute herein involves a contract interpretation issue related to a retroactive pay dispute. Grievant Kevin Clemens filed the grievance herein (Jt.Ex.2). The parties stipulated that there were no procedural questions and the grievance were properly before Arbitrator Fitzsimmons for decision.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>II. ISSUES</b></i></h4>
<p>Was Grievant entitled to full retroactive pay from March 14, 2014 until his voluntary termination on December 19, 2014 since the Contract was not ratified until March 17, 2015? If so, what shall be the remedy?</p>
<p>Does the grievance filed herein apply to all bargaining unit member or only Grievant Kevin Clemens?</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>III. RELEVANT CONTRACT PROVISIONS</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 21</h4>
<h4 align="center">MANAGEMENT RESPONSIBILITY</h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">21.1 <i>Management Responsibility</i>. It is the exclusive responsibility of the Company to manage the business and direct the work force except where expressly and specifically modified, limited, or restricted by the provisions of this Agreement. This shall include, but not be limited to, determining the size of the work force and the number of employees needed at any particular time or place; using improved methods, material or equipment; determining work assignments and tours; developing and administering work standards and performance requirements; and being the sole judge of the quality and acceptability of communications services rendered to the public. All other customary management rights shall be reserved solely by the Company. (Jt.Ex.1).</p>
<p class="continued">2.2 <i>Classifications of Employees</i>. Employees &ndash; Whenever the term &ldquo;employee&rdquo; appears in this Agreement, it shall be construed to mean a regular full-time employee.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Definitions:</p>
<p class="continued">2.2.1 Full-time employee &ndash; A person who is normally scheduled to work forty (40) hours a week. (Jt.Ex.1).</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 3</h4>
<h4 align="center">GRIEVANCES</h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">3.1 A grievance shall be a complaint, question, or controversy by any employee or group of employees or by an authorized Union representative, with respect to the interpretation or application of any provision of this Agreement. No grievance shall be eligible for handling hereunder unless filed in compliance with Section 3.2 and within the time limits and according to the procedures established in Section 3.4. Grievances not so presented or processed shall be considered waived by the Union.</p>
<p class="continued">3.2 Each grievance shall briefly describe in substance the specific matters complained of in sufficient detail that dates, time(s) if pertinent, occurrences, and the nature of the circumstances causing the grievance can be identified readily. The names and locations of employees concerned shall also be given where the grievance relates to specific employees as opposed to a general complaint. There shall also be a statement as to the specific section(s) of this Agreement believed to have been violated or misinterpreted and the desired remedy. (Jt.Ex.1).</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>IV. SUMMARY POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b><i>A. Company</i></b></h4>
<p>That the grievance filed herein was filed as an individual grievance on behalf of Kevin Clemens.</p>
<p>That Grievant retired on December 19, 2014 and was no longer an employee of the Company when the Contract was ratified on March 17, 2015.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>B. Union</b></i></h4>
<p>That the grievance filed herein was a Class grievance filed on behalf of all union members. That the Company violated the Contract when it failed to pay a retroactive wage increase based on all hours worked in 2014.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>V. SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE</b></i></h4>
<p><i>Jason Vellmer</i> testified he is a Staff Representative for the Union. He was involved in negotiating the current Contract. (Jt.Ex.1, T.17,18). He served on the Union bargaining committee with Edgar McCarter and Josh Heuser. He took notes during negotiations. (Union Ex.1). Edgar McCarter also took notes. (Union Ex.2). These notes included the fact that the Union was negotiating for retroactive pay increases for all hours worked when the Contract eventually became ratified. (T.18-20). The Company only brought up the issue of retroactive pay being limited to a forty hour week after the Contract was ratified. On April 2, 2015 he emailed Dan Groninger, who chaired the Company's bargaining committee, to verify the retroactive pay. (T.20; Union Ex.3). Groninger responded on April 6, 2015 that &ldquo;retro pay will be based on 40 hours a week.&rdquo; (T.21). In McCarter's notes dated May 19-20, 2014, it states: &ldquo;Retroactivity removed if not adopted by August 29, 2014.&rdquo; (T.22,23). The Company always understood the Union position of full retroactive pay. McCarter's notes of bargaining on October 21, 2014 state: &ldquo;Ensure retroactivity on wage of ratification of Contract.&rdquo;</p>
<p><i>Lois Grimes-Patow</i> testified she is now retired from the Union but previously served as Administrative Director of the Union's office in Washington, D.C. (T.37,38). She coordinated work with local unions including the Union herein. (T.38). On this Contract she was not involved in bargaining itself but on oversight of the bargaining process. Her role was to ensure that national bargaining demands were addressed in all contract negotiations. Jason Velhner was bargaining the Contract herein and she discussed the proposals frequently with him during the process. He called her after the Union voted down the Contract for a second time. She spoke to Company Director of Labor Relations, Bill Stubbs, in January 2015 to find out why contract ratifications failed. Stubbs told her that retroactive pay may be a problem because the Contract was not ratified before the end of 2014. She did not reach any agreement with the Company because she had no authority to do so. (T.38-45). The negotiations were difficult because it involved five different local Unions over a large geographical area. She spoke to Stubbs again in early February, 2015 and advised him that retroactive pay was very important to the Union and needed to be further addressed with Jason Vellmer at the bargaining table. (T.46-48). On cross-examination she admitted she was directly involved in Arkansas contract negotiations and very little retroactivity was involved in the final contract there. She worked to help get the current Contract ratified but she did not negotiate that Contract.</p>
<p><i>Kara Hutchason</i> testified she is a Staff Representative for the Union. She was involved in the Grievance filed herein. She discussed the Grievance with Dan Groninger at a grievance meeting where retroactive pay was discussed. She received the Company's Answer to the Grievance. (Jt.Ex.2). She was not at the bargaining table so not aware of retroactivity discussions. (T.55-58). She admitted the Grievance stated the issue related only to Grievant herein but said her meeting with Groninger discussed retroactive pay for technicians and all other employees. The Union only requested payroll information for Grievant. (Union Ex.4). She met with Groninger regarding two other employees who also filed grievances for retroactive pay. (T.58-61).</p>
<p><i>Dan Groninger</i> testified he has been the Company's Labor Relations Negotiator for thirty years. He serves as Chief Negotiator for the Company at all negotiations. He heard the Grievance herein at Step 2 by telephone with Kara Hutchason. He determined that the Grievance filed herein was limited to Grievant's claim that he was denied retroactivity. (Jt.Ex.2; T.63-67). Hutchason told him at the Step 2 meeting that the Union's position was that it was a class action grievance for all employees. Based on past experience he determined this was only a local 6300 grievance for Grievant and did not include the other four Union locals. He identified other class action grievances filed by the Union. (Co.Ex.1). In those grievances the Union refers to &ldquo;denying bargaining unit members.&rdquo; (T.67-69). Local 6300 filed two grievances regarding retroactive pay and Local 6311 filed one grievance on that issue. He interprets the Contract to require the Union to file a general or class action grievance if they take the position that other bargaining unit members are included in the grievance. (Jt.Ex.1, Sec.3.2). The Company also received a payroll information request only for the Grievance herein on April 15, 2015. (Co.Ex.2).</p>
<p>Grievant voluntarily terminated his employment on December 19, 2014 and the Contract was not ratified until March 17, 2015. Grievant was not an &ldquo;employee&rdquo; at the time the Contract was ratified. (Jt.Ex.1, Sec. 2.2.1). On the prior Contract dated 2011 &ndash; 2014, the parties agreed to a lump sum retroactive pay increase but no retroactive payment was made to employees who voluntarily terminated their employment before ratification of that Contract and the Union did not grieve that issue. (T.73-76). At the Step 2 meeting he denied Grievant's request for retroactive pay.</p>
<p>He negotiated the current Contract with Jason Vellmer. He knew based on prior negotiations that Vellmer needed final approval from Lois Grimes Patow who had final approval before there is an agreement to submit to members for a vote. He identified Company settlement proposals made during negotiations. (Jt.Ex.3). He also identified notes taken by Labor Relations Manager Tammy Mason at bargaining sessions. (Co.Ex.3). The Company agreed to &ldquo;full retroactivity&rdquo; if the Contract was ratified before May 15, 2014 but it was not ratified by that date. On May 20, 2014 he submitted the Company's proposal to the Union which included &ldquo;full retroactivity&rdquo; if the Union ratified it before June 20, 2014. The Contract was not ratified by the Union before that date. On July 29, 2014 he submitted another settlement proposal to the Union which did not specifically address retroactivity but during negotiations he agreed on full retroactivity but the Union did not submit the proposal to its members for a vote. (T.76-98). On September 12, 2014 he wrote to Vellmer summarizing the Company's position. (Co.Ex.4). In that letter he stated that it was the Company's position that a future ratification of the Contract would not be part of the settlement. (T.101-102). Bargaining resumed on October 21-22, 2014, with the assistance of a Federal mediator. The Company agreed to &ldquo;full retroactivity&rdquo; if the Contract was ratified by November 21, 2014. That package was not submitted to the Union for ratification. Negotiations continued on November 20, 2014 and the Company agreed to full retroactivity if ratified before December 21, 2014. The Union members voted not to ratify the tentative Contract. Since the Contract was not ratified the Company proposal of &ldquo;full retroactivity&rdquo; was withdrawn.</p>
<p>In January 2015, Bill Stubbs, the Company's Director of Labor Relations, began discussions with Lois Grimes Patow. He had no further discussions with Vellmer and the Union ratified the November 20, 2014 Company proposal on March 17, 2015. Since the Company's last proposal was not ratified by the Union before December 20, 2014 he considered retroactive pay to be off the table. (T.102-110). After the Contract was ratified on March 17, 2015 the Company made retroactive wage payments for 2014 based on a forty hour week, retroactive wage payments for 2015 for all hours worked.</p>
<p><i>William Stubbs</i> testified he is the Company's Director of Labor Relations. Dan Groninger reports to him. He was involved in negotiation planning but did not directly participate in negotiations until the Contract proposal was voted down the second time by the Union on December 20, 2014. At that time he determined that the Company's offer including retroactivity was off the table. (T.123-126). Thereafter, on January 5, 2015 he emailed Grimes-Patow and they spoke by phone on January 7, 2015. He thereafter summarized that conversation by email to Groninger and his boss, Joe Osa. (Co.Ex.5). He told Grimes-Patow that it would be very difficult for the Company to do a full retroactive pay calculation since the 2014 year had expired due to difficulties with the Company's payroll systems. He told her the Company could do retroactivity based on a forty hour week for 2014 and full retroactivity for 2015. (T.126-130). He spoke to Grimes-Patow again on February 3,,2015 and he again told her retroactivity would be based on a forty hour week for 2014 and full retroactivity for 2015. He memorialized that discussion in an email that day to Groninger and Osa. (Co.Ex.6). That was his last discussion with Grimes-Patow. (T.130-132). Grimes-Patow was always involved in the final approval for national support of any agreement.</p>
<p>On cross-examination he admitted that his January 7, 2015 email to Groninger and Osa stated: &ldquo;She indicated that she fully understood that but hoped we would not remove the option yet.&rdquo; (Co,Ex,5). His second email on February 3, 2015 to Groninger and Osa stated: &ldquo;She hoped we would be willing to keep everything in place until then. I told her we would but expected a positive result.&rdquo; (Co.Ex.6). By that he meant that he referred to the discussion on January 7, 2015 that retroactivity was based on forty hours for 2014 and full retroactivity for 2015. (T.134-138).</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>VI. DISCUSSION AND DECISION</b></i></h4>
<p>The questions to be decided by the Arbitrator in this dispute are, first, whether the Company violated the Contract when it refused to pay Grievant retroactive pay from March 14, 2014 until his voluntary retirement on December 19, 2014. The second question to be decided is whether the grievance filed herein applies to all bargaining unit members or only to Grievant.</p>
<p>The burden is upon the Union in this Contract interpretation case as its grievance seeks to interpret the Contract. The Union must prove by a preponderance of the evidence that the Company violated a specific provision of the Contract. It is the Arbitrator's duty to determine the intent of the parties as expressed in the Contract. If the disputed Contract language is clear and unambiguous, the Arbitrator will give such language its plain meaning. However, if the disputed language is reasonably susceptible to more than one meaning, the language may be considered ambiguous and the Arbitrator may choose to rely on other interpretive aids such as bargaining history or past practice of the parties.</p>
<p>The great majority of the facts in this case are undisputed. The Company and Union have a long-standing collective bargaining relationship. During negotiations for the current contract the Company was represented by Dan Groninger and the Union was represented by Jason Vellmer. Bargaining on the current contract began on February 25, 2014 only a few weeks until the prior contract was due to expire. That contract expired on March 14, 2014 and both parties agreed to extend that contract while negotiations continued. Groninger presented the Company's first Settlement Offer on March 14, 2014 which stated that the Company &ldquo;agrees to full retroactivity should a tentative agreement be ratified by a majority of members on or before May 15, 2014,&rdquo; (Jt.Ex.3). Groninger was adamant that the retroactive wage increase would be taken off the table if the contract was not ratified by that date. The Company's first Settlement Offer was rejected and negotiations resumed in April and May, 2014. Groninger made two Settlement Offers including Settlement Offer B on May 19, 2014 and in both offers the Company agreed to full retroactive wage increase &ldquo;should a tentative agreement be ratified by a majority of members on or before June 20, 2014,&rdquo; (Jt.Ex.3). The Union took Settlement Offer B to its members for a vote but the Union members voted it down.</p>
<p>Negotiations resumed on July 28, 2014 and the Company made a third Settlement Offer. Groninger noted in that Offer that &ldquo;should this package not be ratified by a majority of its members no later than August 29, 2014 the Company reserves the right to amend the package to include the Company's wage proposal contained therein.&rdquo; Groninger again told the Union that retroactivity depended on ratification by August 29, 2014. Vellmer declined to submit the Settlement Offer to the Union for a vote by August 29, 2014. When no new negotiations were scheduled Groninger wrote Vellmer on September 12, 2014. In that letter he stated: &ldquo;&hellip; if and when we reach an agreement ratified by a majority of your members retroactivity will not be part of the settlement.&rdquo; (Co.Ex.4). It was not until bargaining resumed on October 21, 2014 that the Company presented Revised Settlement Offer B to the Union. (Jt.Ex.3). Again, in that Settlement Offer Groninger stated: &ldquo;&hellip; should this package not be ratified by a majority of its members no later than November 21, 2014, the Company reserves the right to amend the package to include the Company's wage proposal contained therein.&rdquo; Groninger verbally told Vellmer that the package includes full retroactivity provided that Revised Settlement Offer B was ratified by Union members on November 20, 2014. Vellmer chose not to submit this package to Union members for a vote.</p>
<p>Negotiations resumed on November 20, 2014 and the Company presented the Union with the Second Revised Settlement Offer B. This Offer included the following: &ldquo;&hellip; should this package not be ratified by a majority of its members no later than December 20, 2014 the Company reserves the right to amend the package to include the Company's wage proposal contained therein.&rdquo; The Company's Second Revised Settlement Offer B was voted down by Union members on December 20, 2014.</p>
<p>On January 7, 2015 William Stubbs, Director of Company Labor Relations and boss of Groninger called Lois Grimes-Patow at the Union's national office to see what could be done to conclude a contract. Grimes-Patow was Vellmer's boss at the national office. Stubbs explained to Grimes-Patow that since it was now 2015, the Company would still give Union members a full retroactive pay but it would only be based on a 40 hour work week. Several more discussions between Stubbs and Grimes-Patow occurred thereafter. There were no more discussions between Groninger and Vellmer. The Union took the Company's Second Revised Settlement Offer B to its members for a vote and it was finally ratified on March 15, 2015.</p>
<p>Following the ratification of the Contract the Company made full retroactive payment to all its active employees on the Company payroll as of the date the Contract was ratified. The Company paid these employees retroactive pay based on a forty hour week for 2014 and retroactive pay for all hours worked in 2015. The Company did not pay Grievant any retroactive pay because he terminated his employment before the Contract was ratified.</p>
<p>The first issue to be decided by this Arbitrator is whether the grievance filed herein by Kevin Clemens was an individual grievance or a &ldquo;Class&rdquo; grievance. The Contract sets out the grievance procedures as follows:</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 3</h4>
<h4 align="center">GRIEVANCES</h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">3.1 A grievance shall be a complaint, question or controversy by any employee or group of employees or by an authorized Union representative, with respect to the interpretation or application of any provision of this Agreement. No grievance shall be eligible for handling hereunder unless filed in compliance with Section 3.2 and within the time limits and according to the procedures established in Section 3.4. Grievances not so presented or processed shall be considered waived by the Union.</p>
<p class="continued">3.2 Each grievance shall briefly describe in substance the specific matters complained of in sufficient detail that dates, time(s) if pertinent, occurrences and the nature of the circumstances causing the grievance can be identified readily. The names and locations of employees concerned shall also be given where the grievance relates to specific employees as opposed to a general complaint. There shall also be a statement as to the specific section(s) of this Agreement believed to have been violated or misinterpreted and the desired remedy. (Jt.Ex.1).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The grievance filed herein on April 15, 2015 stated as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;In accordance with the Provisions of Article 3 &ndash; Grievances &ndash; of the 2013 Labor Agreement between the Communications Workers of America and CenturyLink of Missouri, LLC the Union wishes to submit the following grievance.</p>
<p class="continued">The matter for consider is complaint&num;104-15-J of Kevin Clemens, Communications Technician, 1275 CenturyLink Dr., Wentzville, Missouri, concerning Management's decision on April 7, 2015 to deny Mr. Clemens the retroactive pay increase of 1<fraction numer="1" denom="2"/>&percnt; negotiated by the Company and the Union under the 2014-2017 Labor Agreement for all his hours worked during the period of March 15, 2014 thru January 24, 2015 under the extension agreements negotiated between the parties for the 2011-2014 Labor Agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union charges the Company with violations of Article 1, Intent and Purpose; Article 2, Recognition and Area Designation, and Article 19, Wages of the 2014-2017 Labor Agreement as well as the agreements between the Union and the Company to extend the 2011-2014 Labor Agreement, as well as any unjust treatment and any other applicable Article of the Labor Agreement between the Parties.</p>
<p class="continued">To avoid forwarding this grievance to the next level of the grievance procedure, the Union requests a meeting within 14 calendar days upon receipt of this letter. Please contact Jo Wise at 314.991.0200 ext. 249 to make the necessary arrangements.&rdquo; (Jt.Ex.2)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The burden is upon the Union in this contract interpretation case to prove that the Company violated the Contract when denying this grievance. The Union must further prove that this grievance was a &ldquo;Class&rdquo; grievance and not an individual grievance of Kevin Clemens. The plain meaning of the language in this grievance is that it was filed only on behalf of Kevin Clemens as an individual. There is no mention in the grievance that it is a Class grievance or that it in any way relates to any group of employees. The Contract states in part:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;The names and locations of employees concerned shall also be given where the Grievance relates to specific employees as opposed to a <i>general complaint</i>.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">There is no mention in the grievance that it is being filed for anyone other than Grievant Kevin Clemens. The Union admitted that it filed two other <i>separate</i> grievances on behalf of bargaining unit employees Dean Buckman and Bryan Thomas on the same issue of retroactive pay. Neither of those two grievances alleged they were being filed as a Class grievance on behalf of a larger group of employees. The evidence was undisputed that the Union had filed Class grievances in the past on behalf of groups of employees. (Co.Ex.1). If the Union intended the grievance to apply to more people than Grievant it should have spelled that out in the grievance or articulated that the complaint applied to a group of employees. The Union has failed to meet the burden of proof that the grievance filed herein was a Class grievance.</p>
<p>Having found that the grievance filed herein was an individual grievance, I will now decide it on its merits. It is true that there was no evidence presented by the Union that the Company ever agreed to a retroactive pay increase to employees who terminated their employment before the Contract was ratified. Grievant terminated his employment on December 19, 2014 and the Contract was ratified thereafter on March 15, 2015. However the Contract, in Article 19, states it is effective March 15, 2014 and Grievant was an employee of the Company at that time until his retirement on December 19, 2014. Grievant worked under the Contract until his retirement and is entitled to the retroactive pay increase agreed to by the Company and Union.</p>
<p>The final issue then is whether Grievant is entitled to retroactive pay based on a forty hour week or full retroactive pay based on all hours worked. The Company's offer of full retroactivity was always conditioned on Contract ratification by a specific date. The Company's purpose was to incentivize the Union to ratify the Contract. The last offer by the Company was presented on November 20, 2014 and conditioned full retroactivity to the Union ratifying the Contract by December 20, 2014. The Union voted the Contract down on December 20, 2014. Therefore, the offer of the Company of full retroactivity expired. Negotiations thereafter were conducted on a national level between Bill Stubbs on behalf of the Company and Lois Grimes-Patow, Administrative Director of the Union's national office in Washington, DC. The evidence was undisputed that Jason Vellmer did not have authority to finalize the Contract. He could only reach a &ldquo;tentative&rdquo; agreement which must be approved by Grimes-Patow and Bates at the national level. Stubbs testified that he told Grimes-Patow that full retroactivity based on all hours worked for 2014 was off the table but a lump sum retro payment based on a forty hour week would be made if the Contract was ratified. Stubbs based his position in part that the Company's payroll system made it extremely difficult to do a full retroactive pay calculation. Grimes-Patow admitted that Stubbs told her that full retroactivity for 2014 was a problem but denied she had authority to finalize a Contract on behalf of the Union. There were no further discussions on a local level between Vellmer and Groninger after Settlement Offer B was vote down by the Union on December 20, 2014. However Settlement Offer B was resubmitted to the Union for a vote and was ratified on March 15, 2015. Thereafter the Company made retroactive payments to the Union members for 2014 based on a forty hour week and for 2015 based on all hours worked.</p>
<p>The burden is on the Union to prove that the Company agreed to full retroactivity based on all hours worked in 2014. I find that the Union has failed to do so. The last Settlement Offer of November 20, 2014 which included full retroactivity was voted down by the Union on December 20, 2014. Thereafter that offer by the Company expired. The only negotiations thereafter were conducted on a national level between Stubbs and Grimes-Patow. The Company's evidence was credible that Stubbs told Grimes-Patow that retroactive pay for 2014 would be based on a forty hour week. Grimes-Patow admitted that Stubbs told her that was the Company's position. Grimes-Patow had final approval on any Contract offer as Vellmer could only reach a &ldquo;tentative&rdquo; agreement. Clearly Grimes-Patow had, at a minimum, apparent authority to reach an agreement with the Company on a tentative agreement before the proposed Contract was submitted to Union members for ratification. Therefore, I find that the Company and Union agreed to a retroactive wage payment based on a forty hour week for 2014 which took effect when Union members ratified the Contract on March 15, 2015.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>VII. AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>The grievance is sustained in part. The Company is ordered to make a retroactive lump sum payment based on a forty hour work week to Grievant Kevin Clemens from March 14, 2014 until his retirement on December 19, 2014.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>