<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>UNITED PARCEL SERVICE CO. and INTERNATIONAL BROTHERHOOD OF TEAMSTERS, AIRLINE DIVISION, LOCAL UNION NO. 2727</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>GR. &num; 2013-2966</p>
<p>March 31, 2016.</p>
<p>Mitchell B. Goldberg, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>OPINION AND AWARD</b></h4>
<h4 align="left">I. <i>Introduction and Background.</i></h4>
<p>This is a labor arbitration proceeding conducted under the terms and conditions of the parties' collective bargaining agreement (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo;). Article 6 sets forth the grievance procedure and Article 7 provides for a System Board of Adjustment under the Railway Labor Act for resolving labor disputes that are not resolved during the grievance steps. Grievance 2013-2966 was filed by Wade Crady (&ldquo;Grievant&rdquo;). It alleges that the Company violated the CBA (Article 13) when it failed to award him an overtime assignment that he volunteered for beginning Sunday night on February 24, 2013. He alleges that the Company improperly bypassed him for two assignments, and instead awarded the overtime work to two other employees on the overtime sign-up sheet, both of whom had accumulated more hours in their overtime banks that the Grievant had accumulated in his bank. The grievance requests that the Grievant be made whole for the Company's CBA violation, and that he receive pay at the applicable rate for the overtime shift that he should have worked.</p>
<p>The Company denied the grievance at each step and the matter proceeded to the System Board of Adjustment in accordance with Article 7 of the CBA. A reporter transcribed the proceeding and prepared the official record. The parties offered testimonial evidence and submitted documentary exhibits. Witnesses were examined and cross-examined. Post-hearing briefs were filed after all of the evidence was received. The parties stipulated that all procedural and substantive requirements of the grievance/arbitration procedures were complied with that are necessary to bring this issue to a final and binding conclusion.</p>
<h4 align="left">II. <i>Applicable Contract Provisions and Joint Interpretations.</i></h4>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE 13 &ndash; FULL TIME EMPLOYEE OVERTIME</p>
<p class="continued">Section 5 &ndash; Overtime Procedures</p>
<ol type="lc-letter" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>In awarding any full shift overtime, the first preference will be given to employee(s) with at least eight (8) hours rest between the employee's scheduled punch out to the scheduled start time of his next report. The Company will not deny an employee an overtime shift with less-than-eight (8) hours rest if he would have otherwise been entitled to be awarded the shift and no other eligible bidder for that shift had more than eight (8) hours off provided the number of shifts awarded for that day, with more than eight (8) hours rest, is not reduced. The procedure set forth in the prior sentence will be implemented in SDF once the electronic award system is implemented.</p></li>
<li><p>Full time employee overtime will be awarded on a rotational basis to provide all employees equal opportunity to work available overtime. The Company and Union will act jointly to administer this procedure and will cooperate to the fullest extent possible for its effective operation, however, any time spent by any employee covered by this Agreement contacting employees for overtime or maintaining overtime records, will be compensated.</p></li>
<li><p>The eligible and qualified employee with the least amount of awarded overtime hours in the applicable work center who can complete all hours of the overtime need will be awarded or given the opportunity to work the available overtime. The eligible and qualified employee with the next least amount of overtime roster hours in the applicable work center who can complete all hours of the overtime need will be awarded or given the next opportunity to work available overtime. This process will continue until available overtime needs within a work center are satisfied.</p></li></ol>
<p>Joint Interpretations are essentially discussions held between party representatives to discuss the meaning of changed language from the prior CBA in an effort to reach an agreement as to the effect of the new language on the employer's operations and on the employees' working conditions. The Joint Interpretation are transcribed and memorialized. Mr. Wilder was the Union's representative discussing the changes that were made in the present CBA. He stated that the purpose of the 8-hours rest first preference is to satisfy the Company's interest in limiting the amount of premium time or double pay paid for overtime. The second preference goes to the employee with the fewest number of awarded overtime hours. That employee has the opportunity to work the scheduled overtime &ldquo;before an employee who has a higher number of awarded overtime &ndash; hours for the period in question.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The problem of competition between employees who typically sign up for multiple overtime opportunities &ldquo;on the days they want to work&rdquo; raised the problem that was dealt with the parties at the bargaining table. Mr. Wilder addressed the problem in more detail after discussing the purpose of the 8-hour rest rule. He stated:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Now, the same process &lsqb;fewest hours&rsqb; is followed with the employee with the next fewest hours and so on until all volunteers are matched with overtime preferences that will not result in them being paid double time. Obviously, if no volunteers can satisfy the eight-hour rest rule, the overtime opportunity should be awarded to the bidder with the fewest awarded overtime hours. That is not what happens because bidders with the fewest overtime hours are already matched with overtime opportunities that will not result in their being paid premium pay. The method often resulting in employees with more awarded overtime hours winning an overtime opportunity desired by an employee with fewer overtime hours, even though neither employee satisfied the eight-hour rest rule. So, ultimately, under the existing system, coveted overtime awards paying at the premium rate are going to bidders with the highest number of awarded overtime hours simply because &ndash; more deserving bidders have already been matched with overtime assignments meeting the eight-hour rule. The remedy agreed to by the parties in Section 1.a. is that employees with less than eight hours of rest will not be denied overtime shifts so long as there are no employees desiring that shift who do satisfy the eight-hour rest rule.</p>
<p class="continued">That satisfied the union interest in fairness. The company's interest was met by the proviso in that sentence that reads as follows: &ldquo;Provided the number of shifts awarded for that day with more than eight hours rest is not reduced.&rdquo; Now, it's obvious that this new system will require more sequences of matching volunteers with overtime opportunities than is presently feasible according to the Company under the manual system currently in place. That is why the parties agreed to defer implementation of the new system until after an electronic award system is implemented that will then enable the administrator to perform the various matching sequences so that employees are properly matched given the preferences, first the eight hour rule, and then secondly, the fewest number of overtime hours&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip; it was pointed out that under the new system, there will be no fewer shifts being awarded to employees with more than eight hours rest than under the current manual system. The new system will simply result in a more accurate allocation of overtime opportunities according to the preferences in the agreement.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left">III. <i>Facts</i></h4>
<p>The basic facts underlying the grievance are undisputed. The Grievant signed the overtime shift preference document indication that he was volunteering for overtime assignments for 11 different shifts for February 24, 2013. The Signup Report also indicates that the Grievant was willing to work back-to-back shifts for 7 of the 11 shifts. One of the shifts was shift 13.MT&ast;. Mark Alexander, another AMT who normally works Shift 7 at SDF, signed up for 13.MT&ast; as well. This was his normal work shift, 07:00-20:30 Saturday, Sunday and Monday. The Grievant's regular shift is 22:30-07:00, Monday-Friday. The Grievant would have been working his night shift and would have continued on the following day shift if he received the overtime award. Alexander was working overtime on the 07:00-20:30 shift and would continue another overtime shift following his overtime day shift. Both bidders did not have 8-hours of rest; all bidders who had 8-hours of rest were assigned overtime shifts under the EOT, which was in effect at the time. Alexander had far more hours in his overtime bank than the Grievant at the time of the award, 82 for Alexander and 26 for the Grievant. Notwithstanding this disparity in overtime hours, the Company awarded Alexander the overtime assignment.</p>
<p>The Union contends that the least amount of hours requirement must apply for each overtime assignment that is made for a particular day. If this were done, the Grievant would have received the award, since both he and Alexander did not have the 8-hours of rest, which is the first preference consideration. The Company disagrees. It interprets Section 5 differently by applying an overtime rotation in a progression, first to those bidders with 8-hours rest, and second to those with the least overtime hours in their bank to the bidder with the least hours. Once each assignment is made, the remaining bidders on the remaining shifts that have not as yet been assigned using the lowest hours standard for those remaining bidders. However, they could be selected over another bidder who has lower bank hours, if that bidder had already been awarded an overtime bid for one of the shifts that they preferred, or signed up for that day.</p>
<p>Once the process of awards is finished for the day, it starts over for overtime shifts that are needed for the following day. Employees sign-up for overtime shifts that they are willing to work. There are many shifts that could produce overtime opportunities. Once the Company decides its overtime needs, it will look to see which employees signed up for the particular shift. This is when the preference standards kick in; first to those with the required 8-hours of rest and the lowest hours, and then to those who did not have the 8-hours of rest through the progression.</p>
<p class="continued">The dispute arises, as indicated by this grievance, and two others that had similar issues, when the overtime shifts have been assigned to those with rest, and no rest, leaving some shifts unfilled. If there are two or more employees who have not as yet been assigned an overtime shift, the remaining unfilled shift needs to be assigned. The Union insists that among those employees who have yet to be assigned an overtime shift, the employee with the least amount of overtime bank hours must be selected, notwithstanding that they have already received an overtime assignment for the day. The Company believes that Section 5 applies to the number of shifts that awarded &ldquo;for that day&rdquo; means that it must attempt to fill an overtime request for each employee who signs up for that day. In order to provide an assignment for each overtime bidder it must do so instead of awarding the remaining assignment to a bidder with lower hours, but one who has already received an assignment.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>IV. Evidence, Discussion and Findings.</i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i>Contract Interpretation Principles</i></h4>
<p>The Union has the burden of proof in a contract interpretation dispute. It must persuade the arbitrator that its position is the correct interpretation of the agreement, and the parties' intent. The arbitrator's role is to weigh the evidence and determine whether the Union has met its burden by a preponderance or the greater weight of the evidence.</p>
<p>The starting point in interpreting the parties' intent is their chosen words or language that was used to express their intent. The words and their plain meaning or ordinary meaning are important, but the Restatement (Second) of Contracts, while focusing heavily upon the language, goes further and relies upon an analysis of the context in which the words are used, and the surrounding and prevailing circumstances. It starts by explaining that meanings can &ldquo;almost&rdquo; never be plain except in a context. One must look at the relevant evidence of the situation and relations of the parties, the subject matter of the transaction, preliminary negotiations and statements made therein, usages of trade, and the course of dealing between the parties. &ldquo;But, after the transaction has been shown in all its length and breath, the words of the integrated agreement remain the most important evidence of intention.&rdquo;<ftnote num="1"><para><italic>Restatement (Second) of Contracts</italic>, Section 212, cmt B (1979).</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="center"><i>Bargaining History</i></h4>
<p>The 1990-1995 CBA addressed voluntary overtime selection in Section 5. It stated that selections for voluntary overtime assignments were to be done by seniority on a rotational basis. The concept of selection with preference to employees with the lowest overtime bank hours was introduced in the 1995-2001 CBA. The employee with the lowest amount of awarded overtime hours in the applicable work center or shift would be given the next opportunity. The selection would continue on the same basis for the next opportunity, and so on. During that time, however, employees worked either day shifts or night shifts. Day shift employees could not bid for opportunities on night shifts, and night shift employees could not bid for day shift overtime opportunities. The principle was restated in the 2001-2006 CBA that overtime was to be awarded on a rotational basis to provide all employees an equal opportunity to work available overtime. However, a new preference was established, that full-shift overtime was to be first offered to those bidders with at least 8-hours rest between their scheduled punch out to the scheduled start time of their next report. By this time, there were no longer day and night shifts. Employees could bid for overtime on any full-time shift.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>The Negotiations For the 2006-2013 CBA</i></h4>
<p>The Union proposal on May 16, 2007 proposed that overtime would be processed and awarded by shift (day shift, afternoon shift and night shift) &ldquo;and not by calendar day, in chronological order of need.&rdquo; The lowest hours for selection would continue &ldquo;even if the employee has bid for multiple shifts of overtime.&rdquo; &ldquo;So long as the employee has signed up for all shift(s), and continues to be the employee with the lowest number of recorded overtime hours, the employee will be awarded the overtime.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Company rejected the Union proposal in its counter proposal on November 18, 2008. The Union reinstated its &ldquo;shift&rdquo; assignment language in its counter to the Company on November 19, 2008. The Union agreed to Company proposed language on January 29, 2009 that preference is given to those with 8-hours rest and the lowest overtime hours. Those without 8-hours rest would not be denied overtime if the number of volunteers with rest were awarded the number of shifts with more than 8-hours rest and that list is not reduced. This same concept that began to be similar to the final language in this CBA was presented by the Company to the Union on February 3, 2009. On February 4, 2009, the Company for the first time added the words &ldquo;for that day&rdquo; in their proposal in the clause that states: &ldquo;&lsqb;It&rsqb; would not deny an employee an overtime shift &lsqb;with less than 8-hours rest if he was entitled and no other eligible bidder had the rest&rsqb; provided the number of shifts awarded for that day with more than &lsqb;8-hours&rsqb; rest, is not reduced.&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>The Ambiguity of Selection by Shift or by Day Remained</i></h4>
<p>The parties disagree as to what was said, understood, or conveyed across the bargaining table, but it is clear that there remained a latent ambiguity or an unfilled gap in the language on the precise issue in dispute; whether selection of the remaining overtime shifts (those volunteers with less than 8-hours rest) were to be given to the employees who on that day had the lowest number of overtime hours in their bank, regardless if they already received overtime assignments according to their preferences, or whether the Company could select among the employees who had not received an overtime assignment for the day, and the Company could select the employee with the lowest number of hours in their overtime bank from that group. The Company relies upon the words &ldquo;for that day&rdquo; in Section 5a. to support its position, and the Union relies upon Section 5c., which states that the eligible and qualified employees &ldquo;with the least amount of awarded overtime hours &hellip; who can complete all hours of the overtime need will be awarded or given the opportunity to work the available overtime.&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>The Jones Grievance Filed on June 8, 2007</i></h4>
<p>Grievant Jones complained that he was denied another overtime shift after he previously received an overtime assignment &ldquo;with rest.&rdquo; The Company began awarding overtime assignments to those without rest, which would have included the Grievant who would be working the overtime assignment he received. It bypassed the Grievant who received his assignment from among those employees with 8-hours rest, and started selection among the group without rest who had not as yet received an overtime assignment for the day. This grievance was settled, but the grievance itself was admitted into evidence for the limited purpose of showing how the Company was selecting employees for overtime assignments at the time, and to show that the Union at least knew about the way the Company was doing things. The Union takes the position that it may have known how the Company was making selections in the Jones grievance, but it nevertheless continued to dispute this process. It was satisfied that the adoption of the new language in the 2006 CBA in Section 5a supported its position that employees with the lowest overtime hours among those with less than 8-hours rest would still receive assignments notwithstanding that they received selections earlier in the process.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>The Earlier Layman Grievance Filed on June 3, 2004</i></h4>
<p>Grievant Layman also alleged that he was bypassed for an overtime shift selection in favor of another employee who had more overtime bank hours. The Union's position was the same as its position here, that the employee with the lowest overtime hours should be entitled to as fill as many overtime shifts that he prefers to work before overtime shifts are awarded to employees with more hours in their overtime bank. The Company denied the grievance and contended that it was continuing to apply the overtime rotation process on a daily basis to all overtime shifts that are awarded at the same time each day, and that the rotation did not reset at the selection of each new shift. In other words, it was contending that it was awarding overtime shifts to those employees who had not already received an overtime assignment for the day &ndash; the same position it is taking here.</p>
<p>The matter went to arbitration, and was referred back to the Overtime Committee for resolution. The parties, however, disagree as to what was discussed and resolved at the Committee. The Company believes that the issue in this case was resolved when the Union made a proposal after the Committee meeting that required all possible overtime shifts for a particular day to be awarded to the employee with the fewest overtime hours, even if the employee already received an overtime shift earlier in the rotation. The Company rejected this proposal and continued awarding overtime bids on a daily rotational basis rather than on a shift-by-shift basis.</p>
<p>The Union, however, believes that it still preserved the present issue for dispute after the Overtime Committee meeting. It contends that the substance of the meeting concerned the Grievant's claim that that he did not receive his shift that he selected as his first choice. Once all employees with rest were given overtime shifts, the employees with no 8-hours rest would be given the opportunity and shifts would be awarded to the employees with the lowest number of overtime hours. They would be awarded &ldquo;their first available desired shift.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Accordingly, the parties remain in disagreement as to whether the Union accepted or acknowledged the Company's rotation method as the accepted way of conducting the overtime rotation.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>Back to the Contract</i></h4>
<p>Each party has language that supports its contention within Article 13, Section 5. The Union's position is based upon the longstanding principle that its members best receive equal opportunities to work available overtime when they are able to bid shift by shift in favor of the bidder with the least amount of overtime hours for the first group of those with 8-hours of rest, and then through the second group of employees who do not have 8-hours rest. This process produces opportunities for &ldquo;doubles,&rdquo; but it expeditiously fills the overtime banks for employees who have yet to be awarded overtime due to their lower hours.</p>
<p>The Company believes its method better serves its interest that all rested and unrested volunteers receive an &ldquo;equal opportunity&rdquo; to work a single shift of overtime before awarding a volunteer a double shift of overtime or &ldquo;back to back&rdquo; shifts &ldquo;for that day.&rdquo; It further believes that it will receive more rested employees and that its overall overtime costs would be less.</p>
<p>I find that this is a burden of proof case where each party's position is supported by the contract language, and each interpretation is as reasonable as the other. However, it is the Union that has the burden of proof in this type of contractual dispute. I find, based upon the evidence in the record before me that the Union's interpretation is reasonable, but that it is not more reasonable than the Company's interpretation. The Union's position accelerates the accumulation of overtime hours for employees with low numbers in their banks by permitting them to work more shifts on a particular day in accordance with their multiple selections. However, the Company's interpretation and applied method provides an equal opportunity for all of the employees who volunteer for overtime shifts based upon the Company's needs for a particular day. When the list is exhausted after all volunteers receive one overtime shift, those who are willing to work additional overtime shifts available for the day will receive more overtime shifts that are based again on selecting among the volunteers with the least amount of overtime hours. When both interpretations reflect the &ldquo;lowest hours&rdquo; standard and &ldquo;the equal overtime opportunity&rdquo; standard that are stated in the contract language and in the joint interpretation, the decision should go against the party with the burden of proof.<ftnote num="2"><para><italic>See, e.g. Bruno's Supermarket</italic>, 123 LA 65, 68 (Nolan, 2006); <italic>Lorillard Tobacco Inc</italic>, 124 LA 782, 784 (Nolan, 2007).</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="left">V. <i>Award.</i></h4>
<p>The grievance is denied for the above reasons.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>