<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>RE: IN THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION: GREATER CLEVELAND REGIONAL TRANSIT AUTHORITY/GCRTA/ATU ARBITRATION PANEL GREATER CLEVELAND REGIONAL TRANSIT AUTHORITY (GCRTA) (Employer/Company) and AMALGAMATED TRANSIT UNION/LOCAL 268 (Union)</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>GRIEVANCE NO.: 01978</p>
<p>October 27, 2016.</p>
<p>THOMAS R. SKULINA, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>OPINION AND AWARD OF THOMAS R. SKULINA, ESQUIRE/ARBITRATOR</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>HEARING</b></i></h4>
<p>A Hearing was conducted at the headquarters of the GCRTA, in Cleveland, Ohio, on August 25, 2016. Counsel for the GCRTA was R.J. Roberto, Esquire/Associate Counsel of The Greater Cleveland Regional Transit Authority of Cleveland, Ohio. The union was represented by Robert E. Davis, Esquire, of Robert E. Davis Co., L.P.A., Cleveland, Ohio. Both parties presented Briefs and they were exchanged by this office on October 10, 2016.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>ISSUE</b></h4>
<p>Whether the filing of the grievance was untimely pursuant to the CBA?</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>COLLECTIVE BARGAINING AGREEMENT</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ARTICLE 14 &ndash; VACATIONS</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>Section 14. Banked Vacation</b></h4>
<p>Employees entitled to 120 hours of vacation must take at least 80 hours of actual vacation in any one year. In addition, they may elect to bank a maximum of 40 hours per year. Employees entitled to 160 hours or more vacation may elect to bank up to a maximum of 80 hours per year. The maximum amount of vacation that may be banked shall be 400 hours.</p>
<p><b>Section 6.</b> An employee who retires on pension during any calendar year shall receive a vacation for that year in accordance with the above schedule calculated to his/her date of retirement.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ARTICLE 9 &ndash; GRIEVANCE PROCEDURE</b></i></h4>
<p><b>Section 3. Grievance Procedure:</b></p>
<p><b>Step 1. &hellip;</b>The grievance shall be presented in writing on a mutually agreed upon Form to the employee's Director within ten (10) days of the event that is the source of the grievance&hellip;</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>FACTS</b></h4>
<p>The grievant began employment on December 17, 1989 as a laborer. He continued to bank vacation time instead of taking it. As of January of 2015 1,096 hours of vacation time was banked.</p>
<p>The Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA), effective August 1, 2014, through July 31, 2017, addressed the issue whether this amount of vacation could be banked.</p>
<p>Article 14 &ndash; Vacation. Specifically states &ldquo;the maximum amount of vacation that may be banked shall be 400 hours&rdquo;. This definitely is considerably less than the grievant had banked.</p>
<p>The employer decreased the grievant's vacation time by 700 hours to keep hours within the 400 hour time allowed in the CBA.</p>
<p>The grievant realized in February of 2015, that his banked vacation time had been reduced to 396 hours down from 1,096 hours (Transcript, Page 37).</p>
<p>The grievance was not filed until September 11, 2015. This was seven months after he discovered he lost 700 hours of vacation time.</p>
<p>The union stipulated that the 400 hour limit was in the contract dating back to the 1990's (Transcript, Page 41).</p>
<p>The grievance (01978) is dated September 11, 2015 and seeks compensation for 700 hours of vacation time which were taken without notification (Joint Exhibit 2).</p>
<p>Article 9 &ndash; Grievance Procedure of the CBA states in Step 1 that &ldquo;the grievance shall be presented in writing&hellip;within ten (10) days of the event that is the source of the grievance&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Thus, before addressing the issue of compensation for the extra hours beyond 400 hours that were banked, the first issue is whether the grievance is untimely and the loss is not arbitrable.</p>
<p>The record is clear that the grievant learned about the extraction of 700 hours of banked vacation as early as February of 2015. The grievance was filed in September of that year, which is about seven months later. It was filed clearly beyond the ten day CBA time limit.</p>
<p>Banked vacation is covered in Section 14 of the CBA. The union presented evidence that this time can be taken the following year or sometime thereafter.</p>
<p>The grievant could get his banked vacation if he retires or resigns (CBA Article 14).</p>
<p>The union presented that the grievant was given no notice that the 700 hours of vacation pay were taken away, however, he testified that he knew back in February the banked hours were reduced.</p>
<p>The union argues that each pay period the grievant's hours do not show on his pay stub renews the period in which he may grieve (Page 4 Union Brief). That agreement can not nullify the fact that the grievant knew many months before the grievance was filed that banked hours were seriously diminished.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>DISCUSSION</b></i></h4>
<p>This is a grievance that was not filed timely pursuant to the CBA.</p>
<p>If timely, there is the long standing language of the CBA that expressly limits banked time to 400 hours.</p>
<p>Hence, even if timely, the award would have to follow the clear language of the CBA (Article 14).</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>The grievance is denied. Costs of the arbitration shall be divided equally between the two parties (CBA, Article 10, Section 3).</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>