<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION between Fraternal Order of Police Capital City Lodge No. 9 and The Franklin County Sheriff's Office</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS No. 160415-54455-6</p>
<p>Grievance No. 16-04</p>
<p>December 15, 2016.</p>
<p>John M. Felice, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>NATURE OF THE GRIEVANCE</i></b></h4>
<p>The undersigned Arbitrator was selected by the parties to hear and decide a matter in dispute between the Fraternal Order of Police, Capital City Lodge No. 9, hereinafter referred to as &ldquo;FOP&rdquo;, and the Franklin County Sheriff's Office, hereinafter referred to as &ldquo;Employer&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The dispute is properly before the Arbitrator in accordance with the Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA) between the parties.</p>
<p>The parties mutually agreed to forego a hearing and submit the instant matter on briefs with testimony submitted via affidavits. Briefs were filed by both parties.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ISSUE</b></i></h4>
<p>Did the employer violate Section 6.11 of the CBA when it failed to timely notify the Grievant concerning an internal affairs investigation?</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>BACKGROUND</b></i></h4>
<p>On December 31, 2015, the Grievant was informed that he was the focus of an internal affairs investigation based on complaints made by the Grievant's ex-wife and her current boyfriend. On March 2, 2016, sixty-two (62) days after the Grievant was informed of the investigation, he was sent a sixty (60) day notice informing him that the investigation was ongoing. Since the internal investigation proceeded beyond 60 days, the application of Section 6.11 of the CBA was triggered. On March 30, 2016, the Grievant received a notification that the investigation had exceeded thirty (30) additional days on March 29,2016. Similarly, the Grievant received notices on April 29, May 30, June 29, July 29, and August 26 that the investigation had exceeded thirty (30) additional days as of April 28, May 28, June 27, July 27 and August 26, respectively. Subsequent to the grievance being filed on behalf of the Grievant on March 10, 2016 regarding a late sixty (60) day notice, internal affairs continued to be consistently tardy in providing the thirty (30) day notification of the ongoing investigation, with the exception of the final thirty (30) day notice which was timely sent after the Employer was aware that the matter of the belated notifications would proceed to arbitration.</p>
<p>The issue of the untimely notifications proceeded through the steps of the grievance procedure without resolution on April 12, 2016, the Sheriff concurred with the Chief's Step 3 response that the March 2, 2016 notification was sufficient to meet the contractual requirement and denied the grievance. When the parties were unable to resolve the dispute by means of the grievance procedure, they submitted the matter to the undersigned arbitrator for final and binding disposition.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>PERTINENT CONTRACT PROVISIONS</b></i></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><b>Section 6.11.</b> &ldquo;Any bargaining unit member who has been under investigation shall be informed, in writing, of the outcome of the case at the conclusion of the investigation. Further, if the investigation exceeds sixty (60) days, a representative of Internal Affairs, shall inform the concerned member in writing that additional time is required to complete the investigation. Thereafter, the concerned member shall receive a status report, outlining the current status of the investigation and the reason requiring additional time for it, every thirty (30) days.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>CONTENTIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<p>The FOP contends that the Employer violated Section 6.11 of the CBA asserting that more than sixty (60) days elapsed before the Grievant was initially notified that the investigation would need additional time. They contend that information obtained after the sixty (60) day notice requirement would be in violation of the CBA and therefore could not be used in any future disciplinary proceedings involving the Grievant. The FOP further asserts that notwithstanding, the CBA does not specify a penalty for late notification, that nay information gathered after the Grievant should have received his initial sixty (60) day notice or each thirty (30) day notice thereafter, were gathered in violation of the CBA. The FOP requests that the grievance be sustained and that an appropriate remedy be issued.</p>
<p>The Employer contends that the FOP's argument that the Grievant should have received written notice from the IAB investigator that his investigation had exceeded sixty (60) days, prior to sixty (60) days having elapsed is not logical or consistent with the sixty (60) day notification requirement set forth in Section 6.11 of the CBA. They further assert that the evidence establishes a practice that the 1AB thirty (30) day notifications were issued after the thirty (30) days had elapsed. The Employer requests that the grievance be denied.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>DISCUSSION AND FINDINGS</b></i></h4>
<p>Based on the clear and unambiguous language set forth in Section 6.11 of the CBA, a disjunctive interpretation of the respective sixty (60) day and thirty (30) day notification requirements in said Section 6.11 of the CBA is necessary in the instant case.</p>
<p>At the threshold, the Employer posits that its actions were consistent with a past practice as verified by various affidavits submitted into evidence that the IAB does not provide notification that additional time is needed until after the initial sixty (60) days or subsequent thirty (30) days, has elapsed.</p>
<p>However, to become a practice, the way of operating must be so frequent, regular and repetitious so as to establish a mutual understanding that the way of operating will continue in the future (See <i>Dayton Steel Foundry</i>, &lsqb;Wagoner 30 LA 35&rsqb;). Lacking mutuality, as is evident in the instant case, the practice is not an established one.</p>
<p>This Arbitrator cannot use past practice as an interpretive guide since the controlling provision in the instant dispute, Section 6.11, is clear and unambiguous. Past practice cannot be used to give meaning to a provision which is clear and unambiguous. Arbitrator Justin in a leading case found that &ldquo;&hellip;when the language used is clear and explicit, the arbitrator is constrained to give the effect to the thought expressed by the words used&hellip;&rdquo; (See <i>Phelps Dodge Copper Products Corp.</i>, 16 LA 229, 233 &lsqb;1059&rsqb;)</p>
<p>It is also a well-founded principle of arbitrable authority that when the words are clear and free from all ambiguity, the letter of it is not to be disregarded under the pretext of pursuing its spirit or intent. With respect to contractual time limits, it is generally recognized by arbitrators that where a labor agreement provides precise time limits, those limits must be strictly observed. Time limits written into an agreement are not fortuitous. The parties agreed upon these time limitations and these time limitations may have been the result of a bargained for exchange. To ignore the time limits set forth in Section 6.11 of the CBA would be tantamount to vitiating the language that the parties have expressly adopted.</p>
<p>After applying a disjunctive interpretation of the specific time limitations for notification, in Section 6.11 of the CBA, a sixty (60) day notice is not required until the investigation exceeds sixty (60) days. The position of the FOP, with respect to this sixty (60) time limit, is that the IAB would have to send the Grievant notification that the investigation will exceed sixty (60) days prior to it exceeding sixty (60) days. The sixty (60) day notification, after sixty (60) days had elapsed, is consistent with the language set forth in Section 6.11 which, in pertinent part, reads &ldquo;&hellip;if the investigation <i>exceeds sixty (60) days</i>&rdquo; (emphasis added). Accordingly, the Employer did not violate Section 6.11 of the CBA with respect to the sixty (60) day notification disputed in the instant case.</p>
<p>The remainder of the language specifying the thirty (30) day notification requirement reads &ldquo;&hellip;thereafter, the concerned member shall receive a status report, outlining the current status of the investigation and the reason requiring additional time for it, <i>every thirty (30) days</i> (emphasis added).&rdquo; If the arbitrator were to accept the Employer's interpretation of the thirty (30) day notification requirement, it would nullify this express contractual obligation. One axiom of contract instruction applicable in the instant case is that the arbitrator cannot void or nullify any provision of the labor agreement in an award. The arbitrator's authority to hear and decide a grievance dispute arises from strict adherence to the contractual provisions that underline his/her appointment. The belated thirty (30) day notifications from the IAB violated the thirty (30) day specific time limitation ingrained in Section 6.11 of the CBA.</p>
<p>There is no penalty or enforcement provision for failure to meet the contractual notification requirements in Section 6.11 of the CBA. However, the arbitrator finds that the notification requirements constitute an indispensable part of the internal affairs investigation process which enables employees to know the status of the investigation and the reasoning for requiring additional time if that is necessary. Without the ability to enforce contractual notification requirements, the IAB would in effect have wide latitude in providing notification when they, at their discretion, desire to forward such notification. This would be an unreasonable interpretation of the language engrained in Section 6.11 of the CBA.</p>
<p>Generally, most collective bargaining agreements have a void relating to arbitrable remedies. However, in the absence of language limiting the scope of a remedy in the agreement itself, arbitrators generally have broad discretion to fashion an appropriate remedy. (See <i>Gilmore Envelope Corporation</i>, 110 LA 1036, 1041 &lsqb;Ross, 1998&rsqb;). Unless the labor agreement provides otherwise, &ldquo;&hellip;the primary authority implicitly granted to the arbitrator is the authority to award specific performance of the provisions of the agreement&rdquo;. The US Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit, found that with respect to the remedial power of an arbitrator, &ldquo;The authority to decide the meaning and application of the agreement, necessarily implies&hellip;the authority to prescribe a remedy.&rdquo; <i>Dexter Axle Co. v. Machinists</i>, Dist. 90, Lodge 1315, 418 F.3d 762, 769 (7th Cir., 2005)</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>After reviewing the facts and evidence including the Affidavits presented in the instant case, the grievance is sustained in part and denied in part. The Employer did not violate Section 6.11 of the CBA with respect to the sixty (60) notification.</p>
<p>However, the Employer violated Section 6.11 of the CBA with respect to the thirty (30) day notification requirement. Accordingly, the IAB investigation involving the Grievant shall be considered closed as of March 2, 2016. The Grievant shall be informed in writing of the findings and conclusions of the investigation within five (5) days from date of this award. The arbitrator shall retain jurisdiction for thirty (30) days following the date of this award to ensure that the remedy is effectuated.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>