<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of a Controversy Between UNITED STEELWORKERS LOCAL 675, Union, And SHELL OIL PRODUCTS US, Employer.</p>
<p>Re: Warehouseperson&num;1 Higher Pay For Performing Control Lab Testing Work</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>AAA Case No. 01-14-0001-1829</p>
<p>Grievance No. C.165.006.14</p>
<p>July 28, 2015.</p>
<p>Claude Dawson Ames, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ARBITRATOR'S DECISION AND AWARD</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>I. INTRODUCTION</b></i></h4>
<p>This arbitration proceeding arises pursuant to the Articles of Agreement (&ldquo;Agreement&rdquo;) between the UNITED STEELWORKERS LOCAL 675 (&ldquo;USW&rdquo; or &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) and SHELL OIL PRODUCTS (&ldquo;Shell&rdquo; or &ldquo;Company&rdquo;), under which Claude Dawson Ames, Esq., was selected to serve as Arbitrator from a panel provided by the American Arbitration Association, and whose FINDINGS, DECISION and AWARD, shall be final and binding upon the parties. The arbitration hearing was conducted on May 28, 2015 in Carson, California.</p>
<p>Testimony of witnesses was under oath and no stenographic transcript was taken at the hearing. The parties were afforded a full opportunity to present documentary and testimonial evidence, to examine and cross-examine witnesses and for rebuttal. The parties stipulated that all procedural requirements have been complied with or waived and the matter is properly before the Arbitrator. The Union and the Employer's closing briefs were received timely on July 1, 2015 and July 8, 2015, respectively. The hearing was officially closed by the Arbitrator on July 9, 2015.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>II. STATEMENT OF CASE</b></i></h4>
<p>The Company blends and packages a range of automotive fluids, including motor oils and transmission and brake fluids at its Los Angeles Lubricants Plant. These products utilize a base oil to which chemicals and additives are introduced. Throughout the blending process, samples of the products are drawn and tested, with attention to elements such as appearance, crackle, viscosity and cold crank. When the blending process is complete, the product is staged in storage tanks pending release to a production line for packaging. The final sample test is a control lab test, which confirms the product is correctly blended. The control lab test must yield a confirmed positive result prior to the final product's release from production. Delay in conducting the control lab test delays turnover of product in the storage tanks and advancement of the product to the packaging department.</p>
<p>The parties' Agreement establishes several job classifications and corresponding hourly compensation rates. The parties stipulated that in their 1995 Agreement, in addition to those employees' other responsibilities, they added Article 3(D) requiring Warehouseperson &num; 1's to perform control lab testing. (JEx 4) The 1995 Agreement also established a new classification within the bargaining unit, a Laboratory Technician (&ldquo;Lab Tech&rdquo;). Every Agreement between the parties since 1995 has contained Article 3(D).</p>
<p>David Burgess testified that he was hired by the Company in 1974 as a Warehouseperson &num;2. After a few years he moved up the ladder and became a Warehouseperson &num;1 (Lead). At that time, he would collect product samples and take them to a lab for testing. He was never directed by management to do the control lab testing. He then became a Blender &num;1 and &num;2, and as such he collected the samples, took them to the lab and waited to be notified of the results. After he became a Lab Tech, he performed the required testing, signed off and notified the warehouse to ship the product. On or about December 31, 2012, he accepted a severance package along with three other lab techs, making the lab short handed. Mr. Burgess testified that it was the Lab Techs' duty to approve all samples. The Lab Tech performed a broader range of duties than other classifications; for example, the Lab Tech performed the appearance test, which was not performed by the Warehouseperson &num;1's.</p>
<p>David Ford testified that he was hired 17 years ago and as a Warehouseperson &num;2 and &num;1 (Lead) had never been directed by management to perform control lab testing. He was a Blender for two and a half years; as a Blender, he did not test for viscosity or crackle. That testing is performed by a Lab Tech. On one occasion as a Blender, he was directed to run the control lab testing with the help of a supervisor, and was paid the lab tech rate for four hours.</p>
<p>Saul Sanchez testified that he was hired 13 years ago and has been a Warehouseperson &num;1 for almost three years. As a Warehouseperson &num;1, he never tested samples; he took the samples to the Lab Techs. But two or three months after he became a Warehouseperson &num;1 (Lead), his supervisor, Robert Thomas, asked him to do sampling to test viscosity and cold crank. He was not paid the higher Lab Tech rate when he did the sampling. He testified he did not know if the tests he performed were control lab tests. He did these tests 12 or more times.</p>
<p>The parties stipulated that in lieu of testimony, the statement of Tim Evitts would be accepted into evidence. (U Ex. 1) His statement indicates that there were several occasions when Supervisor Joe Luna, required him to run lab tests in the morning before the lab techs arrived and during their meal periods and breaks.</p>
<p>Plant Manager Paul Hafemann testified that when Lab Techs are not available to perform the control lab tests, Warehouseperson&num;1's are asked to do so, based on Article 3D; performance of this test is part of their duties. Warehouseperson &num;1 s are not asked to perform any control lab test duties that are not within their job classification. Over time, the product line has expanded and in some cases, the duties of testing may have changed.</p>
<p>Quality and Control Manager James McGinnis testified that a sample test is a type of test which verifies the product description and is a control lab test. This is the last test performed before the product is shipped to the customer. There is a distinction in the job responsibilities between the Warehouseperson &num;1 &lsquo;s and the Lab Techs, in that only the Lab Tech can release and ship the product. The Warehouseperson &num;1 can release the product but can not authorize it to be shipped. The test done by the Warehouseperson &num;1 is the easier of two things to do because the product can be released to run based on the test, but cannot be released for shipping.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>III. RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF THE PARTIES' AGREEMENT</b></i></h4>
<p>This arbitration proceeding is brought pursuant to the parties' Agreement (J Ex. 1):</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ARTICLE 3. Employee Duties</b></i></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">A. Employees are expected to perform any duties to which they are assigned. Ordinarily, such assignments shall be within the employee's particular classification, but an employee may be temporarily assigned to work in a classification other than his or her regular classification.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">D. Blender &num;1's and Warehouseperson &num;1's, among other responsibilities, will be required to perform control lab testing.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ARTICLE 5. Job Classifications and Wage Rates</b></i></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">A. Employees under this Agreement shall be paid at an hourly rate. The classifications covered by this Agreement and the hourly rates for each of these classifications are contained in Appendix &ldquo;A&rdquo;, which is attached hereto and made a part thereof.</p>
<p class="continued">B. When an employees performs work in a higher rated classification, the employee shall receive the higher rate of pay for only those hours worked in the higher rated classification. When an employee temporarily works in a lower rated classification, he or she shall receive his or her regular rate of pay.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ARTICLE 11. Seniority and Layoffs</b></i></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">L. In accordance with Article 3 &ndash; Employee Duties, Paragraph A of this Agreement, temporary vacancies in any classification that the Company desires to fill, will be filled by qualified, interested employees from the next lower classification in order of department seniority. The junior qualified employee will be required to take the temporary vacancy if all other qualified employees in the next lower classification decline the temporary vacancy. If qualified employees are not available from the next lower classification, the vacancy may be filled from the next higher classification in inverse order of department seniority.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>APPENDIX &ldquo;A&rdquo;</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>WAGE RATES- LUBRICANTS COMPANY</b></i></h4>
<table width="585" columns="1">
<tr>
<td width="40%"><p></p></td>
<td width="40%"><p></p></td>
<td width="10%"><p></p></td>
<td width="10%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p><b>Job Classification</b><br/>&hellip;</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p><b>2/1/2013</b></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>&hellip;</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>&hellip;</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Blender &num;1: After 1 year</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>&dollar;29.68</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Warehouseperson &num;1</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>&dollar;28.72</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Warehouseperson &num;2 After 48 months</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>&dollar;27.63</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Technician (Laboratory)</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>&dollar;31.42</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
</tr>
</table>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>APPENDIX &ldquo;B&rdquo;</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>PROMOTIONAL CHART</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>PROMOTIONAL CHART LUBES BUSINESS UNIT</b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>MANUFACTURING</b></p>
<p class="continued">TECHNICIAN (LABORATORY)</p>
<p class="continued">BLENDER &num;1</p>
<p class="continued">WAREHOUSEPERSON</p>
<p class="continued">WAREHOUSEPERSON &num;2</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>IV. ISSUES PRESENTED</i></b></h4>
<p>The parties, having been unable to agree upon the framing of the issue for resolution, stipulated that the Arbitrator may frame the issue.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i>The Union frames the issue as follows:</i></p>
<p class="continued">Did the Company violate Article 5(B) of the Collective Bargaining Agreement between USW Local 675 and Shell (&ldquo;the CBA&rdquo;)?</p>
<p class="continued"><i>The Employer frames the issue as follows:</i></p>
<p class="continued">Whether the Company honored the Agreement by paying employees in the Warehouseperson &num;1 job classification the contractual wage rate applicable to their Warehouseperson &num;1 job classification for the performance of control lab testing duties specifically designated in the Agreement as within the scope of work of that classification. And if not, what is the remedy?</p></blockquote>
<p>The Arbitrator, after review of the evidence and the parties' arguments, adopts the issue as framed by the Union.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>V. POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. <i>Union's Position:</i></b></h4>
<p>The Employer would have the arbitrator ignore express language requiring higher pay for temporary work in higher classifications. Such provisions are commonplace in collective bargaining situations and entirely consistent with wage and hour laws that require payment of higher wages for temporary work in higher classifications. The Union prays that the Arbitrator instruct the Company to apply common sense and basic fairness so as to read the relevant language of Article 3(D) in conjunction with the relevant language in Article 5(B) as there is no evidence that the bargaining parties intended to do away with the requirements of higher pay for temporary work at any time relevant to this matter. There is nothing inconsistent between requiring temporary work in higher classifications, and at the same time, making sure that such work is compensated in accordance with the collectively-bargained pay schedules. There is no exception to the temporary-upgrade language in Article 5(B) that permits the temporary lab testing work in Article 3(D) to be done without the higher pay &ndash; and no evidence was presented that showed that the parties intended to create an exception here, as the Company incorrectly argues. The Union's grievance should be granted.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. <i>Employer's Position:</i></b></h4>
<p>The Agreement requires that the Company pay employees at their classification rate for hours worked on duties within their classification. Article 3(D) defines control lab testing as a Warehouseperson &num;1 duty. The plain language of the Agreement compels denial of the grievance.</p>
<p>The fact that the higher rated Laboratory Technician classification also performs control lab testing takes this grievance no further. The parties added control lab testing to the duties of the Warehouseperson &num;1 classification in 1995 simultaneously with creation of the Lab Tech classification. Control lab tests are a subset of the product sample tests regularly performed by the Lab Techs. Control test duties were added to the Warehouseperson &num;1 classification to ensure a qualified employee would be able to perform the test and release the product to the packaging lines whenever a Lab Tech was not immediately available, avoiding costly delays. For the grievance to be sustained, the Union must prove that control lab testing duties were not appropriate to the Warehouseperson &num;1 classification. Given the clear, unambiguous language of Article 3(D), this argument is foreclosed and the grievance must be denied. Admitted increases in the type and frequency of control lab testing performed by Warehouseperson &num;1's did not breach the Agreement. Since 1995 the Company has exercised its managerial authority under Article 3(D) in the same consistent manner: Lab Techs perform control lab testing whenever possible and Warehouseperson &num;1's are required to perform these tests only when a Lab Tech is unavailable. Warehouseperson &num;1's have not and do not perform any other product sampling testing.</p>
<p>The Union's misplaced reliance on Article 5(B) does not change the fact that the clear, unambiguous language of Article 3(D) disposes of this grievance. Article 5(B) has no application to this case since there is nothing temporary about the 20-year requirement that Warehouseperson &num;1s perform lab testing. In addition, Warehouseperson&num;1's are ineligible for temporary assignments to the higher rated Lab Tech classification by the criteria established in Article 11(L). There is no language in the Agreement exempting Warehouseperson &num;1's from the requirements of that article. An exception could have been written into Article 3(D) had the parties mutually intended Warehouseperson &num;1's to receive the Lab Tech rate for control lab testing work.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>VI. DECISION</i></b></h4>
<p>At issue in this matter is whether the Company violated Article 5(B) of the parties' Agreement by failing to compensates bargaining unit members in the Warehouseperson &num;1 classification for time spent performing control lab testing duties during the manufacture of the Company's products at the Los Angeles Lubricants Plant. The Company denies violating the Agreement and maintains that performing control lab testing is part of the Warehouseperson&num;1's job classification. After a careful and thorough review and analysis of the Agreement, testimonial evidence presented and the parties' post-hearing arguments, it is found by the Arbitrator that the Union has not sustained its burden of proof by a preponderance of the evidence of a contractual violation as alleged.</p>
<p>In a case involving an issue of contract interpretation, the task before the Arbitrator is to determine the intent of the parties when they came to their agreement on a particular matter involving the terms and conditions of employment for the bargaining unit members. To this end, the relevant contract language must first be examined to determine whether that language is sufficiently clear (plain meaning) and unambiguous such that it may be concluded that the contract language accurately and completely demonstrates the parties' agreement. Only if the language is found to be ambiguous will the Arbitrator look outside the Agreement to other evidence of the parties' intentions such as, to reflect the parties' bargaining history or the parties' past practice on the issue. In order to interpret the parties' intent, the contractual Agreement must be construed as a whole, with proper effect given to all relevant words and clauses. Basic rules of contract construction requires that an arbitrator interpret the provisions in a contract in such a way to harmonize the language where ever possible. Further, arbitral authority supports the premise that when the agreed-upon language is clear and unambiguous, an arbitrator lacks the authority to alter or add to the parties' Agreement. In the instant case, it is the Arbitrator's duty to identify and enforce the agreement previously bargained by the parties, rather than to rewrite their Agreement.</p>
<p>Here, the plain language of the parties' contract is sufficiently clear and unambiguous to resolve the parties' dispute without resort to parole evidence. The Union relies upon Article 5(B) of the Agreement for its position, which indicates: &ldquo;When an employee performs work in a higher rated classification, the employee shall receive the higher rate of pay for only those hours worked in the higher rated classification.&rdquo; It then argues, that the Company has required Warehouseperson &num;1's to perform the job duties of a higher rated classification, i.e., Laboratory Technician, without compensating the Warehouseperson &num;1 at the higher Lab Tech pay rate. There is no factual dispute between these parties that the Lab Tech classification is a higher-rated class, based upon the pay rates of the two classifications contained in Appendix A of the parties' Agreement. The dispute arises over whether performance of control lab testing is &ldquo;work in a higher rated classification&rdquo; which would trigger application of Article 5(B) and require the Company to pay a Warehouseperson &num;1 at the Laboratory Technician rate. The Company argues, and the evidence record supports a finding, that the job duty of control lab testing is &ldquo;work&rdquo; performed &ldquo;in&rdquo; <i>both</i> the job classifications of Warehouseperson &num;1 and Laboratory Technician, rather than work contained solely in the higher Lab Tech classification.</p>
<p>To this end, the language of Article 5 must be read in conjunction with Article 3 of the Agreement. Article 3(A) states: &ldquo;Employees are expected to perform any duties to which they are assigned. Ordinarily, such assignments shall be within the employee's particular classification, but an employee may be temporarily assigned to work in a classification other than his or her regular classification.&rdquo; Moreover, <b>Article 3(D)</b> does clearly state: <b>&ldquo;Blender &num;1's and Warehouseperson &num;1's, among other responsibilities, will be required to perform control lab testing.&rdquo;</b> If Warehouseperson &num;1's were to be paid an additional premium to perform control lab testing as they now argue, then it should have been negotiated and expressly stated in their Agreement.</p>
<p>The contractual language of the Agreement indicates that the &ldquo;work&rdquo; or job duty of performance of control lab testing is work assigned to the classification of Warehouseperson &num;1. The Union cannot now argue that completion of that task takes the Warehouseperson &num;1 outside of his or her classification, and places him or her in the higher paying Lab Tech class. The evidence supports a finding that the language of Article 3(D) has been present in the parties' Agreement since the 1995 contract and that the Company's management has occasionally required Warehouseperson &num;1's to perform control lab testing to fill in when a Lab Tech is unavailable. Since the classification of Lab Tech was created in 1995 at the same time Article 3(D) began to require that Warehouseperson &num;1's perform control lab testing as part of their responsibilities, it has not been shown by the evidence record, that performance of that testing was ever solely a duty performed by Lab Techs.</p>
<p>In addition, the language of Article 3(D) adding performance of the control lab testing to the duties of the Warehouseperson &num;1 classification has not been shown to have changed since 1995 and that language does not contain any limitations upon the circumstances under which a Warehouseperson &num;1 is required to perform such testing. It is merely one of the responsibilities of the classification. There being no stated exceptions to the requirement that a Warehouseperson &num;1 perform control lab testing, any admitted increases in the type and frequency of control lab testing asked of the Warehouseperson &num;1's do not violate the language of Article 3(D). It is noted that testimony from Quality and Control Manager James McGinnis demonstrates that the control lab testing is a subset of the various sample lab tests performed by the Lab Tech classification and the responsibility to authorize the shipment of product passing the final control lab testing remains with the Lab Tech. Further, the evidence record indicates that the Warehouseperson &num;1's are only asked to step in and perform the control lab testing when a lab tech is unavailable. Such practice supports the efficiency of the Plant in that delay in the completion of this final testing would delay release of product from the storage tanks in the production arm of the plant to the packaging lines.</p>
<p>It is noted that if the parties had mutually intended that Warehouseperson &num;1's should receive the higher Lab Tech pay rate for their time spent performing control lab tests, in spite of the fact that Article 3(D) states that performing that test is work required of Warehouseperson &num;1's, their Agreement could contain specific language so stating, either in Article 3 or 5.</p>
<p>As a final matter, the Company argues that Article 11 of the parties' Agreement supports its position in this matter. Article 11(L) indicates: &ldquo;In accordance with Article 3&hellip; temporary vacancies in any classification that the Company desires to fill, will be filled by qualified, interested employees from the next lower classification in order of department seniority. The junior qualified employee will be required to take the temporary vacancy if all other qualified employees in the next lower classification decline the temporary vacancy. If qualified employees are not available from the next lower classification, the vacancy may be filled from the next higher classification in inverse order of department seniority.&rdquo; It is found that Article 3(D) directly addresses and resolves the parties' dispute, without the need to refer to Article 11(L). Article 5(B), upon which the Union also relies in its argument, does not restrict an employees' work in a &ldquo;higher rated classification&rdquo; to temporary work. It does speak to an employee &ldquo;temporarily&rdquo; working in a lower rated classification, but that is not the case before this Arbitrator. While, on its face, Article 11(L) is not inconsistent with Article 3 or Article 5, it is not dispositive here, since as the Company points out, it provides that temporary vacancies will be filled by employees from the next-lower classification and Warehouseperson &num;1 is not the next-lower classification to Laboratory Technician. Being asked to perform control lab testing before the Lab Tech arrives in the morning or when the Lab Tech is on break is not a &ldquo;temporary&rdquo; vacancy in the Lab Tech classification contemplated by Article 1 1 (L) and this Arbitrator does not rely on Article 11(L) in making his determination here.</p>
<p>Based upon the above-stated analysis, even when the factual evidence and the parties' arguments are viewed in a light most favorable to the Union, and even when reading relevant language of Article 3(D) in conjunction with the language of Article 5(B), the Union has not shown that the Company has violated the parties' Agreement and the grievance is therefore denied.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Company did not violate the Agreement by requiring Grievants to perform Lab test consistent with their job classification. The Union's grievance is hereby denied.</p></blockquote>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>