<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION BETWEEN LAW ENFORCEMENT LABOR SERVICES LOCAL 123 OFFICERS AND DETECTIVES and THE CITY OF RICHFIELD</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>BMS 16-PA-0975</p>
<p>December 28, 2016.</p>
<p>Charlotte Neigh, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="left">OPINION AND AWARD</h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>JURISDICTION AND PROCEDURE</b></h4>
<p class="continued">Pursuant to the parties&rsquo; Labor Agreement and the procedures of the Minnesota Bureau of Mediation Services, Charlotte Neigh was appointed to arbitrate this matter. A hearing was held in Richfield at which time both parties had a full opportunity to offer evidence. The parties filed posthearing briefs by the agreed date and the record was closed.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>ISSUE AS STATED BY THE PARTIES</b></h4>
<p class="continued">Did the Employer have just cause to terminate the Grievant's employment with the Richfield Police Department?</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>PERTINENT AUTHORITY</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>LABOR AGREEMENT ARTICLE 9. DISCIPLINE</b></h4>
<p class="continued">9.2 The Employer will discipline non-probationary Employees for just cause only. Discipline will be in one or more of the following forms: (a) documented oral reprimand; (b) written reprimand; (c) suspension with or without pay; (d) demotion; or (e) discharge.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>BACKGROUND</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The City of Richfield is an inner-ring suburb bordered by Minneapolis to the north, MSP International Airport to the east, Bloomington to the south, and Edina to the west. Its form of government gives the City Manager authority over all employees, including the Chief of Police. The Richfield Police Department (RPD) command staff comprises a chief, a deputy chief, three lieutenants and several sergeants, overseeing approximately 26 patrol officers (POs) among other officers and support staff. The Grievant was employed as a PO since February 2006; he was a member of the Swat Team, a field training officer (FTO), and a fire-arms trainer. In March 2012 he became one of two canine officers in a newly created special assignment.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant's employment was terminated after an internal investigation into an incident that occurred on October 3, 2015, resulting in allegations that he had: violated his training and expected conduct; used excessive force beyond his authority and training; and failed to properly document or report his contact with the subject. Whether the Grievant's conduct regarding that incident constitutes just cause to terminate his employment requires detailed analysis of the event, which was captured to some extent by: a video from the squad camera synched with an audio recording from the microphone worn by the Grievant; and a 36-second cell-phone video recorded by a witness. Not everything on the audio is clearly intelligible and it is sometimes not possible to determine what is being said. The transcript created by the RPD contains some typographical errors and some other errors found by careful listening. These sources, as well as information developed by an investigation by the Bureau of Criminal Apprehension (BCA) and the Internal Affairs (IA) investigation constitute the evidence of the occurrence.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>OCTOBER 3, 2015 EVENT</b></h4>
<p class="continued">On October 3, 2015, at approximately 6:15 p.m. Dispatch received a call from a Richfield resident who reported that: there were more than 50 Somalis in the park, getting into cars and driving crazy on the roads/almost hit (the reporter) while walking her dog. The Grievant drove his K-9 squad to the park and another PO (PO2) drove a separate squad. They approached from different directions and PO2 entered the park and talked with some of the people there. The Grievant was driving along the eastern edge of the park behind a pickup truck that had to brake sharply on a curve to avoid two vehicles close together coming from the other direction. The Grievant activated his lights and pulled into the oncoming lane to obstruct the two vehicles. The squad video camera was automatically activated at 6:30 p.m. and the microphone on the Grievant's body was synched to the video.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant approached the first vehicle (V1) and told the driver (D1) he had been called because of the way &ldquo;you guys were driving like idiots&rdquo;. D1 was a nearly 20-year-old Somali with three Somali passengers. He denied having been driving around the neighborhood, and he denied knowing the driver (D2) of the second vehicle (V2). In response to the request for a driver license (DL) and proof of insurance, D1 said his DL was at home and he didn't know where the proof of insurance was.</p>
<p class="continued">V2 was occupied by one Somali passenger (P2) and D2, a nearly 16-year-old Somali, who also denied knowing D1 and was unable to produce a DL or proof of insurance; he claimed to have a driving permit but not with him. By communicating with Dispatch the Grievant learned that D2's permit had been revoked. The Grievant warned both drivers that if they could not prove insurance the cars would have to be towed and both drivers used their cell phones to try to come up with insurance information.</p>
<p class="continued">During this initial conversation: D2 repeatedly tried to argue about whether he had been driving too fast or following too closely rather than respond to the request for a DL and insurance proof; D2 said he had not been in the park and had picked up his passenger elsewhere; subsequently he said he picked his passenger up in the park; the Grievant ascertained that neither occupant of the car resided in Richfield; the Grievant could not get a straight answer regarding why they were in Richfield or why so many had gathered in the park; P2 denied associating with the 50 people in the park, claiming to have been &ldquo;just by myself&rdquo;. After approximately six minutes into the stop, the Grievant said &ldquo;Jesus Christ, you guys ever tell the fucking truth one day in your life &hellip; if you can't prove the insurance, I'm towing the car, ok, so fucking find it&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant returned to D1, asking again for proof of insurance, ascertaining that none of the occupants lived in the City, and asking why they were here, where they were coming from, and which ones had been in the park. The response was that none of them had been in the park and they had just come into the area. The Grievant said &ldquo;Jesus Christ you guys are so full of shit I can't believe it&rdquo; and recited the contradictory statements that led him to believe they were lying to him.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant communicated with Dispatch to ascertain the license status of the two drivers and reported the driving violations that he had witnessed and that &ldquo;They are all lying&rdquo; about why they're here and where they're going and whether they were in the park, and there's no reason to lie about just hanging out in the park.</p>
<p class="continued">About 14 minutes into the stop the Grievant returned to D2 to get proof of insurance. He told D2 that: his permit had been revoked, he could not be driving anywhere, he needed to get a licensed driver to drive his car or it wasn't going anywhere, and if he couldn't prove insurance the car would be towed, so he should keep trying to come up with proof of insurance.</p>
<p class="continued">About 20 minutes into the stop the Grievant returned to D1 and gave him a ticket for careless driving &ldquo;for nearly causing an accident&rdquo;. D1 expressed concern that this will &ldquo;go on my license&rdquo; and the Grievant told him &ldquo;don't drive like an idiot&rsquo;, to which D1 said &ldquo;I wasn't driving like an idiot&rdquo;. The Grievant said: &ldquo;I watched you nearly cause an accident because you were speeding around a corner. The time for arguing is done. You want to take it to court and we can talk about it in front of a judge&hellip; but we are not going to discuss it anymore. You can carefully drive away from here ok I don't want to see you back in the City again. I should be towing your car&rdquo;. D1 argued about being excluded from the City. The Grievant clarified &ldquo;not tonight&rdquo;. D1 argued that he has cousins who live there and the Grievant then told them to get out of the car and it was going to be towed. D1 argued and the Grievant explained: &ldquo;For careless driving I can tow your car, I am giving you a break, I'm saying I don't want to see you again tonight driving around my City like an idiot. OK, it does not require an argument it requires a yes sir and drive away carefully. Can you do that?&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant then returned to D2 trying to get the name of his mother for the ticket information. D2 resumed asking what he did wrong and why he was pulled over. D2 was talking to his mother on his cell phone to give her directions on how to get to him while the Grievant was trying to get information from him. D2 said that he had located a licensed driver for his car, indicating one of the three young males sitting on the curb behind his car being monitored by PO2 who had previously arrived to support the traffic stop and taken charge of three Somalis who approached on foot from the park. Regarding insurance, D2 said he couldn't get the proof from his e-mail because his internet connection was too slow. The Grievant warned him again that he needs to &ldquo;figure out a way to get it&rdquo; or the car is going to be towed.</p>
<p class="continued">Although two and a half minutes had passed since D1 was told to drive away, he had not moved. The Grievant returned to his window and told him &ldquo;You need to leave now ok, drive around my squad car, it's time to go&rdquo;. V1 moved away and the Grievant repositioned his squad to be closer to V2. The Grievant returned to his squad to work on the second traffic ticket and as he was exiting, he saw D1 and his passengers approaching on foot along the edge of the street, four minutes after their car moved away. As the Grievant walked toward V2 he said loud enough for D1 to hear: &ldquo;Hey I thought that you weren't coming to the park &hellip;you didn't know anything about the park&rdquo;. As he continued walking away he muttered: &ldquo;You guys never told the fucking truth ever in your life, none of you fuckers&rdquo;. The Grievant then asked D2 about proof of insurance, how long it would be before his mother arrived, and which of the guys on the curb was his cousin with a license. He then went to the rear of V2 to speak with PO2 and the other potential driver.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant then started walking the approximately 50-foot distance to where D1 and his passengers were, along the edge of the park, about 15 feet from the Grievant's squad, and the following exchange occurred:</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant</i>: <i>Thought you didn't know anything about the park and were just driving around</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: Well you just gave me a ticket that is going to go on my license</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Oh I'm sorry. Don't drive like an asshole and you won't get tickets</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: (unintelligible)</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Don't blame me, blame yourself</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: I'm not blaming you, I'm just saying (unintelligible)</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Oh you gave me a ticket and it's going on my insurance. Tough shit. Don't drive like an asshole</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: I am just saying that you gave me a ticket (unintelligible)</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: You're right I did. You're lucky I didn't tow your car too</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: What are you going to tow my car for? What did I do, man?</i></p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Careless driving. Do I need to explain it again?</i>.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>36-Second Video Combined with Transcript From Body Microphone</b></h4>
<p class="continued">At about this time a 36-second video recording was made by D2, showing the Grievant and D1 on the grass near the street. D1 is trailing several feet behind the rest of his group with his cell phone to his left ear as they are headed toward the path to the park. D1 is facing toward the path and the Grievant is facing his right side. Their location was out of the view of the squad camera, so the evidence is a combination of D2's video and the audio from the Grievant's body microphone. The video shows the Grievant and D1 talking as the Grievant gestures back down the street toward the corner where V1 had headed.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: Where is my car now?</i></p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: I'm guessing around the corner. It's not going to take that much to figure it out</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1 (on cell): (unintelligible) yeah hello</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Move along</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">D1 is standing still and as the Grievant is talking he points repeatedly in the direction D1 was heading into the park. His voice gets increasingly loud as he repeats the instruction to move along and he is shouting at the group by the time the confrontation ends.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1 (on cell): This bitch ass cop just gave me a ticket, man</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Move along. Keep running your mouth, it's going to get worse. Move along</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: He gave me a ticket for some fucking whatchamacallit</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">D1 saunters a few small steps forward then stops. The Grievant approaches and points again.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Move along</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant then uses his left hand to push in the area of D1's right shoulder blade and D1 stumbles three or four steps forward and to his left, somewhat down hill, then stops and turns slightly toward the Grievant.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: Quit pushing me (?) (unintelligible)</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Then move when I tell you to</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: (unintelligible) I will move. This is a public place (unintelligible)</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: And we are working right here, now fucking move</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: I'm talking to my (brother? unintelligible) to pick up the car</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">D1 keeps his feet planted where he stopped while he argues with the Grievant. The Grievant again approaches D1, points with his right hand, and slaps his left hand upward on the right rear of D1's head, glancing over the top of his head. This causes the head to jerk forward but does not propel D1's body forward until another shove on the back from the Grievant's left hand causes him to stumble a few steps forward and down hill as the video ends.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>After 36-Second Video Ends</b></h4>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Move now. Move now, go!</i></p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: Are you kidding me?</i></p>
<p class="continued">Various voices can be heard as there is general commotion from the group.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Get the fuck out of here</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">More commotion from the group can be heard. The following statement by the Grievant was inaccurate in the RPD transcription later cited by the Internal Affairs Investigator even though it had been correctly transcribed in the BCA report. The Grievant testified at the hearing that his next statement was in response to some indication from others in the group that they were about to engage with him. This claim is supported by D1's reported statement to the media that after he was hit and shoved, &ldquo;his friends then approached the officer&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Do you all want to go? I'll fuck every one of you fuckers up, move along we're working here</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">Upon hearing the Grievant's raised voice, and after dismissing the three Somalis he had been holding on the curb, PO2 had moved closer to where the Grievant was engaged with D1 and he helped to shepherd the group down the path toward the park. Less than two minutes after confrontating D1, the Grievant returned to D2 and calmly inquired about his mother's location.</p>
<p class="continued">D1's group was lingering near the top of the path and both POs moved closer to them. One of them said something about having &ldquo;got you on video&rdquo;. The Grievant said: &ldquo;You need to move, now, what did I tell you, you guys need to move along now&rdquo;. The group was moving slowly toward the park with one voice saying &ldquo;Let's go&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: You cannot stay here when we're trying to work. We told you to move along, now go, stop standing here and talking and go, everyone of you, go!</i></p>
<p class="continued"><i>D1: You can't fucking hit me though, all right nigga, you got some anger issues</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Another voice: We got you on camera</i>.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Grievant: Move, go</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant then returned to D2 asking what kind of car his mother was driving, and then was approached by neighbors who were concerned about the large gathering and the driving behavior. After reassuring the neighbors that the group had a right to hang out in the park and they could call again if there was any troublesome conduct, the Grievant returned to D2 and noticed that he had Snapchat on his cell phone and said: &ldquo;So you don't have enough internet connection to get on your e-mail, but you can get on Snapchat &hellip; seems a little bit backwards&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">Approximately seven minutes after D1's group was herded down the path, they were coming back up. PO2 approached them and pointed, as he explained in his testimony, to indicate that they should cross the edge of the park on the other side of the trees so as not to get too close again to the scene of the traffic stop.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant instructed D2 to park the car and wait for his mother. He said he was issuing only a ticket for driving after revocation and not for the driving conduct. He cautioned D2 not to drive and said that if he caught him driving again that night he would tow the car. The Grievant also told D2 that his polite remarks should have come at the start of their encounter which didn't need to be a fight, and that coming on with an attitude only makes things worse.</p>
<p class="continued">The squad video ended at 19:11:46, approximately 42 minutes after the stop began.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>After the Stop</b></h4>
<p class="continued">At 7:26 p.m. the Grievant inquired of his Sergeant whether a case number was required for this careless driving citation and learned that it was not but he should &ldquo;put notes in the tag&rdquo;. He made notations on his copy of the two citations, which he testified is his usual practice to help him recall an event if he later needs to testify about it. On D2's citation he wrote: &ldquo;FOLLOWING CAR TOO CLOSELY NEARLY CRASHED AROUND CURVE&bull;DRIVER UNABLE TO PRODUCE INS&bull;CLAIMED TO HAVE PERMIT&bull;MOTHER CAME TO DRIVE CAR&rdquo;. On D1's citation he wrote: &ldquo;SPEEDING AWAY FROM ADAMS HILL PARK (CALLED HERE BECAUSE OF THIS ISSUE)&bull;NEARLY CAUSED ACCIDENT DUE TO CARELESS DRIVING AT THE CURVE OF 73/VINCENT PICKUP TRUCK IN FRONT OF ME HAD TO SLAM ON BRAKES TO AVOID COLLISION&bull;ALL OCCUPANTS THEN WALKED UP ON ME LATER TRYING TO CAUSE TROUBLE&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant finished his shift about midnight and left without reporting this incident. He was not on duty the next day due to a K-9 demonstration and comp time.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>SUBSEQUENT DEVELOPMENTS</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>Week of October 5, 2015</b></h4>
<p class="continued">On Monday, October 5, the command staff received inquiries from reporters regarding a 20-second video on Twitter, showing an officer shoving and hitting D1. This was D2's video minus the first 16 seconds. The command staff eventually got access to the Twitter video and recognized the Grievant. In addition to calls from the media, the Chief received a call from the head of the Somali Human Rights Commission (SHRC), characterizing the event as an &ldquo;assault&rdquo; and demanding a meeting for himself and other members of the Somali community.</p>
<p class="continued">A search for a report produced only the citations and so the command staff was unable to respond meaningfully to the inquiries it was receiving. Multiple media outlets reported the incident, showing the Twitter video and including claims made by D1 and D2 that did not accurately portray the situation as ultimately shown by the evidence. This led to calls and e-mails from concerned citizens outraged by the apparent police brutality, criticizing the RPD and demanding severe action against the Grievant.</p>
<p class="continued">The meeting demanded by the SHRC occurred on October 6 and included D1 and his parents, his attorney, the SHRC head and approximately 20 others. They were placated by the Chief's show of concern and his informing them that: he was referring the matter to the BCA for a criminal investigation; and both POs were being placed on administrative leave. The Chief testified that he subsequently stayed in close contact with the SHRC head to keep him informed of developments.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Hennepin County Attorney Disposition of BCA Referral</b></h4>
<p class="continued">Upon completion of its investigation, the BCA referred its file to the Office of the Hennepin County Attorney to review for the crimes of Terroristic Threats (felony), Misconduct of a Public Official (gross misdemeanor), and Assault (misdemeanor). This Office's authority is limited to felony charges and so it considered only the potential charge of Terroristic Threats and determined that the Grievant's actions did not constitute that charge. The Office declined to charge the Grievant and suggested that a review of potential gross misdemeanor or misdemeanor charges would have to be done by the city attorney.</p>
<p class="continued">Regarding Terroristic Threats, the Office reasoned that: the statute requires a threat to commit a crime of violence with purpose to terrorize another or in reckless disregard of causing such terror; although the Grievant admitted making the statement about &ldquo;fucking every one of you fuckers up&rdquo;, he stated that he did not intend to instill fear but rather to try to control the situation; although D1 claimed during an interview on October 8 that he was &ldquo;personally scared because of the people that'd been dying because of the Black Lives Matter program and all that and so I was personally scared for my own life&rdquo;, he did not report the incident at the time it occurred and made no such claim until after the investigation was initiated. The Office concluded: &ldquo;Most importantly, the statements and actions of (the Grievant) in this incident do not constitute threats to commit felony crimes of violence.&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Special Prosecutor Disposition of BCA Referral</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The City Prosecutor declined, as a conflict of interest, to handle this matter and recommended referring it to a Special Prosecutor to review the BCA file for misdemeanor or gross misdemeanor violations by the two POs. The Special Prosecutor found &ldquo;nothing &hellip; that would indicate (PO2) was guilty of any violation &hellip;&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">Regarding the Grievant, the Special Prosecutor found &ldquo;it would not be possible to prove (him) guilty of any criminal violation beyond a reasonable doubt.&rdquo; He found that the Grievant &ldquo;did not knowingly act in excess of his lawful authority &hellip; in that he was obviously of the belief he was performing legitimate police duties as he understood them&rdquo;; and &ldquo;it could not be proven beyond a reasonable doubt that (the Grievant) unlawfully injured another person based upon the evidence &hellip;&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">The Special Prosecutor reasoned that a jury could not be convinced that the Grievant's actions constituted assault in the fifth degree, which requires an intentional infliction or attempt to inflict bodily harm because: &ldquo;his actions could be construed as ones to enforce his order for (D1) and others with him, to clear the area where the traffic stop investigation was continuing with another driver&rdquo;; and &ldquo;furthermore, &hellip; it could not be proven beyond a reasonable doubt that (the Grievant) inflicted bodily harm on (D1) in that (D1) said that he was not injured and there were no signs of injury or bruising to (D1). Although (D1) states that he had a headache the rest of the day, there is no shown causal connection between the slap to the side and rear of his head and the reported headache.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">The Special Prosecutor declined to file any misdemeanor or gross misdemeanor criminal charges against either PO.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>INTERNAL AFFAIRS INVESTIGATION</b></h4>
<p class="continued">After learning that no criminal charges would be filed, the Chief directed one of the Lieutenants to conduct an internal affairs (IA) investigation. A 12/16/15 notice mailed to the Grievant states that he is being investigated for misconduct, specifically during the 10/3/15 traffic stop, he: made contact with the group of occupants of V1 after they returned on foot; used profanity; pushed one of the males, then struck him in the back of the head; and failed to make any report regarding this use of force. The notice listed the departmental policies that had potentially been violated as: General Standards of Conduct; Direction; Employee Speech; Impartial Policing; Special Incident Review; Use of Force; and Liabilities Associated with Use of Force. The Grievant was ordered not to discuss the investigation with anyone other than his representative or the investigating Lieutenant (Investigator).</p>
<p class="continued">The Investigator sent certified letters in an attempt to schedule interviews with six witnesses who had been identified through the BCA investigation: D1, D2, and their passengers. The only response was from an attorney representing D1, who agreed to an interview.</p>
<p class="continued">Present during D1's interview were: his attorney; his parents; and an outside attorney representing the City. The interview was recorded and a transcription as well as a summary of selected statements were included in the Investigator's report. It is noted that D1's description of events differs from some facts established by the evidence. The Investigator also took statements, which were transcribed, from the Sergeant who had been leading the Grievant's team, PO2 and the Grievant. About one month after the Grievant's interview, the Investigator sent him an e-mail inquiring about his conversation with D2 regarding Snapchat, and in a follow-up e-mail he inquired about the Grievant's knowledge about Snapchat. The Grievant responded to these inquiries.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Internal Affairs Findings</b></h4>
<p class="continued">In his Finding of Fact No. 1, the Investigator sustained the allegation that the Grievant's conduct violated his training and the conduct reasonably expected of a Richfield police officer, citing: the Grievant's training; and his use of profane and abusive language &ldquo;throughout the approximate 42 minute traffic stop&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">Finding No. 2 sustained the allegation that the Grievant used excessive force with D1 beyond his authority and training, citing: his training; the absence of active resistance by D1; his unnecessary and unprofessional level of anger; and contradictions between the Grievant's statements and his training.</p>
<p class="continued">Finding No. 3 sustained the allegation that the Grievant failed to properly document or report his contact with D1, citing: the Grievant's knowledge of the required use-of-force reporting procedure; the Grievant's statement that he had considered writing a CYA (cover your ass) report; and the Grievant's opportunity to inform his Sergeant during the shift, which would have led the Sergeant to direct the writing of a report and to inform the Command Staff of the incident. The Investigator concluded that &ldquo;Not completing any reports of the incident creates an appearance that (the Grievant) was trying to cover up his actions&rdquo;. The Investigator also notes that: PO2 knew that the occupants of V2 were videotaping the incident and notified the Grievant of this; the Grievant was told &ldquo;We got you on camera&rdquo; by one of D1's group; the two POs discussed whether PO2's squad camera had been operating; and the Grievant stated that he was concerned about how the video taken by the occupants of V2 would look.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Policies Violated</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Investigator found that the Grievant's conduct had violated: the Mission Statement; the Oath of Office; Policy #103-Conduct Unbecoming; Policy #104-General Standards of Conduct; Policy #105-Direction; Policy #108-Employee Speech; Policy #136-Impartial Policing; Policy #138-Special Incident Review; Policy #201-Use of Force; Policy &num; 206-Liabilities Associated with Use of Force.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Investigation Conclusions</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Investigator noted that:</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant had been counseled four times since August 3, 2011, including reporting issues related to use of force.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant had received a Documented Oral Reprimand (DOR) in January 2013 for &ldquo;overly excessive strikes to the head and lack of details in his report to justify his actions&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant had been required to go through extensive remedial training on use of force and proper documentation when using force.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The squad video and the Twitter video &ldquo;reveal (the Grievant) to be an angry, easily frustrated officer who continues to use excessive force despite supervisory efforts to coach him, provide extensive remedial training, and discipline him&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">The Investigator's most extensive remarks relate to the Grievant's failure to report the incident:</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; &ldquo;It is extremely troubling that (the Grievant) failed to report the incident&rdquo; either by a written or oral report; the Grievant was told twice by one of the males at the scene that the incident was on video and PO2 advised the Grievant that it was on video; the Grievant considered filing a report but did not; the only report of the incident was the traffic citation &ldquo;with a few cryptic notes&rdquo; and no mention of his use of force.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's explanation, that the incident didn't fit any of the boxes on the form designated for a special incident report, doesn't explain why he didn't: &ldquo;pull an ICR, complete a report, or even a supplemental report&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant commented that he was concerned that on video the incident would look &ldquo;worse than it was&rdquo;; he thought of doing a CYA report &ldquo;just in case &hellip; anything would come of it down the road&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Based on a conversation the Grievant had with D2, it is reasonable to conclude that he assumed the video would never be discovered because he thought it had been sent on Snapchat and so would be automatically deleted;</p>
<p class="continued">The Investigator concluded that:</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's profane language and demeanor throughout the call is problematic, and coupled with his use of excessive force contrary to his training and policy, and his failure to report his actions, constitute &ldquo;extremely troubling&rdquo; conduct.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's stated concern for how the incident would look on video, together with his belief that D2's video would be deleted, are evidence that he was &ldquo;assessing what recording documentation of his actions existed, in an effort to prevent disclosure&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; &ldquo;His conduct and deception suggest he is not capable of being trusted to do the right thing when called upon in the field&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's &ldquo;judgment is completely off-base, and his escalation of a routine traffic stop to excessive force and failing to report it are extremely problematic&rdquo;.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Termination of Employment</b></h4>
<p class="continued">A 4/5/16 letter to the Grievant from the City Manager headed &ldquo;Loudermill Notice - Intent to terminate employment&rdquo; was delivered to the Grievant's home by two Lieutenants. The Grievant was surprised because he had expected only one Lieutenant to visit. He was even more surprised that they were accompanied by a St. Paul officer who removed the Grievant's canine partner. The Grievant asked for a few more hours so that his two daughters could say goodbye to the dog when they returned from school. One of the Lieutenants assured him that they would have that opportunity later, which they never did.</p>
<p class="continued">The Notice scheduled a meeting with the City Manager where the Grievant could have an opportunity to respond. It stated that: the IA investigation sustaining the alleged policy violations had been reviewed by the Chief, who had also reviewed the BCA investigation and the Grievant's personnel file and previous discipline received; and the Chief had also consulted with the City Prosecutor regarding the Department's Brady Disclosure Policy. The letter concluded that if the Grievant did not attend the Loudermill hearing and provide reasons why the City should not terminate his employment, the City Manager would make the final decision based on the information he already had.</p>
<p class="continued">The two Lieutenants also delivered a 3/29/16 memo from the City Prosecutor, responding to the Chief's request for a legal opinion regarding the &ldquo;disclosure implications&rdquo; of using the Grievant in future cases. He opined that the Grievant's misconduct as found in the IA investigation would have to be disclosed in all cases involving the Grievant as a witness. The letter explained that, pursuant to <i>Brady</i>, a Supreme Court case, prosecutors must disclose materially exculpatory evidence to the defense; and the <i>Giglio</i> case requires disclosure of any information regarding the credibility of the prosecution's witnesses. It concluded that the &ldquo;Brady-Giglio rule&rdquo; regarding lack of credibility clearly applied to the Grievant and recommended: disclosing in detail the Grievant's &ldquo;untruthfulness, deceptiveness, dishonesty, or bias in conjunction with his service as a law enforcement officer in all criminal, traffic, and ordinance violation cases&rdquo;; not using the Grievant as a source of information in any complaint; and not using the Grievant's testimony, &ldquo;either corroborated or uncorroborated&rdquo;, in any cases.</p>
<p class="continued">In a 4/8/16 letter a Union attorney notified the City Manager that pursuant to advice of counsel, the Grievant was waiving his appearance at the Loudermill Hearing. The letter stated that &ldquo;while (the Grievant) does not agree with many of the conclusions of the Findings of Facts and Conclusions in this matter, at this point we emphasize one concern. It was concluded that (the Grievant) assumed the video was sent on Snapchat and thus automatically deleted. (The Grievant) denies that this was his assumption. In fact, it is our understanding that there are apps available that allow the capture of Snapchat video which would also refute such an assumption. Further, it appears to be recognized that various other individuals were recording the scene and there is no basis to conclude (the Grievant) believed they were all recording on Snapchat. We request that the City consider the foregoing when making its decision.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">By letter dated 4/13/16 the City Manager notified the Grievant of his decision to terminate the Grievant's employment effective April 14, 2016, &ldquo;based upon the recommendation of your Department Director, (the Chief), and after considering all of the information available to me, including the April 8, 2016 letter from your attorney &hellip; The grounds for your termination are the substantiated findings of serious violations of department policies and procedures.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">The Union grieved the discharge as without just cause, and by agreement of the parties it was moved to Step 3 of the grievance procedure. The City Manager conducted the Step 3 hearing on May 5, 2016, at which the Grievant made several statements, which were noted by an assistant to the Manager. The City Manager denied the grievance in a 5/9/16 letter and the Union appealed the decision to arbitration, requesting mediation and a list of proposed arbitrators from the BMS. Mediation efforts were unsuccessful and the matter proceeded to arbitration for five days of hearing in September and October 2016.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>SUMMARY OF THE PARTIES' ARGUMENTS</b></h4>
<p class="continued">THE EMPLOYER ARGUES THAT:</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; During the 10/3/15 call the Grievant was angry, frustrated and used profanity, and he threatened the young Somali males that he was going to &ldquo;fuck everyone of you fuckers up&rdquo;, in addition to shoving and striking D1.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Twitter video went viral, pointing a spotlight on the RPD, and leading to the discovery of the Grievant's actions.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Neither PO completed any kind of report on the incident; nor did they report it to the sergeant on their shift that night. The only documentation of the contact with D1 and D2 were &ldquo;brief cryptic notations&rdquo; on the citations.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; As the Chief recommended, the City Manager terminated the Grievant's employment on April 13, 2016.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The undisputed proven facts constitute sufficient proof that the Grievant actually engaged in the alleged misconduct, and so the only issue for the Arbitrator is whether the level of discipline imposed is appropriate in light of all the relevant circumstances.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Level of Discipline</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's actions qualify as serious misconduct.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; On Monday, October 5, the Chief's phone and e-mail were blowing up with messages about the Twitter video, from reporters and the Executive Director of the SHRC. The Chief had no idea what was going on and command staff were able to find only copies of the citations.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Chief placed both POs on paid administrative leave because he didn't have enough information, and he determined that the contact was potentially criminal in nature, leading him to ask the BCA to conduct an independent criminal investigation.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Following the conclusion of the criminal investigation, the Chief directed a Lieutenant to review the facts in light of Department policies. An extensive and detailed internal investigation concluded that the Grievant used excessive force, failed to report the incident, and violated his training and the conduct expected of an officer in violation of numerous policies.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Prior to deciding to terminate the Grievant's employment, the Chief conducted an extensive review and analysis of a broad range of factors: reviewing the IA report multiple times; watching the Twitter video at least 10 times; and watching the squad video numerous times. He also used a checklist containing 28 factors to determine the appropriate level of discipline.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Chief concluded that the investigation was fair, objective and complete, and that the witness statements supported the conclusions. He also reviewed the Grievant's complete personnel file, including performance evaluations (PEs), complimentary comments, discipline and counseling.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Chief also considered the extensive training and retraining of the Grievant and past discipline issued to other officers. He concluded that the RPD hadn't had any similar incident with the same record of previous extensive counseling and remedial training.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City's population is 38&percnt; minority and the past year has been stressful on the community and the RPD. There is no alternative to termination of employment due to the serious breach of expected conduct in light of all the significant efforts to correct the Grievant's conduct. The Chief assessed the profound impact on the community caused by the Grievant's actions, including being repeatedly approached by citizens describing the Twitter video as showing an assault. The Chief concluded that this incident will affect the Grievant's ability to do the job in the future because the community perceives him as a &ldquo;thug&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Chief considered the RPD Mission Statement and the Oath of Office/Honor and concluded that the Grievant has failed to live up to the expected integrity and public trust, nor has he taken accountability for his actions.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; As an employer the Chief's first response is to train, coach, counsel and retrain to correct deficiencies before issuing discipline. Over his last four years the Department gave the Grievant numerous chances to follow policy.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant was deceptive by not writing a report, not talking to his supervisor, and specifically discussing with PO2 whether his squad video had recorded the incident. The Chief identified a serious integrity issue in the Grievant's statement that he was thinking he should write a report but then intentionally did not. The Chief can't trust the Grievant.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; A lesser disciplinary action was issued for PO2 because his record did not contain similar discipline, counseling and retraining, and the Chief believed that he could be rehabilitated.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City Manager used his authority to terminate the Grievant's employment because of the repetitive use of force problems after extraordinary mentoring and retraining. He was bothered by the use of excessive force on a routine traffic stop, which is a primary work function of POs. He also knew that the Grievant had repeatedly been trained about blows and strikes to the head.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City Manager also was bothered by the profane language that caused things to be blown up as a direct result of the Grievant's actions and words, exacerbating rather than deescalating the situation.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City Manager also was concerned by how the Grievant talked to D1. It didn't seem that he was dealing with an individual when he kept saying &ldquo;you guys&rdquo;, and it appeared that he seemed to have a bias against these young men.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City Manager was troubled that the Grievant was deceptive by not telling a supervisor or writing a report about what happened, and checking about PO2's squad camera. He expects officers to be honest about making a mistake but the Grievant intentionally tried to cover things up.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City Manager never got the sense that the Grievant was remorseful and wouldn't do the same thing again. His decision was based on the Grievant's continued pattern of misconduct. The Grievant is not capable of rehabilitation, making the same poor judgment decisions after repeated efforts to correct his deficiencies. He cannot be trusted not to hurt someone or cause other damage to the City. The level of discipline is appropriate based on the facts and circumstances and should stand.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Training</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant was extensively trained and retrained on use of force and report writing, through both regular ongoing patrol training and SWAT, K-9, FTO and POST-required use of force training. The Grievant has been repeatedly coached, counseled, trained, disciplined and evaluated concerning use of force and report writing, including seven incidents since 2011.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; No other RPD officer ever had such extensive specialized and intensive remedial retraining as the 80 hours the Grievant had in September and October of 2013, which focused on use of force and report writing. In addition to one-on-one training with RPD's use of force instructor, the Grievant did additional work with the St. Paul Police Department's K-9 training unit.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; POs are not trained to shove a person or strike a person in the head to get their attention or to get them to move along, nor to strike a passively resistant person in the head. The Grievant intentionally and willfully ignored what he was taught when he shoved D1 and struck him in the back of the head. The Grievant stated that he was &ldquo;trying to get (D1's) attention and trying to get him to listen to me and trying to get him to move&rdquo;, but he also admitted that he was not trained to use open hand strikes for this purpose or to gain control. He also admitted that the shoves and strike &ldquo;amped up&rdquo; the situation and that he would not train any new officer to strike a person in the head to get them to move.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Although PO2 described the contact as a &ldquo;slap&rdquo;, he agreed that is not taught in use of force training, and that POs are not trained to use slaps or shoves on someone who is passively resistant; he stated that he would not have slapped D1 and he would not train an officer to do that.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; POs are required to perform according to RPD standards and it is unconscionable to call a group of young Somali males &ldquo;assholes&rdquo;, accuse them of never telling &ldquo;&hellip; the fucking truth ever&rdquo; in their lives, and threatening &ldquo;get the fuck out of here&rsquo; and &ldquo;You don't want to go, I'll fuck every one of you fuckers up. Move along, we're working here&rdquo;. The Grievant repeatedly spewed hate-filled speech during a routine traffic stop, evidence that he is unfit to work as an RPD officer.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Liability and Lack of Remorse</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City has already settled a lawsuit costing the City &dollar;150,000 as a result of the Grievant's use of force towards a suspect on another call. D1 has similarly filed suit against the City.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; At the Step 3 grievance meeting, in response to a question about whether he would do anything different, the Grievant replied &ldquo;maybe&rdquo;. Clearly he does not appreciate the seriousness of using excessive force on a passively resistant individual, and then failing to report the incident to anyone. This is evidence that he can't be rehabilitated and entrusted to police the streets of the City.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Also at the Step 3 meeting, the Grievant said that it was &ldquo;laughable&rdquo; that the IA report described him as angry, contrary to the squad transcript and video showing that he was frustrated, angry, and out of control on a seemingly routine traffic stop.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; POs in large part work independently in one-officer squads patrolling the City. The Grievant's explosive temper with D1 was unjustified, making him a serious liability for the RPD in the future.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Excessive Force</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant used excessive force on D1, whom he acknowledges was passively resistant. The RPD's Use of Force Continuum defines this as a person &ldquo;who fails to comply; uses no force or energy; indifferent to arrest or control&rdquo;. The appropriate response is PPCT - manipulations or carry skills &amp; devices. The open hand strike and shoving are not appropriate until a subject is assaultive.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Face and head strikes are treated differently due to the risk of serious injury. PO2 has tried to minimize Grievant's open hand head strike as similar to an escort hold but the RPD's use of force instructor testified that striking techniques are not permitted for a passively resistant person and would be considered unreasonable force. Undoubtedly, the Grievant's actions violated the RPD policy, which requires an officer to determine what technique will best de-escalate the situation.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The legal standard for judging the use of force by officers is &ldquo;objective reasonableness&rdquo; in the totality of the circumstances, putting things into context from the perspective of the officer at the time rather than with hindsight.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant admittedly approached D1 and initiated contact after he returned to the park. The Grievant testified that he did not see D1 as a threat or feel threatened by him. He testified that he shoved and struck D1 to get his attention, to make him listen and to move. He testified that he did not intend to disorient, injure, or put D1 on the ground. He stated that it was not an officer safety issue or he would have called for back-up.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; It is undeniable that the Grievant was the aggressor. He should have used verbal techniques and advised D1 to move on but instead, approached him from behind as he was talking on the phone and walking toward the park, before shoving, striking in the head, and again shoving him. The Grievant stated that he should not have struck D1 in the head and in hindsight wishes he hadn't done it.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Failure to Report Incident</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's annual PEs since 2011 have addressed the need for clear, accurate and detailed reports regarding use of force and the Grievant never made the necessary and required changes. To the contrary, he considered doing a CYA report on 10/3/15 but then did nothing at all.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant exhibited a repeated pattern of deception in this case, designed so his conduct would not be discovered. The Grievant falsely stated on D2's citation that his &ldquo;Mother came to drive car&rdquo;, although both POs left the area before she arrived. The Grievant admitted that he was concerned the incident was tape recorded or videoed and worried about how it looked on video. A common RPD mantra is &ldquo;when in doubt, write a report&rdquo;, and multiple Union witnesses, including the Grievant testified they were familiar with the phrase.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Incident reports (ICRs) are required when force is used because of criminal cases, civil lawsuits, and administrative reviews. If an officer goes &ldquo;hands on&rdquo; a report should document the action, describing the level of resistance, and any information relating to the violence the officer was facing to explain why the force was reasonable. Additionally, when force is used, a &ldquo;special incident report&rdquo;, also referred to as a &ldquo;salmon&rdquo; sheet because of its color, is required. Employer Arguments - Failure to Report</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant stated that he did not think that the incident was significant enough to warrant a use of force report, which is contrary to his stated concern about how the incident would look on video. He stated that he &ldquo;thought about doing a CYA report just an informational to supplement the citation, but I didn't&rdquo;. The Grievant testified on cross-examination that officers will give a sergeant a heads-up about issues on a call if they think a complaint might be filed, and he has done so on other occasions. The Grievant admitted that he should have done a report so that command staff wouldn't be blindsided on Monday morning.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's claims that he didn't think a report was necessary and it wasn't a big enough deal to notify a supervisor are not credible, especially as he admitted that he left the scene before D2's mother arrived &ldquo;so nothing else would happen&rdquo;. It is more credible that he was trying to hide his actions from Administration, knowing there was no squad footage of the contact, and believing that the passengers&rsquo; videos would have vanished on Snapchat.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City Prosecutor has determined that the Grievant's violations of policy as sustained by the IA investigation would now make him considered a <i>Brady/Giglio</i> officer, which would jeopardize the prosecution of any case in which he was involved. This determination is made by the Prosecutor and not the RPD, which refutes the Union's suggestion that the RPD uses the designation as a club over its officers. Even if the arbitration award returns the Grievant to his position, it will not change his <i>Brady/Giglio</i> status, but just add the award to the information that must be disclosed.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's actions brought months of media attention wth negative phone calls, e-mails, print media and virtual news repeatedly casting a negative light on the City and the RPD. PO2 stated that he told the Grievant that the incident was recorded because &ldquo;&hellip; I just wanted (him) to be aware of that because &hellip; in especially the current climate that causes me some concern &hellip;&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Distinguishing Other Arbitration Decision</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; Precedential value should not be given to a recent arbitration decision reinstating a Minneapolis police officer discharged for use of force, reporting, and verbal conduct. That case is clearly distinguishable: the officer had a good work record as contrasted with the Grievant's; and that call involved a domestic dispute between two females, one of whom was intoxicated and ignored instructions to remain in her apartment and instead interjected herself into the situation.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; That Arbitrator found the officer's two pushes were sufficient to propel the woman to the ground, but were on the mild side of the use of force continuum and not inappropriate to the level of resistance by a woman whose behavior was &ldquo;disquieting&rdquo;. Here D1 was not attempting to interject himself into D2's traffic stop, but was just walking through the area towards the park talking on his cell phone; there are no similarities between the two behaviors, and a domestic call with intoxicated individuals is vastly different from a routine traffic stop.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Employer argued that the second push by the Officer was a &ldquo;take-down technique&rdquo; because he grabbed her throat in conjunction with the push, requiring a written report. The Arbitrator found that the video did not clearly establish that the Officer grabbed her by the throat, and therefore the evidence did not establish that he used a technique requiring a report.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Minneapolis Officer was accused of calling the woman a profane name and the Arbitrator said if that was true it would violate policy but the evidence did not establish it because: neither of the involved citizens testified at the hearing; both were intoxicated and provided differing accounts of when the Officer allegedly used the profanity; and there was no audio recording.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Conclusion</b></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Union erroneously argues that this case is about a dog; it is about a seasoned officer who escalated a minor traffic stop and used excessive force against a passive resistant individual, while attempting to avoid detection by police administration.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Union has not submitted evidence to support its claims that the IA investigation was faulty or biased, or that the decision to terminate employment was predetermined. The investigation was demonstrably thorough, fair and complete.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Union's diversion about whether the City Manager has the authority to terminate employment is untimely as a procedural argument and outside the scope of the Arbitrator's authority. The Union did not support this argument by any evidence; and the Labor Agreement expressly preserves the Employer's authority to discharge employees. The City Attorney's legal opinion refutes the Union's argument.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Only two of the Union's witnesses are still working for the RPD. The other character witnesses who claim they wouldn't have a problem working with the Grievant aren't even employed there, since one of them submitted a resignation effective October 24, 2016.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Based on all the testimony, evidence, and record, the Arbitrator should uphold the discharge of the Grievant and deny the grievance.</p>
<p class="continued">THE UNION ARGUES THAT:</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Reporting and Deception</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City failed to prove that the Grievant was deceptive or untruthful. The Grievant's failure to write a report was not intended to deceive the City. Rather, he believed he had acted within the bounds of his authority, and that he was not required to write a report on his use of force.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator surmised that not completing any report &ldquo;creates an appearance that (the Grievant) was trying to cover up his actions&rdquo;, and reported that it was &ldquo;reasonable to conclude&rdquo; that when he saw D2 on Snapchat he believed that the video had been automatically deleted. Although the RPD transcript of the squad video could be read as supporting this conclusion, it contains a significant error: it attributes to D2 statements actually made by D1 and his group, including &ldquo;We got you on camera&rdquo;. This error makes it appear that the Grievant was led to believe that the only video was recorded by V2 but the Grievant was told by other bystanders that his actions had been recorded. The reasonable conclusion is that the Grievant was fully aware that D2 and others had recorded the incident and that the matter would come to light. This completely undermines the conclusion that the failure to report was an intentional act of deception meant to allow him to &ldquo;get away with&rdquo; his conduct.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The failure to include this exculpatory information in the IA report left the Chief, the City Manager, and the City Prosecutor under a misapprehension about the Grievant's belief that he could &ldquo;get away with it&rdquo;. In an age of digital recording and social media, it is unreasonable for any officer to assume he can &ldquo;get away&rdquo; with something. As PO2 testified, given the &ldquo;scrutiny and hatred toward officers, I always assume&rdquo; that incidents are caught on video.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Although the Grievant should have filed a report regarding his use of force, his failure was nothing more than a policy violation and an error in judgment. This is supported by the statement of the Special Prosecutor when he found that the Grievant believed he had acted within the constraints of law and policy, and concluded that he &ldquo;did not knowingly act in excess of his lawful authority in the course of this incident, in that he was obviously of the belief he was performing legitimate police duties as he understood them &hellip; His actions could be construed as ones to enforce his order for (D1) and others with him, to clear the area where the traffic stop investigation was continuing with another driver&rdquo;. Because the Grievant believed he acted appropriately and no report was necessary, he could not intend to deceive when he believed there was nothing for which to deceive.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant has a reputation for honesty and admitted his error. In a prior arbitration case between these parties, an officer was suspended for ten days for allegedly lying. The arbitrator reduced this to a written reprimand, noting the officer's reputation for honesty, and stated: &ldquo;(The officer) did not attempt to conceal this damaging material fact, but admitted his error without evasion or equivocation &hellip; In the context of his admission, it is inappropriate to attribute &hellip; a motivation to deliberately make an untruthful statement.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; PO2 testified that he did not discuss with the Grievant whether to write a report.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; During his IA statement the Grievant said that he did not even think about whether police administration would find out about the incident but his concern was focused on whether he was required to write a report. He erroneously decided that he was not, which constitutes mistakenly interpreting the rules rather than setting out to deceive.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City failed to meet its burden of proving that the Grievant was deliberately deceptive or failed to tell the truth.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Impartial Policing</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City has failed to prove that the Grievant violated the policy regarding impartial policing.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator's conclusion that the Grievant showed bias or made racist remarks was not supported by the evidence. The Investigator and the City Manager characterized two instances of the Grievant's calling the group &ldquo;you guys&rdquo; as racist, without articulating why they were different from multiple other instances that they did not find inappropriate. The Grievant repeatedly used that term throughout the stop and he testified that he even refers that way to persons of either gender.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City Manager believed the Grievant showed bias but he watched the squad video only one time. He felt that the Grievant was treating D1 and D2 as persons who were &ldquo;less than him&rdquo; and that &ldquo;spoke of bias to me&rdquo;. There is no persuasive evidence to make the big leap from using profanity and arguably disrespectful treatment to concluding the actions were based on ethnicity or race.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; For ten years the Grievant has policed an area with a significant non-white population without ever receiving a complaint alleging misconduct or unacceptable speech based on race or ethnicity. None of the witnesses could recall any instance where the Grievant acted inappropriately related to race or bias.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The conclusion that the Grievant violated the policy requiring impartial policing is not supported by the evidence.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Use of Force</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The evidence supported only the conclusion that the method used was outside of those authorized. It is undisputed that D1 was passively resistant and the Grievant was authorized to use force under the circumstances but the particular method was outside those listed in the Department policy, which include: PPCT-manipulations and Carry Skills and Devices. These methods require placing hands on a subject, using armbars, pressure point manipulations that cause pain, and physically picking up the person. The difference between the listed methods and the force used by the Grievant is minimal.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The next level of force on the Continuum is in response to active resistance, which can be met with chemical aerosols, taser and canine; common sense says that the pushes and slap were less severe than being tased, maced, or attacked by a canine.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Continuum authorized the Grievant to place his hands on D1; he was further authorized to cause pain, bend his arm back and push him forward, and to pick him up and move him. The pushes and slaps were akin in severity to the force authorized by the Continuum but were outside the methods he was trained to use.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City's argument that the slap was an &ldquo;open hand strike&rdquo; is not supported by the evidence. A former RPD use-of-force instructor testified that kind of strike is meant to &ldquo;disorient and gain control&rdquo;, and &ldquo;If properly administered, you'll knock them off their feet; they get launched&rdquo;. He testified that the Grievant's action was not such a strike. This conclusion is supported by the Twitter video that shows D1 not knocked off his feet or launched by the slap. In his BCA statement, even D1 characterized it as a &ldquo;slap&rdquo;, saying that &ldquo;a slap's a slap&rdquo;. The evidence shows that the Grievant did not employ an &ldquo;open hand strike&rdquo; to D1's head.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; A current RPD use-of-force instructor also testified that &ldquo;strikes&rdquo; to the head cause &ldquo;fluid shock and gross motor dysfunction&rdquo;, neither of which was evidenced by D1. There is no evidence that D1 suffered any injury whatsoever.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's actions are not unlike those in a recent arbitration case involving a Minneapolis police officer who pushed a passively resistant woman causing her to fall over hallway steps. When the woman refused to get off her phone, he swatted it out of her hand, he then pushed the woman and she fell. The arbitrator found that the woman's behavior was not threatening anyone and the officer used more force than necessary to secure her compliance but was &ldquo;on the mild side of the use of force continuum and was not substantially inappropriate as a response to (the woman's) pattern of passive resistance&rdquo;. He further found that the &ldquo;first push was forceful but not violent&rdquo;, and neither push caused injury. The arbitrator sustained the excessive force allegation &ldquo;but at a less severe level than as alleged by the City&rdquo;. He found that this serious violation warranted a significant penalty but discharge was a step too far for a &ldquo;modest use of force violation&rdquo;. The discharge was reduced to an unpaid suspension of 40 hours.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; D1 did not fall and the slap did not cause injury. The City has failed to prove that the Grievant used excessive force.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Investigation Not Fair or Objective</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The errors, mischaracterizations and omissions in the IA report demonstrate that: it was neither fair nor objective; and the investigation was aimed at terminating the Grievant's employment rather than gathering facts.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator testified that he found the transcript of the squad video to be true and accurate, but it was not and the inaccuracies are material. This undermines the Investigator's credibility and the accuracy and reliability of his report.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The report stated only one instance of a use of profanity referring to officers, by D1 on his cell phone. Upon cross examination the Investigator admitted more profanity was offered by D1 and others in the group. This mischaracterization and omission of important facts favorable to the Grievant brings into question the accuracy of his report and his objectivity.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The report did not note that in his IA statement D1 did not notice the Grievant's use of profanity during the stop prior to the time of the shove. The Investigator did not inquire as to whether he heard the Grievant's statement about &ldquo;fuck up every one of you fuckers&rdquo;. The absence of D1's reaction to this statement, and his failure to notice the Grievant's profanity, are material to determining what effect the Grievant's conduct had on D1. Consequently, the thoroughness of the investigation and its objectivity are questionable.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator concluded that the Grievant made &ldquo;a series of contradictions between (his training)&hellip;.and his statements regarding the &hellip; force he used &hellip; against D1&rdquo;. On cross-examination he acknowledged that these could be nothing more than the difference between explaining his actions and explaining his training and what he should have done. This shows the Grievant's acceptance of responsibility and his ability to critique himself, and his capacity for rehabilitation. The Investigator decided to give them some nefarious meaning such as regretting getting caught. This was not an objective conclusion but smacks of the City's approach to the investigation, i.e., that the purpose was to slant the evidence to support termination of employment.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator testified that the Grievant had no legitimate reason to &ldquo;use police action&rdquo; when he approached D1 fifteen feet from the squad. This was contradicted by the Chief and a Lieutenant who testified that they would have approached D1 and asked if he needed something. The former use-of-force instructor testified that he would approach out of concern for D1's decision to return and stay in the area for over a minute; his &ldquo;antenna&rdquo; would be up given that D1 drove away and returned and had not been patted down. The Investigator's erroneous conclusion that the Grievant did not have a legitimate reason to engage D1 colored his assessment of the Grievant's subsequent actions and the Investigator's decisions to omit exculpatory evidence from his report.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator sent letters to witnesses requesting interviews but made no effort to contact them when they failed to reply. One of them was known to have been five feet from the Grievant when he pushed and slapped D1, and then made the &ldquo;fuck up every one of you fuckers&rdquo; statement. The Investigator did not even refer to this witness&rsquo; statement as given to the BCA, which corroborates the Grievant's assertion that the group's location and failure to comply with directives to leave caused him to use strong verbal tactics and profanity to gain control. The failure to seek out this witness&rsquo; statement and the omission of the fact that he was five feet from the Grievant demonstrates the lack of thoroughness of the investigation and suggests a decision not to cite evidence favorable to the Grievant.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator concluded that the videos &ldquo;reveal (the Grievant) to be an angry, easily frustrated officer&rdquo;. On cross-examination he admitted that this description did not refer to his work history prior to this incident. Not one witness testified that the Grievant's character and conduct were those of an &ldquo;angry, easily frustrated officer&rdquo;. This sweeping generalization based on 42 minutes of a ten-year career shows the lack of objectivity in the investigation.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator's report failed to include the information that the squad video could not be modified by the Grievant. This is significant to whether the failure to write a report was deceptive. The Grievant knew that his body microphone would pick up his profanity and tone of voice and that this recording would be automatically downloaded and accessible to the City. This omission demonstrates that the investigation was neither fair nor objective.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator interviewed the Grievant more than four months after the incident. The Grievant had not seen the squad video or read the transcript before this, which was not noted in the report. The Investigator testified that he did not know whether the Grievant had seen the squad video during his BCA interview. His failure to include facts that would explain inconsistencies between the video and the Grievant's statement demonstrates the lack of fairness and objectivity.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator's choice of words demonstrates his lack of objectivity. He described the Grievant's notes on the citation as &ldquo;cryptic&rdquo; with &ldquo;no mention of his use of force&rdquo;. It is undisputed that the notes are for the exclusive convenience of the officer's memory if he is called to testify. The word &ldquo;cryptic&rdquo; appears to be chosen to support the conclusion that the Grievant was deceptive. Despite his knowledge of the purpose of the notes, the Investigator chose to imply that they should have included the use of force. One can conclude either that: the Investigator does not know how to write a citation; or someone else wrote that conclusion. Either way, the fairness and objectivity of the investigation is suspect.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator did not provide the context of the Grievant's uttering: &ldquo;You guys never told the fucking truth ever in your life, none of you fuckers&rdquo;. He erroneously stated this was made &ldquo;to the group&rdquo; but the Grievant was walking toward V2 with his back to D1 and the utterance was not directed at anyone. This error is significant because this utterance was one of two identified as the basis for the allegation of violating the impartial policing policy. This apparent slanting of the evidence added fuel to the City's case to terminate employment, and demonstrates the lack of objectivity and fairness in the investigation.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Investigator failed to obtain all of the relevant evidence. The BCA report noted that D2's video in its possession was longer than the Twitter video and if the Investigator had conducted a thorough review of the BCA report he would have found that video was missing. The extra time is material because it shows the Grievant standing near D1 and speaking with him before utilizing appropriate force when D1 did not comply.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Chief failed to adequately review the investigative materials and the IA report to discover the errors, mischaracterizations and omissions prior to sending them to the City Prosecutor and the City Manager. This failure had serious consequences in leading the City Prosecutor to conclude that the Grievant was fatally <i>Brady/Giglio</i> impaired, and the City Manager to conclude that the Grievant's employment needed to be terminated. Moreover, it unequivocally demonstrates the City's intent, from the beginning of the investigation, to terminate the Grievant's employment.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The evidence demonstrates the City's intent was to terminate employment rather than investigate the facts. The report's defects are fatal to its reliability and significantly undermine the City's conclusions that the Grievant was untruthful, deceptive and biased.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City's offer to trade the Grievant's dog for his resignation, followed by a refusal to allow an opportunity to say good-bye to the dog, was petty, punitive, and vindictive and is an apt embodiment of the City's intent throughout the investigation and termination.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Penalty not Evenhanded and Without Discrimination</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The penalty was not applied evenhandedly or without discrimination.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; In a prior arbitration between these parties, the arbitrator characterized disparate treatment as disciplining in a significantly different manner substantially similar employees for substantially similar misconduct. The Chief's request for a <i>Brady/Giglio</i> analysis prior to issuing discipline was not only premature and careless, but inconsistent with past practice, which constitutes disparate treatment.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; In a previous disciplinary matter involving a different officer who misrepresented in his report that he had done a follow-up on an investigation as instructed, he received a written reprimand and no referral for a <i>Brady/Giglio</i> analysis occurred. Similarly, a sergeant who was found to agree with another officer to include inaccurate facts in his report received a suspension but was not referred for a <i>Brady/Giglio</i> analysis. The severity of these acts was much greater than those of the Grievant, in that both overtly misstated actual events, as opposed to Grievant's &ldquo;sin of omission&rdquo;. Not only did these two not lose their jobs, they escaped <i>Brady/Giglio</i> analysis and were later promoted to sergeant.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; It is irrelevant that there was a different Chief during those earlier events; an Employer does not get a &ldquo;do-over&rdquo; for purposes of disparate treatment with a new Chief. Furthermore, both the Chief and the Deputy were employed by the RPD at the time of those two earlier disciplinary matters and the Deputy conducted one of the investigations and drafted the written reprimand. The City Manager was either in office or the head of human resources during those disciplinary matters and so should have been aware of the materially different discipline being meted out to the Grievant. Both matters are public data and should be retained in the sergeants&rsquo; personnel files, so there is no excuse for the City's failure to consider its past practice regarding discipline for untruthfulness or deception.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The <i>Brady/Giglio</i> analysis based on the Investigator's findings of untruthfulness and deception will forever need to be disclosed to defendants and had the uncontroverted effect of ending the Grievant's career as a law-enforcement officer. The Grievant was effectively terminated based solely on the Investigator's findings, without any due process and prior to his &ldquo;real&rdquo; termination by the City Manager.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant was treated in a disparate manner when the Chief prematurely and carelessly requested a pre-disciplinary <i>Brady/Giglio</i> determination. The fact that it cannot be grieved makes this more egregious, and highlights the significance of the disparate treatment.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Lack of Progressive Discipline</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's only discipline during his ten years with the RPD was an oral reprimand. To jump from the lowest level of discipline to the most severe is unusual and requires compelling evidence.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City's conclusion that the Grievant was deliberately deceptive is without merit, and the force used was on the mild side of the Continuum, both of which could have been concluded by a fair and objective investigation.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The evidence is not persuasive that nothing short of termination will suffice. Without more, the decision to terminate fails the progressive discipline test.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Adequate Notice Was Not Provided Regarding the Salmon Sheet Requirement</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; Policy requires a report for use of force through a Special Incident Report, also called a &ldquo;Salmon Sheet&rdquo; due to its color. The form contains boxes to check regarding type of force used ranging from significant resistance, through use of deadly force. The practice is not to document all uses of force: verbal skills are a use of force but not documented; some past instances of the types of force authorized for passive and active resistance have not been documented.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The form's first level is &ldquo;response to significant resistance&rdquo;; the policy does not define &ldquo;significant&rdquo; but &ldquo;passive resistance&rdquo; is less than significant. Authorized methods for dealing with passive resistance are not listed on the Salmon Sheet.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant explained that his decision not to complete a report or Salmon Sheet was the lack of a place for reporting force used on a passively resistant person, therefore he concluded that he was not required to complete it or an incident report. The Grievant believed that he understood the policy. In a prior arbitration between these parties, the arbitrator reduced a suspension to a written reprimand when the officer thought that he understood what was required under pursuit policy.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Without a clear and consistently followed policy and a corresponding Salmon Sheet, the City cannot hold the Grievant accountable for failing to complete one.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Termination Was Not Reasonably Related to the Seriousness of the Offense</i></h4>
<p class="continued">&bull; The issue is whether the Grievant's conduct, when considered along with his length of service and all the other mitigating factors in his record, was enough to justify the ultimate penalty of termination. Other arbitrators and experts have opined that: just cause refers to a rule of reason that protects employees from unjust discipline, and can be shorthand for what an arbitrator thinks is fair; discipline may be considered excessive if it is disproportionate to the degree of the offense, punitive rather than corrective, or if mitigating circumstances were ignored.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's conduct, while unacceptable, was not serious enough to justify termination. A single act of bad judgment does not amount to just cause for termination, as decided in cases where the arbitrator found the behavior to be isolated and atypical. The Grievant described the incident as &ldquo;out of character&rdquo; and the evidence supports his testimony. No witness ever saw him being inappropriately angry. The evidence established that this incident was an aberration.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's use of profanity may be perceived by the general public as inappropriate but as two of the Union witnesses testified, officers use profanity as a control tactic. A former RPD sergeant who supervised the Grievant testified that &ldquo;street language&rdquo; worked better than putting hands on. PO2 testified that &ldquo;not everyone responds to polite&rdquo; conversation, and some persons only understand profanity.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The evidence includes a message from a sergeant to the Grievant, calling a suspect a &ldquo;fucker&rdquo;. The Grievant's profanity may have violated policy but its use by RPD officers and at least one supervisor is not uncommon.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City argues that the media attention and the widespread Twitter video are significant factors preventing the Grievant from returning as a PO, citing numerous articles and voicemail recordings to prove the impact on the community. It is not surprising that the Chief's peers ask him about the matter, given that he apparently shared private personnel data with them while seeking their advice. Other media coverage a few weeks later regarding the fact that the officer who shot Jamar Clark had formerly been with the RPD likely intensified the criticisms of the RPD.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Recently arbitrators have reinstated several metro law-enforcement officers for actions far worse than the Grievant's, and in the context of significant media attention and public outcry. In one case the arbitrator recognized the misconduct as an aberration and reinstated the officer. In another case, the arbitrator found that &ldquo;a modest use of force violation&rdquo; did not warrant termination.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The level of discipline is out of proportion to the conduct considering the Grievant's record. The counselings regarding use of force associated with his canine are not surprising considering that, with no RPD canine trainer, the Grievant was learning on the job and subjected to second-guessing by his supervisors. After the remedial training the Grievant had only one minor incident with the canine and no more problems with writing adequate reports.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The City cannot argue, as the City Manager did, that it used &ldquo;every tool&rdquo; over the years to rehabilitate the Grievant. He received only one oral reprimand and the City Manager admitted that he could have been suspended without pay, placed on a last-chance agreement, and/or required to wear a body camera. The City also could have requested a fitness for duty evaluation regarding the Grievant's alleged anger problem. The City cannot claim that it used every tool so as to disregard progressive discipline.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Other mitigating factors include the Grievant's nomination for officer of the year and other compliments received, as well as testimony from current and past officers that they would trust the Grievant and be willing to work with him. The Grievant's reputation among RPD officers and supervisors was for honesty, commitment, ethics and dedication. He was recognized for his calm in high-stress situations and was respectful and receptive to counseling and criticism. His dedication to his canine partner was abundantly evident when he struggled to maintain his composure while testifying about the dog and the circumstances of his removal from the Grievant's home. He is currently training dogs in his home for individuals and teaches pursuit driving at a local college. He has strong connections to the community and is the father of two daughters.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Arbitrator must consider the Grievant's unwavering willingness to take responsibility for his conduct and his repeated admissions that he was wrong. Despite not knowing what his squad video and audio recorded prior to his interviews for BCA and IA, he at all times described the situation in a manner consistent with the squad video. He carefully and honestly explained his thought process, and acknowledged that his actions were wrong.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; A lesser penalty is all that is warranted by the evidence.The Grievant should be reinstated with full backpay and his discipline reduced to a more appropriate level.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>ANALYSIS AND DISCUSSION</b></h4>
<p class="continued">After it was determined that the Grievant's actions on October 3, 2015 did not warrant any criminal charges against him, the Chief ordered a Lieutenant to conduct an internal investigation into whether they constituted misconduct. The 12/16/15 notice to the Grievant specified the allegations as: making contact with the occupants of V1 after they returned on foot; using profanity; pushing one of the males and then striking him in the back of the head; and failing to make any report regarding this use of force. The Investigator's report concluded that:</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's profane language and demeanor throughout the call is problematic, and coupled with his use of excessive force contrary to his training and policy, and his failure to report his actions, constitute &ldquo;extremely troubling&rdquo; conduct.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's stated concern for how the incident would look on video, together with his belief that D2's video would be deleted, are evidence that he was &ldquo;assessing what recording documentation of his actions existed, in an effort to prevent disclosure&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; &ldquo;His conduct and deception suggest he is not capable of being trusted to do the right thing when called upon in the field&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant's &ldquo;judgment is completely off-base, and his escalation of a routine traffic stop to excessive force and failing to report it are extremely problematic&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">The 4/13/16 letter cited these as &ldquo;substantiated findings of serious violations of department policies and procedures&rdquo;, constituting grounds for termination of employment. The Investigator's findings of misconduct were also the basis for the recommendation by the City Prosecutor that the Grievant should not be used as a source of information in any future cases, even if his testimony could be corroborated.</p>
<p class="continued">In addition to challenging the level of disciplinary action, the Union has challenged the fairness and objectivity of the investigation and its findings, necessitating a detailed review of the evidence.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Making Contact</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Grievant had been told by the occupants of V1 that they were not involved with the gathering in the park, and none of them lived in the City of Richfield. They failed to give any coherent reason for their presence in the City. In response to D1's continuing protests about the ticket, the Grievant told him that they were not going to discuss it anymore and he could appeal it in court. He also said that he was giving him a break by not towing his car, and that he didn't want to see him again that night driving around the City like an idiot. After being directed to drive away carefully, D1 did not move for 2 1/2 minutes, until the Grievant again told him to go.</p>
<p class="continued">Approximately four minutes later the Grievant was alerted by the barking of his canine and saw that D1 and his passengers were approaching the squad in which he was sitting, coming on foot from the direction in which V1 had headed when it pulled away. The Grievant acknowledged their presence by saying loud enough for them to hear: &ldquo;Hey I thought that you weren't coming to the park &hellip;you didn't know anything about the park&rdquo;. The Grievant spoke to D2 and then went to the rear of V2 where he spoke to PO2 and one of the Somalis seated on the curb. After that he walked approximately 50 feet to where the occupants of V1 were still present within approximately 15 feet of his squad. During this time the group had not made much progress toward the path to the park: D1 was trailing a few feet behind the others, and the canine continued barking.</p>
<p class="continued">The Investigator testified that: it was not necessary for the Grievant to approach D1, given that he had already been cited and released; and if there was a need to deal with the group, the alternative would have been to call for assistance. Other witnesses disagreed with this assessment. It is troubling that the Investigator faulted the Grievant for making contact with D1's group, which became the basis for attributing everything that followed to improper motivation and conduct by the Grievant,. This causes doubt about the objectivity of the investigation and the reliability of the report.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant's statements in both investigations and his testimony were impressively credible, given their consistency and accuracy, and considering that he hadn't seen the squad video or transcript of what had transpired more than four months before he was questioned by the Investigator. The Grievant's IA statement and testimony were consistent: his awareness of possible problems with the situation was raised by the insulting language, insolence and contempt of D1 and his passengers; he was on heightened alert when he saw the group returning; from behind V2 he could hear them talking and he thought D1 was talking to him; the group was too close to the squad and there was no reason for them to be there; they were being rowdy and saying things like &ldquo;Fuck the police&rdquo; and calling him names; and no officer would ignore that situation.</p>
<p class="continued">The former use-of-force instructor testified that he would be very concerned about &ldquo;why they were walking back to me&rdquo; and his &ldquo;antennae would go up&rdquo;; he would ask why they were there; and ask them to leave or go into the park. The Chief testified that he would walk up, make contact, and ask what they were doing. PO2 testified that: if the group did not move when told to, he would approach to talk; D1's proximity to the squad raised alarms, especially after having been sent away; and D1 had an opportunity to access a weapon from the trunk of the car, and his not being patted down for weapons raised alertness. It is concluded that the Grievant's approach to D1 and his group was prompted by legitimate safety concerns and did not constitute misconduct.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Profanity and Demeanor</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Investigator's report stated that the videos revealed the Grievant &ldquo;to be an angry, easily frustrated officer&rdquo;. However, on cross-examination he conceded that was so only &ldquo;at times in this incident&rdquo; and that he did not know of other instances during the Grievant's career. As the Grievant first approached the two drivers he calmly stated his legitimate reasons for stopping them. Neither driver could produce the required license or proof of insurance, and the Grievant showed restraint by giving them time to produce proof of insurance rather than proceeding to have the cars towed, which was within his authority.</p>
<p class="continued">After six minutes of being lied to and treated disrespectfully, he voiced his annoyance to D2 and his passenger, using profane and vulgar language: &ldquo;Jesus Christ, you guys ever tell the fucking truth one day in your life &hellip; if you can't prove the insurance, I'm towing the car, ok, so fucking find it&rdquo;. After returning to V1 and getting more lies from the occupants in response to his questions, he said: &ldquo;Jesus Christ you guys are so full of shit I can't believe it&rdquo;. After the occupants of V1 returned on foot, he muttered to himself with his back to D1, as he continued walking away: &ldquo;You guys never told the fucking truth ever in your life, none of you fuckers&rdquo;. The Grievant did not &ldquo;call a group of young Somali males &lsquo;assholes&rsquo;&rdquo;, as argued by the Employer. He accused D1 of driving like an &ldquo;asshole&rdquo;, and like an &ldquo;idiot&rdquo;, meaning irresponsibly, describing the behavior rather than labeling the person. The drivers of the cars did not report the language as offensive during the investigation, and they and their passengers used similar language while expressing their opinion of the Grievant and cops.</p>
<p class="continued">Immediately after his two-minute confrontation with D1, ending with the threat to &ldquo;fuck every one of you fuckers up&rdquo;, the Grievant returned to calmly talk to D2 about the location of his mother. The Grievant then had to again approach D1's group, which was not progressing down the path. He again ordered them, without using coarse language, to move along. He did not react to their taunts of &ldquo;good cop bad cop&rdquo;, D1's calling him a &ldquo;nigga&rdquo;, or their telling him that they got him &ldquo;on video&rdquo; and &ldquo;on camera&rdquo;. He then returned to calmly address D2, and had a conversation with a few neighbors, calmly reassuring them about the situation. After giving D2 breaks by not ticketing him for his driving conduct and not towing his car, he gave him some friendly advice about how his recent polite behavior should have come from the start and that reacting with attitude is going to make a situation worse. Despite admittedly being angry and upset with D1's provocation, the Grievant maintained a professional demeanor throughout most of the incident, and although his lapses may warrant counseling, they are not cause for disciplinary action.</p>
<p class="continued">Policy #108-Employee Speech requires officers to refrain from indecent or profane language; however, the record indicates that it is common among officers and, as PO2 and a former sergeant testified, at times calculated to be a more effective way of communicating on the street. The Grievant testified that sometimes aggressive talk is necessary to get a subject's attention, which seemed to apply in this situation. The record does not reveal any past disciplinary action for any officer based on using coarse language. Given this apparent lack of enforcement, it is concluded that the Grievant's use of this type of language in this situation was not a basis for disciplinary action, although in a different situation it could be.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Excessive Force</b></h4>
<p class="continued">As the Grievant approached D1 and his group, he was questioning why they were back in the park after having denied they were going there. D1's response was to continue complaining about the traffic citation. The Grievant had already: told D1 that the time for arguing was past and there would be no more discussion; and determined that the proximity of D1 and the others to the squad car and the traffic stop was a safety concern. The Grievant was legitimately concerned that D1 was getting the other people in the area riled up and the situation was escalating. The Grievant told D1 to move along, pointing into the park; D1's response was to tell someone on his cell phone that &ldquo;This bitch ass cop just gave me a ticket &hellip; for some fucking whatchamacallit&rdquo;. The Grievant warned D1 to stop &ldquo;running his mouth&rdquo; and told him repeatedly that he needed to move along, pointing in the direction of the basketball court, and not ordering him to leave the City, as D1 subsequently claimed.</p>
<p class="continued">As D1 stated to the BCA, he was ignoring the Grievant. His failure to comply with the order to move along meant the Grievant needed to choose a method to enforce it. The Grievant stated that during that split second it crossed his mind to arrest D1 for obstruction but he rejected that option as likely to cause even more &ldquo;commotion&rdquo; than was already occurring in the context of D1's group of four, V2's two occupants, three other young Somali males behind V2, and approximately 50 more Somalis gathered nearby in the park. This choice was reasonable under the circumstances.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant decided that the quickest and safest option for gaining control and compliance was to physically shove D1, causing his feet to move in the direction he said he wanted to go. After stumbling a few steps, D1 defiantly planted his feet and turned to argue some more with the Grievant. In a further effort to gain compliance, the Grievant hit D1 on the back of his head, which did not cause him to move his feet, and the Grievant followed up with another shove. These two shoves and the hit to the head were captured on the video posted on Twitter, leading to the media and public uproar.</p>
<p class="continued">This hands-on contact caused at least one of the group to give some indication of coming at the Grievant, as he testified, and as D1 reportedly told the media &ldquo;his friends then approached the officer&rdquo;. This led the Grievant to say &ldquo;Do you all want to go? I'll fuck every one of you fuckers up, move along, we're working here&rdquo;. As testified by the Grievant, and found by the Office of the Hennepin County Attorney, the Grievant made this statement in an effort to control the situation. This effort succeeded, causing the group to back off and start to leave, as stated to the BCA by a passenger from V1.</p>
<p class="continued">It is troubling that the IA Investigator's report relied on an erroneous transcription of this statement, even after it had been correctly transcribed by the BCA. The RPD's transcript reads: &ldquo;You don't want to go, I'll fuck every one of you fuckers up &hellip;&rdquo;. This suggests that the Grievant was escalating the situation by initiating engagement with the entire group and threatening them, rather than responding to a threat emanating from the group. Reliance on this erroneous transcription resulted in depicting the Grievant as an out-of-control aggressor rather than a seasoned officer relying on his experience to defuse a threat and deescalate the situation.</p>
<p class="continued">RPD's policy on Use of Force states that:</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Police officers use the minimum force that is reasonably necessary to effectively bring an incident under control, while protecting the life of the officer and/or others.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; Police officers are authorized to use Department-approved non-deadly force techniques for resolution of incidents to bring an unlawful situation safely and effectively under control.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The use of excessive force violates the constitutionally protected civil rights accorded to all citizens and constitutes the most serious breach of Departmental procedure. The willful violation of any individual's constitutionally protected rights by an employee of this Department <b><i>shall</i></b> subject the employee to severe disciplinary action, and may result in termination.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; All reported uses of force should be reviewed by command staff to determine whether: rules, policy or procedures were violated; the relevant policy was clearly understandable and effective to cover the situation; and training is currently adequate.</p>
<p class="continued">Although the policy references &ldquo;Department-approved non-deadly force techniques&rdquo;, it does not list what they are or address the issue of non-approved techniques. Nor is there any evidence in the record that techniques not included in training are absolutely prohibited. The training materials state that the amount of force objectively reasonable is based on the totality of circumstances. Legal precedent has established that &ldquo;The reasonableness of a particular use of force must be judged from the perspective of a reasonable officer on the scene, rather than with the 20/20 vision of hindsight&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">The policy's section on the use of force continuum provides:</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; The use of force continuum relates, in a general sense, various levels of resistance encountered and the most appropriate weapon or compliance techniques to reasonably overcome that resistance; intended as a guide to understand the options available for various situations. On the street, additional factors, such as the rate of escalation, available assistance, and multiple assailants may affect a response.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; A passive resistant subject who fails to comply without using force or energy may be met with these tactics: PPCT-Manipulations; Carry Skills and Devices.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; An actively resistant subject who is non-assaultive but flees or employs force to make arrest more difficult may be met with these tactics: PPCT-Manipulations/Stuns; Chemical Aerosol; Electronic Control Weapon; Canine.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; A subject who is threatening assault or attacking or threatening self-harm may be met with these tactics: Striking Techniques - Kicks, Knees, Elbows and Hands; Contact Weapons; Less Lethal Munitions; Canine.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; One of the contributing factors is: Multiple Assailants - Uncontrolled Individuals.</p>
<p class="continued">The Employer's position about the appropriate force and techniques for the 10/3/15 situation is confusing. The use-of-force instructor testified that open hand head strikes are allowed for active resistance but the continuum shows them belonging to the higher level of an assaultive subject. The Employer also argues that the Grievant violated policy by using shoves, which are not part of his training, and yet suggests a shove might be appropriate for a higher level of resistance although shoves are not listed anywhere on the continuum. This ambiguity was pointed out by the Grievant in his IA statement, where he said that: the continuum is a guideline and not set in stone; and there were contributing factors including the multiple uncontrolled individuals and the number of officers.</p>
<p class="continued">The Employer has suggested that the Grievant's failure to call for backup belies his claim that he needed to use the force that he did. The Grievant has reasonably and credibly explained that: the situation was contained until the occupants of V1 returned on foot; the situation started to escalate when D1 resumed complaining about the ticket, getting the others riled up; and if the escalation had continued any longer he would have called for backup, but he thought he could effectively bring it under control and he succeeded.</p>
<p class="continued">A fundamental problem with the allegation of excessive force is the RPD's characterization of the Grievant's contact with D1's head an an &ldquo;open hand strike&rdquo; of the type permitted only in response to active resistance. The evidence shows that was not the type of strike used by the Grievant. A former RPD use-of-force instructor testified that: he and the current use-of-force instructor implemented the open-hand head strike technique in approximately 2000; it was designed to disorient and gain control of a resistant subject; if properly administered, it causes a fall to the ground; a properly cupped hand strike to the back of the head with follow-through will &ldquo;launch&rdquo; the subject; and this is not what he saw the Grievant doing on the video.</p>
<p class="continued">The video corroborates the Grievant's claim that, rather than using his dominant right hand backed up by his hips to deliver an open-hand strike to hurt, knock down or disorient D1, he deliberately used his left hand with limited force to deliver an upward glancing blow to the upper right part of the back of D1's head to get him to stop arguing and move away from the area. The video shows that although D1's head jerked forward, his feet did not move until the second shove sent him stumbling a few steps. D1 did not report the incident or claim any injury, except stating after the investigation was underway that he had a headache later. D1's claims of injury in a recently filed lawsuit are not deemed as proof for the purposes of this arbitration.</p>
<p class="continued">It is undisputed that D1 was passively resistant, failing to comply with the Grievant's repeated order to move away from the area of the traffic stop and proceed to the basketball court, his claimed destination. The RPD's continuum for use of force specifies that such passive resistance can be addressed with techniques that require placing hands on a subject in ways that cause pain: manipulating pressure points, and using an armbar. These listed techniques likely would result in at least as much discomfort as a glancing slap to the back of the head or being shoved a few steps with limited force. Also, as the Union argues, the slap and shove are far less forceful than the techniques specified for the next level: chemical aerosols, taser, and canine. It is concluded that the amount of force used by the Grievant did not exceed the amount of force inherent in the techniques listed for passive resistance.</p>
<p class="continued">The Employer argues that POs are not trained to shove a person to get their attention or to get them to move along, alleging that the Grievant intentionally and willfully ignored what he had been taught by using techniques that were outside his training. PO2's unrebutted testimony was that shoving is a tactic that is used but not trained. As noted above, it has not been shown that shoving, or other techniques not covered in training, are necessarily prohibited. It is concluded that the Grievant's use of force was not excessive or unreasonable in this incident, given the totality of the circumstances and its effectiveness in deescalating the situation without injuring D1.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Failure to Report</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The policy on Use of Force states:</p>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;A written report and a <i>Special Incident Report</i> prepared according to Department procedures will be required in the following situations:</p>
<p class="continued">1) When a firearm is discharged outside of the firing range;</p>
<p class="continued">2) When a use of force results in death or injury;</p>
<p class="continued">3) When a non-lethal weapon is used on a person;</p>
<p class="continued">4) When an officer threatens the use of deadly force;</p>
<p class="continued">5) Any force used in response to significant resistance.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">The policy on Special Incident Review states: &ldquo;This Policy provides for reporting and review of major incidents. It lists the types of incidents that must be reported and the proper reporting procedures&rdquo;. Among the types listed is &ldquo;Use of force, threatened, deadly and non-deadly&rdquo;. The form provided is called a salmon sheet because of its color, and contains boxes for indicating whether the type of incident is: use of force, officer assaulted, pursuit, or bias crime. The section for indicating the type of force used refers to &ldquo;significant resistance&rdquo; and lists: taser; mace; baton; canine apprehension; threatened use of deadly weapon; and use of deadly force. The salmon sheet is meant to be attached to the regular Incident Report that is created for criminal offenses that are assigned a case number. The absence of the lesser techniques on this form suggests that passive resistance is not considered to be &ldquo;significant resistance&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">On 10/3/15 the Grievant was told by his Sergeant that the type of traffic citation he issued to D1 did not require a case number and incident report, but he should make notes on the citation about the incident. This is what the Grievant did, noting on D1's citation the nature of the careless driving, and that &ldquo;all occupants then walked up on me later trying to cause trouble&rdquo;. The Grievant credibly testified that he made these notes as part of his usual process, to help him remember the situation if he was later called to testify. The Grievant has never claimed that these notes were meant to substitute for any required report.</p>
<p class="continued">According to the Grievant's statements, when he thought about whether he should write a report on the encounter with D1, he considered: the absence of a case number and file; and that the level of force used did not rise to the level that required a Special Incident Report. Although at some point it crossed his mind that maybe he should file a CYA (cover your ass) report in case some issue might arise, he chose not to do so. The Grievant has admitted that: he knew that his contact with D1 had been recorded by more than one of the Somalis present; and he was concerned that it might look worse on video than it did in his head. He inquired whether it had been recorded by PO2's squad camera because, according to the Grievant, he wanted to see how bad it looked, which might have prompted him to write a report and/or inform the Sergeant, as he had done previously when he anticipated a possible complaint. The Grievant also has admitted that he: is aware of the RPD practice that when in doubt, a report should be written; should have alerted the command staff but he &ldquo;screwed up&rdquo;; and can't explain the disconnect in his thinking.</p>
<p class="continued">The Investigator testified that all physical force, including the lowest level of listed techniques, requires a salmon sheet. He attributed the rareness of this in reports over an 18-month period to their not being used very often, which raises a question about their usefulness. If the RPD intends that all instances of &ldquo;hands-on&rdquo; must be reported, the policy and the salmon sheet should be revised to make this clear. As currently stated and understood by the POs, the Grievant's reasoning that the level of force he used did not require a salmon sheet was technically correct.</p>
<p class="continued">However, in the existing climate of heightened concern about the relationship between law enforcement and communities of color, and the prevalence of incendiary videos arousing community anger, it is not acceptable that the Grievant failed to alert the command staff of this incident. This failure caused them to be blindsided when the media started calling about the Twitter video, and caught in the embarrassing situation of not knowing how to respond. Although the command staff may have been unable to provide information until it investigated the matter, an alert would have enabled them at least to comment that an investigation was underway, and they would not have suffered the embarrassment of not knowing that one of their officers had been involved in what the abbreviated video made appear to be an abusive racial incident.</p>
<p class="continued">Unfortunately for everyone, the media coverage of the video and the statements by the two drivers precipitated a storm of criticism that blew the incident out of proportion. The Chief's reaction to the Somali leader's accusation that it constituted an &ldquo;assault&rdquo; was to refer the matter to the BCA for a criminal investigation and to suspend the two POs from duty pending the investigation. During the following months the POs were prohibited from discussing the incident with anyone except their representatives and so their explanation could not be taken into account. After the investigations resulted in no criminal charges, public pressure dictated an internal investigation to determine misconduct and punish the Grievant.</p>
<p class="continued">In this environment, the Grievant's actions were viewed in the worst possible light, leading to the conclusion that his failure to report the incident was intended to cover it up and get away with serious misconduct. However, this conclusion is not supported by the evidence. The Grievant was aware that more than one witness had recorded his contact with D1, as he was told by a couple of Somalis and by PO2 at the scene. The Grievant was also aware that such recordings regularly appear on the internet. The Grievant's comments to D2 about Snapchat were intended to convey the Grievant's awareness that D2's earlier claim of not being able to establish a good enough internet connection to retrieve his insurance information was suspect. The Employer's late-blooming hypothesis that the Snapchat comment meant that the Grievant expected the sole video to have disappeared is not convincing, and as the Grievant testified, if he had been asked about this in person rather than by e-mail, he could have cleared up the Investigator's misapprehension about the Grievant's knowledge of Snapchat.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union concedes that the Grievant should have filed a report but argues that his failure to do so was a mistaken interpretation of the rules and a simple policy violation. The Union cites previous RPD disciplinary matters where: an officer who lied in his report about having followed up on an investigation as instructed received a written reprimand; and a sergeant was suspended for having agreed with another officer to include inaccurate facts in his report. The Union argues that these deliberate acts of deception were more serious than the Grievant's &ldquo;sin of omission&rdquo;, which should be considered in determining what discipline is appropriate.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant's previous counseling regarding report writing focused on the need to include more relevant detail and did not involve a failure to do reports when required, except in one minor incident involving the canine biting and tearing a backpack. It is concluded that the Grievant's failure to report this incident was not intended to conceal it or deceive the RPD, and so did not constitute misconduct. However, it was a lapse in judgment that contributed to serious turmoil and disruption, warranting disciplinary action.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Racial/Ethnic Bias</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Investigator's report listed policies determined to have been violated by the Grievant,:</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; #103-Conduct Unbecoming a Police Officer, which requires officers to: perform impartially without expressing prejudice concerning race, color, creed, religion, national origin; etc.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; #136-Impartial Policing: &ldquo;In an effort to prevent the perception of biased law enforcement, officers shall &hellip; be respectful and professional.</p>
<p class="continued">Despite the listing of these policies referring to impartial policing, the allegations against the Grievant did not specify that his alleged misconduct was motivated by racial or ethnic bias, and the Employer has not directly accused the Grievant of such. However, the Employer alludes to race-related concerns: it argues that 38&percnt; of the City residents are minority, and the Grievant's actions were stressful on the community; the Chief testified that he kept the head of the SHRC informed of developments; and the City Manager testified that the Chief and staff did a good job of defusing the Somali community. The City Manager also testified that based on his single viewing of the squad video: he was concerned about the condescending way the Grievant talked to D1 as though he saw him as less than himself; and he didn't seem to be dealing with an individual when he kept saying &ldquo;you guys&rdquo;, which indicated bias against a class of people.</p>
<p class="continued">On cross-examination the Investigator was asked if there was any basis for concluding that the Grievant's actions were based on race; he responded that it was the Grievant's referring to the subjects as &ldquo;you people&rdquo;. After reviewing the transcript, he conceded that the Grievant had not done that but pointed to the Grievant's addressing them as &ldquo;you guys&rdquo;, and accusing a group of Somalis he had never met before of never telling the truth one day in their life as indicative of racial bias. The Investigator conceded that the Grievant had referred to the group as &ldquo;you guys&rdquo; multiple other times without suggesting racial bias.</p>
<p class="continued">This incident started with a large group of Somali young people congregating in a neighborhood park, and some of them driving carelessly on the residential streets. The Somali drivers stopped by the Grievant were not selected from a racially diverse group. The Grievant credibly testified that he regularly addresses groups of either gender as &ldquo;you guys&rdquo;, and it is evident that he was addressing multiple people rather than an individual when he did so. He used it multiple times in a neutral way aside from the times when he used coarse and accusatory language. It is concluded that the Grievant's use of &ldquo;you guys&rdquo; does not connote bias against a class of people. However, to the extent that the Grievant failed to be respectful and professional, he failed to avoid the possible perception of biased law enforcement.</p>
<p class="continued">The Investigator's report conceded that the subjects were lying to the Grievant. Aside from the issue of coarse language, it is not unreasonable for an officer to tell subjects that he is not being deceived by the lies offered in response to his questions. Accusing a group of people who are lying of lying is not a basis for concluding racial bias. The Grievant's exaggerating how much the subjects lie likely stemmed from annoyance with their behavior rather than bias.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union persuasively argues that the Grievant had policed this City's racially diverse population for ten years with no complaints about racial bias, and various witnesses testified that in working with him they had never known him to say or do any inappropriate thing related to race or ethnicity. It is concluded that there is no basis in the record for concluding that the Grievant's actions during this incident on October 3, 2015 were motivated by racial or ethnic bias.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Brady/Giglio Status</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The City Prosecutor designated the Grievant as being disqualified as a source of information in future prosecutions, based on the findings of the IA investigation. The City Prosecutor testified that if this arbitration award negates those findings: they will still have to be disclosed to the defense in future cases prosecuted by the City if the Grievant is involved; and perhaps the Arbitrator's negation would also be disclosed. The parties agree that such a designation is not grievable and the Arbitrator has no authority to review it. Nevertheless, it is troubling that such a designation, which can effectively end a career in law enforcement, should be made based on such defective grounds as the flawed findings of the IA investigation.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Performance History</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Grievant's performance evaluations were generally satisfactory or above average, with some categories, such as skill and initiative, sometimes rated as outstanding. His community presentations on behalf of the RPD were praised for their professionalism and he performed well in special assignments such as school liaison and SWAT team. Because of his special assignments and his remedial training in 2013, the Grievant may have been the most highly trained PO in the RPD, which seems to have been reflected in his knowledge and skill level.</p>
<p class="continued">A repeated criticism of the Grievant's performance, and the subject of counseling sessions, was the lack of sufficient detail in his reports to justify the use of force. This problem was compounded after canines were added to the department in 2012, creating a learning experience for everyone. The Grievant faced the challenge of learning how to properly train, control and deploy his canine partner, which led to some counseling by supervisors who may not have completely appreciated the complexities. The Grievant's remedial training in 2013 resulted in improved report writing and K-9 handling.</p>
<p class="continued">The Employer has emphasized the Grievant's previous counseling in support of its position. It is noted that counseling is not a disciplinary action and should not be considered as a factor in progressive discipline. It is also noted that because counseling is not disciplinary action, it cannot be grieved, leaving the supervisor's written opinion about an incident as uncontested documentation with no opportunity for rebuttal. Furthermore, openly disagreeing with the supervisor's assessment would likely be a negative factor in a PO's record, given the hierarchical nature of this paramilitary organization.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant's one disciplinary action was a documented oral warning for using excessive force in arresting a suspect. That assaultive situation was not similar to the 10/3/15 incident, and having determined that the Grievant did not use excessive force in this incident, the previous disciplinary action is irrelevant.</p>
<p class="continued">The City has referenced another lawsuit involving the Grievant that the City has settled; however, that incident involved multiple POs and some Sergeants, all of whom were counseled about it. It is noted that the City Manager testified that he agreed to a settlement that he thought was too high because the mediator advised him that in the current climate a jury was likely to award more. That case has no bearing on the 10/3/15 incident.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant was highly respected and admired by his colleagues, some of whom attested to his skill and professionalism and their trust in working with him. His coworkers felt so strongly about his termination from employment that they organized to protest it and made it clear that they would welcome him back to their ranks.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>SUMMARY OF CONCLUSIONS</b></h4>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Making contact with D1's group after it returned on foot to the area of the traffic stop was prompted by legitimate safety concerns and did not constitute misconduct.</p></li>
<li><p>Although the Grievant's coarse language violated RPD policy and could offend other subjects in different types of situations, its use in this case does not warrant disciplinary action.</p></li>
<li><p>Although the Grievant showed that he was upset and angered by D1's provocation, which may warrant counseling, his demeanor throughout the bulk of the incident was not inappropriate and does not warrant disciplinary action.</p></li>
<li><p>The force used by the Grievant in this incident was not excessive or unreasonable, given the totality of the circumstances.</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant's failure to either write a report or inform his supervising Sergeant of this incident was not intended to conceal it or deceive the command staff, which would constitute misconduct, but was a lapse in judgment constituting unacceptable performance that warrants disciplinary action.</p></li>
<li><p>There is no basis for concluding that the Grievant's actions were motivated by racial or ethnic bias.</p></li></ol>
<h4 align="center"><b>AWARD</b></h4>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>The Employer did not have just cause to terminate the Grievant's employment with the Richfield Police Department.</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant's failure to properly report the incident constituted unacceptable performance, warranting disciplinary action in the form of a three-shift unpaid suspension.</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant shall be reinstated to his position and made whole for losses due to the termination of his employment with the exception of a three-shift period of unpaid suspension.</p></li></ol>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>