<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration between United Food &amp; Commercial Workers District Union Local One, Union, and Tops Markets, LLC, Employer.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>November 30, 2016.</p>
<p>Michael G. Whelan, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Opinion and Award</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Introduction</i></b></h4>
<p>The instant matter arises under the 2014-2017 collective bargaining agreement (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo;) between Tops Market, LLC (&ldquo;Employer&rdquo; or &ldquo;Tops&rdquo;), and the United Food &amp; Commercial Workers District Union Local One (&ldquo;Union&rdquo;). The parties to the CBA selected Michael G. Whelan as the Arbitrator to decide three consolidated grievances submitted by the Union arising out of the same incident. The parties presented evidence and argument on June 14 and 15, 2016, and August 11, 2016, in Amherst, New York. At the close of the evidentiary hearing, the parties agreed to submit post-hearing briefs on or before September 16, 2016. Two enlargements of time were subsequently provided, and post-hearing briefs were timely submitted by the parties on October 3, 2016. On that date, the hearing record was deemed to be closed.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Issue</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">The parties stipulated to the arbitrability of the grievance and to the following statement of the issue:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Whether the discharge of the Grievants was for just cause. If not, what is the appropriate remedy?</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Relevant Contract Language</i></b></h4>
<p align="center"><i>ARTICLE 2</i></p>
<p align="center"><i>MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</i></p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">2.1 The operation and management of the Employer's stores, employees of which are covered by this Agreement, including the location, opening and closing of the same, the products to be handled and sold and the supervision of the working force, including but not limited to the right to hire, suspend or discharge for proper cause and the establishment and maintenance of rules for the safe and efficient operation, are vested exclusively in the Employer. The Employer retains all rights and authority except as the same may be specifically abridged or modified in this Agreement.</p></blockquote>
<p align="center"><i>ARTICLE 26</i></p>
<p align="center"><i>PREMIUM PAY</i></p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">26.3 Employees performing the job of &ldquo;Manager on Duty&rdquo; will receive a one dollar (&dollar;1.00) per hour premium for all hours worked as such.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Relevant Employer Policies</i></b></h4>
<p align="center"><i>TOPS COUPON POLICY</i></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>We are happy to accept your manufacturer coupons under the following guidelines:</b></p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>TOPS reserves the right to limit the quantities of coupons redeemed per day, per customer.</p></li>
<li><p>TOPS reserves the right to accept or reject any coupon.</p>
<p>&hellip;</p></li>
<li><p>We will not accept photocopies of any coupons.</p>
<p>&hellip;</p></li>
<li><p>Where available, TOPS GasPoints earned on the redemption of manufacturers' paper coupons limited to 10 coupons/100 TOPS GasPoints per household, per day. &hellip;</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued"><b>Double coupon policy</b></p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Customers with a TOPS BonusPlus or BonusCard will receive double the value of manufacturers' paper coupons with a face value of up to 99&cent;.</p></li>
<li><p>We reserve the right to limit four (4) double coupons per same item, per day, per household&hellip;. (C-1).</p></li></ul>
</blockquote>
<p align="center"><i>POS FRAUD AND BONUSPLUS FRAUD</i></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i><b>POS Fraud and Improper Use of a Tops BonusPlus</b></i></p>
<p class="continued">It is a violation of Tops policy for any Associate to engage in POS (Point of Sale) fraud and/or to obtain or attempt to obtain additional dollars, reward points (including but not limited to Tops GasPoints or other reward points towards company promotions), merchandise, rebates, cash, promotional items, or other personal benefit of the Tops BonusPlus without paying the full and proper authorized price for products and services, or by using or allowing the use of your personal Tops BonusPlus for purchases made by anyone other than you or an immediate family member living in your household. Such activities will be investigated thoroughly, and may subject you to disciplinary actions, up to and including separation of employment and, where appropriate, prosecution to the fullest extent of the law.</p></blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i><b>Associate POS Fraud and Tops BonusPlus violations include, but are not limited to:</b></i></p>
<p align="center">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">9. Using or allowing the use of any Tops BonusPlus, including your own, to exceed authorized limits.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Facts</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>The parties</i></h4>
<p>Tops' Buffalo Division operates a number of grocery stores in Western New York and Western Pennsylvania. The Union is the bargaining representative for employees in these stores, with the exception of certain managers, supervisors, professional employees, and guards. The Grievants &ndash; GGG, SSS, and WWW &ndash; were all members of that bargaining unit and employed by Tops at Store 22, located in Niagara Falls, New York. All three of the Grievants were terminated for alleged violations of Tops' coupon policy in October 2015.<ftnote num="1"><para>All dates refer to 2015, unless otherwise indicated.</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>Staffing the &ldquo;front-end&rdquo; of Store 22</i></h4>
<p>Tops' grocery customers check out and pay for their purchases at registers in the front end of the store, which is also referred to as the point-of-sale (&ldquo;POS&rdquo;). In Store 22, the front end has several registers where cashiers ring up customer purchases, including transactions where customers may present coupons for discounts on products they are purchasing. The store also has self-checkout registers, called &ldquo;EZ-scan&rdquo; stations. If customers using the EZ-scan stations need assistance, they are assisted by an EZ-scan attendant. Cashiers and EZ-scan attendants are led by customer service leads (&ldquo;CSLs&rdquo;), who provide them with assistance. CSLs are authorized to manually override the computer registers, which are programmed to limit certain transactions. Cashiers, EZ-scan attendants, and CSLs are all bargaining-unit positions. The front end is managed by a customer service manager (&ldquo;CSM&rdquo;), which is a managerial, non-bargaining-unit position. The CSM supervises all the cashiers, E-Z scan attendants, and CSLs, and also has the ability to manually override the registers.</p>
<h4 align="left">C. <i>The Grievants and their positions</i></h4>
<p>Grievant GGG was hired by Tops on September 7, 2013. He was employed as a cashier, a position he held until approximately February of 2014, when he was promoted to CSL. GGG also at times worked as an EZ-scan attendant. GGG held the position of CSL from February 2014 until his termination on October 8<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<p>Grievant SSS was hired by Tops on March 1, 2014. SSS did not testify at the hearing, and the record does not address her position at the time of hire. SSS was a cashier at the time of her termination on October 16<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<p>Grievant WWW was hired by Tops on September 28, 1984. During her thirty-one years with Tops, WWW held several positions, including bakery clerk, bulk food clerk, assistant manager of bulk foods, cashier, pharmacy clerk, CSM, photo lab manager, and floral manager. From about 2004 until her termination, WWW at times assumed the role of manager-on-duty (&ldquo;MOD&rdquo;). MOD is not a job classification. Rather, it involves assuming the duties of the store manager when the store manager or other salaried, non-bargaining-unit employees are not present in the store. When WWW assumed the role of MOD, she received a &dollar;1 per hour premium on top of her regular pay. WWW was the floral manager at the time of her termination on October 9<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<h4 align="left">D. <i>Tops' Coupon Policy and BonusCard Fraud Policy</i></h4>
<p>Tops uses several types of coupons in order to encourage sales and customer loyalty. The type of coupon relevant to this matter is a manufacturer coupon, which, as the name suggests, is issued by the manufacturer of the product. Customers who present valid manufacturer coupons to Tops' cashiers at the POS are granted a discount on the purchase of the applicable item equal to the face value of the coupon. After receiving manufacturer coupons at the POS, cashiers place them in their registers. Tops collects the coupons daily, and they are sent to a clearinghouse for redemption, where Tops is paid an amount equal to the face value of the coupons. The clearinghouse will not reimburse Tops for photocopies of coupons.</p>
<p>Tops places certain restrictions on the use of manufacturer coupons, pursuant to the Tops Coupon Policy (&ldquo;Coupon Policy&rdquo;). The following guidelines in the Coupon Policy are relevant to this matter:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>We will not accept photocopies of any coupons.</p>
<p>&hellip;</p></li>
<li><p>Where available, TOPS GasPoints earned on the redemption of manufacturers' paper coupons limited to 10 coupons/100 TOPS GasPoints per household, per day. &hellip;</p>
<p>&hellip;</p></li>
<li><p>Customers with a TOPS BonusPlus or BonusCard will receive double the value of manufacturers' paper coupons with a face value of up to 99&cent;.</p></li>
<li><p>We reserve the right to limit four (4) double coupons per same item, per day, per household.</p></li></ul>
<p>Tops also has a promotional program known as BonusPlus or BonusCard. Under this program, customers, including employees, may receive a BonusCard that entitles them to certain benefits and discounts on purchases. For example, customers and employees with a BonusCard are eligible to get double the value of manufacturer's coupons on purchases, subject to limitations described in the Coupon Policy. They may also use manufacturer coupons to accumulate points off the purchase of gas (&ldquo;GasPoints&rdquo;). For every 100 GasPoints accrued, customers are eligible to receive 10&cent; off per gallon of gas purchased at Tops fuel stations.</p>
<p>Employees are required to sign an acknowledgment at hire and at regular intervals thereafter indicating that they have read and understood the &ldquo;POS Fraud and BonusPlus Fraud&rdquo; policy (&ldquo;Bonus Card Fraud Policy&rdquo;). Among the 13 listed violations of the BonusCard Fraud Policy is &ldquo;&lsqb;u&rsqb;sing or allowing the use of any Tops BonusPlus, including your own, to exceed authorized limits.&rdquo; The BonusCard Fraud Policy also cautions employees that violations &ldquo;may subject you to disciplinary actions, up to and including separation of employment&hellip;.&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="left">E. <i>Progresso soup promotion</i></h4>
<p>In September 2015, an unusual set of circumstances arose under which it was possible to get cans of Progresso soup for free. Typically, Progresso soup sold for &dollar;1.69 a can. Under a Tops store promotion, the price of Progresso soup was reduced to &dollar;1 per can. At the same time, there was a manufacturer coupon in circulation for Progresso soup that provided for a reduction of 50&cent; off the price of each can. If this coupon was used in combination with a Tops BonusCard, which provided for doubling the value of the coupon, customers could receive a can of soup for free.</p>
<p>Six Tops employees at Store 22, including the Grievants, eventually learned of this method of obtaining free cans of soup, and some of them set out to use it. Several hundred photocopies of the manufacturer coupons for Progresso soup were made, and several Tops employees, including CSL DDD obtained copies. On September 23<sup>rd</sup>, DDD approached WWW, who was the MOD at the time, and explained to WWW that it was possible to get Progresso soup for free using the combination of the store promotion, the manufacturer coupon, and the BonusCard. DDD also told WWW that DDD had a lot of photocopies of the coupons, and DDD asked WWW if WWW wanted any. WWW asked for 30 and sought assurance from DDD that they were allowed to use photocopies. DDD assured WWW that cashiers take photocopied coupons all the time.</p>
<p>WWW pulled 30 cans of Progresso soup from the shelves and approached GGG, who at that time was in the front end working as an EZ-scan attendant. WWW advised GGG of her intent to obtain the soup using the coupons and her BonusCard, and she sought assurance from GGG that it was permissible to use the photocopies to obtain the free soup. GGG assured WWW that it was acceptable. WWW then gave GGG the 30 cans of soup, the 30 photocopied coupons, and her BonusCard. WWW then went outside the store to take a break while GGG rang up the transaction.</p>
<p>The EZ-Scan stations are programmed to restrict the number of items that are subject to double coupons to four, which is the limit under the guidelines in the Coupon Policy. This limiting feature may be overridden, however, by CSLs. GGG used his ability to override the system to ring up all 30 cans of soup. In addition, GGG structured the transaction to avoid another restriction on obtaining GasPoints, which are limited to 10 manufacturer coupons per household per day. GGG rang up the 30 cans in three separate transactions of 10 each. In that way, GGG enabled WWW to receive GasPoints for all 30 cans of soup. When WWW returned from her break, the soup was all bagged up and ready to go. In total, WWW received 30 cans of free soup and 360 GasPoints.</p>
<p>Later in the evening on September 23<sup>rd</sup>, SSS obtained 10 cans of free soup and 100 GasPoints using this method. Again, GGG processed the transaction and overrode the system to allow exceeding the four-item limit on the use of double coupons.</p>
<h4 align="left">F. <i>The investigation</i></h4>
<p>CSM MMM was responsible for collecting manufacturer coupons from Store 22 registers to be sent to the clearinghouse for reimbursement. On the morning of September 24<sup>th</sup>, Sodor noticed that there were over 200 photocopied coupons &ndash; each for 50&cent; off a single can of Progresso soup. Sodor notified other members of management at Store 22 about the photocopied coupons. Given the scope of the matter, EEE, an asset protection senior detective, was assigned to conduct an investigation.</p>
<p>During his investigation, EEE recovered more than 300 photocopied Progresso soup coupons that were processed at Store 22 registers on or about September 23<sup>rd</sup>. He learned that five Tops employees were involved in these transactions, including SSS and WWW, and that GGG had processed the SSS and WWW transactions. EEE interviewed each of the employees involved, including the Grievants, who had Union representation during these interviews. EEE summarized his findings with respect to each employee involved, including the Grievants, in an asset protection report.</p>
<h4 align="left">G. <i>Grievants' termination</i></h4>
<p>Based on the results of EEE's investigation, Tops determined that the Grievants violated the Coupon Policy and the BonusCard Fraud Policy by either using the photocopied coupons to obtain free merchandise and GasPoints or processing the transactions. Tops viewed these offenses to be sufficiently serious to warrant immediate termination. All six employees involved in the transactions that occurred on or about September 23<sup>rd</sup> were terminated</p>
<p class="continued">Pursuant to the grievance procedure in the CBA, the Union timely filed grievances challenging Grievants&rsquo; terminations. The Employer denied those grievances, which led to the Union initiating the instant arbitration proceedings.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Discussion</i></b></h4>
<p>The term &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; in the employment context is used to stand for the notion that there are limitations on managerial discretion to discipline employees. In determining the question of just cause, an arbitrator is called upon to interpret that phrase as a term of art that is unique to collective bargaining agreements. While an arbitrator may refer to sources other than the collective bargaining agreement for enlightenment as to the meaning of just cause in the context of the facts of the particular case, the essential role of the arbitrator is to interpret the collective bargaining agreement. In interpreting the meaning of just cause in the instant case, this Arbitrator draws the essence of the meaning of that phrase from the CBA.</p>
<p>It is well-established in labor arbitration that when, as in the present matter, an employer's right to discipline an employee is limited by the requirement that any such action be for just cause, the employer has the burden of proving by clear and convincing evidence that the discipline was for just cause. Therefore, the Employer has the burden of persuading the Arbitrator by clear and convincing evidence that there was just cause for the termination of the Grievants.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>The Just Cause Standard</i></b></h4>
<p>A determination of whether just cause exists for discipline requires at least two primary determinations. The first is whether there is a reasonable basis under the collective bargaining agreement to impose discipline on the employee in the first instance. If there is a reasonable basis upon which to impose discipline, the second determination is whether the penalty imposed is reasonable under the totality of the circumstances. These are two distinct inquiries and must be dealt with separately.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>I. Whether There was a Reasonable Basis to Impose Discipline</b></h4>
<p>The determination of whether there was a reasonable basis to impose discipline consists of a number of substantive and procedural elements. Primary among the substantive elements is the existence of sufficient proof that the employee engaged in the conduct for which he or she was disciplined. Other elements include a requirement that an employee know or reasonably be expected to know ahead of time that engaging in a particular type of behavior will likely result in discipline; and a requirement that discipline be administered even-handedly &ndash; that is, that similarly situated employees be treated similarly and disparate treatment be avoided.</p>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>Whether Grievants engaged in misconduct</i></h4>
<p>The first issue for determination is whether the Grievants engaged in the conduct for which they were terminated. The basis for the Employer's termination decisions are included on Tops' Record of Associate Corrective Action forms and Tops' Termination forms for all the Grievants. On these forms, the stated reason for the terminations was violation of the Coupon Policy. The Employer also presented evidence and argument that the Grievants violated Tops' BonusCard Fraud Policy.</p>
<h4 align="left">1. <i>Use of photocopied coupons</i></h4>
<p>The Coupon Policy states that Tops &ldquo;will not accept photocopies of any coupons,&rdquo; thus prohibiting the use of photocopied coupons. SSS and WWW used photocopies of coupons for Progresso soup, and GGG conducted these transactions. As such, all three Grievants violated this provision of the Coupon Policy.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the Union presented evidence that Tops had a practice of accepting photocopied coupons that conflicted with this provision of the Coupon Policy. In instances where employers have condoned policy violations in the past, arbitrators often will not hold employees accountable for violating those policies. N. Brand, <i>Discipline and Discharge in Arbitration: ABA Section of Labor and Employment Law</i> 81-83 (BNA 1998). There are also instances where the past practices of the parties are given binding effect. Generally, to be binding on the parties, strong proof is required that the practice is (1) unequivocal; (2) clearly enunciated and acted upon; and (3) readily ascertainable over a reasonable period of time as a fixed and established practice accepted by the parties. F. Elkouri &amp; E. Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i> 607-08 (6<sup>th</sup> ed. 2003). A common element of these defenses based on an employer's past enforcement of rule violations is that the employer knows the rule is being violated and chooses not to enforce it.</p>
<p>GGG testified that he accepted photocopied coupons because &ldquo;it was a routine practice&rdquo; and that CSM MMM gave him permission to take them. MMM denied that accepting photocopied coupons was routine or that she gave GGG or any CSL permission to accept photocopied coupons. MMM admitted, however, that at times &ndash; perhaps once every three months &ndash; she would allow good customers to use photocopied coupons.</p>
<p>Brianna Fish (&ldquo;Fish), who worked as a cashier for a little over a year prior to the Grievants' terminations, was called by the Union and provided testimony that addresses the inconsistencies in GGG' and MMM's testimony. Fish testified that she was told by MMM not to take photocopied coupons. Whenever Fish was presented with photocopied coupons from a customer, Fish would contact MMM, who never denied customers the use of them. For example, Fish testified that MMM would allow a regular customer to use multiple photocopied coupons to purchase items once or twice a week for months. Further, Fish testified that all the CSLs Fish worked with, including GGG, DDD, and Kilmer, always asked for an override from a CSM to approve the use of photocopied coupons.</p>
<p>Fish's testimony establishes two key points. First, while MMM had approved the use of a limited number of photocopied coupons in violation of the Coupon Policy, it was not Tops' routine practice to accept photocopied coupons.<ftnote num="2"><para>In fact, this matter first came to light because MMM, who collected the coupons from the registers on a daily basis, noticed a significant number of photocopied coupons on September 24th.</para></ftnote> Most significantly, it is also clear from Fish's testimony that CSLs were not given the authority to accept photocopied coupons, and they always called MMM to approve the acceptance of them.</p>
<p>Under these circumstances, it was not the routine practice of cashiers, E-Z scan attendants, or CSLs to accept photocopied coupons. Rather, the practice was that cashiers and CSLs knew they could not accept photocopied coupons, and they did not accept them without getting approval from the CSM. As such, the Coupon Policy's prohibition on photocopied coupons was not rendered invalid by a past practice or lax enforcement.<ftnote num="3"><para>MMM's waiver of the photocopy prohibition for good customers may raise issues about whether it was a proper exercise of her management authority or whether it may have signaled to her subordinates that it was acceptable to accept photocopied coupons. Nevertheless, the testimony of MMM, which was corroborated by Fish, establishes that bargaining unit employees knew that they did not have the authority to override this aspect of the Coupon Policy.</para></ftnote> For these reasons, the Employer has established clear and convincing evidence that the Grievants violated the photocopy prohibition in the Coupon Policy.</p>
<h4 align="left">2. <i>Limits on the use of double coupons</i></h4>
<p>The Coupon Policy also states that Tops will &ldquo;reserve the right to limit four (4) double coupons per same item, per day, per household.&rdquo; The language of this section of the Coupon Policy is a reservation of rights for Tops, and not a prohibition, such as the prohibition on photocopied coupons. Although the Coupon Policy does not read as a blanket prohibition on exceeding the limit, a provision of the BonusCard Fraud Policy states that &ldquo;&lsqb;u&rsqb;sing or allowing the use of any Tops BonusPlus, including your own, to exceed authorized limits&rdquo; is a violation of the BonusCard Fraud Policy. Inasmuch as the use of four double coupons for the same item, per day, per household is an express limitation for authorized use, Tops' employees subject to the BonusCard Fraud Policy cannot exceed that limit.</p>
<p>SSS used her BonusCard and 10 photocopied coupons which were doubled to acquire 10 cans of free Progresso Soup. WWW used her BonusCard and 30 photocopied coupons which were doubled to acquire 30 cans of free Progresso Soup. Thus, both of these Grievants exceeded the authorized limit of four double coupons per item, per day, per household. In both of these situations, GGG conducted the transactions. Therefore, all three Grievants violated these provisions of the Coupon Policy, as expressly limited by the BonusCard Fraud Policy.</p>
<p>However, the Union argues that the double-coupon limit was not enforced in practice. As discussed above, if a policy is not enforced in practice, it is problematic to hold employees accountable for violations of that policy. Here, the registers and EZ-scan stations were programmed to only permit the use of four double coupons per item, per transaction. In order to exceed that limit, the register would have to be overridden manually by either a CSL or a CSM. The Union presented evidence that Tops permitted customers to exceed the limit on the use of double coupons, although MMM denied that she had ever done so, and she insisted that she did not tell anyone else they could do so. Even if such overrides were provided to customers on occasion, those customers were not subject to the BonusCard Fraud Policy. On the other hand, there was no evidence presented that prior to the incidents at issue here, this type of override was ever provided to Tops' employees who were subject to the BonusCard Fraud Policy. For this reason, there was no practice that conflicted with the BonusCard Fraud Policy provisions applicable to employees. Thus, the Employer has established clear and convincing evidence that the Grievants violated the limitation on the use of double coupons in the Coupon Policy and the BonusCard Fraud Policy.</p>
<h4 align="left">3. <i>Limits on GasPoints</i></h4>
<p>The Coupon Policy further states that &ldquo;TOPS GasPoints earned on the redemption of manufacturers' paper coupons limited to 10 coupons/100 TOPS GasPoints per household, per day. &hellip;&rdquo; WWW used her BonusCard and 30 photocopied coupons to acquire 300 GasPoints on September 23<sup>rd</sup>. GGG rang up these purchases in three lots of 10 cans each, with each lot earning the limit of 100 GasPoints. GGG denied that he structured the transaction in this way to circumvent the 100 GasPoint limit, but he was not able to provide a plausible alternative explanation for why he rang up the transactions in this manner. For these reasons, both GGG and WWW violated the Coupon Policy concerning the limits on the accumulation of GasPoints.</p>
<p>For the above-stated reasons, the Arbitrator concludes that the Grievants engaged in the conduct for which they were terminated.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>Whether Grievants knew or could reasonably have known that violating these policies could be grounds for their termination</i></h4>
<p>Another element of the just cause standard is whether the employees knew or reasonably could be expected to know ahead of time that engaging in a particular type of behavior will likely result in discipline. This element concerns whether clear and reasonable work rules have been established and promulgated. The Union argues that WWW and GGG were not given clear training on the use of coupons, which the Employer should have learned during its investigation into the incident.</p>
<p>The work rules at issue in this matter are the Coupon Policy and the BonusCard Fraud Policy. The Coupon Policy, which apparently is intended to reward customer loyalty and promote sales, contains restrictions to curtail potential abuse by customers and employees that has the potential to negatively affect the company's finances. The BonusCard Fraud Policy lists unauthorized uses of the BonusCard. There does not appear to be any dispute that the limitations established in these policies are reasonable.</p>
<p>As both coupons and BonusCards are used exclusively at the POS, the employees who work there must be familiar with the Coupon Policy and BonusCard Fraud Policy. These policies are made known to customers and employees in several ways. The Coupon Policy is on Tops' website, and it is posted at the customer service desk in Store 22. Some cashiers also have tear-out pads containing the Coupon Policy that can be given to customers. All employees who operate registers and EZ-scan stations are trained about the policy. As it relates to the instant matter, the individual Grievants were provided with access to or training on the Coupon Policy.</p>
<p>GGG received cashier training on coupons and the BonusCard Fraud Policy within days after he was hired in September 2013. Several months later, in May of 2014, GGG was trained to be an EZ-scan attendant, and he received additional training on how coupons are handled at the EZ-scan stations. In August of 2014, GGG was trained to be a CSL, where he again received training on vendor coupon acceptance, double coupons, and BonusCard usage. GGG acknowledged during the Employer's investigation and at the hearing that he was familiar with the Coupon Policy.</p>
<p>WWW was a cashier in 2004, and on a job application she submitted in 2007, she claims to have experience at Tops working on a register, as a CSM, and as a MOD. There is no documentary evidence in the record establishing that she was trained in the Coupon Policy; however, at the time of the incident leading to her termination, WWW was serving as an MOD and had access to the store policy manuals that contain the Coupon Policy and BonusCard Fraud Policy.</p>
<p>WWW claims that she was unfamiliar with the Coupon Policy and that she did not receive training on the policy. This claim seems extremely unlikely given the positions in which she served, including as a cashier, a CSM, and a MOD. Those positions either require that the employee enforce the Coupon Policy or, in the case of CSM or MOD, assist subordinate front-end employees who may have questions about enforcement of the policy. For these reasons, even if WWW did not know the Coupon Policy at the time of the incident at issue, she should have known it.</p>
<p>The BonusCard Fraud Policy applies to employees, and it lists unauthorized uses of the BonusCard. In June of 2015, GGG signed a form acknowledging that he had read and understood the BonusCard Fraud Policy. WWW also signed acknowledgement forms indicating that she had read and understood the BonusCard Fraud Policy on January 27, 2011; December 13, 2013; and June 15, 2015.</p>
<p>Although SSS did not testify at the hearing, she was a cashier and the Coupon Policy was reviewed with her in June of 2014. In addition, she signed a form acknowledging that she had read and understood the BonusCard Fraud Policy on June 15, 2015.</p>
<p>Both GGG and WWW argue that even though they received copies of the BonusCard Fraud Policy on multiple occasions, they did not read it, either because they were not given time to read it, or the manager who asked them to sign the acknowledgment told them they did not have to read the policy. This argument has some surface appeal because in many work environments employees are asked to sign and acknowledge numerous policies, some of which can be lengthy, complicated, or filled with &ldquo;legalese.&rdquo; The difficulty with this argument here, however, is that understanding and enforcing the Coupon Policy and BonusCard Fraud Policy is central to the front-end positions and those overseeing those positions. As the primary backups and support for cashiers enforcing or operating under these policies, CSLs and the MOD have an obligation to know these policies well.</p>
<p>In sum, all the Grievants had access to the Coupon Policy and BonusCard Policy in locations that were familiar to them. All the Grievants were cashiers at one point in their tenure, and training on and enforcement of the Coupon Policy is a routine aspect of that position. In addition, the Coupon Policy was reviewed with GGG and SSS, and all the Grievants signed off on the BonusCard Fraud Policy at least once in recent proximity to the incident. For these reasons, the Grievants either knew or should have known these policies.</p>
<p>There remains the issue of whether Grievants could be expected to know that they could be disciplined or discharged for violations of the Coupon Policy or BonusCard Fraud Policy. The BonusCard Fraud Policy form that all the Grievant's signed, the Tops Corrective Action Guidelines, and the Tops Retail Union Associate Handbook all provide for &ldquo;disciplinary action, up to and including separation of employment&rdquo; for violations of the BonusCard Fraud Policy. For that reason, Grievants either knew or should have known that they could be terminated for violating these policies.</p>
<h4 align="left">C. <i>Whether the work rules at issue were fairly enforced</i></h4>
<p>Work rules must be fairly enforced to meet the just cause standard. The issue of fair enforcement of rules includes consistent enforcement of reasonable work rules and consistent treatment of employees who commit similar violations under similar circumstances. Here the evidence shows that all the employees involved in similar transactions were terminated. There is insufficient evidence in this record upon which to conclude that the Employer's treatment of the Grievants was inconsistent with other similarly situated employees.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>Conclusion on Whether There was a Reasonable Basis to Impose Discipline</b></h4>
<p>For the above stated reasons, the Arbitrator concludes that there was a reasonable basis upon which to impose discipline on the Grievants for their violations of the Coupon Policy and the BonusCard Fraud Policy.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>II. Whether the Penalty was Reasonable Under the Circumstances</b></h4>
<p>Once it is established that there was a reasonable basis to take disciplinary action, there remains the issue of whether the penalty imposed was reasonable under the totality of the circumstances. As concluded above, there was a reasonable basis for the Employer to take disciplinary action against the Grievants for their violations of the Coupon Policy and the BonusCard Fraud Policy, so the issue becomes whether those sustained violations warrant the termination of the Grievants. The question of whether a disciplinary penalty is reasonable under the circumstances generally involves the nature and severity of the offense; whether the discipline was progressive in nature; and the employee's prior record and length of service.</p>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>The nature and severity of the offense</i></h4>
<p>The Grievants' violations of the Coupon Policy and BonusCard Fraud Policy are in the nature of fraud or theft because these violations enabled the Grievants to get (1) free merchandise that they otherwise would have had to pay for and (2) points toward a reduction in the price of gasoline that they otherwise would not have been entitled. The actual title of the BonusCard Fraud Policy &ndash; &ldquo;POS Fraud and BonusPlus Fraud&rdquo; &ndash; makes clear to employees that Tops treats these violations as fraud. Fraud and theft are generally treated as serious violations, and their severity is rarely seen as <i>de minimis</i>. This is because an essential bond of trust is broken when employees defraud their employers, regardless of the amount of cash, merchandise, or other items of value involved. N. Brand, <i>Discipline and Discharge in Arbitration: ABA Section of Labor and Employment Law</i> 226-27 (BNA 1998).</p>
<p>The Union concedes that the Grievants used poor judgment in the transactions discussed above, but argues that their actions were good-faith mistakes made without the intent required to commit fraud or theft. Further, the Union notes that an intent to steal is present when an employee, for personal gain, knowingly and willfully takes something belonging to another without permission. As this standard relates to the Grievants, the Union argues that they testified credibly that they did not know they were doing anything wrong.</p>
<p>This argument is not credited. Several Tops employees took hundreds of cans of soup out of the store without Tops receiving any money or redeemable coupons in exchange. To an objective observer, these transactions would seem highly suspicious. For employees who had the responsibility to enforce the Coupon Policy and who were subject to the BonusCard Fraud Policy, they should have known these transactions were wrong. Although it does not appear that any of the Grievants was the &ldquo;mastermind&rdquo; who initially figured out the method to obtain free soup and GasPoints using photocopied coupons, overriding authorized limits on double coupons, and structuring the transactions to exceed the daily limit on GasPoints, they had an obligation to stop these transactions, or at least to question them. Instead, the Grievants decided to use or participate in that scheme themselves.</p>
<p>Moreover, although violations of the Coupon Policy and BonusCard Fraud Policy relate to fraud or theft, it is possible to violate them unintentionally and still be culpable for those violations. As discussed above, front-end employees are required to enforce the Coupon Policy, and they are subject to the BonusCard Fraud Policy. In that regard, the responsibility to enforce these policies increases with the employees' rank. That is why CSLs have the authority to override transactions that cashiers cannot, and CSMs have the authority to override transactions that CSLs cannot. The MOD is the highest-ranking employee in the store. It is not a valid defense for employees who have the responsibility to enforce policies to claim that they did not understand them. If Grievants did not understand them, then they should have sought guidance from someone higher in the organization prior to acting.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>Whether the discipline was progressive</i></h4>
<p>Progressive discipline as an element of just cause suggests a system of progressively more severe penalties to address misconduct and allow employees the opportunity to learn and improve. In cases of severe misconduct, however, where the offense damages the employer-employee trust, arbitrators do not usually require progressive discipline. <i>Id</i>. In the instant matter, the violations of the Coupon Policy and BonusCard Fraud Policy are of a severe nature that do not typically call for progressive discipline.</p>
<h4 align="left">C. <i>The Grievants' work records</i></h4>
<p>In addressing the question of the appropriateness of a disciplinary penalty, a long and meritorious work history is often a mitigating factor, especially in matters that do not involve serous misconduct. In this matter, the Grievants have varying amounts of service and culpability, and each will be addressed separately.</p>
<p>GGG had a good record of just over two years prior to the incident that led to his termination. This short period of service does little to mitigate in his favor. On the other hand, it is recognized that he is the only Grievant who did not personally benefit from his actions by receiving any cans of soup or GasPoints, and that he was in the difficult position of feeling he had to protect his girlfriend, another Tops employee involved in the scheme. Overall, these factors do not outweigh the severity of the offense in a way that would make the penalty of termination unreasonable.</p>
<p>The character of SSS's employment over her relatively short tenure of 18 months is unknown, as she did not testify at the hearing, so her work record does not weigh on her behalf.</p>
<p>WWW had over 31 years of good service prior to the incident that led to her termination. Although this record of good service has been taken into consideration, it does not outweigh the seriousness of the offense under the circumstances. Rather, WWW's long service and the assignment she held at the time of the incident highlight her culpability. Over her long service, WWW had served in many roles in the store, including as a cashier and, according to her internal job application, as a CSM, where she would have been trained in the Coupon Policy and the BonusCard Fraud Policy. She also would have worked with these policies on a daily basis. Even if WWW's testimony that she did not receive such training is credited, in her role as the MOD &ndash; the highest-ranking Tops employee in the store at the time of the incident &ndash; WWW had a responsibility to know these policies and to enforce them. At the least, she should have questioned these suspicious transactions or stopped them, but instead she chose to participate in them. Under these circumstances, WWW's long period of good service does not lessen the seriousness of the offense or suggest that the penalty of termination was unreasonable.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>Conclusion on Whether the Penalty was Reasonable Under the Circumstances</b></h4>
<p>For the above stated reasons, the Arbitrator concludes that termination of the Grievants was reasonable.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Conclusion on the Issue Presented</b></i></h4>
<p>The Arbitrator determines that there was just cause to terminate the Grievants.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Award</b></i></h4>
<p>I, the undersigned Arbitrator, hereby AWARD, as follows:</p>
<p>1. The grievances are DENIED.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>