<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>City of Binghamton, Employer, and Teamsters Local 317, Union.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No. A2016-106</p>
<p>January 6, 2017.</p>
<p>Michael G. Whelan, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Opinion and Award</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Introduction</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">The instant matter arises under the 2014-2017 collective bargaining agreement (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo;) between Teamsters Local 693 (currently, Teamsters 317) (&ldquo;Union&rdquo;) and the City of Binghamton (&ldquo;City&rdquo; or &ldquo;Employer&rdquo;). The parties to the CBA selected Michael G. Whelan as the Arbitrator to decide a grievance submitted by the Union. The parties presented evidence and argument on November 17, 2016, in Binghamton, New York, and on that date the hearing record was deemed to be closed.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Issue</i></b></h4>
<p>The parties stipulated to the arbitrability of the grievance, but did not stipulate to a statement of the issue on the merits and agreed to let the Arbitrator fashion the issue.</p>
<p>The Union's statement of the issue on the merits is:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Did the City violate the parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement by contracting out unit work? If so, what shall the remedy be?</p></blockquote>
<p>The City's statement of the issue on the merits is:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Did the City violate the parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement by retaining a contractor? If so, what shall the remedy be?</p></blockquote>
<p>The parties' statements of the issue reflect their different views of the case. To the City, the case is about the right to contract, pursuant to the Management Rights Article. To the Union, the case is about the ability to protect unit work, pursuant to the Recognition Article. Both of these views of the case are discussed below. Primarily because the issue here turns on giving effect to an express contractual right over an implied right, the Arbitrator has determined that the issue to be decided is:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Did the City violate the parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement by retaining a contractor? If so, what shall the remedy be?</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Relevant Contract Language</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>1. MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><b>1.1.</b> The Employer and Teamsters Local 693 recognize that the Employer has sole responsibility for managing City Government; controlling City property; and maintaining orderly and efficient operations. Accordingly, the Employer retains rights, including but not limited to, the following:</p>
<blockquote><p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">1.1.2. To determine the amount of overtime</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">1.1.7. To procure and purchase services, by others, under contract or otherwise.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p></blockquote></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>3. SPECIAL CONFERENCES</b></h4>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><b>3.8. RECOGNITION</b></p>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>3.9.</b> The Employer hereby recognizes Local 693 as sole, exclusive representative for collective bargaining on behalf of all Employees of the Employer in the Department of Public Works: Bureau of City Services (Sanitation and Building &amp; Shops), Bureau of Transportation (Streets, Signals and Central Garage), Bureau of Parks &amp; Recreation, Bureau of Water, Bureau of Sewer, and other titles annexed as Appendix &ldquo;E&rdquo; (not all inclusive) of this Agreement, with the exception of clerical personnel, all competitive Class supervisory personnel, part-time, seasonal or temporary Employees, and appointed personnel not subject to any of the provisions of the Civil Service System.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>14. OVERTIME</b></h4>
<blockquote><p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>14.2.</b> Overtime shall be on a rotational basis, and shall be offered to employees on a rotation basis within job classification and bureau. Overtime shall be offered equally to employees working within the same job classification. If an employee has chosen to not be called for overtime, the Employer may remove the employee's name from the overtime lists, except for emergency calls. Supervisory employees shall not be permitted to work out of their class, except in cases where properly classified employees have been called out but are not available.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>14.8.</b> It is understood that in situations where following the normal overtime procedures will jeopardize the completion of a project, the regular rules set forth in <b><xref pub="fedlaw" root="federal-law-nlra" normval="14.2">Section 14.2</xref></b> above regarding overtime shall not apply. In these cases, overtime shall be offered first to the employees regularly working the specific project which requires overtime. However, if the completion of the project will require more than four (4) hours additional time beyond the regular shift or more than two (2) consecutive days of overtime equaling eight (8) hours or more, than &lsqb;sic&rsqb; the regular rules regarding overtime shall apply.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>15. SENIORITY</b></h4>
<blockquote><p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>15.8.</b> Seniority shall apply to layoffs, promotions, transfers, and any other benefits afforded by this Agreement, except where specifically stated otherwise.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>15.11.</b> If the Employer is making a temporary work assignment that requires an Employee to work in a lower Classification or to use equipment typically limited to work of a lower Classification, the Employer shall offer this work to the most senior employee available.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>15.12.</b> If the Employer is assigning an Employee to a temporary assignment in another department or sub-unit, and, if an Employee within the department or sub-unit where the temporary assignment is being made would prefer the assignment, then, the Employer shall give preference to the Employee(s) with the most seniority, experience and qualifications when making the temporary assignment. Under these circumstances, a more senior Employee may defer the assignment to a less senior Employee within the department or sub-unit.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>49. MAINTENANCE OF BENEFITS</b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>49.1.</b> Any benefit presently enjoyed by the Employees who are party to this Agreement shall be retained and remain in force as if such benefit is a written part of this Agreement, except where such benefit has been abridged by this Agreement or by mutual consent of Teamsters Local 693 and the Employer.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Facts</i></b></h4>
<p>The City of Binghamton is home to a population of about 47,000 residents. The City employs about 600 employees, and about 170 of this number are Public Works employees in a blue-collar bargaining unit represented by Teamsters Local 317. Grievants MB, BS, and RH (&ldquo;Grievants&rdquo;) are members of that bargaining unit who perform building maintenance work.</p>
<p>The City's Police Department is located in City Hall, and it is maintained by bargaining unit employees. For reasons that are not relevant here, the City deems it necessary to do extra cleaning of Police Department facilities outside of regularly scheduled work hours. The Grievants are among a small group of Public Works employees who are assigned to do this extra cleaning for four hours on an overtime basis every Saturday and on holidays. For at least the last four years, one maintenance worker at a time was given this assignment on a rotating basis.</p>
<p>On at least one occasion prior to the incident that led to the instant matter, a crew of six maintenance workers was brought in to do &ldquo;deep cleaning&rdquo; of the Police Department. This deep cleaning involved a thorough cleaning of the administrative area, jail, and locker rooms. The nature and extent of this deep cleaning went far beyond the work that was ordinarily done during the normal work week or during the four-hour rotating shift on Saturdays and holidays.</p>
<p>On Saturday, April 23, 2016,<ftnote num="1"><para>All dates refer to 2016, unless otherwise indicated.</para></ftnote> it was Grievant BS's (&ldquo;BS&rdquo;) turn in the rotation to clean the Police Department for four hours on an overtime basis. BS reported for work that morning and proceeded to perform his usual duties. During BS's shift, a crew of about ten non-City workers came in and cleaned the Police Department. This crew cleaned for eleven and one-half hours that Saturday and the next day, Sunday, April 24<sup>th</sup>. It was later learned that the City had contracted with a company called &ldquo;Brooms over Broome&rdquo; to clean the Police Department.</p>
<p>The crew from Brooms over Broome performed deep cleaning of the Police Department facilities that is more involved than the normal cleaning done by unit members during the week and for four hours on Saturdays and holiday. Other than the more thorough nature of deep cleaning, the actual cleaning work itself was generally the same type of work done by unit members with the same type of tools and equipment &ndash; mops and cleaning machines. The only exception to this was that the Brooms over Broome crew used a different type of cleaning fluid than is normally used by City workers. The use of this fluid did not require any particular expertise, and unit members had the ability to use this product.</p>
<p>BS reported the existence of the outside crew to the Union, which promptly drafted a grievance form on April 25<sup>th</sup>. The parties were unable to resolve that grievance, which led to the instant arbitration proceedings.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Positions of the Parties</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left">1. <i>The Union's Position</i></h4>
<p>The Union submits that deep cleaning the Police Department is bargaining unit work, pursuant to the Recognition Article in the CBA, and for that reason it should have been assigned to bargaining unit members. The Union also claims that contractual provisions governing overtime, seniority, and maintenance of benefits restrict any contractual right the City may have to contract out bargaining unit work.</p>
<p class="continued">In addition, the Union argues that it is a well-established past practice for unit members to clean the Police Department on a rotational basis for four hours every Saturday. Moreover, the Union contends that if the deep cleaning could not be accomplished during the normal 4-hour rotational assignment, then a six-person crew of unit members should have been brought in as had been done in the past. Further, the Union claims that the City's previous use of contractors was limited to work that the City did not have the equipment or expertise to perform.</p>
<h4 align="left">2. <i>The City's Position</i></h4>
<p>The City contends that the CBA explicitly gives it the absolute right to subcontract the deep cleaning work, a right that is not limited to the availability of specified equipment. The City further contends that the sort of deep cleaning that was done &ndash; over two days with a large crew, where furniture was moved &ndash; was not consistent with any past practice. To the extent that there is any practice, it is for one person working four hours on a Saturday, not deep cleaning. Finally, with respect to the contractual provisions regarding overtime as a prevailing benefit, the City contends that overtime is not a prevailing benefit because the City has the right to stop providing overtime at any time.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Discussion</i></b></h4>
<p>In contract interpretation matters, it is the party bringing the grievance that bears the burden of persuasion. In the instant matter, the Union must therefore demonstrate that the City's contract with an outside vendor to clean the Police Department is inconsistent with some limitation, contractual or otherwise, in the CBA.</p>
<p>In considering the Union's claim, it may be useful to examine general arbitral principles that apply when unions challenge the ability of employers to contract out work ordinarily performed by bargaining unit members. Under circumstances where a labor agreement is silent on whether an employer has the right to contract out such work, the &ldquo;reserved rights doctrine&rdquo; provides that the right to contract services is an inherent managerial right that is retained by employers in the absence of an express or implied limitation in the labor agreement. F. Elkouri &amp; E. Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i> 637-41 (6<sup>th</sup> ed. 2003). Some arbitrators have found implied limitations based on various factors, including the nature of the work, available labor, the reasonable or arbitrary nature of the contract, or past practice. F. Elkouri &amp; E. Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i> 743-54 (6<sup>th</sup> ed. 2003).</p>
<p>In the instant matter, however, the CBA is not silent on the matter of contracting of services. Rather, the CBA states that &ldquo;the Employer retains rights, including but not limited to the following: &hellip; &lsqb;t&rsqb;o procure and purchase services, by others, under contract or otherwise.&rdquo; Although this provision may seem to end the discussion, it remains necessary to examine the entire CBA to determine whether there are other provisions that may limit this apparent broad grant of authority to contract services. As an initial matter, it is significant to note that the CBA does not contain an express limitation on the City's right to contract services.</p>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>Whether the Recognition Article limits the City's right to contract deep cleaning</i></h4>
<p>One argument advanced by the Union is that deep cleaning is bargaining unit work that cannot be performed by contractors by virtue of the Recognition Article in the CBA. This argument is based on the fact that the City has recognized the Union as the sole bargaining representative for City employees in certain organizational units and job titles within City government. The argument follows that the work performed by employees within these units and titles may not be performed by other City employees or contractors who are not represented by the Union.</p>
<p>There is longstanding arbitral authority for the proposition that recognition clauses create an <i>implied</i> contractual limitation on the ability of employers to contract services that are ordinarily performed by bargaining unit members. Crawford, <i>The Arbitration of Disputes over Subcontracting</i>, Challenges to Arbitration, Proceedings of the 13<sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting, National Academy of Arbitrators, ed. Jean T. McKelvey 60-65 (BNA 1960) (<i>cases cited therein</i>). However, there is a dearth of arbitral support for the notion that an implied obligation that would limit an employer's right to contract services should control over express language permitting such contracting, and such an extraordinary result is not warranted here.<ftnote num="2"><para>This conclusion is limited to the facts of this case. It is possible that contracted services that extend for long periods of time or that displace unit workers may raise questions about whether workers performing those services begin to take on the attributes of <quote>employees</quote> that are covered under the Recognition Article.</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>Whether other implied limitations limit the City's right to contract deep cleaning</i></h4>
<p>As stated above, some arbitrators have found implied limitations on the right of employers to contract services based on the availability of labor, or whether the contract was reasonable or arbitrary. F. Elkouri &amp; E. Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i> 743-54 (6<sup>th</sup> ed. 2003). The Union raises arguments that relate to these factors. The Union claims that it has not contested past City contracts with vendors who supplied services that unit members were not capable of performing due to lack of equipment, expertise, or staffing, but in this matter its members where capable of performing deep cleaning of the Police Department. Again, arbitrators who have determined there to be an implied limitation on the right to contract based on the availability of labor or the reasonableness of the contract have done so in cases where the labor agreement was silent on the issue of the employers' right to contract. Here, the CBA is not silent on the issue of the City's right to contract services, and when the parties agreed to permit the City to do so, they did not correspondingly limit the City's right to contract to situations where the City lacked equipment, expertise, or staffing.</p>
<h4 align="left">C. <i>Whether other CBA provisions limit the City's right to contract deep cleaning</i></h4>
<p>The Union also argues that contractual provisions governing overtime, seniority, and maintenance of benefits restrict any contractual right the City may have to contract out bargaining unit work. This argument is based on the concept that the assignment of unit members to perform the deep cleaning must comply with overtime and seniority provisions of the CBA, and it is a prevailing benefit that must continue. Under the logic of this argument, unit workers would have to be used to perform the deep cleaning because they have seniority over any temporary contract workers. The problem with this argument is that these contractual provisions only apply to employees in the bargaining unit. As discussed above, the City has the right to contract services and the temporary contract workers that perform these services are not covered under the Recognition Article or any other article in the CBA.</p>
<h4 align="left">D. <i>Whether past practice limits the City's right to contract deep cleaning</i></h4>
<p>The Union also argues that it is a well-established past practice for unit members to clean the Police Department on a rotational basis for four hours every Saturday. In support of this argument, the Union asserts that this practice of four-hour Saturday cleaning has occurred for a long period of time on a clear and consistent basis, and has been known and accepted by both parties. The Union is factually accurate, but the issue of whether any such practice exists is beside the point here, because a unit member was assigned to clean for four hours on the Saturday in question.</p>
<p>A more relevant argument advanced by the Union is that deep cleaning of the Police Department by bargaining unit members is a binding past practice. Generally, to be binding on the parties, strong proof is required that the practice is (1) unequivocal; (2) clearly enunciated and acted upon; and (3) readily ascertainable over a reasonable period of time as a fixed and established practice accepted by the parties. F. Elkouri &amp; E. Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i> 607-08 (6<sup>th</sup> ed. 2003). Because the Union claims the existence of a past practice, it has the burden to produce such strong proof.</p>
<p>This argument faces several hurdles, two of which cannot be overcome. First, there is insufficient evidence upon which to find the existence of a binding past practice. When determining whether parties' treatment of a term of employment has been &ldquo;readily ascertainable over a reasonable period of time,&rdquo; the frequency of its occurrence is significant to the extent that expectations are created among employees about how the matter will be addressed. Many reported arbitration decisions focus on this factor, and it is generally recognized that one or two occurrences do not constitute a binding past practice. F. Elkouri &amp; E. Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i> 608, n. 17 (6<sup>th</sup> ed. 2003). Here, there is evidence of one instance prior to the instant dispute where unit members had performed deep cleaning of the Police Department. This one prior instance does not support a conclusion that deep cleaning of the Police Department by unit members was &ldquo;readily ascertainable over a reasonable period of time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Second, even if strong evidence of a binding past practice of using unit members to perform the deep cleaning could be established, that practice would conflict with the contractual provision giving the City the right to contract services. Generally, when the plain language of an agreement conflicts with a past practice, the language of the agreement controls. F. Elkouri &amp; E. Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i> 627-28 (6<sup>th</sup> ed. 2003). Thus, upon notice of the discontinuation of any past practice that may have existed, the City could rely on the contractual provision permitting it to contract services.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Conclusion</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">The CBA permits the City to contract services, and there are no implied or contractual limitations on that right that apply in the instant matter. For this reason, the Arbitrator concludes that the Union did not meet its burden to establish that the City violated the CBA when the City retained a contractor to perform deep cleaning of Police Department facilities in April 2016. Having concluded that the City did not violate the CBA, it is unnecessary to address the remedy issue.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Award</i></b></h4>
<p>I, the undersigned Arbitrator, hereby AWARD, as follows:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>The grievance is DENIED.</p></li>
</ol>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>
