<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of the Arbitration between FRATERNAL ORDER OF POLICE, OHIO LABOR COUNCIL, INC. and CLARK COUNTY SHERIFF</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS Case No. 16-00467-6</p>
<p>October 25, 2016.</p>
<p>Tobie Braverman, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center">OPINION AND AWARD</h4>
<p>The Clark County Sheriff (hereinafter referred to as &ldquo;Employer&rdquo;) and Fraternal Order of Police, Ohio Labor Council, Inc. (hereinafter referred to as &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) have submitted the grievance of Carrie Taylor (hereinafter referred to as &ldquo;Grievant&rdquo;) to the Arbitrator for decision under the auspices of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service. Hearing was held at Springfield, Ohio on July 14 and July 20, 2016. The parties submitted post hearing briefs which were received by the Arbitrator on September 19, 2016. The parties stipulated that the grievance is properly before the Arbitrator for decision, and further stipulated that the issue for decision is as follows:</p>
<p>Did the Employer violate the Collective Bargaining Agreement when it terminated the Grievant, and if so, what is the appropriate remedy?</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>FACTS</b></i></h4>
<p>The Employer is the county wide law enforcement agency for Clark County, Ohio, the county seat of which is Springfield, Ohio. As part of its duties, it operates the Clark County jail, and the Union represents the sworn staff at the jail. The jail is housed in the same building as the Springfield police department, with access to each being at opposite ends of the lobby. The lobby on the Sheriff side is open at one end to the front doors and the Springfield side. In its center are permanently anchored benches. Public restrooms are located on one wall, which are, according to posted signage, locked from 8:00 p.m. to 7:00 a.m. The lobby is equipped with a motion activated surveillance camera. The command center is located on the street side of the building. It is located behind secured doors, and communication with the lobby is through an intercom system. The command center has a window with a view of the lobby, and is manned at all times by deputies. Off of the command center are storage areas and other offices, including the Sergeants' office. That office is a windowless room with work stations on which there are located computers and monitors. A small room off of the office is used for storage of equipment. Although in relatively close proximity to the command center, the Sergeants' office does not have a view of the command center. Communication with the command center is through the intercom. Those intercom communications can be heard throughout both of those rooms by anyone in the room. On the opposite wall of the lobby is another secured door leading to the administration side of the offices, which also has a window for public access which is staffed during business hours. Employees frequently cross the lobby from the command center to the opposite doors to exit the building, but there are available alternative routes. Additional secured doors on the fourth wall provide access to the jail and an area which may be utilized to hold individuals temporarily when necessary.</p>
<p>The Grievant began her employment with the Employer as a Deputy in September, 1999, and was promoted to the position of Sergeant in July, 2012. On May 13, 2015, the date on which the events occurred which gave rise to her termination and the instant grievance, she was working as a shift sergeant at the jail on the second shift. For deputies, that shift is from 3:00 p.m. to 11:00 p.m. Sergeants work from 2:30 p.m. to 10:30 p.m. to allow time for the passing of information from the outgoing to the incoming sergeant before roll call for the shift. The Grievant and Sergeant Krista Cox were assigned to second shift that evening, and Sergeant Eric Sullivan was on duty on third shift.</p>
<p>The incident that unfolded on that evening, and which ultimately led to the Grievant's termination, began at approximately 10:05 p.m. when Christopher Dent entered the lobby. Dent is former deputy who was terminated some time ago due to alcohol related offenses. While there is some disagreement among witnesses as to his condition upon arrival, it appears that he was somewhat inebriated at that time, and his condition worsened as the events unfolded.<ftnote num="1"><para>It was later discovered that Dent was in possession of a bottle of vodka from which he had apparently been drinking. It was found on his person nearly empty when he was ultimately booked into the jail.</para></ftnote> Deputies Tyler Reaver and Von Apel, who was being trained by Reaver, were in the command center. Dent came to the command center window and stated that he wanted to speak to a Sergeant concerning an incident. Apel communicated this information over the intercom to the Sergeants' office. Both the Grievant and Cox were in the office working on end of shift duties, and the Grievant recalled hearing this communication.</p>
<p>Cox responded to the command center window a few minutes later. According to Apel and Reaver, Dent stated that there was a situation down the street to which the Sheriff Department needed to respond. When asked twice for additional detail, however, Dent could not provided it, and Cox explained that as a result, there was nothing that could be done. Dent apparently left the window, and Cox returned to the office, where she telephoned Springfield police to advise them that Dent was in the lobby and was intoxicated. At some point thereafter, Apel advised the Sergeant's office via the intercom that Dent was now lying next to the door to the command center. Cox replied that he should be left alone. Apel relayed the information to the jail floors that Dent was intoxicated in the lobby, and deputies should therefore avoid the lobby when exiting the building.</p>
<p>According to the video evidence and testimony of deputies who were present, at approximately 10:30 p.m. Deputy Mario Troutman, Jr. entered the lobby. Troutman, who was assigned to book-in that night, was going to the command center to retrieve a key he needed to file inmate property. After entering the command center and hearing conversation about Dent's presence in the lobby, he went to the window to look for Dent. At around the same time David Carty entered the lobby to turn himself in on an outstanding warrant.</p>
<p>Because Troutman could not see Dent, he asked Carty if he could see someone in the lobby. Carty replied that he could, and then realized that the individual lying on the bench was Dent with whom Carty was familiar, having been an inmate in the jail while Dent was a deputy. Carty approached Dent, and began to record the scene on his phone. He told Dent to get up, and while Dent did manage to stand, he stumbled around the lobby, clearly severely intoxicated or otherwise impaired. He fell on several occasions, and attempted to shove or lean on Carty. At some point Dent again approached the command center window, and Troutman asked Dent to provide him with the name of someone who could pick him up. Dent's response was incoherent. Troutman therefore called Dent's brother in law, who is also a deputy, but who was unable or unwilling to pick him up.</p>
<p>Several minutes later, at approximately 10:50 p.m., Carty began to video again with his phone, and commented aloud that Dent was urinating on the floor. At that point Deputy Apel again contacted the Sergeant's office via the intercom to advise that Dent had urinated on the floor near the women's restroom door. Cox again responded that he should be left alone. The Sergeant's office was advised on another occasion regarding Dent's condition and conduct in the lobby when Deputy Ryan Weaver came through the lobby to download the pipes from second shift.<ftnote num="2"><para>The pipes are a system of inmate count monitoring which are collected from each floor of the jail. The information is then downloaded on equipment located in the room off of the Sergeant's office.</para></ftnote> Weaver testified that when he observed Dent and Carty recording him, he spoke to the deputies in the command center who advised him that they had been instructed by Cox not to engage. When he entered the Sergeant's office, Cox, Taylor and Sullivan were all present. He inquired of Cox as to what was going to be done about Dent, and was advised that he was not doing anything and should be left alone.</p>
<p>Deputy Jeff Boswell similarly testified that he walked through the lobby at 10:50 p.m., and noticed Dent and Carty. He began to approach, but was alerted by Deputies Troutman and Weaver who knocked on the glass, shook their heads &ldquo;no&rdquo; and waved him into the command center. When he was told to do nothing, he went to the Sergeant's office, where all three Sergeants were present. He testified that he advised all three that there was about to be a problem in the lobby, but although all three made eye contact, none gave him any verbal response.</p>
<p>The testimony of nurse Kimberly Mason was that as she was preparing to leave work she saw Dent in the lobby as Carty was videoing him with his phone, and then observed him urinate in the lobby. She entered the command center as Cox and the Grievant were preparing to leave work and inquired why nothing was being done. Cox replied that Dent was just drunk. Mason pointed out that he had just urinated in the lobby in front of the women's restroom. Cox jokingly replied that &ldquo;at least he almost made it&rdquo;. There was no testimony that the Grievant responded in any way. At 10:56 p.m., Cox and the Grievant left the command center, and thereafter left the building, leaving Sergeant Sullivan in charge.</p>
<p>The Grievant testified that toward the end of her shift on May 13 she was performing end of shift duties. These include preparing any necessary incident and other required daily reports, reviewing several types of reports submitted by the deputies and accounting for all money received that date. She recalled that on that night, she was counting the money for the day, and documentation supports that recollection. She testified that she did remember hearing the initial intercom communication that someone in the lobby was asking to speak to a sergeant. Cox left to respond, and upon returning advised the Grievant that it was Dent in the lobby, and he was intoxicated. According to the Grievant, Cox also stated that she had been advised by a custodian that someone was with Dent, and the Grievant therefore assumed he had a ride home. The Grievant denied that she heard the intercom messages from the command center saying that Dent was lying in front of the door or that there might be a problem in the lobby between Dent and Carty. She did, however, hear the intercom call late in the shift as she was preparing to leave, stating that Dent had urinated in the lobby. The Grievant testified that the call did not relay any sense of urgency, and since she was getting ready to leave, she assumed that Sullivan would take care of the situation on third shift. She additionally denied hearing either Boswell or Weaver in the office requesting that something be done about Dent. It is undisputed that the Grievant personally observed Dent for the first time when she exited through the lobby at the conclusion of her shift.</p>
<p>By this time, Carty had left the facility, and Dent had passed out on a bench in the lobby. Shortly after midnight, Sergeant Barnhart, who was assigned to third shift road patrol, received a phone call from Deputy Moody. He inquired as to whether Barnhart had seen the Facebook videos which Carty had posted of Dent in the jail lobby. Moody sent the videos to him, and after viewing them, Moody contacted both Sullivan and Lieutenant Clark. It was after this communication that Sullivan finally affected an arrest of Carty at 1:00 a.m. Carty ultimately pled no contest to charges of Disorderly Conduct and Public Indecency, and was sentenced to fifteen days in jail.</p>
<p>The incident did not end with the arrest, however. Carty, being indignant that Dent had been permitted to remain in the jail lobby drunk and urinating in public, not only posted the videos to Facebook with derogatory commentary about the Sheriff Department, but also contacted the media. Sheriff Gene A. Kelly was greeted the following morning with media accounts including the Carty video, and spent a significant amount of time attempting to deal with the media fall out that resulted. As a result of what he clearly viewed as a mishandling of Dent, he contacted Fred E. Meadows, an investigator with the Greene County Prosecutor's office to investigate the matter to determine if criminal charges against any Clark County employees was called for. After the completion of his investigation, Meadows recommended the pursuit of a misdemeanor charge of Dereliction of Duty against Cox. After reviewing Meadows' report, Kelly opted not to pursue the charge, but instead commenced an Internal Affairs Investigation of Cox, Sullivan and the Grievant.</p>
<p>Shortly before the issuance of the report of that investigation, which was in large part repetitive of the investigation of Meadows, the Grievant was provided with a notice dated September 18, 2015 advising her that of the charges against her and that a pre-disciplinary hearing would be conducted on September 29, 2015.<ftnote num="3"><para>The report is dated September 21, 2015. It can only be presumed that its conclusions were known to Sheriff Kelly while still in draft form prior to its finalization.</para></ftnote> The pre-disciplinary hearing was conducted by Clinton County Colonel Brian Prickett, who concluded that the Grievant was guilty of violation of six cited rules of conduct by virtue of her failing to act to aid of or arrest Dent despite being made aware of the situation. Prickett noted that the conduct was especially egregious in light of recent high profile police shootings in the national media and the negative publicity which resulted from this event. The Grievant was thereafter given notice dated October 9, 2016 that her employment was being terminated immediately. It should be noted that Cox and Sullivan were also terminated. Cox's termination was upheld by Arbitrator LaVerne N. Boyd in an Award dated September 9, 2016, and Sergeant Sullivan's grievance had not yet been heard at the time of the hearing in this matter. A timely grievance was filed, and the matter proceeded through the grievance procedure without resolution to arbitration.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>RELEVANT CONTRACTUAL PROVISIONS</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>ARTICLE 2 - MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><i>Section 2.1 Management Rights</i> The Union recognizes that except to the extent modified by this Agreement, the Employer has and will retain the full right and responsibility to direct operations of the Department, including but not limited to the following:&hellip;</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">d. To suspend, discipline, demote or discharge for just cause &hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">h. To adopt reasonable rules and regulations, not in conflict with this Agreement &hellip;</p></blockquote></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>ARTICLE 18- DISCIPLINE/PERSONNEL RECORDS</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><i>Section 18.1 Just Cause</i> No employee having completed his probationary period shall be disciplined or discharged except for just cause.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Section 18.2 Form of Discipline</i> Disciplinary action may include (a) verbal warning; (b) written warning; (c) discharge from employment; (d) working suspension; (e) suspension without pay; (f) loss of vacation; (g) reduction in rank.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Section 18.3 Progressive Discipline</i> Except in situations of gross employee misconduct, the Employer shall discipline employees in accordance with the principle of progressive discipline.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>GENERAL ORDERS</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><b>G.O. 101 Enforcement Agency Role - (A)(1) Oath of Office:</b> All personnel, prior to assuming sworn status as a Clark County Deputy Sheriff, shall take and subsequently abide by an oath of office &hellip; to enforce the laws of not only the constitution of the United States, but of the State of Ohio and, where applicable, those of governmental sub-divisions.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>G.O. 101. Appendix B Cannons of Police Ethics-Article VII Conduct toward the Public:</b> Law enforcement officers, mindful of their responsibility to the whole community, shall deal with individuals of the community in a manner calculated to instill respect for its laws and its police service. Law enforcement officers shall conduct their official life in a manner such as will inspire confidence and trust. Thus, they will be neither overbearing nor subservient as no individual citizen has an obligation to stand in awe of them nor a right to command them. The officers shall give service where they can and require compliance with the law. They will do neither from personal preference or prejudice, but rather as duly appointed officers of the law discharging their sworn obligation.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>G.O. 101 Rules of Conduct - Appendix D Rules of Conduct</b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">(1) <i>Violation of Rules</i>: Employees of the Sheriffs Office will not commit any acts or omit any act, which constitute a violation of any of the rules, Regulations, Directives, or Order of the. Office, whether stated in these Rules of Conduct or elsewhere.</p>
<p class="continued">(2) <i>Unbecoming Conduct</i>: Employees of the Sheriff's Office will conduct themselves at all times, both on and off duty, in such a manner as to reflect most favorably on the Office. Unbecoming conduct will include that which brings the Office into disrepute or reflects discredit upon the member of the Office or that which impairs the operation or efficiency of the Office or Deputy&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">(6) <i>Neglect of Duty</i>: Employees of the Sheriff's office shall not commit any acts expressly forbidden or omit any acts that are specifically required by the laws of this state, these Rules of Conduct, or any other orders, directives, policies, or procedures of this office. Employees shall not engage in any activity or personal business, which could cause them to neglect or be inattentive to duty&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">11. <i>Unsatisfactory Performance</i>: Sheriff's employees shall maintain sufficient competency to properly perform their duties and assume the responsibility of their postilions. Sheriffs employees shall perform their duties in a manner which will maintain the highest standards of efficiency in carrying out the functions, objectives and Mission of the Office.</p>
<p class="continued">Unsatisfactory performance may be demonstrated by a lack of knowledge of the application of laws required to be enforced, an unwillingness or inability to perform assigned tasks, the failure to conform to work standards established for the employee's rank, grade, or position, the failure to take the appropriate action on the occasion of a crime, disorder or other condition deserving attention, or absence without leave.</p>
<p class="continued">O.O. 202 Unity of Command (III)(B) Command of Organizational Components: Whenever two or more employees of the same rank are on duty and supervising the same area of responsibility within a Division, they will have complete control of any situation in which they are involved. If, in the unlikely event, a conflict occurs, the Division Commander/Lieutenant will make the final determination.</p>
<p class="continued">G.O. 202 Unity of Command (IV)(B) Command Protocol: The ranking deputy involved in a non-routine, unplanned situation shall retain command unless this authority is temporarily delegated or reassigned due to the nature of the event.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<p><i>Employer Position</i>: The Employer contends that it has met its burden of proof to demonstrate that the Grievant is guilty of the offenses with which she is charged and that the penalty of discharge is the appropriate penalty for her failure to act on May 13, 2015. The Grievant had clear notice of the Rules of Conduct, and those rules provide clear and reasonable expectations for employees of the Employer. The evidence demonstrated that the Grievant was aware of a problem in the lobby. While she denied hearing all of the communications from the Deputies, she was aware that Dent was intoxicated in the lobby and later that he had urinated in the lobby. Although Cox took command of the situation, since the Grievant was of equal rank, she had an obligation pursuant to G.O. 202(III)(b) to take responsibility for the situation. The Grievant admitted that she had no idea whether Dent was asleep, passed out from alcohol poisoning or dead when she walked by him in the lobby. Despite this fact, she did nothing to determine his well being or take action to aid him in violation of G.O. 203(II)(A) which makes supervisors accountable for situations within their control.</p>
<p>The Employer argues that the Grievant's denial of knowledge of Dent's situation or the concerns of the deputies should not be credited in light of the testimony of Deputy Boswell which demonstrates that he came into the office and directly advised all three sergeants of a potential problem in the lobby absent immediate intervention. The Grievant still chose not to act. Similarly, Deputy Weaver testified that the Grievant was present when he came to the Sergeant's office to ask if something could be done about Dent. Nurse Matson similarly testified that she raised the issue of addressing Dent in the Grievant's presence. In light of this testimony, the Grievant's claim of lack of knowledge should not be credited. Under the circumstances, she had an obligation to act, and failed to do so.</p>
<p>Additionally, the Grievant's failure to act was in violation of G.O. 101(2) which requires employees to conduct themselves in such a manner as to reflect favorably on the office. As a result of the failure to act on the part of the Grievant, Cox and Sullivan, there is no question but that the Employer was the subject of unfavorable publicity, both on Facebook and in the local news media, with local television stations playing the video taken by Carty. The Grievant's failure to act unquestionably brought the Employer into disrepute.</p>
<p>Finally, the Employer contends that the Union's argument that a thorough investigation was not conducted must be rejected. The matter was investigated by both Internal Affairs and Inspector Meadows of Greene County. A large number of interviews were conducted, and available video evidence was thoroughly reviewed. The investigations were both thorough as well as impartial and fair. The conclusion that the Grievant committed gross misconduct was appropriate, and this misconduct warranted the severe penalty imposed based upon the totality of the circumstances of this case. The grievance should be denied in its entirety.</p>
<p><i>Union Position</i>: The Union argues initially that the Employer has failed to meet its burden of proof to demonstrate that the Grievant is guilty of the charges against her. This burden of proof should be beyond a reasonable doubt, and that burden has clearly not been met here. The evidence demonstrated that while the Grievant was aware of Dent's presence in the lobby, it was Cox who spoke to him, and the Grievant unaware that any action needed to be taken. The Grievant was advised by Cox that Dent was with someone, and she therefore assumed that he had a way home and there was no cause for concern. When Sullivan arrived for work, he observed Dent, and expressed no cause for concern. She did not learn that Dent had urinated in the lobby until she was literally on her way out the door, and since she was off duty, she assumed that Sullivan would take care of the situation. This being the extent of the Grievant's knowledge, she had no basis on which to take any action, and her failure to do so did not violate any applicable rules. Further, the Union notes, all of the witnesses at hearing agreed that it was Cox, and not the Grievant, who ordered the deputies not to engage Dent. She therefore cannot be held responsible for that decision. The lack of any notation in the jail log indicates that the deputies did not view the incident with any real concern, and inconsistencies in their testimony leaves the level of their expressed concern in doubt. Their own lack of concern is additionally demonstrated by the fact that although they are sworn peace officers and could have acted on their own, they did not either act or contact the Grievant to express their concern with Cox's orders.</p>
<p>The Union further contends that the Employer failed to conduct a complete and thorough investigation, a necessary component of just cause. Neither Meadows' investigation nor the Internal Affairs investigation interviewed any of the Springfield Township officers involved who observed Dent. Noting that these officers did not intervene, the Union stresses that it was important to interview them in order to obtain their perspective on the situation. There were additionally no interviews of the third shift deputy in the command center in order to ascertain her observations even though Dent remained in the lobby for an hour into third shift. Further, although Meadows interviewed Dent, the Employer did not do so. Finally, the notice of pre-disciplinary hearing was issued before the Internal Affairs investigation report was finalized indicating that a determination on the Grievant's discipline was made before the hearing.</p>
<p>Additionally, the Union argues, none of the cited policies required the Grievant to take any action. As a Sergeant, she, like all peace officers, has a degree of discretion in any given circumstance. Further, she was led to believe that allowing an individual to sleep in the lobby is acceptable since the evidence clearly established that other individuals have been permitted to do so.</p>
<p>Finally, unlike Cox, there was no recommendation of prosecution of the Grievant, and unlike both Cox and Sullivan, she was not charged with dishonesty. The Grievant has been employed for seventeen years, and had no active discipline in her record. In fact her only previous disciplinary action was a now expired verbal warning. Her actions here did not rise to the level of gross misconduct. In light of her employment record as well as the contractual commitment to progressive discipline, the purpose of which is to be corrective rather than punitive, the greatest degree of degree of discipline which should be imposed is that of a verbal warning. The Grievance should be sustained, and the Grievant should be reinstated with full back pay and benefits as well as the removal of the record of this matter from her personnel file.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS</b></i></h4>
<p>This being a case of termination, the burden of proof rests with the Employer to demonstrate that the Grievant is guilty of the offense with which she is charged, and that the commission of that offense warranted the penalty of discharge. While the Union urges that the Employer's burden of proof here should be proof beyond a reasonable doubt, it must be noted that that burden of proof is reserved in the American judicial system solely for criminal matters in which there is a risk of loss of liberty. The Grievant's termination from employment, while having severe consequences, clearly does not put the Grievant at risk of loss of liberty, and there is no allegadon that she is guilty of misconduct which could lead to criminal charges. The Arbitrator must therefore reject the beyond a reasonable doubt standard of proof. Generally, this Arbitrator has subscribed to the requirement that the two elements of the Employer's burden of proof be demonstrated by the intermediate clear and convincing evidence burden of proof. This standard of proof recognizes the severe and lasting impacts that a discharge has on the Grievant and her ability to obtain future employment by requiring greater proof than a mere preponderance of the evidence. That is the burden of proof which will be applied in the instant case.</p>
<p>It is also necessary to address the Union's contention that the Employer failed to conduct a full and fair investigation, resulting in a lack of just cause for the termination. The evidence presented at hearing demonstrated that the Employer conducted two separate investigations of the events of May 13, 2016. The first was investigated was conducted by Meadows with an eye toward determining if criminal charges were warranted against any employee on duty that night. The second was conducted internally to determine if disciplinary action against Cox, Sullivan and the Grievant was appropriate. The Union notes that neither investigation included an interview with the City of Springfield officers who observed Dent or Deputy Martin, the third shift deputy on duty in the command center. The Union finally notes that the Employer did not interview Dent himself.</p>
<p>In assessing this contention, it must first be noted that when the Employer began its own internal investigation, it already had access to the completed investigation by Meadows. This investigation included notes regarding an interview of Dent, who recalled very little of the evening's events. His recall being sketchy at that time, it is difficult to discern any significant value in interviewing him again a month later. The Meadows report also includes emails regarding the officer from Springfield who observed Dent in the lobby. It is a second hand email accounting of his observations. It is clear, however, that while he saw Dent, he had no interaction with him. It is again apparent that an interview would have added little to the investigation. This is particularly true in light of the fact that videos, which provide a clear picture of Dent's condition, are available and provide the best evidence of Dent's condition. While neither investigation appears to have interviewed Martin, the Union's contention is that she should have been interviewed concerning Dent's condition during third shift. Again, however, it is clear that the Dent's condition was made abundantly clear by available video evidence, and while Martin could likely have provided relevant observations, they would not be critical, but rather largely redundant. While the investigations conducted by the Employer did not exhaust every potential detail, the Arbitrator must conclude that they were extensive and fair. They certainly gave a clear picture of the events of that night, and were not so flawed as to result in a conclusion that there was no just cause for the Grievant's termination based upon the investigation.</p>
<p>The Union finally notes regarding the investigation, that the Employer issued the Notice of pre-disciplinary hearing on September 18, 2015, while the internal investigation was not completed until three days later on September 21, 2015. The Union contends that this is evidence of predetermination of the result of the hearing. While the Employer did not offer any explanation for this action at hearing, the fact that the pre-disciplinary hearing notice preceded the completion of the report does not appear to have had a significant impact on the decision here. As noted above, the internal investigation was for the most part a repeat of the Meadows investigation, and that investigation was already completed. The Employer had that report in its possession, and undoubtedly the Sheriff had an opportunity to review it and form an opinion as to discipline. Further, it must be noted that the pre-disciplinary hearing was conducted by Colonel Brian Prickett of Clinton County. There was no evidence presented which demonstrated that he had formed any pre-hearing conclusions or that he had even seen either of the reports. Under these circumstances, the evidence does not support the conclusion that the discharge was so procedurally flawed that it cannot be sustained on the basis that the internal report was concluded three days after the issuance of the pre-disciplinary hearing notice.</p>
<p>Ultimately the question which must be decided in this case is whether the Employer has demonstrated by clear and convincing evidence that the Grievant's conduct on May 13, 2015 was a violation of any of the cited rules. The evidence presented at hearing in the final analysis dictates the conclusion that the Grievant is guilty of unbecoming conduct, neglect of duty and unsatisfactory performance as well as the General Orders cited relating to Enforcement Agency Role and Police Ethics. There is some question as to the degree of the Grievant's knowledge as the evening progressed. While witnesses testified as to what they communicated over the intercom, there was no clear proof that the Grievant heard all of those communications. As she noted, she was required to go in and out of the office during that time to deliver reports to various areas, so it is possible that she was not present for all intercom communications. Further, while two witnesses indicated that the Grievant was in the room when they raised concerns regarding Dent and that she appeared to make eye contact, there was no evidence that she responded in any way, and the Grievant testified that she did not hear these comments. Thus, while it appears that the evidence may support the conclusion that the Grievant was aware of all of the reports concerning Dent, the evidence does not rise to the clear and convincing evidence standard. It is rather more of an assumption based upon the Grievant's presumed presence in the room and that she was paying attention. It is simply not clearly proven that the Grievant was fully aware of the entirety of the communications regarding Dent during the time he was present in the lobby.</p>
<p>Even assuming that the Grievant did not hear either all of the intercom communications or the in person communications from deputies regarding Dent, however, certain facts are clear. She was aware at the beginning of the event that Dent was in the lobby and was intoxicated. She later admitted that she was aware of the report that Dent had urinated in the lobby. Finally, when she left work, she saw Dent passed out in the lobby, and undoubtedly walked past the place where he had urinated. On none of these occasions did she question Cox's judgement that Dent should be left alone. There can be no doubt that at the point when she learned that Dent urinated in a public place, she should have, at a minimum, questioned Cox as to the propriety of letting Dent remain in the lobby, and if Cox continued to fail to act, she should have taken charge of the situation. Dent had, at that point, not only committed a criminal act, but had created an unsanitary situation in the lobby and demonstrated that his mental state was such that he was not behaving rationally or appropriately. At a minimum, the Grievant should have called for someone to check on Dent's physical state to determine whether or not he was in need of medical attention and called for someone to clean the urine from the lobby floor. She did neither, and her failure to act violated the rules requiring her to do so in the interest of the safety of both the public in general, and of Dent in particular.</p>
<p>The Grievant's explanation for her failure to take any action was that she was at the end of her shift by the time she became fully aware of the situation and assumed that Sullivan would deal with it. She did not, however, go so far as to even speak to Sullivan to insure that her assumption was correct. Ultimately, one can only conclude that she was content to let others act, and chose to ignore the situation. Pursuant to the work rules, however, it was her obligation to act both to protect Dent and the public and to enforce the law. She failed to do so, and her failure to do so rose to the level of gross misconduct.</p>
<p>Having determined that the Grievant committed the offense with which she is charged, the remaining question is that of whether the penalty meted out for her offense is appropriate in the circumstances present in this case. There can be no doubt that the decision to terminate the Grievant was influenced in significant part by the fact that video of the incident was posted on Facebook and covered by local media. This clearly reflected poorly on the Employer. It resulted in accusations of both favoritism, since Dent was a former deputy, and indifference due to the lack of concern for his safety and that of the public. The publicity, however, cannot be the sole determinant in assessing the propriety of the discipline to be meted out to the Grievant. In this day and age when virtually everyone has a video camera in his pocket, it must be presumed that there is a real and present possibility that events are being recorded and that those recordings will be posted to social media. While it is important that law enforcement personnel in particular be mindful of this fact, the mere fact of the additional attention cannot exclusively drive the penalty for misconduct.</p>
<p>In this case, the Grievant's offense occurred when she failed to act after knowing both that the Grievant was intoxicated and had urinated in the lobby. As noted above, Cox was the Sergeant who had taken command of the situation, and it was her primary responsibility to handle it. Sullivan then became responsible when he took command on third shift. The Grievant, however, was never in command of the situation. Her offense is that of indifference and an apparent failure to act in the face of the inaction of Cox and Sullivan.<ftnote num="4"><para>While the Union argues that the deputies on duty could have acted independently if they felt Cox's order to not engage was unlawful, as officers of a subordinate rank, they were clearly in a different position than the Grievant who was of equal rank to Cox and Sullivan.</para></ftnote> In view of all of the circumstances presented, including the appearance of favoritism toward Dent, his potentially dangerous state of inebriation, and the presence of urine on the floor of the lobby creating a public health hazard, the Grievant, as a commanding officer, was obligated to take action despite the fact that she was not the first officer to take command of the situation. Her failure to do so was gross misconduct which warrants disciplinary action.</p>
<p>The Grievant's culpability, however, is not the same of that of Cox and Sullivan, and as such, a lesser degree of discipline is appropriate. Further, it must be noted that the Grievant is a seventeen year employee with a clean disciplinary record prior to this incident. This should also serve to mitigate the penalty in her case, particularly in light of the Agreement's commitment to the principles of progressive discipline. In light of these considerations, the Arbitrator finds that the Grievant should be disciplined with a significant suspension to make it clear that her misconduct was severe, and that her own conclusion that her inaction warranted no more than a written warning inappropriately minimizes the magnitude of her failure to act.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>The grievance is sustained in part. The Grievant shall be reinstated to employment without back pay, but with full seniority and shall retain her rank as Sergeant. The period of her time off work from her termination to reinstatement shall remain on her record as a disciplinary suspension for the relevant contractual time. The Arbitrator shall retain jurisdiction for thirty days to resolve any disputes regarding remedy.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>