<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>Public Housing Agency of St. Paul, St. Paul, Minnesota (&ldquo;Agency&rdquo;) &amp; American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District No. 5 (&ldquo;Union&rdquo;)</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>BMS Case No. 16-PA-0550</p>
<p>December 22, 2016.</p>
<p>Mario F. Bognanno, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="left">I. <i>JURISDICTION</i></h4>
<p>The Parties to the above-captioned matter are the Public Housing Agency of St. Paul (&ldquo;Agency&rdquo;), and the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees, District No. 5 (&ldquo;Union&rdquo;). St. Paul's public housing programs are administered by the Agency, and the Union is the bargaining agent that represents certain administrative staff employed by the Agency. The Parties are cosigners to a Collective Bargaining Agreement (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo;) that was in effect at all times relevant to the instant matter. Article 18, GRIEVANCE PROCEDURE, Section 18.4, Step 4 of the CBA provides as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">A grievance unresolved in Step 3 and properly appealed to Step 4 by the UNION shall be submitted to arbitration subject to the provisions of the Public Employment Labor Relations Act of 1971, as amended. The selection of an arbitrator shall be made in accordance with the &ldquo;Rules Governing the Arbitration of Grievances&rdquo; as established by the Public Employment Relations Board.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 1) Pursuant to this section of the CBA, the Parties selected the undersigned to decide the disputed grievance.</p>
<h4 align="left">II. BACKGROUND</h4>
<p>Korin Zeiher was an Administrative Support Technician employed by the Agency. She did not report to work on the Monday through Friday five (5) day workweek of June 1, 2015 through June 5, 2015. Moreover, she failed to notify her supervisor of her absences and none were due to an emergency. (McMurray Aff. at Ex. 2) Relevant to these circumstances are two (2) distinct sections of the Parties' CBA, each of which provides as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Article, 6, Section 6.6, <i>NOTIFICATION OF ABSENCES</i>: Employees shall be present for work at the start of their scheduled work day. Employees unable to be present at the start of their scheduled work day or who will be absent shall notify their supervisor, or designee, within 15 minutes of the start of their scheduled work day, except in the event of an emergency. Absences from work without such above prior notification or without the prior approval of the employee's supervisor shall constitute just cause for disciplinary action as provided by Article 17.</p>
<p class="continued">Article 15, Section 15.75, <i>FAILURE TO REPORT TO WORK</i>: Employees who fail to report for work without notification to their supervisor, or designee, for 3 consecutive work days shall be considered to have resigned from employment, unless because of an emergency such notice could not have been given.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 1<b>)</b> Based on the foregoing facts and pursuant to these contractual provisions, on June 9, 2015, Ms. Zeiher was given a Notification of Personnel Action in which the Agency held that her absences constituted a &ldquo;voluntary resignation.&rdquo; (McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 2) Subsequently, the Union grieved, challenging this determination of Ms. Zeiher's employment status (hereafter referred to as &ldquo;Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance&rdquo;) A Step 1, Step 2 and Step 3 grievance meeting was held on June 30, 2015, July 21, 2015 and September 1, 2015, respectfully. (Id.) In a letter dated September 10, 2015, addressed to Ms. Zeiher and John Ewaldt, AFSCME Field Representative, the Agency gave the Union its Step 3 answer: The Agency declared &ndash; repeating its Step 1 and Step 2 written declarations &ndash; that it intended to enforce the precise wording of Sections 6.6 and 15.75 of the CBA and, therefore, to sustain its decision that Ms. Zeiher had &ldquo;voluntarily resigned.&rdquo; (McMurray Aff. at Agency Exs. 2 and 3)</p>
<p>On September 19, 2015 &ndash; nineteen (19) days after the Agency had given the Union its written answer to the Parties' Step 3 grievance meeting &ndash; Mr. Ewaldt advised the Agency of the Union's intent to advance Ms. Zeiher's grievance to Step 4 of the grievance procedure, namely, to arbitration. (McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 4) The Agency demurred, referring to Article 18, Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA and, specifically, to the last sentence therein:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><i>Step 3</i>. If appealed, the written grievance shall be presented by the UNION and discussed with the Executive Director. The Executive Director shall give the UNION the PHA's Step 3 answer in writing 10 calendar days following the Step 3 discussion. <i>Any grievance not appealed in writing to Step 4 by the UNION within 10 calendar days following the Step 3 answer shall be considered waived</i>.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 1; Italics added) In an October 1, 2015 e-mail, Mike McMurray, Human Resources Director, told Mr. Ewaldt that the Agency considered Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance to be waived because his notice of intent to arbitrate was untimely. Referring to the CBA's Section 18.4, Step 3 language, Mr. McMurray observed,</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Any grievance not appealed in writing to Step 4 &lsqb;arbitration&rsqb; by the Union within 10 calendar days following the Step 3 answer shall be considered waived.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">(Id.) Because the Union's notice of intent to arbitrate was dated nineteen (19) calendar days &ndash; not ten (10) calendar days &ndash; after receipt of the Agency's Step 3 written answer, Mr. McMurray considered Ms. Zeiher's grievance to have been waived. In his reply, Mr. Ewaldt stated, &ldquo;You may argue time line issues at arbitration.&rdquo; (McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 5)</p>
<p>On December 18, 2015, Sandra Curtis, an AFSCME Field Representative<ftnote num="1"><para>Ms. Curtis succeeded Mr. Ewaldt as the Union's representative in the instant matter.</para></ftnote>, advised Mr. McMurray that she had requested a grievance arbitrator panel from the Minnesota Bureau of Mediation Services. (McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 6) On December 21, 2015, Mr. McMurray replied, stating that the Union's request to arbitrate Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance was not timely and, therefore, &ldquo;&lsqb;W&rsqb;e do not intend to arbitrate this matter.&rdquo; (Id.) On December 28, 2015, Ms. Curtis responded, stating that no one party to the CBA may refuse to arbitrate a threshold issue like procedural timeliness. In so many words, she advised that the timeliness issue and Ms. Zieher's substantive grievance could be resolved at a &ldquo;bifurcated&rdquo; arbitration proceeding. Under such a proceeding, the timeliness issue (hereafter referred to as Ms. Zieher's timeliness grievance) would be adjudicated first and, if the Union prevailed, Ms. Zieher's substantive grievance would be heard and decided on its merits. (Id.) On December 31, 2015, Mr. McMurray reiterated that the Union's arbitration request was untimely and, hence, Ms. Zeiher's grievance was waived. (Id.) On February 8, 2016, Ms. Curtis again asserted the Union's right to a bifurcated arbitration. (McMurray Aff. at Ex. 7) On February 17, 2016, Mr. McMurray again demurred. (Id.)</p>
<p>Consequently, the Union filed a motion in Ramsey County District Court, requesting that Ms. Zeiher's timeliness grievance be determined through arbitration. Subsequently, on July 7, 2016 the Court ordered arbitration. Because the facts underlying Ms. Zeiher's timeliness grievance were not in dispute, the Parties agreed to forgo an evidentiary hearing in favor of arguing the matter of procedurally timeliness <i>via</i> memoranda. The Agency's memorandum was filed on October 28, 2016, the Union's memorandum was filed on November 22, 2016, and the Agency's Reply memorandum was filed on November 23, 2016. Thereafter, the case record was closed, and the undersigned took Ms. Zeiher's timeliness grievance under advisement.</p>
<h6 align="left"><b>II. <i>ISSUE</i></b></h6>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Whether Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance is procedurally arbitrable &ndash; timely &ndash; under the terms and conditions set forth in Article 18, Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA?</p>
</blockquote>
<h6 align="left"><b>III. <i>ARGUMENTS OF THE PARTIES</i></b></h6>
<p class="continued"><b>A. <i>For the Agency</i>:</b> The Union admits that its request to arbitrate Ms. Zeiher's employment status was not submitted within ten (10) calendar days following the Agency's written Step 3 answer. Hence, the Agency argued, as the language of Article 18, Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA plainly states, the Union's grievance is waived. In relevant part, the referenced language is as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Any grievance not appealed in writing to Step 4 by the UNION within 10 calendar days following the Step 3 answer shall be considered waived.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(McMurray, Aff. at Agency Ex. 1) Further, the Agency pointed out, the Parties' waiver agreement is amplified in Article 18, Section 18.71 of the CBA:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">18.7 <i>Waiver</i></p>
<p class="continued">18.71 <i>If a grievance is not presented within the time limits set forth above, it shall be considered &ldquo;waived.&rdquo; If a grievance is not appealed to the next step within the specified time limit or any agreed extension thereof, it shall be considered settled on the basis of the PHA's last answer</i>. If the PHA does not answer a grievance or appeal thereof within the specified time limit, the UNION may elect to treat the grievance as denied at that step and immediately appeal the grievance to the next step. <i>The time limits in each step may be extended by mutual written agreement of the PHA and the UNION</i>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">(Id.; italics added) Uniquely relevant to this language is that the ten (10) calendar day time limit in Section 18.4, Step 3 could have been extended by mutual agreement. Nevertheless, the Agency averred, Mr. Ewaldt did not propose any such extension.</p>
<p>Based on the forgoing contractual provisions and the undisputed facts presented, the Agency argued that the Union waived its right to arbitrate Ms. Zieher's substantive grievance, and as provided in Section 18.6 of the CBA, said grievance was settled on the basis of the Agency Step 3 grievance response. Moreover, citing a scholarly treatise and arbitral precedents, the Agency showed that when the CBA contains clearly articulated time limits for prosecuting a grievance that the union does not observe, the grievance is dismissed.</p>
<p>Next, the Agency argued that the Parties' CBA strictly limits arbitral authority. On point, the Agency cites Article 18, Section 18.61 of the CBA, which states:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">18.6 <i>Arbitrator's Authority</i></p>
<p class="continued">18.61 <i>The arbitrator shall have no right to amend, modify, nullify, ignore, add to, or subtract from the terms and conditions of this Agreement</i>. The arbitrator shall consider and decide only the specific issue(s) submitted in written by the PHA and the UNION, and shall have no authority to make a decision on any other issue not so submitted.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(Id.; italics added) Pursuant to the above-italicized language, the Agency urged the Arbitrator to find the Union's grievance waived because: (1) the Union's arbitration request was made beyond the ten (10) calendar day time limit required by CBA's Section 18.4, Step 3; (2) there was no Section 18.71 agreement between the Parties to extend the time limit; and (3) the CBA language in Section 18.61 renders immaterial any other excuse or mitigation the Union may assert. Regarding point (3), the Agency argued that to give material weight to any such excuse/mitigation would be to ignore and nullify not only Section 18.61 of the CBA, but also the unambiguous language in Sections 18.4, Step 3 and 18.71. To conclude, the Agency argued that the Union's grievance, in so many words, is asking the Arbitrator to violate the very CBA he is asked to enforce.</p>
<p>For the above-stated reasons, the Agency requested that the undersigned deny the Union's grievance.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>B. <i>For the Union</i>:</b> The Union began its argument by stipulating that Mr. Ewaldt missed Section 18.4, Step 3's ten (10) calendar day timeline. However, it observed, he did so because of unforeseeable and unavoidable factors and not because of malfeasance. Personal tragedy and related complications impeded Mr. Ewaldt's work as a Union Representative. Yet, the Union urged, said difficulties should not deprive Ms. Zeiher of her right to &ldquo;due process&rdquo; (i.e., to have her substantive grievance arbitrated). Mr. Ewaldt's &ldquo;human error&rdquo; ought not to be construed to mean that he intended waiver of Ms. Zeiher's right to due process. He followed Section 18.4's timelines during Steps 1 and 2 of the grievance procedure, and during the Step 1, 2 and 3 grievance meeting discussions, Mr. Ewaldt did not as much as insinuate that Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance ought not to be arbitrated. The missed Step 3-to-Step 4 (arbitration) timeline occurred upon the death of Mr. Ewaldt's mother: A cancer victim. The grief and stresses of that tragedy caused Mr. Ewaldt to miss the referenced timeline: A benign human error.</p>
<p>Concerning the merits of Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance, the Union argued as follows: first, Ms. Zeiher did not voluntarily resign, as the Agency claims, she was terminated for violating Article 15, Section 15.75 of the CBA; second, Section 15.75 of the CBA is only occasionally and disproportionately enforced by the Agency; third, at the time in question, Ms. Zeiher's dependent teen age daughter was expecting a baby and with her due date imminent, Ms. Zeiher absented herself from work between June 1 and June 5, 2015, inclusive; and fourth, the Agency knew why Ms. Zeiher was absent from work, and she attempted to notify her employer on four (4) of the five (5) days she was absent. Clearly, the Union observed, the facts of Ms. Zeiher's substantive case remain in dispute and, as such, she deserves due process.</p>
<p>Pertaining to the merits of the Ms. Zeiher's timeliness grievance, the Union stated that Mr. Ewaldt's mother was diagnosed with cancer in 2011 and thereafter, until her passing, he was her &ldquo;primary care giver.&rdquo; He cared for his mother's day-to-day medical needs and attended to her comfort, while performing his responsibilities as a Field Representative. In mid-September, 2015, Mr. Ewaldt moved his handicapped sister from Duluth, MN to the Twin Cities so the two (2) of them could be near their mother whose condition had become critical. On October 11, 2015, their mother passed away.</p>
<p>As a dedicated Field Representative, Mr. Ewaldt would never intentionally sidestep the CBA's expressed timeline provisions. Nevertheless, throughout the course of one's professional life tragedies, resulting in human error, happen and, at a minimum, said error warrant's indulgence. Hence, the Union urged, Mr. Ewaldt's grief ought not to impede on Ms. Zeiher's right to have her substantive grievance heard.</p>
<p>Moreover, the Union continued, historically the administration of the Parties' grievance procedure has been informal and flexible. To illustrate, the Union referenced five (5) examples. In one instance, three (3) months elapsed between the time an employee was disciplined and the scheduling of that employee's Step 1 grievance meeting. (Nelson Aff. at Union Ex. 1) Next, an internal e-mail describes the Union plan to advise the Agency that the timeline for filing a Step 1 grievance does not begin until it has received a copy of the Agency's disciplinary action notice. (Nelson Aff. at Union Ex. 2) In a third case, the Parties understood that once the Agency fulfilled an information request proffered by the Union, the grievance in question would be discussed at Step 2. (Nelson Aff. at Union Ex. 3) The Union's fourth example of the informality and flexibility that characterizes the Parties administration of their grievance procedure is that on January 17, 2012, the Union requested a delayed grievance hearing, and on January 25, 2012, the Agency's response was &ldquo;I'll wait to hear from you when you are ready to hold the step 1 meeting.&rdquo; (Nelson Aff. at Union Ex. 4) The Union's fifth example pertains to a December 31, 2012 e-mail in which the Union asked the Agency for more time to grieve an employee's reprimand. On that same date, the Agency replied,</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Hi. Your email is our notification of the intent to grieve. Go ahead and take what time you need to proceed as long as it's reasonable.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(Nelson Aff. at Union Ex. 5)</p>
<p>Finally, the Union argued, the present matter is procedurally timely by virtue of the Parties' grievance administration practices, as discussed above. Arbitral doctrine provides, <i>inter alia</i>, that enforceable past practices often determine how contract language ought to be interpreted and applied. However, in the present matter, weight was not given to the Parties' flexible grievance administration practices. Why? Because, the Union stated, Ms. Zeiher's timeliness grievance arose after <i>new</i> personnel had transitioned into the role of Union representative and Human Resource Director.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>C. <i>For the Agency in Reply</i>:</b> In rebutting the content of the Union's memorandum, the Agency observed that the Union, for the first time, asserted that it missed the Step 3-to-Step 4 (arbitration) timeliness deadline because of Mr. Ewaldt's tragic personal circumstances which, in turn, caused him to commit a &ldquo;human error.&rdquo; This explanation, the Agency continued, does not excuse the Union from complying with its obligations under the CBA. Moreover, Mr. Ewaldt neither notified the Agency of his personal circumstances nor did he request a grievance timeline accommodation and, further, neither did the Union itself.</p>
<p>The Union's memorandum illustrates situations where the Agency had agreed to extend grievance timelines or made other scheduling accommodations. Nevertheless, said accommodations are allowed under the CBA, Section 18.71, which states in part:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">The time limit in each step may be extended by mutual written agreement between the PHA and the UNION.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 1) Over all, the Agency conceded, it does agree to Union requests to extended timelines, as the Union points out, but said requests are made in <i>advance</i> of being taken. On point, the Union failed to identify a single instance in which the Agency disregarded an enforceable timeline without prior written agreement between the Parties. Regarding Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance, the Agency did not agree to extend the discussed timeline because Mr. Ewaldt &ndash; tragic as his personal circumstances may have been &ndash; did not request an extension.</p>
<p>Finally, the Agency argued, Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance was foreclosed because of Mr. Ewaldt's untimely request to arbitrate; therefore, the argument that Ms. Zeiher's is being wrongly denied due process rights should be directed at Mr. Ewaldt and the Union, not the Agency. The Union, not the Agency, is responsible for complying with the requirements imposed by the CBA, and the Union is solely responsible for the contractual consequences of that failure.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>IV. <i>ANALYSIS AND OPINION</i></b>: As posed above, the Issue in this case is as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Whether Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance is procedurally arbitrable &ndash; timely &ndash;under the terms and conditions set forth in Article 18, Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA?</p></blockquote>
<p>The Union's answer to this question is &ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance is arbitrable. In support of this answer, the Union offered three (3) theories of the case. First, the Union acknowledged that Mr. Ewaldt's effort to advance Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance to arbitration was untimely. Nevertheless, it argues that personal tragedy &ndash; not malicious intent or negligence &ndash; explains why he missed Section 18.4, Step 3's ten (10) calendar day timeline. The tribulations caused by his mother's lingering illness and death, and the assumed care of his handicapped sister were overwhelming, draining Mr. Ewaldt of his ability to timely fulfill the responsibilities of a Field Representative. Under these circumstances, the Union urges, human kindness and clemency &ndash; not the strict enforcement of Section 18.4, Step 3's waiver language &ndash; ought to control.</p>
<p>The Union's second theory of the case is that the facts underlying Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance are in dispute: Ms. Zeiher did attempt to notify the Agency of her absences; and Ms. Zeiher did not voluntarily resign, rather she was terminated. Under such circumstances, the Union argues, Ms. Zeiher has due process rights under the CBA (i.e., &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; rights) and under the 5<sup>th</sup> and 14<sup>th</sup> amendments to the U.S. Constitutional. Accordingly, to judiciously determine the facts of the matter and to decide whether Ms. Zeiher voluntarily resigned or was unjustly terminated from her position as an Administrative Support Technician, an arbitration hearing is both required and warranted.</p>
<p>While the two (2) above theories are compelling, the question is whether they are anchored in CBA-compliant language and, therefore, determinative. Arbitrators are faithful to the enforcement of the contracting parties' intentions as reflected in the written terms and conditions of their CBA. Fidelity to any other decisional standard would have resulted in the demise of labor arbitration as the contracting parties preferred means for resolving inter-party differences over the intended interpretation and application of their CBA's written words: The less-preferred alternative means being &ldquo;industrial conflict.&rdquo; Hence, it is not surprising that nearly all CBAs include language to remind arbitrators from whence their decisions ought to derive. Indeed, Section 18.62 of the instant CBA provides, in part, that the arbitration's</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&hellip; &lsqb;D&rsqb;ecision &hellip; shall be based solely on the arbitrator's interpretation and application of the expressed terms of this Agreement and the evidence and testimony presented.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 1)</p>
<p>Ultimately, deciding the present matter demands that the undersigned interpret and apply the expressed terms of the last sentence in Section 18.4, Step 3, which states:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Any grievance not appealed in writing to Step 4 by the UNION within 10 calendar days following the Step 3 answer shall be considered waived.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(Id.) This sentence is not ambiguous; it clearly states the Parties' intention with respect to the timely appeal of any grievance to arbitration. It is undisputed that Mr. Ewaldt failed to appeal Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance to arbitration within the Parties mutually agreed upon ten (10) calendar day timeline. Therefore, to assent to the Union's &ldquo;clemency&rdquo; theory, which is to find Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance to be arbitrable under Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA, clearly contradicts the Parties' intended result, namely, waiver, whenever an appeal to arbitration is untimely, <i>ceteris paribus</i>.</p>
<p>Mr. Ewaldt's circumstances were difficult, even tragic. However, the Arbitrator is bound by the CBA. Further, the language in the last sentence of Section 18.71 of the CBA was drafted in anticipation of such difficulties. That sentence provides,</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">The time limits in each step may be extended by mutual written agreement of the PHA and the UNION.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(McMurray Aff. at Agency Ex. 1) Applied to the present matter, Mr. Ewaldt had ten (10) calendar days to e-mail the Agency, requesting that the Step 3-to-Step 4 timeline in Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA be extended. The record evidence suggests that the Agency would have granted such a request. Additionally, in the opinion of the undersigned, in all likelihood it would be wrong to conclude that such an effort is more than should reasonably be expected of Mr. Ewaldt. Ultimately, the undersigned rejects the Union's clemency theory. To find otherwise would contradict the unambiguous language of Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA, and the Arbitrator would be in violation of Section 18.6 of the CBA's language, which prohibits him from amending, modifying, nullifying, ignoring and so forth its terms. The Arbitrator is bound by the CBA.</p>
<p>Moreover, this same conclusion applies to the Union's second theory. As discussed above, that theory pertains to Ms. Zeiher's due process rights. For the Parties to have time-limited any appeal to arbitration, is for them to have simultaneously time-limited a unit employee's access to due process (i.e., arbitration). However, the Union's third theory, namely, its past practices theory, warrants considered analysis because under some circumstances unambiguous language can misrepresent the parties' contemporary intentions with respect to the interpretation and application of a contract term.</p>
<p>Relevant to its third theory, the Union, citing learned authority, correctly argues that past practices under contract language &ndash; even unambiguous language &ndash; may control how said language is interpreted and administered. For example, if, over time, the Agency had been lax in the strict enforcement of the unambiguous language in Section 18.4, Step 3, and if the Parties had come to expect laxity, either implicitly or explicitly, then this language would not render untimely Mr. Ewaldt's appeal to arbitration, and it would not bar Ms. Zeiher's access to arbitration. Moreover, at some point, if the Agency had decided to begin strict enforcement of the language in Section 18.4, Step 3, then it also must have put the Union on notice of its intent to do so. In the instant matter, the Union argues that the Agency has been flexible (i.e., lax) in the enforcement of Section 18.4, Step 3's unambiguous language, and it offered examples of said laxity.</p>
<p>The Arbitrator has carefully considered the Union's examples. He focused on whether the Union's examples show (1) that the Agency has not enforced Section 18.4, Step 3's due process waiver by allowing arbitration when the ten (10) day calendar day timeline has been exceeded, and (2) whether the Agency has not treated said employees as having voluntarily resigned under this condition. None of the Union's five (5) examples pass either of these two (2) tests. Note that Nelson Affidavit, Union Exhibits 1 through 5, respectively, pertain to: (1) a long-delayed Step 1 grievance meeting; (2) when the Step 1 grievance-filing &ldquo;clock&rdquo; should begin; (3) to convening a class action grievance at Step 2; (4) a granted request for more time to prepare for a Step 1 grievance meeting; and (5) another granted request for more time in advance of convening a Step 1 grievance meeting.</p>
<p>The Union failed to meet its burden of proving by credible evidence that the Parties' past practices exhibited anything other than the strict enforcement of the language in Section 18.4, Step 3. In fact, none of the Union's examples even apply to Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA. Hence, the undersigned concludes that Mr. Ewaldt's appeal of Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance to arbitration was untimely under the language in Article 18, Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA, and that her position with the Agency was voluntarily vacated.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>V. <i>AWARD</i>:</b> For the reasons discussed above, Ms. Zeiher's substantive grievance is not procedurally arbitrable under the terms of Article 18, Section 18.4, Step 3 of the CBA.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>