<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>Owens Community College -and- Fraternal Order of Police, Ohio Labor Council, Inc.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS No. 16-02213</p>
<p>Issued: January 5, 2017.</p>
<p>Colman R. Lalka, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><small-cap>Opinion and Award</small-cap></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i>INTRODUCTION</i></h4>
<p>This arbitration proceeding was conducted pursuant to Article 9 of the November 1, 2014 <i>Agreement between The Fraternal Order of Police, Ohio Labor Council, Inc. and Owens Community College</i>. Hearing was held in Perrysburg, Ohio on October 19, 2016. At the hearing, sworn testimony was taken with the Parties being provided an equal opportunity to examine and cross-examine witnesses; exhibits were offered and made part of the record. Both Parties submitted Post Hearing Briefs.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>STATEMENT OF THE CASE</i></h4>
<p>The Grievant was issued a three-day suspension for violation of the Use of Force Policy and discourteous treatment of others. The Union grieved three-day suspension as being in violation of the Parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement. The grievance was processed, without resolution, through the steps of the Parties' contractual grievance procedure, and the matter is now before this Arbitrator for final and binding determination.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>ISSUE</i></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Was the Grievant issued a three-day suspension in violation of the Parties' Labor Agreement? If so, what shall the remedy be?</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i>COLLECTIVE BARGAINING AGREEMENT</i></h4>
<p>In addition to Article 9 providing for a grievance and arbitration procedure, the following provision of the Parties' Labor Agreement is applicable to these proceedings:</p>
<blockquote><p align="center">ARTICLE 8</p>
<p align="center">CORRECTIVE ACTION &amp; EMPLOYEE RECORDS</p>
<p class="continued">SECTION 8.1 The College will not discharge, suspend or otherwise discipline members except for just cause and the treatment of members shall be similar to that of other members. The College agrees to apply the principles of progressive discipline where appropriate. However, certain actions by their nature may be severe enough to justify deviating from progressive disciplinary principles. &hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">SECTION 8.2 No member shall receive a verbal or written reprimand prior to a conversation with the Supervisor issuing the discipline. Members shall not be demoted, suspended or discharged without first being given an opportunity to attend a pre-disciplinary hearing where the member may give his/her version of the events at issue. An employee may waive his/her right to a pre-disciplinary hearing. &hellip;</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p>In addition to the above provisions of the Collective Bargaining Agreement, the following provisions of the Police Division Use of Force Policy are applicable to these proceedings:</p>
<p align="center">OWENS STATE COMMUNITY COLLEGE</p>
<p align="center">DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC SAFETY</p>
<p align="center">POLICE DIVISION</p>
<p align="center">USE OF FORCE</p>
<p align="center">SECTION 43.1</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">3. Definitions</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">A. Reasonable Belief&mdash;Exists when facts or circumstances that the officer knows, or should know, are such to cause an ordinary prudent person to act or think in a similar way under similar circumstances.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">D. Serious Physical Injury/Bodily Injury/Physical Violence/Physical Harm&mdash;Any act which carries a substantial risk of death, permanent incapacity, disfigurement or prolonged or intractable pain.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">4. Procedures</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">D. Escalating Factors to the Use of Force</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">1. Officers are authorized to use a higher degree of force &hellip; under any of the following circumstances:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">a. When there is more than a single offender, or there are bystanders or others who may intervene or interfere with the situation.</p>
<p class="continued">b. Whenever there exists the possible use of drugs and/or alcohol, or the mental capacity of the offender is impaired as to escalate the level of hostility and aggressiveness towards the officer or innocent bystanders.</p>
<p class="continued">c. Whenever there is the reasonable and articulable suspicion of the presence of a weapon (fake gun, bulge in jacket, etc.).</p>
<p class="continued">d. If there are any physiological capabilities, or size differential which work to the disadvantage of the officer.</p>
<p class="continued">e. Whenever there is an unavailability of backup, or there are time constraints; or whenever the officer is required to make an immediate arrest.</p>
<p class="continued">f. When there is a known history of violent behavior by the assailant, based on the officer's experience or credible information, such as a transmission from dispatch.</p>
<p class="continued">g. Whenever there are unusual circumstances or factors beyond the officer's control that introduce a higher than normal degree of risk to the officer or others.</p></blockquote></blockquote>
<p class="continued">E. Other Considerations in the Use of Force</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">3. Display of firearm&mdash;An officer shall not draw or exhibit a firearm unless the circumstances surrounding the incident create a reasonable belief that it may be necessary to use the firearm to prevent serious physical harm or death to the officer or others.</p></blockquote></blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i>DISCUSSION</i></h4>
<p>In 2011 the Grievant began employment with Owens Community College as a student worker through the Department of Public Safety. From that position, the Grievant became a part-time Security Officer, and then a full-time Dispatcher. For the last three years, the Grievant has been employed as a full-time Police Officer.</p>
<p>On February 1, 2016, the Grievant was in his patrol car, in Lot L, alongside Sgt. Ernie Shiffler. As the two men were conversing, Sgt. Shiffler stated that a semi-trailer truck was approaching on Biniker Rd. Tractor-trailers are not permitted on Biniker, which has a small roundabout that such large vehicles are unable to successfully negotiate. The semi drove around the roundabout, caused minor damage, and proceeded onto Oregon continuing north.</p>
<p>The Grievant asked Sgt. Shiffler if he should conduct a traffic stop of the tractor-trailer, and received an affirmative response. Due to traffic and the speed of the truck, the Grievant was unable to immediately pull behind the semi, an empty flatbed. As the Grievant caught up to the flatbed, which was pulling into a right turn lane, the Grievant activated his overhead lights and siren. When the Grievant pulled immediately behind the flatbed, which was stopping for a red light, the light changed, and the driver of the flatbed made the turn, and continued for a distance of .59 miles, at speeds within the posted limit of twenty-five miles per hour.</p>
<p>The road is two lanes, with no place for the driver of the flatbed to pull off. The Grievant continued behind the flatbed with siren and lights activated. At one point, at a stop sign, the driver of the flatbed stopped, and the Grievant, thinking the driver would remain stopped, began exiting his cruiser. The driver of the flatbed, however, proceeded through the intersection, and the Grievant continued his pursuit. A short distance later, the flatbed pulled off the road into a business' commercial parking lot. The Grievant continued behind the flatbed into the parking lot, exited his vehicle, and drew his firearm.</p>
<p>The Grievant testified that he drew his firearm after observing the driver through the truck cab's side-view mirror. In that regard, the Grievant gave two varying accounts of the driver's actions: 1) in his report after the traffic stop the Grievant stated the driver was &ldquo;reaching his hands around his driver seat,&rdquo; and 2) at the arbitration hearing the Grievant testified the driver could be seen reaching toward the passenger seat.</p>
<p>Video and audio from the dash cams of the Grievant and Sgt. Shiffler, as well as audio of a subsequent fact-finding interview of the Grievant conducted by Scott W. Steinke, were accepted into evidence. Scott Steinke at that time was a Lieutenant serving as Acting Chief, and has since assumed the position of Chief. The Grievant's dash cam video discloses that after the door of his vehicle could be heard closing, the Grievant yelled twice for the drive to show his hands. Before the first time the Grievant yelled, the window of the tractor can be seen being lowered, and a split second prior to the Grievant yelling the second time, the driver was placing his hands out of the window. That is, the driver was complying with the Grievant's first command.</p>
<p>Approximately one minute later, Sgt. Shiffler, who followed in his vehicle, can be seen walking into the field of view of the Grievant's dash cam. Two minutes after Sgt. Shiffler entered the field of view, two Northwood police cruisers can be seen entering the parking lot. They were advised by Sgt. Shiffler that their assistance was not needed.</p>
<p>After the driver exited the cab of the truck, the driver attempted to explain that there was no place for him to pull over as the reason he did not stop earlier. The Grievant spoke to him in a loud voice, arguing that he, the driver, could have stopped as soon as he observed the Grievant behind him with lights and siren activated. At one point, the Grievant can be heard stating in a loud voice that, &ldquo;I have half the county up here in route right now because you're not stopping.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Approximately twenty or thirty minutes after the stop the Grievant produced a report of the incident. The Grievant's incident report reads:</p>
<blockquote><p>On Monday, February 1, 2016, I, Officer John Eggleston #111, was sitting in a marked patrol vehicle in Lot L on the Owens State Community College campus. I was sitting next to Sergeant Ernie Shiffler #105, when we both observed a white semi truck driving westbound on Biniker Driver, attempting to drive around the round-a-bout. The semi truck turned northbound onto Oregon Road and was moving at a fast pace. I began to try to catch up to the semi truck. Sergeant Shiffler advised me that the semi truck had caused some minor turf damage to the round-a-bout landscaping &hellip; I was finally able to catch up to the semi truck &hellip; I initiated my overhead lights and audible siren. The semi truck stopped for a moment, but then proceeded eastbound onto Wales Road. I called out on the radio to my dispatcher that I was attempting to stop a semi truck &hellip; We got to the Wales Road and Tracy Road intersection and the semi truck stopped, and I got out of my vehicle and started to approach the semi truck, thinking that the driver finally stopped. I informed my dispatcher over the radio that I had the truck stopped at Wales and Tracy. As soon as I got up to the back bumper of the trailer, the driver took off again, still proceeding eastbound on Wales Road. I ran back to my vehicle and informed my dispatcher that the driver took off from me again and that we were continuing on Wales Road. The semi truck then turned left into the Seaway Scaffolding business &hellip; The driver finally came to a complete stop and I got out of my vehicle and I noticed that the driver was starting to make some furtive movements (reaching his hands around his driver seat). I pulled my department-issued firearm and ordered the driver to show me his hands. The driver hesitated for a moment and I yelled out the command to show me your hands again, in which the driver complied and put both his hands out the window. As soon as I observed the driver complying with orders, I put my firearm back in my holster. I went up to the truck and I opened the driver door and ordered the driver to step down out of the cab. &hellip; I asked the driver &hellip; why he didn't stop and &lsqb;the driver&rsqb; stated that he did not know that I was behind him with my lights on. I informed &lsqb;the driver&rsqb; that I had activated my lights and siren at Oregon Road just south of Wales and he did not stop. &lsqb;The driver&rsqb; continued to say that he never saw me, I informed &lsqb;the driver&rsqb; that I even went into the opposite lane of travel to get his attention, and he still didn't stop. &lsqb;The driver&rsqb; then admitted that when he started to stop, he turned onto Wales Road, and that he had seen me behind him as he was turning on to Wales Road from Oregon Road. &hellip;</p></blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p>In that the matter involved a pursuit, an automatic review was triggered pursuant to departmental policy. Required information was missing from the Grievant's above report, and Ch. Steinke emailed the Grievant instructing him to supplement his report pursuant to the applicable departmental General Order. In the supplement, the Grievant indicated:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Operating Speeds During Pursuit:</p>
<p class="continued">Lowest Speed: 12 MPH</p>
<p class="continued">Highest Speed: 25 MPH</p>
<p class="continued">Total Length of Pursuit:</p>
<p class="continued">3,119 feet or 0.59 miles</p>
<p class="continued">Total Elapsed Time:</p>
<p class="continued">3 minutes</p>
<p class="continued">Observed Traffic Violations:</p>
<p class="continued">Vehicle swerved over the right shoulder solid white line one time on Wales Road near Oregon Rd.</p></blockquote>
<p>Ch. Steinke also received a report of the stop from Sgt. Shiffler. Sgt. Shiffler's report reads:</p>
<blockquote><p>At 1726 hours on February 1, 2016, Officer John Eggleston and myself were in Lot M talking when Officer Eggleston observed a tractor-trailer vehicle enter the round-about on Biniker, just east of Oregon Road. Officer Eggleston left the parking lot attempting to catch up to the vehicle and make a traffic stop. I also left the parking lot and paused for a moment to check for any damage caused by the vehicle when it ran up and over the sidewalk area of the round-about. There was visible damage to the turf and heavy black tire marks on the sidewalk.</p>
<p>I radioed Officer Eggleston and advised him of what I had found. Officer Eggleston advised that he was attempting to stop the vehicle &hellip; Officer Eggleston radioed that they were continuing east on Wales Road. I overheard radio traffic from Northwood Police that they were monitoring our radio traffic, and believing that we had a vehicle pursuit in progress, had two of their units head in our direction. I advised Officer Eggleston (over the radio) that if the semi had not stopped by the time they reached the intersection of Wales and Tracy roads, he was to let the semi go. Officer Eggleston radioed that they had stopped at the intersection of Wales and Tracy. Officer Eggleston then radioed back that the truck was moving again and was continuing eastbound on Wales from Tracy. As I approached the intersection from the south, I was able to see the semi pull into the parking lot of Seaway Scaffold, which is located at the north-east corner of the intersection. Officer Eggleston exited his patrol car and approached the driver's side of the semi. I was able to see that Officer Eggleston had drawn his sidearm and I could hear Officer Eggleston yelling at the driver instructing him to show him (Officer Eggleston) his hands. I activated the lights on my patrol car and once I was able to maneuver my vehicle through traffic at the intersection, I pulled into the parking lot behind Officer Eggleston's vehicle.</p>
<p>When I approached the spot where Officer Eggleston was he had re-holstered his sidearm and opened the driver's door on the semi and had ordered the driver to exit the vehicle. He then patted down the driver and obtained his identification. While obtaining his identification, an argument began between the driver and Officer Eggleston. At this point, two officers from Northwood arrived and I advised them that we were all set.</p>
<p>When the argument began to escalate, I intervened and told the driver to be quiet and took Officer Eggleston aside and instructed him to go ahead and write and issue the citation. After the citation was issued and the driver released, Officer Eggleston returned to the station to complete his report. I advised him to be sure and park so that the video footage from his dash camera would upload to the station's computer system.</p>
<p>When I arrived on station, Officer Eggleston and myself reviewed the video from this stop. We had a discussion about the pursuit and subsequent stop. Among the topics we discussed was his lack of information about the vehicle (license plate, description) given to the dispatcher and his response when the truck driver started laughing at him. I emphasized that we simply cannot show our anger no matter what someone may be doing in an attempt to provoke an angry response from us as officers.</p></blockquote>
<p>After his review of the dash cam footage and the reports of the Grievant and Sgt. Shiffler, Ch. Steinke, on February 12, conducted a fact-finding interview of the Grievant. Also present during the interview was the Grievant's Union Representative, Jackie Wegman. During the interview, Ch. Steinke discussed with both the Grievant and Ms. Wegman what he, Ch. Steinke, felt was wrong with the Grievant's behavior during the traffic stop. The Grievant agreed that his behavior could have been better, indicating:</p>
<blockquote><p>CH. STEINKE: How did you think your interaction with &lsqb;the driver&rsqb; went?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: I could have done a lot better on that. When I watched the video again, I, to be quite honest, I looked at it and I was like, wow, that's not normally how I, you know, I usually conduct myself.</p>
<p>I mean, call it adrenaline or what, you know, but I just, the fact that he, you know, he started laughing, getting, you know, giggling and thinking it was a joke and that it wasn't a serious, you know, thing, it, you know, to me, I was like, this isn't a joke, this is serious, this is a very serious situation, whether you think that you were just trying to find a place to pull over now which is one of the excuses he gave. This isn't funny, you know, this is a serious thing.</p>
<p>But I definitely, looking at the video, I was like, that's not how I would definitely handle it in the future. I could have been better, a better professional in my interaction with him, the way I talked to him, my demeanor towards him, that definitely could be improved. Because when I watched the video, to myself, I'm like, oh, I mean, that's, that to me tells me I can improve and do better next time.</p></blockquote>
<p>Regarding drawing his firearm, a review of the verbatim exchange is informative:</p>
<blockquote><p>CH. STEINKE: One question I guess I have as an observer, as a professional observer, I know a lot of these answers before I ask them, but I think it's helpful for me to understand your perspective of things, that I ask them, so while I know some of the answers to these questions, I'm not pointing fingers, I'm just asking for clarification, so that either we're on the same page on things or not.</p>
<p>So, you know, police officers are always scrutinized and these are common issues that come up, we see cops on TV all the time being recorded by iPhones a thousand times more than we ever did prior to Jackie &lsqb;Wegman&rsqb; and I ever becoming cops, so our need to maintain our composure probably is, not that we shouldn't avoid that, but I think it's important to remember that there's always been that need.</p>
<p>So one of the things I wanted to hit on was your display of a firearm. Have you had an opportunity to review the use of force policy about that?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: From the pursuit or just the firearm policy itself?</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: The use of force is where you would find the, I didn't ask you to review this, so maybe you didn't, and that's fine.</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: I didn't, but I have before, yes.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: So I guess my question is, I'm going to put words in your mouth a little bit, but typically your display or brandishing of a firearm is based on facts that you've articulated to me that cause you to believe that there's a potential for a risk of serious physical harm to either yourself or others. Is that a fair assessment?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: Yes.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: And it's usually based on a reasonable belief that there's a necessity to draw your firearm, and that reasonableness by the court standards, Jackie &lsqb;Wegman&rsqb;, you can correct me because it's been so long since I thought of this, but the court standard is a reasonable police officer, given similar circumstances, and their beliefs as to whether or not that's reasonable. The public may not always view that to be an accurate depiction of what we should be doing, but the courts have ruled that a fair assessment of what is typically from the view of a reasonable police officer. So I guess my question comes, if you have a reasonable belief that there's a risk of serious physical harm, either to yourself or others, because you didn't mention this during your critical analysis of yourself, so was there ever a consideration to conduct a felony style traffic stop and wait for backup, things like that?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: Not in this situation, I wouldn't have done a felony type stop. And the reason why is because he did, one, because of the speed of this traffic, attempt to make the traffic stop. First off, if it would have gone, I'll just put this out there. If we would have gone more than under the limit, I wouldn't have gone after him for what my original PC was, for the going off Biniker &mdash;</p>
<p>MS. WEGMAN: Did you say under or over? What did you say?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: I'm sorry, under, we were under the &mdash;</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: I understood. I mean, it's no big deal. I get what you're saying. It's not an issue, but I understand what you're saying.</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: I just wanted to say that, but the reason why I didn't do a felony stop and have him come out backwards like &mdash; sorry.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: I assume, I was in the academy in 1995, so you're going to need to educate me. I assume they still teach this stuff in the police academy, right?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: Yes.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: That when faced with a potential aggressor in a traffic stop situation where there's a risk of serious physical harm or a belief to believe that you're, may be facing danger like that, to wait for backup typically if you can, to conduct a felony style traffic stop, which is order people back to you.</p>
<p>So, go ahead, I know you were going to say why you didn't do that.</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: Okay. The reason why I didn't is, I mean, the whole reason why I pulled out my firearm, like I stated earlier, was because, you know, I was giving commands to him, and I saw him making movements in the, you know, in the truck. Because of the fact that he failed to comply to stop for me, I took that into consideration, you know, and I didn't see any other indicator, I mean, during the whole time of trying to stop him, he didn't wave to me, he didn't turn his four-ways on, so to me, that meant he's not complying with my order to stop.</p>
<p>Because of that, the fact that I saw the movement in the cab, and that's why I took my firearm out to begin with. But as soon as he complied, I mean, my firearm wasn't even out for probably more than thirty seconds, if even that.</p>
<p>As soon as he rolled down the window and his hands were out the window, I gave it a moment and said, keep them out, they stayed out, they never even made movement, they stayed out the whole time, that serious risk of harm and threat went away immediately. And that's when it went back in my holster and that's why I didn't do, that's why I went up to the cab, his hands stayed there the whole time.</p>
<p>If he would have pulled them back in, that would have been a different situation, but it didn't happen that way. They stayed out the whole time, I approached, slowly opened the cab door, he had his hands there the whole time, he did the one hand to do the seat belt, had the one hand to move his cell phone off of his lap and a piece of paper or whatever it was, then he stepped down out of the cab, so &mdash;</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: Then, here, I guess the question I have is at what point did you pull your gun out? Did you pull it out when you got out of the car before you made your approach, or did you already begin your approach before you drew your firearm?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: No, I was behind my car door at that time.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: Okay.</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: Because they teach you in the academy to use the car door as a barrier.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: Right.</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: That if they start shooting at you, to use the frame or whatever.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: For cover?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: For cover and stuff. So I stayed behind the door until, you know, I noticed that he was complying, and that's when I put it away and then walked up to &mdash;</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: So you're saying you didn't have it out when you began your approach, because &lsqb;Sgt. Shiffler&rsqb; said in the video<ftnote num="1"><para>The video of Sgt. Shiffler's dash cam.</para></ftnote> he saw you with your gun out, so I'm curious, was your gun out when you approached, because he seemed to say that. I haven't talked to him, so I don't know.</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: Yeah.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: But he said in the video you had your gun out.</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: Yeah.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: Was your gun out when you approached the truck, or was it out just when you were behind the car door?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: Well, I mean, I had it out, but, I mean, I'm sure he saw it. Because, I mean, I saw him looking at me the whole time through the mirror, so I'm sure he saw it at that point.</p>
<p>But when I walked, when I was physically walking up to the cab and stuff &mdash;</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: You had already reholstered?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: Yeah. I mean, I may have walked around the car door as I was putting it back in, but, I mean, I was not, you know, up at the cab door with it out or anything like that.</p>
<p>I mean, because at that point, he was complying and I had put that away already.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: The media sensationalize the word contempt of cop, so I'm very hesitant to use it anytime I talk to anybody, but it seems to be the best way to describe what I'm going to ask you. Was in any way the reaction that you had and your opinion of it, I mean, you've described, you know, you could have done better in your reaction to his actions in terms of his laughing and smiling, did you feel like you were always in control of yourself, or did you feel like, that you drawing your firearm was partially due to that?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: No, the firearm pulling, I had complete control the whole time of that. The only thing that I may have lost a little control over was when I was maybe about to start arguing with him at one point in questioning him.</p>
<p>CH. STEINKE: That's when &lsqb;Sgt. Shiffler&rsqb; intervened?</p>
<p>GRIEVANT: That's when &lsqb;Sgt. Shiffler&rsqb; intervened. But it never at all, at any time when I had my firearm out, I was always in control, I always had a good view of the situation, I was one step ahead of everything.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As the conclusion of the fact-finding interview drew to a close, Ch. Steinke determined discipline was appropriate for discourteous treatment of the driver and the Grievant drawing his sidearm. He discussed with Ms. Wegman his concern that if the Grievant had a reasonable belief that he was subject to serious physical harm, why did he, the Grievant, not wait for backup. Ch. Steinke also expressed concern that the Grievant did not react proportionately to the situation, and the potential for the situation escalating.</p>
<p>After the interview concluded, Ch. Steinke and Ms. Wegman discussed discipline consisting of a one-day suspension for discourteous treatment of the semi-driver. Ms. Wegman left Ch. Steinke's office for approximately fifteen minutes, returned, and indicated that the Grievant had agreed to the one-day suspension.</p>
<p>Pursuant to the agreed upon discipline, on February 17 Ch. Steinke forwarded an email to the Grievant along with attached waiver of pre-disciplinary hearing form and a copy of the Disciplinary Report Form. The Disciplinary Report Form reads:</p>
<blockquote><p>In accordance with General Order 41.14, I conducted a post-pursuit review of a Failure to Comply reported Monday, February 1st, 2016 by Officer John F. Eggleston, the results of which revealed that Officer Eggleston did correctly initiate a traffic stop of a semi-tractor/trailer &hellip; for causing minor damage to real property and for failure to obey traffic control devices. However, in reviewing the relevant in-car video, reports, and interviews of Officer Eggleston and his supervisor Sgt. Ernest Shiffler, Officer Eggleston's treatment of &lsqb;the semi-driver&rsqb; was antagonistic and discourteous. Officer Eggleston escalated a relatively minor traffic offense into an unprofessional verbal exchange requiring intervention by his supervisor. Officer Eggleston is being advised that his treatment of &lsqb;the driver&rsqb; was inappropriate and disproportionate to the facts known to him at the time. A one day unpaid suspension to be served at a time determined by the Interim Director/Chief of Police based upon operational needs.</p></blockquote>
<p>Approximately two or three days later, Ms. Wegman called Ch. Steinke and advised that the Grievant was reconsidering the agreed upon discipline, and desired more time before responding to Ch. Steinke's February 17 email. Having heard nothing further, Ch. Steinke, on February 21, emailed the following to Ms. Wegman:</p>
<blockquote><p>I don't believe I ever provided you a copy, so please find attached our Department's Use of Force Policy. Since it will become a part of my recommendation for a 3-day suspension to Human Resources should our original agreement become void, I have highlighted the relevant section that I read aloud during Officer Eggleston's fact-finding interview. I look forward to his final decision on our original agreement no later than Monday, February 22nd.</p>
<p>I will also be providing you Officer Eggleston's training records reflecting his being refreshed in the Use of Force Policy each year, most recently just this past December, should it become necessary. Please call me Monday if you have any questions or if you want to discuss it further.</p></blockquote>
<p>The following day, February 22, Ms. Wegman called Ch. Steinke and indicated that the Grievant had determined to rescind the negotiated discipline of a one-day suspension. Ms. Wegman also indicated to Ch. Steinke that she had received his email of the previous day. Subsequently, in that the negotiated discipline had been rescinded, on February 29 Ch. Steinke emailed the Grievant notice of a pre-disciplinary hearing to be conducted on March 8. On March 1, by reply email the Grievant indicated to Ch. Steinke that he was waiving his right to the pre-disciplinary hearing.</p>
<p>On March 18, 2016 Ch. Steinke emailed to the Grievant a completed Disciplinary Report Form, which reads:</p>
<blockquote><p>On Monday, February 1st, 2016 Officer Eggleston conducted a traffic stop of a semi-tractor/trailer &hellip; In reviewing the relevant in-car video, reports, and interviews of Officer Eggleston and his supervisor Sgt. Ernest Shiffler, Officer Eggleston's treatment of &lsqb;the semi-driver&rsqb; was antagonistic and discourteous, Officer Eggleston escalated a relatively minor traffic offense into an unprofessional verbal exchange requiring intervention by his supervisor. Officer Eggleston's treatment of &lsqb;the driver&rsqb; was inappropriate and disproportionate to the facts known to him at the time. Officer Eggleston drawing his firearm from it's holster was unreasonable. Officer Eggleston did re-holster his firearm within moments of drawing it, but a decision to draw and display a firearm requires a &ldquo;reasonable belief&rdquo; that it may be necessary to prevent serious physical harm. Officer Eggleston exposed himself to the driver by approaching the semi-tractor, even though he had been in a relatively safe place of cover, he did not wait for backup only moments away before approaching the driver, and he did not require the driver to comply with standard felony stop procedures; this all suggesting that Officer Eggleston did not have the requisite &ldquo;reasonable belief&rdquo; the driver posed a threat of serious physical harm. The facts known to Officer Eggleston at the time were; (1) a semi tractor/trailer caused minor damage to real property while circling a roundabout, and (2) the driver failed to yield to an emergency vehicle for three minutes for a total distance of .59 miles at a maximum speed of 25 miles per hour, ultimately pulling into a parking lot.</p>
<p>A three day unpaid suspension to be served at a time determined by the Interim Director/Chief of Police based upon operational needs.</p></blockquote>
<p>The Union grieves the three-day suspension and points out that, pursuant to <i>Miami Twp. Bd. of Trustees v. Fraternal Order of Police, Ohio Labor Council, Inc</i>. (1998), 81 Ohio St.3d 269, an Arbitrator, after determining there was Just Cause to discipline an employee, has the authority to review the appropriateness of the discipline imposed. The Union notes that the Grievant was suspended for discourteous treatment of others and improper display of a firearm, and contends that the Employer failed to establish Just Cause for either. In its defense, the Union contends: 1) the Grievant was not discourteous, 2) the Grievant is not guilty of improper display of a firearm, 3) the suspension is not reasonably related to the seriousness of the offense, and 4) the Grievant was disciplined without benefit of a pre-disciplinary hearing.</p>
<p>Additionally, the Union points out that Sgt. Shiffler, in his statement, never indicated that the Grievant was discourteous. Moreover, the Union states, the Employer failed to call Sgt. Shiffler as a witness, thereby denying the Union the opportunity of cross-examination. The Union also contends that the Employer has no policy regarding discourteous treatment of others, and emphasizes that at no point did the Employer cite or introduce such a policy. The Union goes on to cite the first of the seven tests of Just Cause, &ldquo;Did the Employer give the employee forewarning or foreknowledge of the possible or probable disciplinary consequences of the employee's conduct?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Other than remedy, for reasons noted below it will be unnecessary to address the existence of a policy regarding discourteous treatment of others, nor will it be necessary to address whether the Grievant had forewarning or knowledge of the disciplinary consequences of discourteous conduct. Also, in that the Grievant made certain admissions in the fact-finding interview and in his testimony at the hearing, hearsay statements of Sgt. Shiffler can be disregarded.</p>
<p>To be first addressed is the Union's contention that the Grievant was disciplined without benefit of a pre-disciplinary hearing as required by Article 8, Section 8.2. The Employer's reliance on the Grievant's March 1 waiver of the pre-disciplinary hearing, the Union believes, is misplaced. The Grievant, according to the Union, believed he was only waiving a pre-disciplinary hearing on the charge of discourteous treatment, not the use of force.</p>
<p>After all, the Union continues, Ch. Steinke's primary focus during the fact-finding interview was on whether the Grievant was discourteous to the semi-driver. After the interview, the Grievant was offered a one-day suspension for discourteous treatment, and there was never any discussion of whether there would be a use of force charge, and the Disciplinary Report Form reflecting the one-day suspension never included a use of force charge.</p>
<p>The Arbitrator notes, however, that during the fact-finding interview, Ch. Steinke did, in fact, spend time and express concern regarding the Grievant having drawn his firearm. Inquiry was made of the Grievant as to why he, the Grievant, did not conduct a felony stop or wait for backup. Inquiry was also made regarding the point at which the Grievant drew his firearm, where the firearm was as the Grievant approached the truck cab, at what point he re-holstered the firearm, and the duration of time the firearm was out of the holster. Moreover, in the Chief's February 21 email to Ms. Wegman, he attached the Use of Force Policy and indicated it would become part of his recommendation for a three-day suspension should the Grievant decline the agreement reached at the conclusion of the fact-finding interview.</p>
<p>In the view of the Arbitrator, after Ms. Wegman's February 22 call to Ch. Steinke wherein she indicated the Grievant would not accept the negotiated discipline, the parties were in the position of where they would have found themselves had a negotiated discipline not been reached. That is, the disciplinary process began anew. The argument that the Grievant was unaware any discipline other than a one-day suspension would be considered is not convincing.</p>
<p>The Department's Use of Force Policy defines <i>Reasonable Belief</i> and <i>Serious Physical Injury/Bodily Injury/Physical Violence/Physical Harm</i> as quoted above. While the Union argues that the Grievant kept the firearm in the low ready position and never pointed his firearm at the semi-driver or the semi-cab, it is noted, as the Employer points out, that the Use of Force Policy addresses and only allows for the drawing of a firearm under enumerated circumstances. If at least one of the enumerated circumstances is non-existent, the policy does not authorize the drawing of a firearm even if held in the low ready position or not pointed at a person or object.</p>
<p>The Union also contends that the Grievant had his firearm unholstered for six to eight seconds at the most, and never had his finger on the trigger. While the Grievant's sidearm cannot be seen on the dash cam video due to the view being obstructed by the flatbed, comparing the video with the Grievant's statements during the fact-finding interview renders the account of six to eight seconds accurate as the time the Grievant's sidearm was unholstered. However, as noted above, the Use of Force Policy does not authorize the drawing of a firearm in the absence of one of the enumerated circumstances. This applies regardless of the time the firearm is unholstered or the location of the trigger finger.</p>
<p>Due to the uncertainty of why the driver was refusing to stop, the Union contends that the Grievant had no way of knowing if the truck was stolen, the driver had outstanding warrants for his arrest, or was fleeing a crime scene. The difficulty with this argument, in the view of the Arbitrator, is that during the pursuit the Grievant never radioed in the license plate number of the truck. This would have resulted in a records search with at least one or two of those questions being answered. It also must be noted that what has been described as a pursuit was nothing more than the semi proceeding on a two lane road, that had no place to pull off and stop, all the while observing the twenty-five mile-per-hour posted speed limit.</p>
<p>It is the Union's belief that the circumstances surrounding the entire incident created a reasonable belief that it was necessary that the Grievant use his firearm to prevent serious physical harm or death to himself or others. This reasonable belief, the Union contends, is based not only upon the driver's refusal to stop, but also on the Grievant's observation of the driver through the semi-cab's side-view mirror.</p>
<p>It is noted, however, that in his written incident report, the Grievant indicated he observed &ldquo;furtive movements&rdquo; of the driver reaching his hands around his driver seat. At the arbitration hearing, the Grievant testified that he observed the driver's upper body move to the right. The Grievant expressed concern that the driver could have a weapon on the passenger seat, on the floor, or in the center console. The Union points out that the Use of Force Policy permits Officers to use a higher degree of force under certain circumstances.</p>
<p>Specifically, the Union cites Sections 43.1(4)(D)(1)(c) and (g), quoted above. Subsection (c) provides for an articulable suspicion of a weapon, and, as examples of an articulable suspicion, indicates &ldquo;fake gun, bulge in jacket, etc.&rdquo; This situation is not applicable to the circumstances of this traffic stop. The Grievant did not see the driver until he exited the cab, and, therefore, could have seen a &ldquo;fake gun, bulge in jacket, etc.,&rdquo; at the time he drew his firearm. The reason for drawing the firearm, the Grievant stated, was the driver's movements in the cab.</p>
<p>Regarding Subsection (g), there were no unusual circumstances beyond the Grievant's control that introduced a higher than normal degree of risk. From radio chatter, the Grievant was aware backup was available and the Grievant can be heard stating to the driver, &ldquo;I have half the county up here in route right now because you're not stopping.&rdquo; Had the Grievant felt he was in danger, he should have waited for backup to arrive. Sgt. Shiffler can be seen arriving on scene in about one minute, and two Northwood cruisers are seen on the dash cam arriving two minutes after that.</p>
<p>The Employer emphasizes that the reasonable belief standard as provided in the Use of Force Policy is an objective standard. That is, whether the facts known to the Grievant during the traffic stop were such that they would have caused an ordinary prudent Officer to act in a similar manner. Ch. Steinke testified that a reasonable Police Officer would have viewed the situation facing the Grievant as a failure to yield, not a high speed pursuit, or a person known to be armed or driving a stolen vehicle.</p>
<p>A driver in the cab of a truck is in an advantaged position, and if there is a reasonable belief of physical violence, the cab should not be approached. The Officer should, instead, await the arrival of backup, or conduct a felony stop if backup is unavailable. The Grievant did neither, and this, the Employer believes, establishes that an ordinary prudent Officer would not have reacted as the Grievant had, and draw his firearm.</p>
<p>The Employer additionally questions the &ldquo;furtive movements&rdquo; the Grievant claims took place. In his incident report, the Grievant indicated the driver was &ldquo;reaching his hands around the driver seat.&rdquo; During the fact-finding interview, the Grievant stated:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">When I got out of my cruiser, I noticed, I was looking in his mirrors to see what he was doing, and I saw that he was starting to, he was making some movement in there. I didn't know what he was doing, and because of the situation of him not complying with stopping, I withdrew my firearm &hellip;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In what the Employer believes was an attempted to exaggerate the furtive movements claimed to have been seen, at the arbitration hearing for the first time the Grievant stated that he saw the driver's upper body turn to the right and start moving around. Truck drivers are known to carry weapons, the Grievant stated, and he felt the driver was reaching for something.</p>
<p>In that the Grievant's claim that the driver was reaching toward the passenger seat was raised for the first time at the arbitration hearing, the Arbitrator agrees with the Employer's assessment that the claim was an exaggeration, and must be discounted. The Arbitrator, applying an objective standard, believes an ordinary prudent person facing similar circumstances would not have reacted as the Grievant had, and draw his sidearm. That is, the Grievant violated the Department's Use of Force Policy.</p>
<p>The Employer points out that while Article 8.1 provides for progressive discipline, it also provides that &ldquo;certain actions by their nature may be severe enough to justify deviating from progressive disciplinary principles.&rdquo; In this instance, Ch. Steinke indicated that deviating from progressive discipline was justified in that the drawing of a firearm carries with it a potential for an escalation to violence and physical harm to the public or to the Officer. The Chief stated, &ldquo;The very nature of the offense, the drawing of a firearm outside of policy, creates a riskier-than-should-have-been situation. It always does.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In that regard, it must be emphasized that on the dash cam video, a person in work clothes is seen walking around the truck during the stop. That person is subsequently seen entering the business of the parking lot where the semi stopped, and is presumably an employee. Thus, at least one person can be seen in the immediate area, thereby increasing risk to the public.</p>
<p>The Chief testified, without contravention, that the three-day suspension is consistent with the measure of discipline he normally issues, and added that he has given such suspensions for less. In the view of the Arbitrator, the Employer has established Just Cause for the three-day suspension for violation of the Use of Force Policy. In that, as mandated by Article 8.1, Just Cause has been established for the three-day suspension, the Arbitrator may not substitute his judgment for that of the Employer's and order a lesser form of discipline.</p>
<p>Having so found it is unnecessary to address the behavior of the Grievant toward the driver, and the Arbitrator refrains from doing so. However, in the absence of a policy regarding discourteous treatment of others, and the discipline to be expected for same, reference to the Grievant's discourteous treatment of the semi-driver is to be removed from his record.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>CONCLUSION</i></h4>
<p>Based upon the foregoing, the above identified issue is answered in the negative. That is, the Grievant was not issued a three-day suspension in violation of the parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement, and the grievance is denied in part.</p>
<p>The grievance is sustained regarding discourteous treatment of others, and reference to discourteous treatment of others is to be removed from the Grievant's record.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>
