<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION BETWEEN FIRESTONE POLYMERS, LLC EMPLOYER and IUOE LOCAL 407 UNION</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS 15-56166-7</p>
<p>February 4, 2016.</p>
<p>Stephen Crable, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>I.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>STATEMENT OF THE CASE</b></i></h4>
<p>On February 10, 2015, Firestone Polymers (&ldquo;Company&rdquo; or &ldquo;Firestone&rdquo;) terminated Henry Davis (&ldquo;Grievant&rdquo;) an employee of the Company. The justification for for Firestone's action was Grievant's alleged willful or negligent failure to follow Company safety rules during his work shift on January 16, 2015, and his alleged concealment of critical information from the Company during the Company's investigation of a fire that occurred on equipment operated by Grievant on January 16, 2015. IUOE Local 407 (&ldquo;Union&rdquo; or &ldquo;Local 407&rdquo;), the collective bargaining representative for Company employees at the plant location in Lake Charles, Louisiana, grieved the termination pursuant to the relevant Collective Bargaining Agreement (&ldquo;Agreement&rdquo;) between the Company and Union. The parties subsequently utilized the offices of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service to select the undersigned Arbitrator to resolve the dispute. The Arbitrator held a hearing on November 12, 2015, beginning at 9:00 am and ending after 8:00 pm, in Lake Charles, LA. During the hearing, both parties presented witnesses, offered exhibits and made arguments. A certified shorthand reporter transcribed the testimony at the hearing, and the parties submitted written briefs on January 8, 2016. There is no dispute that the grievance is properly before the Arbitrator.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>II.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>STATEMENT OF THE ISSUE</b></i></h4>
<p>Whether the Company terminated the Grievant for just cause, and, if not what is the appropriate remedy?</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>III.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>POSITION OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. <i>Company</i></b></h4>
<p>Firestone argues it properly terminated Grievant for his willful and negligent actions surrounding a fire that occurred on his equipment during his January 16, 2015 work shift and his omissions and misleading statements made during the Company investigation of the fire. The Company submits that the termination was proper as Grievant admitted to violating multiple Company safety policies and procedures, admitted his awareness of the policies and procedures, and acknowledged that he expected to be disciplined, and in fact welcomed discipline, for his failure to follow such procedures. The resulting fire caused significant monetary loss to the Company and could have caused injury to or death of fellow employees. While these circumstances on their own justify the Company's termination decision, Grievant also was not forthcoming during the course of the Company's lengthy and exhaustive investigation, as he withheld information (and thus, misrepresented facts) in his written statement and his first interview with management. The Company notes that its progressive discipline policy specifically provides that an employee may be terminated for a single, serious performance lapse including negligence, carelessness or willful acts which result or could result in damage to company property or equipment or injury. Company rules also allow for termination if an employee misrepresents or falsifies Company reports. The Company distinguishes the discipline imposed on Grievant, from lighter discipline imposed on other employees whose performance lapses did not involve misrepresentations or intentional rule violations. Finally, Firestone notes that it has terminated other employees for single violations of Company safety rules.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. <i>Union</i></b></h4>
<p>The Union argues that the termination of the Grievant is not for just cause and that the Grievant should be reinstated with back pay and benefits. In support of its position the Union contends the Company failed to provide any concrete proof that Grievant committed the alleged terminable infractions. Specifically, the Company did not meet its burden to prove, by the weight of the evidence: that Grievant was not forthright in Company investigatory interviews; that Grievant intentionally failed to follow Company procedures following a high-high temperature reading on his equipment; and, that Grievant failed to follow the LOTO procedure, as practiced on the shop floor, when digging a plug from his equipment. Moreover, the Union argues the Company subjected Grievant to disparate treatment. The Company disciplined Grievant more harshly that other employees who committed the same, or more serious, performance lapses. The Union argues the Company has never terminated an employee for a fire or single operational rule violation. Finally, the Union urges that mitigation is appropriate since progressive discipline was not properly applied in this case. Mitigation is particularly appropriate in view of Grievant's sixteen years of commendable Company service.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>IV.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF THE AGREEEMENT, COMPNAY POLICIES AND PROCEDURES</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. AGREEMENT</b></h4>
<p class="continued">Section 16.5:</p>
<p class="continued">When an employee is found to be unjustly discharged, suspended, demoted, or laid off, he/she shall be reinstated without a break in seniority or loss of wages&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 16.6</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitration Committee shall have no authority to later, modify, or make exceptions to the provisions of this Agreement. The Committee's authority shall extend only to giving a proper interpretation of this Agreement and its several provision in the case of a dispute that cannot be settled through the regular grievance procedure.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. COMPANY PROCEDURES</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>From Procedure 9600: Dewatering and Drying in Process 2</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>General</b></h4>
<p class="continued">This specification covers the startup, shutdown and operation of the equipment used in the dewatering, drying and packaging of rubber crumb in Process 2.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Safety &amp; Health</b></h4>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>3.0 Precautions around Moving Equipment</b></h4>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">If necessary to unplug Anderson expander hopper, be certain the motor is stopped and not at &ldquo;0&rdquo; speed.</p>
<p class="continued">If it will require body parts to break the plane of the equipment to remove the plug, the Lockout/Tag out procedure must be followed.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Operating Procedures</b></h4>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>1.15 Start Anderson Extruder</b></h4>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">e.</p>
<table width="585" columns="1">
<tr>
<td width="50%"><p></p></td>
<td width="50%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2"><hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" valign="top"><p><b>IF</b></p></th>
<th align="left" valign="top"><p><b>THEN</b></p></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2"><hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>temperature exceeds high-high alarm</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>shut down, notify foreman, and inspect die plate for signs of burnt rubber.<br/>The die plate should then be removed, the rubber run out, and new dies installed.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2"><hr/></td>
</tr>
</table>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>If temperature reaches the high-high temperature alarm on TIC-1039A, the Anderson override will shut down Anderson (Interlock).</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>The die plate should then be removed, the rubber run out, and new dies installed.</b></p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>C. COMPANY POLICIES</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>From the Discipline Policy Lake Charles Plant</b></i></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">4.0 Repeat Violations will result in progressive action up to and including Discharge</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">4.1 Lockout/Tag Out Procedure</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>First Offense&mdash;Near Miss Report/Written Reprimand with Suspension Without Pay</p></li>
<li><p>Second Offense&mdash;Discharge</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">4.10 All willful or negligent violations of established plant Safe Work Practices that may cause injury to an associate, other associates, or damage to plant facilities will be disciplined according to the severity of the violations and may result in immediate termination.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>COMPANY RULES OF CONDUCT</b></i></h4>
<p class="continued">One of the necessities in any industry is the establishment of a basic understanding of what is expected of each teammate in regard to performance, quality, adherence to policies and conduct.</p>
<p class="continued">Following is a list of rules which were developed in order to provide for a safe and fair workplace for all teammates. For those reasons, Management insists the following rules be adhered to. Failure to do so will lead to some form of discipline with termination of employment being a possibility depending upon the seriousness of the offense.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">2. Negligence, carelessness or willful acts which result or could result in damage to company property or equipment, injury to an associate, or defying the authority of supervision, or other displays or conduct that harm or injure operations or jeopardize the successful operations of the company.</p>
<p>&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">10. Misrepresentation of facts in obtaining employment, falsifying reports or records, including personnel, absence, sickness, and production records, or falsely claiming injury.</p>
<p>&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">12. Refusal or failure to perform work assigned or refusal or failure to follow directions or instructions of management.</p>
<p>&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">14. Willful or negligent violation of safety rules, including failure to wear required personal protective equipment.</p>
<p>&hellip;</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>V.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>BACKGROUND</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. Firestone Business and Manufacturing Process 2</b></h4>
<p>The Company facility in Lake Charles, Louisiana produces a synthetic rubber product for making automobile tires, using a demanding manufacturing process that involves flammable rubber and chemicals, water, high temperatures, high pressure, and a series of complex machines that rely on manual operators and computer programs to operate and monitor temperature, pressure and other functional data. Even under ideal circumstances, this manufacturing process creates a work environment that is potentially hazardous to employees and Company property. Fires caused by equipment, materials or operator error are unfortunate but not uncommon in this demanding environment. In addition to causing possible employee injury or property damage, a fire on a critical piece of equipment can disrupt production and cause lost revenue until the Company investigates the cause of the fire and returns the machine to service. To minimize or eliminate the risk of employee injury and property damage, the Company has adopted extensive, detailed operating safety rules and procedures. These procedures are periodically reviewed and revised in response to accidents, fires or other hazards that actually have occurred at the Lake Charles plant.</p>
<p>In January 2014 Grievant worked as a &ldquo;B&rdquo; Operator in Process 2. At the time, Grievant had achieved nearly 16 years of commendable service for the Company. He had worked in most non-management jobs in the plant, including Operator positions in both Process 2 and Process 3.</p>
<p>In Process 2, a slurry of water and rubber crumbs travels through a series of steps that dewater and concentrate the rubber by applying heat, pressure, and chemicals. Ultimately, a rubber product used for making tires is produced. As part of this process, the rubber material falls down a chute into the Anderson hopper of an extruder, which is an elongated screw barrel assembly with a die plate at the end inside the first stage dryer. The extruder turns and feeds the rubber material down the barrel toward the die plate. As the screw turns and the rubber is driven toward the die plate, the volume decreases, and pressure and temperature increase. The die plate at the end of the extruder screw acts similar to a meat grinder where the rubber strings out as it goes through the die plate and then is cut with a spinning cutter to distribute it into smaller pieces into the first stage dryer. As the rubber is pushed through the die plate, the water molecules vaporize, thus drying the rubber. The rubber then passes from the first stage dryer to the second stage dryer, where it is further dried. The high pressure and high heat (acceptable operating temperatures approaching 380 degrees F) used to dry the rubber material creates a risk of fires despite various procedures and equipment safeguard taken by the Company to avoid fires.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. Company Investigation of July 2014 Process 2 Fire and Revisions to Procedure 9600</b></h4>
<p>On July 14, 2014, a fire occurred in the Process 2 unit involving B operator Theron McClendon and the Anderson equipment. The Company investigated and formed a cross functional team of individuals, including operations, engineering, supervision, quality control, and safety, to review the fire incident and, based upon their analysis, make recommendations to avoid future fires. Grievant, because of his knowledge base and experience as the senior B operator in Process 2, was selected to participate on the review team and contribute to the revision of Procedure 9600 &ndash; Dewatering and Drying in Process 2. Procedure 9600 is a series of operating instructions that were at the heart of the July 14, 2014 fire in Process 2 and are central to the Grievant's subsequent termination.</p>
<p>Grievant actively participated in the route cause analysis of the McClendon fire and obtained a good understanding of what caused the fire. In that case, the die plate was plugged and McClendon tried to force rubber through the die plate, which created a pressure build up, friction and gel. The end result was a fire. The Company suspended McClendon in consequence of his actions. The Company did not impose more severe discipline on him because it believed there was some understandable confusion in McClendon's mind about the proper procedures to be followed. In light of this confusion, the Company immediately retrained all operators in Process 2, including Grievant, on the proper steps for responding to a High-High temperature alarm. A high-high alarm is an audible alarm triggered by a temperature that is safely below the gelation and ignition temperature for the rubber being processed by the equipment. An individual Operator has the discretion to lower, but not increase, the high-high setting on his equipment.</p>
<p>In September 2014, the Company formally issued Revision 17 to Procedure 9600 and retrained employees, including Grievant, on the procedure. On September 5, 2014, Grievant signed a Training Record accepting and acknowledging the revisions to Procedure 9600. The Training Record consists of a cover sheet as well as a complete copy of the revised Procedure. The cover sheet of the Training Record is a half page summary, with 8 short bullet points. One of the bullet points explicitly states that &ldquo;If a High-High alarm/shutdown is reached, the foreman is to be notified, the die plate removed, and new dies installed.&rdquo; Similarly, the full text of Procedure 9600 addresses high-high temperature alarms and mandates the operator to &ldquo;shut down, notify foreman, and inspect die plate for signs of burnt rubber. The die plate should then be removed, the rubber run out, and new dies installed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The requirement that the foreman be notified of a high-high alarm was not a new requirement implemented by Revision 17 of the Procedure. Even in prior revisions to the Procedure, operators were required to notify the foreman of the high-high alarm; Revision 17 added the requirement for operators to also remove the die plate and install new dies (instead of simply inspecting the die plate as required under prior versions of the Procedure). The revised Procedure also explicitly addresses how operators should handle plugs of rubber material that occur in the Anderson hopper: stating &ldquo;If it will require body parts to break the plane of the equipment to remove the plug, the Lockout/Tag out procedure must be followed.&rdquo; Lockout/Tag out (&ldquo;LOTO&rdquo;) is a procedure by which the operator isolates and de-energizes all potential energy sources for the equipment. This LOTO requirement in Procedure 9600 predated Revision 17 and was not one of the specific countermeasures contained in the September 2015 revisions to Procedure 9600. However, the new requirement in Procedure 9600 for removing and replacing the die plate to clear a plug necessarily required the equipment to be LOTO'ed for die plate replacement.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>C. Safety Issues and Company Safety Campaign</b></h4>
<p>Although the safety record for the Lake Charles plant was excellent during 2013, the record at the plant deteriorated in 2014. In November of 2014, following the July 2014 Theron McClendon fire incident and two other safety incidents at the Company's Lake Charles and Orange, Texas facilities, Plant Managers Gene Lavengco and Bob Handlos began a safety campaign with employees to put safety first and to rigorously follow the Company's safety rules and procedures. As part of this initiative, the Company distributed safety literature to all employees and emphasized safety in individual and group meetings with plant manager Gene Lavengco. Hourly employees and managers attended these meetings which were themed, &ldquo;Safety First, Always.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Safety First, Always Policy adopted by the Company specifically referenced recent fire and other safety incidents in both Lake Charles and Orange. In order to try to prevent further incidents and accidents in the future, the Policy emphasized that safety is everyone's responsibility The Policy underscored three major points:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&bull; <b>Do not shortcut your job, FOLLOW THE STANDARD.</b></p>
<p class="continued">&bull; <b>Do not hesitate to stop the machine or operation when required if safety, quality or the environment are at stake.</b></p>
<p class="continued">&bull; <b><i>&ldquo;COMMUNICATION&rdquo;, &ldquo;TEAM WORK&rdquo;</i>, and <i>&ldquo;BOTTOM UP&rdquo;</i> are the key items to achieve our goal.</b></p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Safety First, Always Policy was communicated to all employees, including managers. Firestone distributed the Policy to team members through their departments and posted the Policy on all plant bulletin boards and electronic monitors.</p>
<p>In his meetings with employees and managers, Gene Lavengco presented information about the recent safety accidents at the Lake Charles and Orange, Texas plants. The accidents included the July 2014 Theron McClendon fire, an October 2014 LOTO incident which resulted in employee Mullins losing fingers, and another incident at the Orange plant. Lavengco specifically covered the Safety First Policy, as well as management's reemphasis of adherence to safety procedures and rules. Lavengco asked all personnel in attendance at the meetings to sign pledges with him to commit to the safety first mindset. Grievant signed a pledge with Mr. Lavengco on November 14, 2014.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>D. January 16, 2015 Fire in Process 2 Involving Grievant</b></h4>
<p>On January 15, 2015, Grievant reported for an overtime shift beginning at 4:00 p.m. on the 15<sup>th</sup> and ending at 4:00 a.m. on the 16<sup>th</sup>. When the shift started, Grievant lowered the high and high-high alarms on his equipment to temperatures lower than the 385-degree maximum specified by Company procedures. For purposes of the high-high alarm, the maximum temperature permitted by the Company procedures is 385 degrees on the Anderson equipment. Grievant lowered the temperatures to give himself an added safety margin. About 1:30 a.m., Grievant received a call from the board operator advising him to shutdown Process 2 because of boiler room problems that would stop the feed to Process 2. When feed is reduced or eliminated, the equipment must be adjusted to compensate for the reduction. As a result of reduced or shutoff feed, the equipment is susceptible to a rapid rise in temperature caused by the metal to metal contact of the screw continuing to turn without product to form a buffer.</p>
<p>As Grievant began to slow his machine, the operating temperature rose, the high temperature alarm sounded and the water injection system engaged. The water injection system initially caused the temperature to lower below the set high mark, and the system reset itself and continued to function. Once the water dissipated, the temperature quickly began rising, setting off the high-high alarm and engaging the interlock. The Grievant determined that a plug in the die plate had created the problem. Grievant and another employee inspected the die plate, which smelled of burned rubber. Grievant used his hand rather than the tools provided by the Company to remove plug. His hand broke the plane of the equipment. Grievant did not LOTO the equipment, nor did he call his supervisor or replace the die plate that incurred the plug.</p>
<p>Sometimes after a plug is removed, there is a residue of rubber or gel left behind in the housing of the hopper. This rubber can harden and cause further problems with the equipment if not removed. Grievant attempted to avoid this problem by a series of brief, intermittent starts to his machine to clear any rubber residue. While this procedure is permitted, it is not the protocol mandated by Procedure 9600 in dealing with a high-high alarm. In the period between the boiler room shut down and start up, the temperature of Grievant's machine fell below the high and high-high alarm temperatures.</p>
<p>After being down for over an hour, Grievant received a call that the boiler room was ready to restart the feed to Process 2. Grievant's dryer had been running, so he was ready to resume production. Grievant believed that his machine was free of any blockages and commenced production by closing the cone on the French Oil Mill portion of his equipment. As he did so, he saw dark smoke, the temperature on his machine rose rapidly and a fire erupted. The deluge switches activated and put out the fire, and Grievant contacted the guard house to report the fire</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>E. Company Investigation of Fire and Grievant's Involvement</b></h4>
<p>Before the end of Grievant's shift and during the early morning hours of January 16, 2015, Foreman Todd August obtained a signed, written statement from Grievant regarding the fire. In his statement, Grievant indicated that Process 2 was shut down for about 2 hours immediately prior to the fire. He asserted that the start up following the shut down was normal and that the temperature of the equipment was below the alarm levels for gelation of rubber. According to the Grievant, he saw rubber on the bed and assumed the dies were not plugged. As he restarted the French Oil Mill, Grievant's noticed smoke and then fire on the equipment. Grievant's January 16<sup>th</sup> written statement did not mention a high-high temperature alarm or any other abnormalities during Grievant's shift prior to the fire occurring. During the arbitration hearing, Grievant indicated he did not mention the earlier problems with the high-high alarm and equipment shut down because he thought the Company was only concerned with events immediately prior to the fire.</p>
<p>On the morning of January 16, Kevin Giles, who was the operations team leader responsible for the Process 2 unit, reported to work and began investigating the fire in Process 2 Later that same day, Giles and other management representatives met with Grievant to learn more about the possible causes of the fire. At this point in the investigation, Management had Grievant's written statement and some video footage showing the Anderson equipment a few minutes before the fire. The Company was beginning to pull and process more detailed data regarding the operation of Process 2 but did not have that information available yet. Since the start up of the operation looked normal, the Company sought any additional information or insight from the Grievant as to how the fire occurred.</p>
<p>The Company version of the January 16 afternoon meeting and Grievant's version differ on the key point of whether the Company limited its inquiry to the fire or asked about any irregularity during the Grievant's shift. According to team leader Giles, he asked Grievant if he noted or observed any abnormalities or notable occurrences during his shift. When asked by Grievant if he was asking about the start-up, Mr. Giles answered &ldquo;at any time during your shift.&rdquo; Grievant replied &ldquo;no, nothing other than the fire after start-up.&rdquo; Mr. Giles then reiterated the question regarding any abnormalities during his entire shift. Grievant again replied, &ldquo;no.&rdquo; Mr. Giles thanked Grievant for coming in early to discuss the incident and informed him that the Company would continue the investigation and wanted any information Grievant could provide.</p>
<p>According to the Grievant, he orally provided the Company with the same information during the January 16 afternoon meeting as he previously provided in the written statement made a few hours earlier. During the afternoon oral interview, Grievant indicated that he totally focused on the events surrounding the startup of the equipment immediately prior to the fire. The Grievant indicated that this startup occurred according to normal operating procedures, with all temperatures within the standard. Grievant did not tell the Company about the high-high alarm or the plug because the system had been down for two hours before coming back up, and he did not think that the high-high or plug had anything to do with the fire. Grievant maintained that he was not questioned about his entire shift, and his understanding was that the meeting was focused on the fire only.</p>
<p>Following the January 16<sup>th</sup> interview with Grievant, management continued to investigate the fire, pulling additional video and trend data from Grievant's shift. It was only then that the Company learned of operational irregularities during Grievant's shift that occurred within 2 hours of fire. From the combined review of the video and trend data, Giles and the management team identified operational irregularities not mentioned by Grievant in his January 16 written statement or his January 16<sup>th</sup> oral interview. Of note, the Company discovered that there was a pressure build up and blow back of plugged rubber material in the Anderson hopper equipment around 1:30 a.m. on January 16. According to Company, this pressure build up and blow back corresponded with the activation of a high-high temperature alarm. Once the high-high alarm activated, the Anderson screw stopped (went into computer interlock), but the temperature continued to increase another 100 degrees to 460 degrees, rather than cool down. The rising temperature indicated that the rubber materials had likely undergone a gelation process. Gelation results in the rubber product becoming hard. Company operating procedures are intended to avoid gelation because these gelated or hardened materials can plug the die plate and increase the risk of fire.</p>
<p>After the activation of the high-high temperature alarm and lockout of the equipment, the Anderson hopper was plugged with rubber material. The Grievant removed the guard around the hopper so that the plugged material could be cleared prior to restarting the unit. On the video, Grievant was observed violating Procedure 9600 by sticking his arms and hands beyond the plane of the hopper to remove the plugged material without first LOTO&rsquo; ing the equipment. Subsequently on the video, Grievant was observed applying water to the mouth of the hopper via a water hose, which is not provided for anywhere in Procedure 9600 and is not normal practice.</p>
<p>The Company's detailed investigation also showed that less than 2 hours later when Grievant restarted the Process 2 equipment, a fire occurred within 2<fraction numer="1" denom="2"/> minutes of the restart. The fire occurred in the same die area where Grievant had attempted to clear a plug. The fire lasted for about a minute and a half, until it was extinguished by the deluge system. Mr. Giles found no evidence that Grievant notified foreman Todd August of the initial high-high temperature alarm interlock that activated over two hours prior to the fire. There was nothing in Grievant's January 16<sup>th</sup> written statement or his initial interview regarding the high-high alarm or notifying the foreman of the alarm, nor was there any mention in the operator log sheet filled out by Grievant for his shift. The Company also found there was no evidence that maintenance was called out to remove the die plate and install new dies following the activation of the initial high-high temperature alarm and prior to the fire. These procedures are important because they ensure that there is no gelated material behind the die plate or restricted/plugged dies in the die plate, which increases the risk of fire.</p>
<p>In light of the additional information discovered during the Company investigation, Giles and other management representatives again met with Grievant on January 21, 2015. Giles began the meeting by asking Grievant if anything else happened that could have contributed to the fire; Grievant responded &ldquo;no.&rdquo; When Giles questioned whether anything happened while the unit was being brought down prior to the fire, Grievant acknowledged that a plug occurred in the Anderson hopper and he dug out the plug. Giles then reviewed with Grievant, the violations of Procedure 9600 that occurred, focusing on Grievant's decision to not notify the foreman that the unit had shut down because of a high-high temperature interlock, and the fact that the die plate was not removed. Once presented with this data, Grievant admitted these procedural violations and indicated it was his decision not to inform the foreman of the high-high alarm, stating he thought the machine was OK when rubber came out. Grievant also acknowledged smelling scorched or burnt rubber while he was digging out the Anderson hopper plug prior to the restarting of the unit and the fire. When the Company showed Grievant his his Training Record on Procedure 9600 and the countermeasures from the July 2014 fire, Grievant acknowledged that he was a member of the review team that decided the foreman should be informed and the die plate pulled when the unit hits a high-high temperature interlock.</p>
<p>Following the January 21, 2015 interview, the Company withheld the Grievant from service pending the Company's continuing investigation into the fire. On January 30, 2015, Grievant was called into the Human Resources office to meet with Human Resources Manager Sherry Griffin and team leader Giles. Grievant brought a union representative, William &ldquo;Bill&rdquo; Gross, to this meeting. Griffin informed Grievant that she had reviewed the notes of the investigation and discussed the Company rules and procedures he violated. She also gave him the opportunity to provide any explanation. Grievant admitted that he made a bad judgment call. He did not dispute his failure to follow Procedure 9600's requirements to notify his foreman and change the dies when a high-high alarm occurs.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>E. Decision to Terminate Grievant</b></h4>
<p>The Company's internal deliberations that followed the January 21 meeting culminated in the Company's decision to terminate Grievant's employment. As articulated by Giles, who made the recommendation (with which HR Griffin and Plant Manager Lavengco concurred), Grievant violated the following Rules of Conduct:</p>
<ul type="none">
<li><p>&squf; Rule &num;1 &ndash; Negligence, carelessness or willful acts which result or could result in damage to company property or equipment, injury to an associate or defying the authority of supervision, or other displays or conduct that harm or injure operations or jeopardize the successful operations of the company.</p></li>
<li><p>&squf; Rule &num;12 &ndash; Refusal or failure to perform work assigned or refusal or failure to follow directions or instructions of management.</p></li>
<li><p>&squf; Rule &num;14 &ndash; Willful or negligent violation of safety rules &hellip;</p></li>
<li><p>&squf; Rule &num;10 &ndash; Misrepresentation of facts in &hellip; falsifying reports or records, including personnel &hellip; and production records &hellip;.</p></li></ul>
<p>In Giles view, Grievant's violations of Rules 1, 12, and 14 stemmed from his willful and conscious decision not to comply with the requirements of Procedure 9600, which itself is considered a Safe Work Practice and which includes several safety rules that are intended to reduce the risk of unsafe work conditions and fires and prevent injury to personnel and equipment. Giles determined that Grievant violated Rule 10 because Grievant withheld information (and, thus, misrepresented facts) in his January 16, 2015 written statement and initial interview. The Grievant withheld critical information from the Company when he failed to advise the Company of the high-high temperature alarm activating, his decision not to notify the foreman and to not remove the die plate after receiving the high-high alarm, his smelling of burnt rubber and his digging of the plug in the Anderson hopper. All of these events occurred within two hours of the subsequent fire. While Giles also considered Grievant's length of service and his good service record, these factors did not offset, in his view, the intentional and negligent violation of multiple safety rules.</p>
<p>On February 10, 2015, Ms. Griffin met with Grievant to inform him of his termination. Safety Manager Clay Kennedy also attended the meeting and took notes. At the meeting, Griffin discussed the Company's lengthy investigation, as well as Grievant's multiple violations of the Rules of Conduct and the Company's safety procedures and operating standards. She specifically referenced Grievant's failure <b>to</b> follow the Procedure 9600 work instructions and standards that he helped to develop in response to the July 2015 fire. Griffin discussed Grievant's failure to LOTO the equipment before Grievant stuck his hands down near the screw to remove the rubber plug. She also noted that Grievant was not truthful and forthcoming during the Company's investigation process. In view of the foregoing, Griffin informed Grievant that plant manager Gene Lavengco had decided to terminate Grievant's employment with the Company.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>VI.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>DISCUSSION AND OPINION</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. Reasonableness of Procedure 9600 and Relevant Discipline Rules</b></h4>
<p>In the context of this case, no extended discussion is needed to conclude that Procedure 9600 and the relevant Company's discipline rules are reasonable and an appropriate exercise of the Company's discretion to promote a safe workplace.</p>
<p>Procedure 9600 has two main directives that are material here. The first is the mandate for an operator to notify a foreman of a high-high interlock, then remove and replace the die plate when the operator incurs a high-high temperature on the Anderson equipment. The Company revised this aspect of Procedure 9600 in the fall of 2014 following a fire in July 2014 on the Anderson. The Company created a root cause analysis team that studied the July 2014 fire and concluded the best way to avoid a fire after the equipment incurs a high-high temperature is for the employee to notify his supervisor of the high-high, clear any burned or clogged rubber from the equipment, and remove the old die plate and replace it with a new one. Removing the die plate necessarily requires the equipment to be LOTO'ed. The second directive in Procedure 9600 requires an employee to totally shut down (or LOTO) a piece of equipment before any body part breaks the plane of the equipment. This directive is not a new mandate but one that has been in effect.</p>
<p>The record establishes that both mandates in Procedure 9600 are reasonable and intended to contribute to a safe and efficient work environment. The first directive was recommended by a multi discipline study group and appears to be a logical step to reduce the risk of fires, employee injuries and property damage. The second directive was not the result of any empirical analysis, but common sense validates the reasonableness of a rule that forbids an employee from inserting any body parts into a potentially dangerous machine without first completely locking down the machine.</p>
<p>The Company discipline rules at issue here, Rules of Conduct 1, 10, 12 and 14 and Plant Discipline Policy 1.0-4.0, also pass the test of reasonable in the context of this case. Taken as a whole, these Rules call for progressive discipline when the offending employee conduct can be corrected by counselling, warning or disciplinary suspensions. At the same time, the rules reserve the Company's right to terminate an employee, even for the first offense, for some types of serious conduct. Offenses that allow the Company to bypass progressive discipline and move to termination include employee misrepresentations, dishonesty, and intentional, willful or negligent conduct. Rule 14 singles out willful or negligent conduct that violates safety rules as particularly serious misconduct. A progressive disciple system with the types of exceptions contained in the Firestone policy are quite common place in the industrial context, and the Company policy passes the test of reasonableness.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. Application of Procedure 9600 and Discipline Rules to Grievant's Actions</b></h4>
<p>The Company, of course, has the burden of proving Grievant's misconduct and showing that the seriousness of the misconduct provided just cause for termination. The record in this case shows that the Company met these burdens by establishing that Grievant willfully and negligently ignored the safety procedures mandated in Procedure 9600. The Grievant did not notify his foreman of the interlock and high-high operating alarm. He did not remove and replace the die plate, and he did not LOTO the Anderson before using his hand to clear the plug in his machine. The record also shows Grievant impeded the Company's initial investigation by failing to disclose, early on in the investigation, the high-high temperature readings, the interlock of his equipment, and the plugged die plates that occurred close in time to the fire on January 16, 2015.</p>
<p>There can be no doubt that Grievant was aware of and understood Procedure 9600. After the July 2014 fire, and only a few months before the incident giving rise to his termination, the Company retrained all operators, including the Grievant, on the importance of involving a foreman in response to a high-high alarm on the Anderson equipment. Moreover, during the same time frame, the Grievant was a member of a route cause analysis team created to determine the cause(s) of the July fire. Ultimately, the study team recommended changes in Procedure 9600 that reiterated the requirement for an operator to notify a foreman of a high-high temperature/interlock <i>and</i> added the requirement that an operator must remove and replace the die plate after encountering a high-high alarm. On September 5, Grievant received training and signed for the revisions to Procedure 9600. The training record signed by Grievant included 8 short bullet points, covering less than half a page. The eighth bullet point is short and to the point: <b>&ldquo;If a High-High alarm/shutdown is reached, the foreman is to be notified, the die plate removed and new die installed.&rdquo;</b> (emphasis supplied).</p>
<p>In the face of his unquestionable awareness of the procedures for handling a high-high alarm, Grievant admitted that it was his decision not to notify his foreman of the alarm, that it was his decision not to remove the die plate as required under Procedure 9600, and that his decisions were &ldquo;&hellip; a bad judgment call.&rdquo; After the high-high alarm on January 16, Grievant's line was down for nearly two hours, which gave him more than enough time to have followed the correct procedures for handling the high-high alarm without disrupting production. But he failed to do so. These facts compel the conclusion that Grievant willfully and negligently ignored the very Procedures which he helped develop for avoiding fires when the Anderson incurs a high-high alarm. This conduct clearly is the type of &ldquo;&hellip;negligence, carelessness or willful acts which result or could result in damage to company property or equipment, injury to an associate&hellip;&rdquo; and warranted termination.</p>
<p>With respect to the provision of 9600 prohibiting an employee from breaking the plane of equipment with a body part, that prohibition already had been in effect for several years, and it seems undeniable that Grievant knew of the potential for serious injury by inserting his hand into a machine designed to heat and compress rubber. Finally, given the Grievant's experience in operating various pieces of sophisticated Company equipment, it is not credible for the Grievant to have failed to make the possible connection between the high-high shutdown of his equipment, the smell of burning rubber and the fire that occurred within 2 minutes of re-starting his machine on January 16, 2015. This latter consideration further adds to the seriousness of Grievant's willful disregard of Procedure 9600.</p>
<p>The Union argues that the mitigating considerations require the reduction of the termination to a lesser penalty. These considerations include Grievant's long and good service record; the harshness of the Grievant's discipline compared to the Company's treatment of other employees for similar misconduct; and the lax enforcement or condonation by Company foremen of safety rule violations on the plant floor. These arguments, taken separately or together, do not mitigate the finding of just cause.</p>
<p>Grievant has a lengthy record as a good employee for the Company, but this record can not excuse the seriousness of Grievant's willful and negligent conduct. While the Company apparently has never terminated an employee for the sole reason of a single fire or a single injury, it has terminated employees for single acts of serious misconduct potentially compromising the safety of the plant or fellow employees. Grievant's actions fall into the latter category of offenses rather than the former. Grievant's actions are distinguishable from employees who were disciplined less severely by virtue of his careless, negligent and willful actions.</p>
<p>Regarding the condonation argument, there is some evidence that foremen may have been aware of employees using tools to clear a plug without LOTO'ing the Anderson, but there is no evidence that any management official condoned or approved an employee breaking the plane of the equipment with his hand to clear a plug without LOTO'ing the equipment. The record shows the Company made extensive efforts to reeducate its employees, including all managers, on the proper procedure for handling high-high interlocks on the Anderson after the July 14 fire. Firestone provided individual safety training and education to the Grievant, other employees and managers during September 2014. The Company mounted an aggressive safety campaign during the late fall of 2014 to raise the awareness and underscore the importance of following safety rules and working safely. Given these considerations, the assertion that managers were aware of and permitted operators to ignore Procedure 9600 after the July 2014 fire is unpersuasive. Whatever the practice may have been on the shop floor <i>before</i> the July 2014 fire, there is no <i>persuasive, credible</i> evidence that supervisors were aware of and condoned employees unilaterally ignoring Procedure 9600 after the July 2014 fire.</p>
<p>Had the Grievant informed his foreman of the high-high interlock on January 16, 2015, and the foreman directed the Grievant not to remove and replace the die plate, those facts would have presented an entirely different case. But the facts of this case show that Grievant intentionally chose not to involve his foreman and not to follow the other safety precautions built into 9600. By so acting, he ignored the very procedures he helped develop for avoiding a fire after a high-high interlock occurs on the Anderson. And a fire resulted.</p>
<p>In view of the foregoing, the record does not persuade the Arbitrator that the Grievant's termination should be overturned or the penalty reduced to a suspension short of termination.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>VII.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>The Company terminated the Grievant for just cause. The grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>