<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between the CITY OF CLEVELAND, OHIO And CLEVELAND POLICE PATROLMEN'S ASSOCIATION</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No. 53 390 00324 13</p>
<p>Award: September 30, 2014.</p>
<p>Paul F. Gerhart, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>OPINION AND AWARD</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>Procedural Background</b></h4>
<p>The Cleveland Police Patrolmen's Association (the Union), is the collective bargaining agent for Patrol Officers employed by the City of Cleveland, Division of Police (the Employer or City). During the term of their 2010-2013 labor agreement (the Agreement, JX 1), the parties were unable to resolve a grievance involving the City's termination of Police Officer Shani Hannah. Under the provisions of the Agreement, Article XXII, Grievance Procedure, the undersigned was selected through the auspices of the American Arbitration Association (AAA) and appointed subject to the rules of said Association to issue a final and binding decision in the matter.</p>
<p>Upon the mutual agreement of the parties, a hearing was held on May 8, 2014, in a Conference Room at Burke Lakefront Airport, Cleveland, Ohio. At the time of the hearing, the parties stipulated that the grievance was properly before the arbitrator. During the course of the hearing, each party was accorded the opportunity to examine witnesses and present other evidence. A stenographic record of the proceeding was made by Karen Toth, Fincun-Mancini Court Reporters, Cleveland. Witnesses were sworn but not separated. At the conclusion of the presentation of evidence, the parties waived oral argument and agreed to file post-hearing briefs. Such briefs were delivered to the arbitrator via e-mail on July 16, 2014 and were exchanged by the arbitrator on the same day at which point the record in the matter was closed.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Grievance</b></h4>
<p>On May 22, 2013, Grievant was discharged by the City. Her letter of discharge signed by Martin L. Flask, Director of Public safety, read in part (JX 2, p12):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">On Wednesday, July 11, 2012, you pled guilty to Ohio Revised code Assault, 2903.13, a misdemeanor of the first degree&hellip;. &lsqb;Y&rsqb;ou were sentenced to the Cuyahoga County Jail for a term of six (6) months. The execution of the sentence was suspended. You were sentenced to serve twelve (12) months of probation, perform court community work service for twenty-five (25) hours, submit to random drug testing and successfully complete an anger management program.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The letter indicated that P. O. Hannah entered a plea of &ldquo;No Contest&rdquo; to the allegations set forth in the charging letter. Further it included the following (JX 2, p13):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">The incident that led to the criminal and, administrative charges began Sunday, March 11, 2012 when you engaged in a dispute during which you stabbed your boyfriend with a knife, you fled from the scene and an attempt to take your own life was thwarted by responding Cleveland police officers. You were ultimately arrested and indicted for Felonious Assault, a felony of the second degree.</p>
<p class="continued">On Wednesday, July 11, 2012 you pled guilty to Assault in violation of Ohio Revised Code 2903.13, a misdemeanor of the first degree and were subsequently sentenced by the court.</p>
<p class="continued">Your conduct, during and after the incident for which you were found guilty ln a count of law, raises serious concerns about your fitness to continue employment with the Cleveland Division of Police. Although you were found guilty of a lesser offense than that for which you were indicted, the evidence clearly revealed that you used a weapon in an attempt to inflict serious bodily harm on another. The use of a weapon to inflict harm on another is inexcusable and unacceptable conduct by an officer of the Cleveland Division of Police.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip; &lsqb;Y&rsqb;ou are hereby terminated from employment with the Cleveland Division of Police effective May 22, 2013.</p></blockquote>
<p>Shortly thereafter, in an undated grievance, Steven W. Kinas, Vice President of the CPPA filed the following grievance on behalf of P. O. Shani Hannah (JX 2, p14):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">FACTS:</p>
<p class="continued">On May 22, 2013 the above officer was terminated from employment with the City of Cleveland without just cause. The finding of guilt and the punishment imposed &lsqb;are&rsqb; contrary to the just cause provisions of the CBA. The termination is in violation of Articles IV, XXII, XXIX, the Witnesseth Clause, and the past practice between the parties. The termination is also disproportional to past disciplinary cases where officers have engaged in similar conduct and not been terminated.</p>
<p class="continued">REMEDY:</p>
<p class="continued">Officer Shani Hannah should be reinstated with full back pay and restoration of all lost benefits together with any other relief to which she may be entitled.</p></blockquote>
<p>The parties were not able to resolve the matter through earlier steps of the grievance procedure so it is now before this arbitrator for final and binding determination.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Issue</b></h4>
<p>The parties did not stipulate the issue at the hearing, but their positions on the issue are nearly the same. In its brief, the City asserted that the issue is whether P. O. Hannah's termination was for just cause as argued by the City or if the City violated the CBA when it terminated Hannah as argued by the CPPA. The Union stated the issue simply as whether the City of Cleveland had just cause to terminate Cleveland Police Officer Shani Hannah for alleged rule violations that stemmed from a March 11, 2012 off-duty incident.</p>
<p>Accordingly, the arbitrator has determined that the issue is whether the City had just cause to terminate Grievant Shani Hannah, and if not, what is the appropriate remedy?</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Relevant Contractual Provisions</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>ARTICLE IV</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">(4) Except as expressly limited by the terms of this Contract, any and all rights concerned with the management of the Division of Police are the exclusive and sole responsibility of the employer. It is further recognized that the City has the right to:</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">(e) Suspend, discipline, demote or discharge for just cause &hellip;.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>Position of the Employer</b></h4>
<p>The following is the arbitrator's summary of the Employer's post-hearing brief.</p>
<p>On August 1, 2012, the City served Police Officer Shani Hannah (&ldquo;Hannah&rdquo;) with a Notice of Disciplinary Hearing (&ldquo;charge letter&rdquo;) as a result of an incident that occurred on March 11, 2012. The disciplinary hearing was originally set in August and October, 2012, but both hearings were continued by agreement of the CPPA and the City so that Hannah could undergo a &ldquo;Fitness for Duty&rdquo; examina-tion. The disciplinary hearing was held on April 18, 2013 by then-Director of Public Safety, Martin Flask. Hannah pled no contest to the charges presented. After hearing all of the evidence, Director Flask terminated Hannah's employment on May 22, 2013. The City respectfully submits that for the reasons discussed, infra, Hannah's termination was for just cause and should be upheld.</p>
<p><i><b>Facts.</b></i> Hannah was employed by the City as a patrol officer for 11 years prior to her termination. As stated above, she represented by the CPPA.</p>
<p><i>Darnell Richardson</i>. It is important to take note of the relationship that Hannah was in when the incident that led to her termination occurred. She was dating a man named Darnell Richardson and had been dating him since the day after Thanksgiving, 2010. He lived with her and her two minor children for at least the last year of the relationship. Richardson has an extensive criminal history including convictions for drug possession, sexual battery, attempted kidnapping with a sexual motivation specification, gross sexual imposition, abduction with a sexual motivation specification, trafficking in drugs, forgery, passing bad checks, theft, another case of forgery, uttering, attempted robbery, trafficking in cocaine, and possession of drugs. (See UX 5 from the disciplinary hearing before Director Flask &ndash; Richardson's criminal record.) He spent at least five years in prison and was required to register as a sexual predator. But Hannah claimed that she did not know about his criminal background and did not know he was deemed a sexual predator. Nor did she know that he was on parole when they met. Again, it is important to note that Hannah is a police officer. She did not do any type of check on the Cuyahoga County website to determine his criminal history, because his parents were &ldquo;good people,&rdquo; even though at one time he had to wear an ankle bracelet and lived at a homeless shelter. But she became aware of his background because he would use it against her, &ldquo;that's when he started threatening my job. Well, I'll just call, you know, the jail and tell them that you knew I was a felon, that you'll lose your job anyway.&rdquo; (Tr 191) She had to know, even if she did not know the extent of his criminal record, that being with a felon was inherently wrong, as a police officer. And yet she stayed with this man that she alleges abused her both emotionally and physically. And she allowed him to move in with her and two minor children for a period of at least a year.</p>
<p><i>Hannah's grandmother's death and the January 2012 incident</i>. Hannah's grandmother, to whom she was very close and who basically raised her, died on November 11, 2011. As Hannah testified, she &ldquo;lost everything. I don't know where I would be if it wasn't for her.&rdquo; (Tr 182) Her grandmother's death caused her later breakdown on January 21, 2012. Although Hannah was not charged administratively for the January 2012 incident, it must be considered in order to understand how and why the incident on March 11, 2012 occurred.</p>
<p>During the day and on the evening of January 21, 2012, Hannah was at the home of Richardson's parents. They were having a cook-out. She testified (Tr 186-187):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">We were drinking at his mom's house. The conversation about Darnell and this other young lady that had been, you know playing on my phone or whatever, that conversation had come up. And I mentioned to his mom, this is not something I want to go through and deal with right now after just losing my mother, because that's what I called her. And, you know, I guess the common practice is instead of talking about it we're going to drink and just attempt to have fun. I cannot recall how many drinks I had before we decided to just leave and go home. I was very upset in the car. My kids tried to calm me down&hellip;. So we were talking. And, of course, me being drunk, I'm talking loudly&hellip;.</p></blockquote>
<p>The &ldquo;young lady playing on my phone&rdquo; was actually someone with whom Richardson was also sleeping. She admitted that she drove from the party in a highly-intoxicated state with her two children in the vehicle. She was also highly agitated during the entire drive home and yelled at her children about her boyfriend and his cheating. When she got home, her ranting continued and the security guard for her apartment was called upstairs because she was so loud. The security guard eventually called CPD to respond because Hannah was screaming and threatening to kill herself.</p>
<p>When CPD arrived on scene, Hannah threatened to &ldquo;eat her gun&rdquo; because she just &ldquo;did not care anymore.&rdquo; (See IAU Investigative Report, CX B). This occurred in front of her children. CPD transported her to St. Vincent Charity Hospital for a psychiatric evaluation and to detoxify. She stayed at St. Vincent for three days where she did not have any alcohol. The staff at St. Vincent recommended grief and also alcohol treatment. She began grief counseling but did nothing regarding the recommendation for alcohol treatment and continued her extensive and out-of-control alcohol usage. In fact, she continued to use alcohol to excess daily until the incident that led to her termination.</p>
<p><i>March 11, 2012</i>. The incident for which Hannah was disciplined occurred on March 11, 2012. All of the above poor judgments resulted in the poor decision she made that evening. On March 11, 2012 about 2210 hours at Hannah's apart-ment, she assaulted and then feloniously assaulted Richardson, while he was lying on her bed. Richardson reported, in a 911 call to CPD, that Hannah stabbed him several times with a knife. Hannah was subsequently arrested several blocks from her apartment and charged with felonious assault.</p>
<p>The Internal Affairs Unit (&ldquo;IAU&rdquo;) investigation revealed that Hannah and Richardson had an argument over an insignificant matter. He ignored her and she became enraged. She produced two knives from a dresser. She assaulted him by grabbing him by the throat causing injury to his neck, assaulted him by hitting him in the face while holding a knife and the knife caused injury to his face, feloniously assaulted him by poking his left thigh above the knee with a knife causing him injury, and feloniously assaulted him twice with a knife in the right hand and then the right knee. He required five stitches to close one of the wounds.</p>
<p>Hannah then realized that her assaults caused serious injury to Richardson and told him, &ldquo;You're bleeding.&rdquo; She left the room and he shut the door behind her and called 911. He told the 911 call-taker that he had been stabbed by Hannah, she had taken the knives with her when she walked out of the room, and he was fearful that she would return and stab him again. Further, Hannah can be heard screaming in the background on the 911 tapes (CX C).</p>
<p>After the stabbing/felonious assault, when Hannah realized that Richardson was on the phone with 911, she placed the knives in the dishwasher and then left the apartment. After a short search by CPD officers, she was found in her vehicle, parked at the end of a dead-end street. When she was located by police, she had a cord wrapped around her neck and it was attached to the &ldquo;ceiling&rdquo; of the vehicle, in an apparent suicide attempt. Officers were forced to smash the vehicle window to get the cord from around her neck and make sure she did not harm herself. The IAU investigation revealed that while Hannah was driving around drunk, she was also texting Richardson and her children. She texted Richardson that she was going to kill herself, she really meant it this time, it was all his fault, and her life was ruined. She also sent texts to her minor daughter that she would have to go live with her father because Hannah would not be around anymore. She later told officers that the texts and the cord around her neck were simply to get attention and to keep her from going to jail.</p>
<p><i>Criminal charges and conviction</i>. But she did go to jail rather than St. Vincent Charity Psychiatric Ward. Hannah was immediately arrested by IAU officers and was charged with felonious assault, a felony of the second degree, as set forth in R.C. &sect;2903.11. She was immediately relieved from duty as a result of this arrest. On March 12, 2012, Hannah was charged by the Cleveland Municipal Prosecutor's office with felonious assault and on March 27, 2012, the Cuyahoga County grand jury indicted Hannah for felonious assault and first-degree misdemeanor assault, as set forth in R.C. &sect;2903.13.</p>
<p>Eventually, the Cuyahoga County prosecutor's office reduced the charge from felonious assault to first-degree misdemeanor assault. On July 11, 2012, Hannah pled guilty to first-degree misdemeanor assault, in violation of R.C. &sect;2903.13. She was sentenced to Cuyahoga County Jail for a term of 6 months. The execution of the sentence was suspended. She was required to serve 12 months of probation, perform 25 hours of community service, submit to random drug testing, and successfully complete an anger-management program.</p>
<p><i>Disciplinary charges and arbitration</i>. In her charge letter, dated August 1, 2012 she was charged with five specifications:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Specification 1, she was arrested and charged by IAU for felonious assault on March 11, 2012.</p>
<p class="continued">Specification 2, she was relieved from duty by IAU after being arrested and charged on March 11, 2012.</p>
<p class="continued">Specification 3, she was charged with felonious assault by the prosecuting attorney on March 12, 2012.</p>
<p class="continued">Specification 4, she was indicted by the Cuyahoga County grand jury for felonious assault and misdemeanor assault on March 27, 2012.</p>
<p class="continued">Specification 5, she pled guilty to misdemeanor assault on July 11, 2012 and further sets forth her sentence.</p></blockquote>
<p>During the arbitration hearing, Hannah admitted the following: she and Richardson were drinking excessively on the day of the incident; she was drunk when the incident occurred; she really did not remember what happened; she was drunk when she left the apartment and drove around the neighborhood drunk; she was located by a CPD zone car and she had her phone cord wrapped around her neck; she texted Richardson and her children from her vehicle and threatened to kill herself; and her drinking had gotten completely out of control.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>Discussion and analysis.</b></i></h4>
<p><i>Standard of Proof</i>. The issue is whether the City has established, by a preponderance of the evidence, that there was just cause to terminate Hannah in light of the fact that she stabbed her boyfriend multiple times, fled the scene while admittedly driving drunk, pled guilty to a first-degree misdemeanor assault charge, and demonstrated a pattern of poor judgment and conduct in violation of City ordinances, rules, and regulations. In general, arbitrators have held that the level of proof required for issues such as discharge is by a &ldquo;preponderance of the evidence.&rdquo; &lsqb;Citation omitted here.&rsqb; The term, &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; has almost universally been applied by arbitrators in employment settings as the standard by which all discipline is judged, even in those situations where it is not specified in the collective bargaining agreement.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Just cause&rdquo; has been defined as follows (Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i>, citing Arbitrator Joseph D. McGoldrick, <i>Worthington Corp.</i>, 24 LA 1, 6-7 (1955):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&lsqb;I&rsqb;t is common to include the right to suspend and discharge for &lsquo;just cause&rsquo;. These exclude discharge for mere whim or caprice. They are, obviously, intended to include those things for which employees have traditionally been fired. They include the traditional causes of discharge in the particular trade of industry, the practices that develop in the day-to-day relations of management and labor and most recently, they include the decisions of courts and arbitrators&hellip;. They constitute the duties owed by employees to management and, in their correlative aspect, is part of the rights of management. They include such duties as honesty, punctuality, sobriety, or, conversely, the right to discharge for theft, repeated absence or lateness, destruction of company property, brawling and the like. Where they are not expressed in posted rules, they may very well be implied, provided they are applied in a uniform, non-discriminatory manner.</p></blockquote>
<p>The City respectfully submits that it has proven by a preponderance of the evidence that Hannah's termination was appropriate given her complete lack of judgment and the severity of her conduct. There are no facts at issue in this case and there is no dispute over whose evidence is valid.</p>
<p><i>The City had just cause to terminate P.O. Hannah and, therefore, did not violate the terms of the Agreement</i>. Hannah stabbed her boyfriend, was indicted for felonious assault, was convicted of misdemeanor assault and, therefore, violated numerous rules, regulations, and laws. She feloniously assaulted her boyfriend by stabbing him with two knives. This led her to plead guilty to a first-degree misdemeanor assault charge. Hannah's poor judgment over several months and her egregious conduct resulted in a conviction under R.C. &sect;2903.13(A) for committing first-degree misdemeanor assault. The facts show that Hannah stabbed Richardson numerous times, hid the knives, fled the scene, and was found with a cord around her neck on March 11, 2012. Further, Hannah was drinking to excess and admitted that she drove away from the scene of the stabbing in a highly-intoxicated state.</p>
<p>In addition to violating State law, through her actions, Hannah violated multiple Cleveland Codified Ordinances, General Police Orders, rules of the Manual of Rules of the Department of Public Safety, and the rules of the Civil Service Commission of the City of Cleveland. These violations substantiate just cause for her termination. The <i>Manual of Rules and Regulations for the Conduct of the Discipline of Officers and Employees</i> details the conduct and duty required of police officers. Rule 2.01 states:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Personnel shall not violate any law of the United States, the State of Ohio, Charter provision or ordinance of the City of Cleveland, or neglect to perform any duty required by law, nor shall they engage in any conduct that would constitute a crime under the laws of the United States, the State of Ohio, or the Charter provisions or ordinances of the City of Cleveland.</p></blockquote>
<p>According to the Manual's &ldquo;Statement of Policy&rdquo;,</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&hellip; any violation of these rules and regulations shall be a basis for disciplinary action. Disciplinary action includes, but is not limited to, verbal and written reprimands and the preferring of divisional charges can result in suspension, loss of pay, demotion or <i>termination</i>.&rdquo; (Emphasis added).</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Furthermore, it states, &ldquo;These rules, regulations, and standards contained in this manual shall apply whether the officer or employee is on or off duty.&rdquo; It is clear that there can be extreme penalties, including termination, for this type of misconduct.</p>
<p>Additionally, Rule 2.14 states:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">The following are additional grounds for disciplining personnel, including removal, in addition to the grounds stated in Civil Service Commission Rule 9.10:</p>
<p class="continued">a. Incompetence</p>
<p class="continued">b. Gross Neglect of Duty</p>
<p class="continued">c. Gross immorality</p>
<p class="continued">e. Failure to obey orders given by proper authority</p>
<p class="continued">f. Any other reasonable and just cause.</p></blockquote>
<p>Hannah violated multiple rules, regulations, and standards relating to the conduct and duty of police officers. Termination or removal is a possible result for each of these violations of conduct and duty. Disciplinary action, including termination, for violations is at the discretion of the Safety Director.</p>
<p>The <i>Manual</i>, Rules 4 and 5, also detail the requirements for officers related to duty and behavior, as set forth below. Rule 4.01 states:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Officers shall protect life and property, prevent crimes, detect, arrest, and prosecute offenders, preserve the public peace and enforce laws and ordinances within the scope of their job classifications and in the accordance to law.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Rule 4.12 states:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Personnel shall be considered to be on duty at all times for purposes of discipline.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Rule 5.01 states:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Personnel shall not engage in any conduct, speech, or acts while on duty, or off duty, which would reasonably tend to diminish the esteem of the Division of Police or its personnel in the eyes of the public.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Rule 5.08 states:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Personnel shall conduct themselves in such a manner as to command the respect of the public.</p></blockquote>
<p>Hannah failed to maintain acceptable behavior or uphold the duty required of a CPD officer. The incident on March 11, 2012, occurred less than two months after the January 21, 2012, incident wherein Hannah was taken by CPD to St. Vincent Charity Hospital for a psychiatric evaluation and to detoxify after threatening to commit suicide in front of CPD officers and her children, after a day and evening of heavy drinking. In both situations Hannah drank to excess and proceeded to drive her car, endangering her and the general public. In the first instance she also endangered her children who were passengers in the car.</p>
<p>Her egregious conduct, lack of judgment, and breach of duty also violated General Police Order 1.1.03, which provides:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Division of Police personnel shall: I. Not engage in any conduct, speech, or acts while on or off duty, which would reasonably tend to diminish the esteem of the Division of Police or its personnel in the eyes of the public, and III. Conduct themselves in such a manner as to command the respect of the public.</p></blockquote>
<p>Hannah's poor judgment and subsequent egregious conduct violated the behavior and duty requirements associated with her position. When Hannah was asked point blank why she pulled the knife on her boyfriend, her response was simply, &ldquo;I don't know. Dumb move. I don't know.&rdquo; (Tr 217) Her actions do not fall in line with the type of conduct and duty that is required of a police officer. Termination is definitely warranted in this case.</p>
<p>Further, Civil Service Commission Rule 9.10 describes the following as causes for discharge:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">1. Neglect of duty</p>
<p class="continued">2. Conduct unbecoming of an employee in the public service.</p>
<p class="continued">10. Willful violation of any of the rules or regulations of the Commission.</p>
<p class="continued">18. For other failure of good behavior, which is detrimental to the service, or for any other act of misfeasance, malfeasance, or nonfeasance in office.</p></blockquote>
<p>Hannah willfully and egregiously committed multiple violent crimes as well as violated rules, regulations, and standards of conduct associated with her position. There are two documented incidents, the more recent of which resulted in a guilty plea to first-degree misdemeanor assault. Hannah admittedly drank to intoxication every day for a period of about 5 months, during which countless other unreported violations may have occurred. The Safety Director has the discretion related to discipline and termination and he considered these facts when deciding to terminate Hannah. He decided the streets of the City would be safer without Hannah patrolling them as an officer. For these reasons stated above, the City had just cause to terminate Hannah.</p>
<p><i>Hannah's complete lack of judgment and egregious conduct resulted in just cause for termination</i>. The City also had just cause to terminate Hannah's employ-ment due to her complete lack of judgment while off duty which might eventually affect her ability to make good judgments on duty. Hannah had displayed a pattern of poor judgment leading to egregious conduct, and Arbitrator Gerhart was concerned that this pattern would continue in the future. Arbitrator Gerhart was so concerned about her lack of judgment that he asked her the following series of questions to try to discern if she would make better judgments, personally and professionally, in the future (Tr 224-229):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Q: The Safety Director has a serious responsibility in making sure the streets of Cleveland are as safe as they can be and he made a judgment that they were safer without your service in the police department. Can you, in your best words, tell me why you think he came down so hard on you?</p>
<p class="continued">A: I feel like maybe in the past that we've had incidents where officers have moved forward with taking their own lives. That was part of the decision. Because I did have to go, you know for evaluations. I do agree that there was a little bit of, you know discrimination involved. I'm not going to say that it was only me being a female. I firmly believe that there was some race issues. That's just my opinion.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">If it came down to my work ethic and my performance on the street and the fact that I don't have any complaints from a civilian whom I may have serviced, that was not taken into account. I don't think that it mattered at all.</p>
<p class="continued">I feel like there was a decision made before we even got to the final hearing. I think it weighted a lot on what, you know, Internal Affairs may have said before we even got to the final day.</p>
<p class="continued">It had already come up that there was evaluations and things of that sort, so that was immediately brought to the table when we sat down. That's how it ended up being three different doctors.</p>
<p class="continued">There was never a question of my ability to do my job while I was in that zone car. I've never offered to work the office. If I had to do the office it was out of, you know, seniority. They chose me. I chose to work that hard and work it hard every day. That was never taken into account when we had that meeting.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Q: So you don't think there is anything peculiar about your case that makes it particularly onerous from his standpoint, other than the one thing you mentioned was the suicide concern that he might have had. Is that the only reason your case was reviewed so harshly by him?</p>
<p class="continued">A: I can't answer that. My opinion.</p>
<p class="continued">Q: You head his testimony, right?</p>
<p class="continued">A: Yes.</p>
<p class="continued">Q: You were here and you heard what he said. And the thing that he hammered away at, and I have to tell you, from an Arbitrator's perspective, my own &ndash; one of my major concerns about an employee when I'm making a decision about whether or not to sustain an employer's discharge is this question of judgment.</p>
<p class="continued">A: Yes.</p>
<p class="continued">Q: Everybody is entitled to make a mistake. And I agree with you wholeheartedly that people need to be forgiven for occasional mistakes that they make. We are all human. But the real reason, the real reason is are you going to repeat these poor judgments? And to some extent I have to make my decision based upon your past judgments. But I have to tell you in the back of my head &ndash; counsel here will get irate when he hears me say this, part of what I have to do is make a prediction. Am I going to be safer on the streets of Cleveland with you out there helping or not?</p>
<p class="continued">A: I would say yes, because what happened that night had nothing to do with the streets. That was my own life, my own &ndash;</p>
<p class="continued">Q: Let me tell you, that's an important consideration on my part. I'm taking that into account. But people make bad judgments, sometimes those flop over into the job.</p>
<p class="continued">A: Okay.</p>
<p class="continued">Q: So if you make a bad judgment with regard to your personal life then that may well have an impact on your job at some point in the future. So I think that that's &ndash; you know, Mr. Flask, I think I have a lot of respect for his judgment so I want to get past this point where judgment is a concern in my mind because if it continues to be a concern I'm not sure that I won't rule against your case.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Do you have access to Ms. Stoner and Medlea?</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">A: I do.</p>
<p class="continued">Q: And are they available to you if you have a problem that you could pick up a phone and talk to one of them?</p>
<p class="continued">A: Of course. Along with Sergeant Dismuke who is not here today.</p>
<p class="continued">Q: Okay. Well, that's important. I think that no matter what happens in this case you should maintain those relationships because obviously with your earlier upbringing you don't have that source of &ndash; and losing your grandmother, you don't have that source of stability that you need. We all need it.</p>
<p class="continued">A: Right.</p></blockquote>
<p>Although Hannah had been deemed fit for duty after her psychological evaluations &lsqb;October 2012 &amp; March 2013&rsqb;, there were stipulations necessary for Hannah to return to service as an officer. These stipulations were that she continue with both her treatment and her sobriety. Specifically, from Dr. Faust's evaluation, &ldquo;Shani Hannah is psychologically fit for duty and should be considered for return to her previous police duties, <i>contingent on maintenance of her treatment and sobriety</i>.&rdquo; (UX 12, p10) (Emphasis added). Hannah's treatment was in the form of counseling with Affiliates and attending Alcoholics Anonymous meetings regularly. However, Hannah admitted she had not maintained either form of treatment, again displaying poor judgment. And she admitted that she was no longer in contact with the CPD Employee Assistance Unit (Tr 208-209). She claimed she discontinued her counseling because she did not have insurance. Further, she admitted that she had not been to an AA meeting in at least six months. Here Arbitrator Gerhart interjected and asked Hannah to repeat her statement. He was understandably surprised by this admission. Further, he was concerned by her lack of a support network because she was not going to counseling anymore nor was she attending AA.</p>
<p>Arbitrator Gerhart asked her the following series of questions regarding her support network:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Q: So that brings me to another question. Do you have a support network beyond these type of folks?</p>
<p class="continued">A: I do.</p>
<p class="continued">Q: How would you describe your support network?</p>
<p class="continued">A: I would say that my family and I are a little bit closer than we have been over the years. My youngest brother and my mom now live in Minnesota. We converse at least twice a week.</p>
<p class="continued">Q: So you are in touch with your mother?</p>
<p class="continued">A: I am. My dad still lives here. We talk often. Basically he's going through some health issues or whatnot, so again I'm assisting him with his life. But right now it's basically the friends that I have gained on the job here that continue to be there for me outside of the uniform.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Charlotte Perkins is a person I work for now. I mean she's been there since day one. When I came on the job in 2003 up until March 11th she's been a very good friend of mine. Most of the women that I encounter are older so they do have a lot of good advice. They will tell me if they see something that I need to address, just like, you know, Sergeant Medlea was saying earlier. If they saw, if they called it &ndash; you know, would call me out on it.</p>
<p class="continued">Right now I'm in church every Sunday. And if I had the insurance I would probably be still going to Affiliates. It's &dollar;155 a visit. I cannot afford that. I make &dollar;10 an hour right now.</p>
<p class="continued">So I can't afford the proper insurance that I need to continue to go to them. But there are people that I do talk to.</p>
<p class="continued">I have been adamant about staying single since then. I don't depend on a relationship. I'm, you know, leaning more towards my family, which is what I have done, been my rock and the shoulder for everybody else. Now it's their turn to help me out.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Q: You're lucky to have them.</p></blockquote>
<p>Her lack of a support system is an issue because, while Hannah claims that she has been sober since March 12, 2012, she did not submit any evidence to substantiate her claim. She did not submit any AA records. And she admitted that she had not been to an AA meeting in over six months.</p>
<p>Further, her lack of insurance does not remove the requirement set forth in the recommendation by Dr. Faust. Counseling and AA meetings were Hannah's forms of treatment and she consciously chose to discontinue both. It is also telling that she includes her family in her support network. She claims both of her parents are now clean and sober and are a source of support for her but she testified that her mother sold her for sex, as a child, to her drug supplier and that even today, she is basically required to take care of her ailing father because he has &ldquo;health issues or whatnot, so again I'm assisting him with his life.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Hannah's poor judgment is obvious. In an attempt at self-victimization during the disciplinary hearing, she stated (Disciplinary Hearing, Tr 21):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">On this particular evening, you know, I was just exhausted with dealing with everything and it just felt like the weight and load was on my shoulders. I understand what statement they took from him, but nobody had to live with this person for two years.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Nor did she. She, and everyone, knew he was cheating on her for a long time and yet she continued to allow him to live with her. And although she claims that she had basically kicked him out by the time the incident occurred on March 11, 2012, it happened in her apartment. She allowed him into the apartment &ndash; to eat and drink with her. If she was really done with him and had kicked him out, her life today would be completely different because the incident on March 11, 2012 would not have happened. Once again, simply poor judgment on her part.</p>
<p>Hannah displayed a pattern of poor judgment leading to egregious conduct in her personal life. There are serious concerns as to whether that pattern would continue, and whether it would spill over from her personal life into her professional life.</p>
<p>Hannah failed to recognize the severity of her actions. Arbitrator Gerhart highlighted the importance of the role of Hannah's judgment in his decision, &ldquo;if (judgment) continues to be a concern in my mind I'm not sure that I won't rule against you.&rdquo; (Tr 228) Hannah's inability to recognize these concerns as reason-able indicate her poor judgment and a lack of accountability for her actions. Hannah's serious lack of judgment was the main concern for Director Flask. She displayed a pattern of bad judgment and refused to acknowledge the severity of her conduct. Arbitrator Gerhart's further concerns reinforce the validity of the decision made by the Safety Director. For the reasons stated above, the City had just cause to terminate Hannah.</p>
<p><i>Hannah's case is distinguishable from those &ldquo;like&rdquo; cases presented by the CPPA as evidence against termination</i>. Lastly, the City had just cause to terminate Hannah because she displayed a pattern of poor decision-making and egregious conduct over an extended period of time, which led to a conviction for a crime of violence, distinguishing this case from past cases in which the grievants were reinstated by the arbitrator. The severity of Hannah's actions sets her case apart from those provided by the CPPA as evidence against termination.</p>
<p>The CPPA argues Hannah's termination was unjust in comparison to other cases wherein police officers were involved in inappropriate conduct in violation of City rules and regulations:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">George Kirby: reinstated by the arbitrator after being terminated. He fractured an arrestee's arm using force to control the arrestee while searching the house for a gun. No charges were brought against Kirby.</p>
<p class="continued">William Forrest and Peter Turner: one officer was reinstated by the arbitrator after both were terminated. The two were drunk at a bar and instigated a fight with a black male and white female by using racial epithets. Neither was convicted of any crime nor were they charged with any racially-motivated crimes. The other officer's termination was upheld because the arbitrator determined that his actions were obviously racially-motivated.</p>
<p class="continued">Daniel Flannery: reinstated by the arbitrator after being terminated. He, while drunk at a bar, was removed for groping patrons. He returned and displayed his badge and brandished his RTA-issued handgun (he was laid-off by the City and working for RTA at the time of this incident) and threatened to kill two patrons. He was not convicted of any crime. The arbitrator reversed the termination because it was not clearly established that Flannery displayed his badge or that he threatened to kill two bar patrons.</p>
<p class="continued">Vincent Lucarelli: reinstated by the arbitrator even after the arbitrator found him guilty of all 7 specifications against him. These specifications included engaging in sexual relationships and sexting with former and current victims of crimes that he had or was investigating. The arbitrator indicated that his conduct was egregious but reinstated him with no back pay because he had a long career as a police officer and several supervisors testified that he could be &ldquo;rehabilitated&rdquo; as an officer. Lucarelli was not charged with any crime.</p></blockquote>
<p>The above cases greatly differ from Hannah. None of these cases involve a police officer that was charged with a felony and later pled down to a first-degree misdemeanor. In fact, none involve a conviction. Hannah was charged and convicted of a violent crime. She displayed a pattern of poor judgment and egregious conduct that violated her duty as a police officer. The evidence shows that her actions were far more severe than those of the officers in the cases above.</p>
<p>The CPPA also cited to several other cases during the hearing wherein officers were charged with domestic violence but were allowed to plead to a lesser charge in order to save their jobs because a conviction for domestic violence means that the officer cannot carry a gun and, therefore, can no longer be a police officer. CPPA President Jeff Follmer admitted that in &ldquo;almost all of&rdquo; those cases the com-plainant did not want to go forward with the prosecution of the case or agreed to an amendment of the charges to a disorderly conduct because the spouse (i.e. police officer) would get fired. In fact, in at least three cases, Roberts, Lane and Parrish, the victim did not want to prosecute at all. These cases are different from Hannah's case. Her victim did not want to prosecute not because he feared that she would lose her job but because he was motivated by greed. He was attempting to get anything he could from her by &ldquo;blackmailing&rdquo; her, i.e., &ldquo;I will not go forward if you give me your motorcycle.&rdquo; (Tr 189)</p>
<p>Under Article 4, section (e) of the CBA, the City has the authority to discipline and/or discharge employees for just cause. Based upon this authority, the City considers each case and determines the proper discipline. In this matter, the City determined that Hannah's actions warranted termination because she stabbed her boyfriend; this led to her pleading to a lesser charge of first-degree misdemeanor assault charge. The above cases fail to support Hannah's claim that her termination was not for just cause because none of the cases involved criminal convictions.</p>
<p><i><b>Conclusion.</b></i> Hannah's termination was for just cause, was not excessive, and was in accordance with the CBA for the following reasons:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Hannah stabbed Richardson multiple times with knives that she had to retrieve from a drawer across the room, causing him to require five stiches; she hid the knives that she stabbed him with in the dishwasher; she fled the scene of the crime while admittedly driving drunk; she was found with a cord around her neck in an apparent suicide attempt; and she texted Richardson and her daughter that she was going to kill herself;</p></li>
<li><p>Hannah violated multiple City ordinances, rules, and regulations wherein it is clearly stated that violation may be cause for termination;</p></li>
<li><p>Hannah pled guilty to a first-degree misdemeanor assault, in violation of R.C. &sect;2903.13, which was pled down from a second-degree felonious assault charge; and</p></li>
<li><p>Hannah displayed a pattern of poor judgment and egregious conduct in her personal life, which calls into question her future judgment while on and off duty.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>For all the above reasons, the City respectfully requests the Arbitrator to deny the CPPA's grievance in its entirety and sustain Hannah's termination.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Position of the Union</b></h4>
<p>The following is the arbitrator's summary of the Union's post-hearing brief.</p>
<p>The Cleveland Police Patrolman's Association (&ldquo;CPPA&rdquo;) has filed this grievance on behalf of Patrol Officer Shani Hannah who was wrongfully discharged for allegedly violating the General Police Orders, rules of the Manuel of Rules, Department of Public Safety, and the rules of the Civil Service Commission of the City of Cleveland (JX 2, p1).</p>
<p>The investigation of Hannah began on March 11, 2012 when she was arrested and criminally charged in an off-duty incident involving her then boyfriend, Darnel Richardson. Hannah was indicted on one count of Felonious Assault as a result of an argument with her boyfriend in which he sustained minor superficial marks and five (5) stitches (JX 3, p14). Richardson repeatedly stated he did not want to press any charges against Hannah. On July 11, 2012, Hannah pled guilty to the amended charge of assault, a misdemeanor of the first degree in Cuyahoga County Court of Common Pleas and was sentenced to one year probation, 25 hours of community work service, drug testing and an anger management program. She successfully completed her probation and complied with all requests of the Court during that time frame. Officer Hannah also returned to work on restricted duty and was returned her service weapon. She had no complaints against her during the time frame from when she returned to work until she received her charging letter. An administrative pre-disciplinary hearing was held on Thursday, April 18, 2013 in front of the Director of Public Safety, Martin Flask, in anticipation of a suspension from duty in excess of ten (10) days (JX 2, p11). Hannah pled &ldquo;no contest&rdquo; to the allegations set forth in the charging letter and presented numerous mitigating factors in support of her retaining employment with the City (<i>Id</i>. at 12). As a result of her disciplinary hearing, Hannah was notified on May 22, 2013 that she was found guilty of all five specifications and she was terminated from her employment with the City of Cleveland, Division of Police, effective immediately.</p>
<p>Officer Hannah's termination is disproportionate to past disciplinary cases where the officers have engaged in similar conduct, such as assault, domestic violence, and other misdemeanor crimes, and have not been terminated. The City also failed to properly consider her notable service record, extensive efforts towards treatment, personal history, remorse, and other mitigating factors. The CPPA believes that a suspension from duty is sufficient punishment for Hannah's actions in this case when considering similar past discipline and the background of this officer. Although Hannah's actions were inappropriate, the capital punishment of termination is excessive and disparate to past disciplinary cases involving fellow officers in the Division of Police and should be reversed. Officer Hannah is deserving of a second chance and should be immediately reinstated to duty.</p>
<p><i><b>Background of Cleveland Police Officer Shani Hannah</b></i>. Officer Hannah has been a patrol officer with the City of Cleveland for over eleven years. During her employment, she received several Commander's commendations and the Distinguished Service Medal (UX 9). The Distinguished Service Medal is awarded to those police officers who demonstrate a high degree of personal initiative, perform substantially above normal requirements in an exemplary manner, or contribute significantly to the achievement of law enforcement goals. Her Medal citation included the following: &ldquo;For exhibiting a high degree of initiative and professionalism it is an honor to bestow upon you, Patrol Officer Shani Hannah, the Distinguished Service Medal.&rdquo; (<i>Id</i>.)</p>
<p>All of Officer Hannah's employment evaluations have been above average throughout her career (<i>Id</i>.). Her evaluations have stated, among other things: (1) &ldquo;Hannah is performing well, she seems to have interest and enthusiasm about the job.&rdquo; (2) Officer Hannah is a dependable and reliable veteran officer who often takes on additional duties for the good of the unit. Would make a good supervisor.&rdquo; (3) &ldquo;She is a good officer who is always willing to lend a hand, she is an asset to the DSU.&rdquo; (4) &ldquo;Officer Hannah is self-motivated and a determined police officer. &hellip; Hannah works well with others and is willing to assist fellow officers at any moment. &hellip; Hannah is an asset to the Cleveland Division of Police.&rdquo; and (5) Hannah passes along her unique reasoning ability in gathering accurate and necessary information that assist her in making sound decisions.&rdquo; (<i>Id</i>.).</p>
<p>Throughout her eleven years with the City, Hannah had always come to work, done her job, and never let her personal life interfere with her duties as a patrol officer. Officer Hannah has never had any complaints about her performance, complaints regarding abuse, use of force complaints, or any other serious determinations against her. (<i>Id</i>. at 27). Prior to her employment with the City, Hannah has had a strong work and educational background (UX 11, p1). To say that Officer Hannah has overcome sincere hardships in her life is an understatement. Hannah had a very troubled childhood and upbringing, marked by many abuses (UX 12, p3). She was born to parents that were addicted to crack-cocaine and unable to care for her. Officer Hannah's mother, an often homeless prostitute, sold her to a crack head to feed her addiction. She was a victim of sexual abuse by family members three times in her childhood, ages 6, 12, and 15. Her mother was physically abusive and made her children watch her smoke crack so they could call 911 if she overdosed. Hannah's mother saw her children as a paycheck and only fought for custody so that she wouldn't lose her welfare check. Hannah's paternal grandmother stepped in and raised her and her brothers when neither parent wanted them.</p>
<p>When she was only 16 years old, Hannah gave birth to her first child. Regardless of her teen pregnancy, she still graduated from high school on time. Hannah has been gainfully employed since she was 15 and has always had a strong work history. By the age of 18, she had worked hard enough to get her own apartment. Hannah has two younger brothers that she took care of due to her mother's addiction. She took full custody of them when she was only 19 years old. Hannah was forced to grow up very quickly due to her circumstances. Officer Hannah has been a victim of domestic violence in her personal relationships, having been slapped, punched, choked, and verbally abused in the past. Most people in her situation would not have come out on the same side she did. Her perseverance and hard work show Hannah's true character and continued desire for success.</p>
<p>On November 11, 2012, Officer Hannah's rock and sole caregiver, her grandmother, passed away. She had fallen sick but on that day, Hannah was the one that had to make the decision to take her grandmother off life support. Not only was she forced to make that hard decision, but she also had to plan the funeral and make all of the arrangements. This death shook Hannah so much that she felt &ldquo;unglued.&rdquo; She felt like she had lost everything. Her responsibilities became overwhelming and she was never able to properly grieve and deal with her emotions. Like many people do in her situation coping with the death of a loved one, Hannah turned to alcohol. She began drinking heavily right after the funeral and did not stop.</p>
<p>Officer Hannah sincerely apologized for and accepted responsibility for her actions on March 11, 2012 (JX 3, p21). Hannah stated, &ldquo;What I did was not right and it was definitely not the way it should have been handled, but it happened. I can't take it back. I just want to apologize for it and &hellip; hopefully be able to move forward.&rdquo; (<i>Id</i>. at 22). After the incident, Hannah was reinstated to work and placed on restrictive duty in the Third District. Her service weapon was returned. During that time frame where she went back to work, there were no complaints filed against Officer Hannah. Overall, this truly was an isolated personal off-duty incident and Officer Hannah has taken every step to rehabilitate herself to make sure nothing like this will ever happen again. She has learned a lot since this incident and grown to be a better police officer, a healthier person, and a better mother to her children. Officer Hannah will not make this same mistake again and she is deserving of a second chance. She has overcome tremendous obstacles and the done everything that the Court and the Cleveland Police Department have asked of her since this incident. She is fit, ready, and waiting to return to the Division.</p>
<p>Officer Andre Cico of the Employee Assistance Unit and a 28 year veteran of the Division, spoke on behalf of Officer Hannah (JX 3, p60). The Employee Assistance Unit works with police officers who have personal, issues with their family, or a difficulty regarding anything on the job. It is a peer support group. Cico and retired Sergeant Dismuke were actively involved in the aftercare Hannah received and speak with her on a daily basis (JX 3, p61). Officer Hannah not only completed the alcohol recovery program at Glenbeigh, but also received many compliments from the counselors. Officer Hannah has gone above and beyond everything that was required in her program and what the Employee Assistance Unit has asked of her. Cico did not express any concerns whatsoever with Hannah as she moves forward with her employment with the Division. Since Hannah returned to duty after the incident, she has been doing her job and the Employee Assistance Unit has not gotten any calls or concerns from her supervisor.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Detective Debra Stoner, also of the Employee Assistance Unit, has been working with Hannah on a personal and professional level. Detective Stoner described that as Hannah's peer counselor, she has seen significant personal growth and change since her incident (JX 3, p63). &ldquo;I've seen the change in her and I think she's a fine police officer, I think she's a woman of strength, and with her history and with the effort that she's put into it, I think she's done very well.&rdquo; (<i>Id</i>. at 64). Detective Stoner not only appeared at the Safety Director's Hearing on April 18, 2013, but she also appeared on Hannah's behalf at the Arbitration Hearing held on May 8, 2014 (Tr 127). Stoner verified that Officer Hannah has done everything that was asked of her and she should be afforded her job back as a result (Tr 129). While working at the Employee Assistance Unit, Detective Stoner assisted numerous officers who have gone through dependency issues, emotional issues, and psychological issues. From her experience in dealing with these cases, including domestic violence cases with serious injuries, Stoner believes Hannah got &ldquo;a raw deal.&rdquo; (Tr 131-132) Hannah is not the first officer to go through Employee's Assistance that was involved in assaultive behavior, drinking problems, or battering issues involving family members (Tr 133). Detective Stoner has seen victims with bloody noses, strangling marking, bruising and other serious injuries (Tr 136). Typically the victim is a female or child, not a male. Officer Hannah's incident was no different than other situations Stoner observed but her treatment from the Division was much harsher. Having worked with Hannah through her recovery, Detective Stoner still believes Hannah is a great officer and she would still be if the City gave her a second chance. Everyone that worked with her said nothing but glowing things about her as a person and an officer.</p></blockquote>
<p>Vice-President of the Black Shield Police Patrolman's Association, Michael Belle, has known Hannah since she became an officer for the Division eleven years ago (JX 3, p66). Not only have they been coworkers, but Officer Belle has also been Hannah's neighbor for the last two years. Office Belle acknowledges that Hannah has suffered some personal issues off the job, but she is an outstanding citizen and still a good police officer. Officer Hannah has performed well at her job and Belle has seen a positive change in her. Overall, Officer Belle believes Hannah will be an asset for the City of Cleveland.</p>
<p>Stephanie Hunter of the Third District Detective Bureau has known Officer Hannah since she worked in the Fifth District (JX 3, p67). After Hannah's incident, she had been working in the Detective Bureau. Detective Hunter is in a unique position to comment on the ability of Hannah to effectively perform her duties as a police officer in the future since she has firsthand knowledge of Hannah's performance on the job for months after her altercation with Richardson. Hannah is a very hard working and is present every day. Officer Hannah's duties have included timekeeping, administrative duties, answering the phones, talking to clients, following up investigations, and any other work the lieutenant assigns to her. Although Officer Hannah has not returned to the street as a patrol officer, Detective Hunter believes Hannah would excel at such a position. Detective Hunter brought up an important distinction that every officer for the Division faces personal and private challenges throughout their career. Officer Hannah did not let her personal issues ever affect her performance in her professional life. Hannah now has the tools to address and cope with her personal challenges that should make her shine ever more in her career.</p>
<p>Sergeant Hughlean Medlea met with Officer Hannah the day after the incident and wanted this arbitrator to know of the true remorse she saw from Hannah that day (Tr 143). In Sergeant Medlea's capacity as the Medical Unit Coordinator, she has dealt with many officers who went through experiences and situations similar to Hannah's incident. After an officer is involved in an incident, he or she has to go through the medical unit prior to returning to work to see what programs and treatment that officer would have to complete. Unfortunately, Medlea has dealt with a lot of officers who were perpetrators of on-duty and off-duty domestic violence or assaults. All of these other officers, many of whom were also convicted of misdemeanors, were put through a program with the Medical Unit and returned to work (Tr 145). Some were even repeat offenders of violence, used weapons, or threatened to use a weapon. The Sergeant gave two examples of officers that emotionally &ldquo;lost it&rdquo; on more than one occasion and were still able to keep their jobs (Tr 156). One officer, within the last year, had a serious breakdown, was abusing alcohol, got in an argument with her husband, discharged her firearm in her residence, and falsified a story about how it happened. In her experience as Medical Unit Coordinator she had also witnessed at least four or five instances where officers threatened suicide or stated they were going to &ldquo;eat their gun.&rdquo; (Tr 169). Not one of the above-mentioned officers was ever terminated for his or her actions. What truly puzzles Sergeant Medlea is that Officer Hannah was not allowed to permanently return to work as all the foregoing officers were permitted to do. Based on Medlea's 34-year history with the Cleveland Police Department, her opinion is that Officer Hannah's termination was unfair and inappropriate (Tr 152).</p>
<p>The most powerful statement Sergeant Medlea made was that knowing everything she knows about Hannah's background and this incident, if she &ldquo;was still on job and &lsqb;Hannah&rsqb; needed a partner to sit in a zone car, I would sit there with her and I'd go through any door that she goes through. She should have her job back.&rdquo; (Tr 158). Sergeant Medlea's trust in Hannah's recovery is something that she is willing to risk her life over.</p>
<p>CPPA President Jeff Follmer attends numerous disciplinary hearings and court hearings with fellow officers to provide them with Union support and guidance. Working patrol on the streets is probably the hardest job in the City of Cleveland. The fact that Hannah not only survived this time on the street, but also had an eleven-year successful career without any complaints supports the conclusion that she can once again be successful if she were to return to work. President Follmer agreed with Sergeant Medlea and said that he would not have any fear if Officer Hannah were to be his partner for the rest of his career (Tr 276).</p>
<p>Officer Hannah has remained sober since the March 11, 2012 incident, takes all of her prescribed medication, and believes her anger and alcoholism are completely under control. The testimony of Officer Andre Cico, Detective Debra Stoner, Officer Michelle Belle, Officer Stephanie Hunter, Sergeant Hughlean Medlea, and CPPA President Follmer gives great weight to not only the recovery Hannah has gone through, but also her professional career with the Division. The City did not present any evidence that Officer Hannah ever performed poorly at her job throughout her eleven years with the Division. Officer Hannah's strong work history and extensive efforts to better herself, along with other mitigating factors, outweighs her single improper act of off-duty conduct.</p>
<p>Even after her termination, she has maintained full time employment as an office administrator for R-Cap Securities to support her family. When she originally took her job as a Cleveland Police Officer, it was to help people who were in situations like hers. If she could change just one person's life or help one child, then she would succeed at her goal. She has always wanted to give back to the community and be there for children as a role model. Many children in Cleveland can tragically relate to Hannah's childhood and she can not only help them, but also show them that even they can surpass their upbringing and become a Cleveland Police Officer. She always took her job very seriously. Hannah's life forever changed on March 11, 2012, but her life shouldn't be ruined for one mistake. Officer Hannah has demonstrated, based upon her professionalism, that she is worthy of the badge and a second chance.</p>
<p><i><b>Facts.</b></i> Officer Hannah's termination stems from a single off-duty incident involving her boyfriend of two years, Darnell Richardson, on March 11, 2012. Office Hannah and Richardson met at a Cleveland Police Black Shield event that he attended. Richardson's father, Joseph Weems, was a retired Cleveland Police Officer. Richardson asked to be introduced to Hannah at the event.</p>
<p>Approximately a year after their initial meeting, Richardson contacted Hannah on Facebook and they began dating. He painted a picture of being a different man than he turned out to be. Many of their initial interactions were in a group with his family. Richardson's parents always invited Hannah and her three children over for dinner. Approximately a year after they began dating, Richardson moved in with Officer Hannah. Officer Hannah began to rely on Richardson for comfort due to her low self-esteem and depression after the death of her grandmother.</p>
<p>What Officer Hannah didn't know about Richardson when they started dating was that he was a convicted felon with extensive criminal history. He has been convicted of gross sexual imposition, abduction of a female, possession of drugs, sexual battery, attempted kidnapping, drug trafficking, forgery, uttering, possession of criminal tools, attempted robbery, and other crimes. He is a registered sex offender. Richardson lied to Hannah about his background when they met. The City tried to stress the absurd notion that Hannah in some way should have run a record check on Richardson prior to her involvement with him. Although Hannah is a police officer, it is unreasonable to run a &ldquo;background check&rdquo; on every person she meets, especially when Hannah knew he came from a family of police officers and they originally met at a police function. Throughout their relationship, Richardson had been physically abusive towards her.</p>
<p>The night of the incident, the couple was drinking liquor and got into an argument about Richardson's cheating and Hannah wanting him to move his things out of her home. Richardson was on parole and one of the conditions of his parole was to abstain from alcohol. This was an escalating fight that lasted hours. During the fight, Richardson threatened Hannah's job and both individuals kept provoking the situation. At one point he kicked the door and slammed her hand. About 10 pm, their verbal argument grew into a physical altercation. Hannah became enraged and went to the dresser drawer to retrieve two knives and she began poking him. She ended up making two shallow knife wounds, one on his hand and one on his leg. As soon as Hannah realized that Richardson was bleeding, she immediately left the room to go get a towel, which shows her instant remorse for her actions. Only a few drops of blood appeared on the carpet. Hannah left the home clearly in distress and was eventually recovered from her vehicle. Hannah broke down and hit rock bottom in her personal life at that point. She temporarily could not deal with it. She admitted that there were &ldquo;no rational actions at all during that night.&rdquo; (Tr 217).</p>
<p>Richardson's wound has been described as &ldquo;superficial,&rdquo; and was approxi-mately 1.5 centimeters long. At the Hospital, Richardson told the doctors that he felt safe at home and was not afraid of anyone hurting him. Sergeant Daniel M. Ross interviewed Richardson at the hospital. Richardson stated that Hannah was upset about life and &ldquo;people not doing right by her.&rdquo; Richardson admitted that he was not responding to her and smirking during their argument. He also admits that he isn't the perfect person to be around. The next day, Richardson asked Hannah to pay him &dollar;2,000 or to give him her motorcycle in exchange for him not pressing charges (Tr 189). He even tried to call her attorney's office. Hannah never entertained such a notion.</p>
<p>After the offense, Richardson told Sergeant Stacho that he did not want to press charges against Officer Hannah on March 16, 2012. He believed she needed counseling and not time in prison. Internal Affairs went to Richardson's parole officer to force him to cooperate. He was served with a grand jury subpoena at the office of his parole officer. On March 26, 2012, Richardson once again requested to sign a complaint withdraw form. The next day, March 27th, Sergeant Stacho again conferred with Richardson, who indicated that he did not want to press charges. In response, Stacho told him it was allegedly too late to withdraw the charges because the grand jury was scheduled for that same day. Richardson stated he was going to check himself into a hospital to avoid the grand jury but Stacho told him the ramifications he would face if he failed to appear due to his parole status. Richardson ultimately appeared for the grand jury but refused to be sworn in. Prosecutor Whinery advised him against refusing to appear. Richardson was compelled under the threat of parole violations to proceed with this prosecution against Hannah. On March 28, the next day, the grand jury indicted Officer Hannah for felonious assault.</p>
<p>Regardless of Richardson's repeated desire not to pursue the case criminally, Officer Hannah eventually plead guilty to misdemeanor assault and was sentenced to a suspended sentence, 12 months of probation, 25 hours of community work service, submit to drug testing and complete an anger management program. The judge specifically indicated that Hannah would be permitted to carry a gun for the purpose of employment during her probation. Hannah complied with all terms and conditions of her sentence and probation. She has gone above and beyond what both the Court and the Division have asked of her. Officer Hannah took responsibility for her actions and does not make excuses for what she did. Based on her personal and professional history, it is clear that March 11, 2012 incident was a disparate act outside of her normal character.</p>
<p>Immediately after the incident, Hannah was suspended without pay pending the outcome of her criminal case. Upon pleading to the misdemeanor assault charge, the City reinstated her to restricted duty the very next day. She was sent down to the range, picked up her firearm, reported to the Downtown Services Unit, and ultimately was assigned to the Third District Detective Bureau. Although she was on restricted duty, Hannah was still active in her work and with the public. During the next eight months, she had no incidents on or off duty.</p>
<p>Hannah truly apologized for her actions and knows that it was completely out of character for her (Tr 189-190). She had realized that she needed help before that night and it is unfortunate it took an incident like this make sure she got that help. After the incident, she went to Employees Assistance and Sergeant Dismuke referred her to Affiliates Behavioral Services for grief counseling. The grief counselor referred Hannah to Glenbeigh to seek treatment for her drinking problem. Glenbeigh recommended a 12-week outpatient program with six months of after care, both of which she completed by October 3, 2012 (UX 10). During her 12 weeks of outpatient treatment, Hannah</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&hellip; attended all sessions required and interacted very well with her peers. She gave appropriate feedback in group. She was assertively honest with a lot of compassion and sensitive for her peers. She completed her treatment plan assignments as requested &hellip; Client has developed a stable support group with her therapist, sponsor, and some family. &hellip; Her prognosis is good.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(UX 13, p2). Officer Hannah received the highest of evaluations on all of her progress reports. Her six month discharge plan stated that Hannah had &ldquo;become a respected senior peer who shared deep wisdom and strong recovery behaviors.&rdquo; (UX 10, p2). Hannah also completed anger management counseling at Affiliates. Most importantly, she has not consumed any alcohol since March 11, 2012 (Tr 208).</p>
<p>Officer Hannah clearly made a mistake on March 11, 2012, but she should be forgiven for this mistake and be given a second chance. Hannah worked for months after the incident and the City did not present any evidence of poor judgment or improper choices made by Hannah during that time. The City of Cleveland will be assisted by Hannah's return to duty because she is now an even stronger woman than she was before. She has access to all the tools she needs and her return to work can be conditioned upon any continuing treatment or program this arbitrator feels is appropriate to ensure Hannah's uphill growth. She now has a good support system and has been active in Church. Ultimately, the City of Cleveland Police Department and all of its services would provide Officer Hannah with one of the best support systems available.</p>
<p><i><b>Officer Shani Hannah is fit for duty and the City terminated her for reasons beyond the scope of her charging letter.</b></i> The CPPA argues that Officer Hannah's alleged &ldquo;fitness for duty&rdquo; is beyond the scope of this instant labor arbitration. Hannah was not brought up on charges for such an allegation or inability to perform her duties as a police officer for the City. This arbitration hearing is to determine whether the City had just cause to terminate Hannah from the Division for events stemming from the March 11, 2012 incident. This argument goes beyond the issue of whether the City had just cause to terminate Hannah for her actions. If the City wanted to bring a specification alleging Hannah was unfit for duty, they could have easily amended her charging letter.</p>
<p>Without foregoing the CPPA's objection, it is clear based upon two indepen-dent evaluations that Officer Hannah is fit for duty (UX 11 &amp; 12). Dr. Francis L. McCafferty met with Officer Hannah in September, six months after her incident with Richardson, and completed his evaluation on October 8, 2012. He notes that Hannah is currently on light duty, still carries her service weapon, and that she wishes to return to full time duty. After a full evaluation, Dr. McCafferty concluded that Hannah, in the doctor's professional psychiatric opinion with a reasonable degree of medical certitude, is capable of returning to full time duty without restrictions. He wrote (UX 11, p8):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Her potential for aggressive acting out is low in view of her being in therapy, on medication and in AA. She is in therapy, attending AA meetings, and is motivated to continue abstinence and treatment. &hellip; Her problem on 3/11/12 was related to alcohol, which is currently in remission.</p></blockquote>
<p>On March 3, 2013, approximately one year after Hannah's altercation with Richardson, Dr. Michael W. Faust also evaluated Hannah's fitness for duty (UX 12). Dr. Faust evaluated a significant amount of material relating to Hannah's background including her criminal case, the Internal Affairs Investigation, her employment history, criminal history of Richardson, medical records of Richardson, awards received by Hannah, and Dr. George Serna's evaluation from August 4, 2012. After evaluating all of these material and speaking to Officer Hannah on numerous occasions, Dr. Faust determined the following mitigating factors applied to Hannah's case: (1) History of sexual abuse since childhood; (2) Parental substance abuse, dependence, and neglect; (3) Death of Ms. Hannah's paternal grandmother in November 2011, who was her primary support and eventual caregiver; (4) Accountability demonstrated by Officer Hannah; (5) Richardson's reported criminal history and desire to not press charges; (6) Reported superficial nature of the injuries inflicted on Richardson; (7) Officer Hannah's participation in counseling and relapse prevention at both Glenbeigh and Affiliates, as well as, compliance with psychiatric recommendations, including the completion of IPD and anger management components; (8) Previous job performance evaluations; (9) Previous work commendations; (10) Ten year police history; (11) No citizen complaints of misconduct in terms of excessive force or abuse of citizens; and (12) Abstinence from all psychoactive substance since March 2012 (<i>Id</i>. at 7).</p>
<p>Dr. Faust concluded that in his professional opinion, given the length of time with her abstinence from alcohol and her adherence to her treatment regimen, her medical condition has become rather well stabilized. Based on Officer Hannah's full background and evidence, the duty restrictions are no longer necessary. For the past year, &ldquo;Officer Hannah has separated herself from toxic relationships and has made remarkable gains in regard to her physical and emotional health.&rdquo; (<i>Id</i>. at 9). Hannah's substance abuse and dependence, as well as her chaotic upbringing, contributed to her accepting toxic relationships into her life and ultimately led to the assault on Richardson (<i>Id</i>. at 10). Since that time she has demonstrated dramatic improvement into her insight and adherence to healthier behaviors and relationships. She appears to be internally motivated to continue improving her own physical and emotional health, and appears to be genuinely invested and more emotionally available to be involved in her children's personal and academic lives. Overall, Officer Shani Hannah is fit for full duty.</p>
<p>Dr. Faust pointed out an important distinction. Officer Hannah continued to receive good employment reviews despite the degree of distress she experienced in her life and the toxic relationships she became involved in (<i>Id</i>. at 9). Officer Hannah had an ability to properly separate her personal life from her professional one, a trait that many other officers aren't able to control. It was only when her personal life started to boil over that she realized that she needed help, help which she has openly received. Overall, Officer Hannah has been deemed fit for duty by both of these doctors that not only evaluated her, but also evaluated the facts and the backgrounds of this instant case. They are fully aware of what traits and mental state it takes to be a Cleveland Police Officer. Despite Hannah's incident on March 11, 2012, both Dr. Faust and Dr. McCafferty determined her fit for full duty.</p>
<p>In addition, the City continuously brought up the January 21, 2012 incident in regards to Hannah's alleged &ldquo;fitness for duty&rdquo; and an unsupported allegation from Richardson that she had previous assaulted him. Officer Hannah adamantly denies ever stabbing Richardson on any occasion prior to March 11, 2012 (Tr 211). Richardson's extensive criminal record shows that he has been stabbed on more than one occasion in relation to his past criminal activity. Hannah once again was not brought up on charges for anything relating to her off-duty incident in January or the untrue allegation of a prior assault. Therefore, this arbitrator should not consider the facts of January incident of the unsupported prior &ldquo;stabbing&rdquo; in determining whether or not the City has just cause to terminate her for the March 11, 2012 incident. It is beyond the scope of this instant arbitration and if the City wanted to terminate her for these incidents and allegations, the City should have properly amended her charging letter to include specifications for those charges. Officer Hannah is not alleging that the January incident did not occur, but, if anything, it further shows her downward spiral in her personal life after the death of her grandmother. The CPPA argues that the Safety Director improperly considered these outside factors in its overall determination to terminate Hannah. This instant Arbitrator should only consider the charged specifications, along with Hannah's mitigating circumstances, to determine if the City had just cause to terminate her employment. It should be noted that the City did not produce any evidence that her ungluing personal life ever affected her job or ability to serve the City of Cleveland.</p>
<p><i><b>The termination of Hannah is disproportional to discipline imposed on other officers for the same or more severe conduct</b></i>. Officer Hannah's discharge for her actions is contrary to past discipline imposed by the City of Cleveland. It is very important to fairly and consistently impose discipline in these cases to promote equal and nondiscriminatory treatment in the workplace. The employer has the burden of proof for off-duty misconduct.</p>
<blockquote><p>Assuming that a violation of a valid rule has been established, an employer must then persuade that the discipline selected is reasonably related to the seriousness of the proven offense in all of the circumstances of the case. Generally, the concept of just cause contemplates an adequate and fair investigation of the facts prior to imposing discipline and recognition of any mitigating facts disclosed by that investigation. Other appropriate considerations include whether the employer's rule has been enforced in a uniform and non-discriminatory manner, and whether, absent proof of a summary discharge offense, the discipline selected is consistent with accepted standards of progressive discipline.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">2008 AAA LEXIS 188, 49-50 (AAA 2008). Based on the charges alleged by the City, the employer's rules have not been enforced in a uniform manner. Officer Hannah should have been disciplined for her actions but also afforded the opportunity to maintain her employment. She was not given an opportunity to correct her behavior or face progressive discipline even though she has an unblemished 11-year career with the City.</p>
<p>Officer Hannah is deserving of the same equal and fair treatment that male officers received for being involved in violent attacks, domestic violence, and other criminal cases where discipline was imposed, yet the officer was not terminated from his job.</p>
<p>On May 21, 2014, the City produced evidential photographs depicting the domestic violence injuries of the victims of Cleveland Police Officer(s) Eric Parish, Chris Lane, Andrea Viccaro, Eric Roberts, Ron James, and Robert Sweeney at the request of the CPPA (UX 14). These photographs demonstrate just a fraction of the injuries received by victims as a result of the off-duty criminal conduct of Cleveland Police Officers.</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Officer Eric Roberts was charged with felony domestic violence and felonious assault (Tr 35). The County referred his case back to the City and Officer Roberts plead guilty to a reduced charge of disorderly conduct and was able to keep his job. The photographs of his victim show severe facial bruising, lacerations, and a black eye.</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Ron James also plead to a reduced charge after initially facing domestic violence charges, making him able to keep his job.</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Andrea Viccaro caused facial injuries including black eyes and a severely split lip to her victim.</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Robert Sweeney slapped his daughter so hard she had numerous bruises all over her body and was sent home from school with a black eye. He was criminally prosecuted for domestic violence and plead guilty to a reduced charge. Officer Sweeney was able to keep his job.</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Chris Lane was recently before the Safety Director facing administrative charges and discipline after he punched his wife so hard in the face that she received two black eyes and a bruised lip. (Tr 35) Officer Lane was charged with domestic violence but the charges were reduced to disorderly conduct and he was permitted to keep his job. (Tr 36).</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">All of the above mentioned victims were innocent and did not have the extensive and violent criminal history Richardson has. Some of these victims even received arguably more significant injuries.</p>
<p>The City failed to distinguish the acts of Officer Hannah or the injuries received by Richardson from any of the victims herein.</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Officers Parente and Burford had assorted felony charges reduced to misdemeanor offenses and were permitted to keep their jobs (JX 3, p46).</p></li>
<li><p>Sergeant Burner was charged with assault after punching someone at the convention center and received a 15-day suspension from duty (<i>Id</i>.).</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Buford was charged with a hit skip violation that rose to the level of a felony due to the injuries of the victim. Any felony or domestic violence conviction would lead to the automatic termination of an officer because he or she would be barred from carrying a service weapon as a felon. Only the Prosecutor's Office has the statutory authority to reduce a felony down to a misdemeanor. Buford's charges were ultimately reduced to a misdemeanor offense and he was able to keep his job (Tr 236).</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Cavett was charged with numerous felony charges, including stalking (Tr 237). Her case was reduced to misdemeanors with no condition of resignation (<i>Id</i>.).</p></li>
<li><p>Police officers are not immune to alcoholism and alcohol related offenses. Kevin Coleman, while off duty at the Public House bar and under the influence of alcohol, beat up another intoxicated patron to the point that he had a broken nose and numerous teeth knocked out (JX 3, p44). Officer Coleman was not prosecuted in that case but a civil settlement was reached for thousands of dollars to cover the victim's injuries. He was disciplined by the Division of Police for conduct unbecoming of a police officer, being intoxicated in a bar, physical force, and other charges. He was permitted to keep his job. Since then, has stayed out of trouble and has now been promoted to Sergeant.</p></li>
<li><p>Patrol Officer Tommy Barnes got into an off-duty fistfight with police supervisor, Sergeant Dean Grazzioli (JX 3, p44). The physical altercation took place in a bar while both parties were drinking. Injuries were sustained by both parties. Although discipline was imposed, they were both permitted to keep their employment.</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Michael Herrin was off duty at a wedding and while under the influence of alcohol he got into a physical fight and brandished his weapon (<i>Id</i>. at 45). Some individuals sustained injuries and his weapon was used in a threatening fashion. Officer Herrin was prosecuted in Medina for assault, menacing and having a weapon while intoxicated for the fight. He was convicted of misdemeanor charges and he was incarcerated for his conduct. Officer Herrin was disciplined and received a 173 day suspension from duty, yet still able to keep his employment.</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Marvin McMichael was intoxicated with a weapon and was charged with assault and menacing (JX 3, p46). He threatened his girlfriend with a shotgun. The Officer was so drunk he defecated on his girlfriend's front lawn. McMichael's personal record had prior discipline for a variety of things, bad actions, bad conduct, abuse of sick leave, tardiness, and other offenses. Officer McMichael plead guilty to misdemeanor charges in Cleveland Municipal Court and kept his job with the City despite his actions and unfavorable discipline history. Unlike McMichael, Hannah does not have any negative reports or serious discipline on her 11-year service record with the Division.</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Kelvin Barrow was on duty when he used the butt of a shotgun against a criminal suspect (JX 3, p46). He was prosecuted for using excessive force since the suspect was injured. The victim's injuries included black and blue marks all over and stitches on his chin to repair a facial laceration. Although he was acquitted at trial for felonious assault, the City pursued administrative disciplinary charges for excessive force. Officer Barrow was disciplined but not terminated. His discipline was a 30-day suspension from duty.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">Other Cleveland Police Officers have been disciplined for the following violations:</p>
<table width="585" columns="1">
<tr>
<td width="22%"><p></p></td>
<td width="55%"><p></p></td>
<td width="23%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" valign="top"><p>Officer</p></th>
<th align="left" valign="top"><p>Violation</p></th>
<th align="left" valign="top"><p>Punishment</p></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Eric Roberts &num;1758</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in improper conduct. Became involved in an altercation with a family member. Found guilty of violating one count of Aggravated disorderly conduct a misdemeanor of the first degree</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Ten Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>John Kiggins</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Plead Guilty to two counts of aggravated menacing, a misdemeanor of the first degree, after being indicted with two counts of felonious assault after discharging his gun in a threatening manner</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>120 Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Alan Buford &num;58</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in improper conduct- Arrested and found guilty of Assault a misdemeanor of the first degree</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Five Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Donny Bettis &num;1523</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in Improper Conduct- arrested for Domestic violence, disorderly conduct and unlawful restraint. He was found guilty of two misdemeanor offenses</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Ten Day Suspension (Five Days in Abeyance)</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Leonard Moore &num;2032</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arrested and charged with Assault, a misdemeanor of the first degree - Improper procedure- accidental taser discharge on non-threatening civilian- uniform violation</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Five Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Eric Parish &num;2045</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in improper conduct- Became involved in an altercation with a family member and charged with domestic violence- found guilty of violating one count of Aggravated disorderly conduct a misdemeanor of the first degree-Failed to notify the division of the aforementioned incident</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Fifteen Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Monica Phillips</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in improper conduct- Became involved in an altercation with a family member- found guilty of one count of misdemeanor assault-Failed to notify the division of the aforementioned incident</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Fifteen Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Tommie Griffin &num;684</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in improper conduct- Arrested and charged with Assault- found guilty of criminal Mischief- Failed to notify the Division of Police</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Two Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Theresa Cavett &num;2399</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in Improper Conduct- Arrested for Felony stalking and found guilty of Menacing by Stalking and Telecommunications Harassment, both misdemeanors of the first degree</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Twenty Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Earl Holcomb</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Guilty of corruption of a minor for misconduct with a juvenile girl</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>90 Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Michael Herrin</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Guilty of Assault, menacing, and having a weapon while intoxicated. He got in a confrontation while intoxicated, put a gun to an individual's throat, and threatened him.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>173 Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>William J. Johnson &num;1552</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in Improper Conduct- Arrested and found guilty of operating a vehicle under the influence of alcohol- Plead guilty to OVI misdemeanor of the first degree</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Seven Day Suspension (Three Days in Abeyance)</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Alex Parente &num;1221</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in Improper conduct- arrested for a felony of the fifth degree and plead guilty to a misdemeanor of the first degree - unauthorized use of property</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Five Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Valerie White &num;1928</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in Inappropriate Conduct-Shoplifting-Found guilty of Theft, a misdemeanor of the first degree</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Fifteen Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Paul Beckwith &num;1047</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in Improper Conduct &ndash; Found Guilty of violating one count of physical control of vehicle while under the influence, a misdemeanor of the first degree</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Ten Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Donnie Hooks &num;525</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in Improper Conduct- Completed diversion program and admitted guilt of several felony theft offenses- engaged in improper procedure- failure to notify proper command staff which resulted in unfavorable publicity to the Division that reasonably tends to diminish the esteem of the Division of Police</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Thirty Day Suspension with last chance agreement</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Andrea Viccaro &num;1747</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in Improper Conduct- Received unauthorized information via the Ohio Law Enforcement Gateway- Found guilty of Unauthorized use of property, a misdemeanor of the first degree</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Ten Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Demond Moss &num;1243</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Inappropriate conduct- Positive random drug/alcohol test for marijuana while on duty</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Twelve Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Kevin Smith &num;1622</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Inappropriate Conduct- Positive random drug/alcohol test for marijuana while on duty</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Fifteen Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Dale Fegueson</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Charged with several counts of driving under the influence of alcohol, becoming involved in an accident, feeling the scene and eluding the police.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>60 Day Suspension</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Margaret Sudy &num;9939</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Inappropriate Conduct- Positive random drug/alcohol test - Provided false information on the Division of Police Personal History Statement</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Five Day Suspension (Two Days in Abeyance)</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Ronald James Jr. &num;928</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Engaged in Improper Conduct- Arrested and found guilty of disorderly conduct</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Ten Day Suspension (Five Days in Abeyance)</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>Although no two cases are alike, the City must properly consider the past discipline it has imposed on other officers to make sure it incorporates fairness to all parties. The facts regarding each of these cases above does not reflect what, if any treatment was received by any of these officers. Officer Hannah's extensive involvement in AA, counseling, and fulfilling all other requests of the Division, Employees Assistance Unit, Medical Unit, and the Common Pleas Court support the fact that this alcohol induced incident was isolated and will not happen again in the future. She has not drunk for over two years since this incident with Richardson took place. Hannah went back to work on restricted duty for eight months with no complaints or inability to perform her job. Officer Hannah has been deemed fit for duty by two separate doctors and completed the treatment plan recommended by the Employee's Assistance Unit. She is deserving of the same treatment and discipline other officers have faced for similar or more severe acts of misconduct and were able to keep their jobs. Officer Hannah does not ask for special treatment; she is only asking for equal treatment</p>
<p><i><b>Position of the CPPA.</b></i> The termination of Officer Hannah violates the just cause mandate of the CBA. Hannah has accepted responsibility for her improper actions on March 11, 2012 and sought extensive treatment. Other officers who committed more egregious and violent acts did not jump through the same hoops that Hannah has to prove that she is fit for duty and this will never happen again. Those officers received suspensions from duty to correct their behavior and Officer Hannah should have been awarded the same opportunity, especially considering her significant mitigating factors. Hannah received inconsistent discipline from past cases of the same or similar conduct and this disparity must be corrected to promote equal treatment in the workplace.</p>
<p>The role of the arbitrator is to determine whether or not the discipline imposed on the officers comports with the concept of &ldquo;just cause.&rdquo; It is the position of the CPPA that the penalty suffered by Hannah was not justified by the seriousness of the offense. As a result, the CPPA is asking for this grievance to be sustained based on the totality of the evidence showing Hannah was not terminated for just cause. The CPPA is requesting that Hannah be restored to duty with all benefits, receive a suspension for her improper conduct, and be awarded any other relief this arbitrator deems appropriate.</p>
<p><i>A. The finding of guilt and termination of Hannah did not comply with the just cause standard of the CBA</i>. Terminating an employee should be the last option an employer faces when determining what discipline is appropriate. Adequate efforts must be taken to allow the employee to correct his or her inappropriate behavior before making such a harsh decision. Discharge is the ultimate penalty with respect to an employee's relationship with his or her employer, having been often aptly referred to as &ldquo;economic capital punishment&rdquo;. &lsqb;Citation omitted here.&rsqb;</p>
<p>Arbitrator Sergent discussed overturning an employer's decision to terminate an employee:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">In analyzing the question of whether discharge is an appropriate penalty arbitrators generally agree that where proof of serious misconduct has been established the decision as to the proper penalty is a matter that lies within the discretion of Management and ordinarily should not be disturbed. However, some limited arbitral review of the penalty is not only proper but also necessary in order to assure adherence to a fundamental precept of just cause, which is fairness.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;disciplinary penalties should be designed to meet the needs of the Company in maintaining discipline and safe and orderly operations. Thus, penalties should be designed so as not to be solely punitive, but to gain assurance that the conduct will not be repeated.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i>American Airlines</i>, 116 LA 161, 165-166 (Sergent, 2001).</p>
<p>The termination of Officer Hannah in this case violates the just cause mandate of Article IV of the Agreement. &lsqb;Article IV, (e) appears in relevant part above at 4.&rsqb; All discipline administered by the City must comport with the standards of &ldquo;just cause.&rdquo; Officer Hannah does not deny her involvement in the acts that ultimately led to her criminal charges on March 11, 2012 but she does argue that the discipline imposed on her does not comport with the concept of &ldquo;just cause.&rdquo; The just cause standard requires clear proof that the penalty imposed is warranted under the circumstances presented. Therefore, it is the City's burden to prove by clear and convincing evidence that Officer Hannah's termination was justified under the circumstances presented. It is the position of the CPPA that the penalty suffered was not justified by the seriousness of her offense in combination with her extensive mitigating circumstances. The City did not meet its burden of proving by clear and convincing evidence that Officer Hannah poses any risk if she were to return to the Division or that her off-duty action on March 11, 2012 relates to her ability to perform the responsibilities required in her job.</p>
<p>The evidence does not support the City's contention of extreme wrongdoing to support termination. Richardson suffered only very minor injuries and he admitted in part that he provoked Hannah by ignoring her and smirking when she was confronting him about his infidelity. Richardson's extensive criminal history, coupled with Officer Hannah's extensive abuse history, should be considered when determining the extent of the wrongdoing of her off-duty actions. In <i>Arvin Industries</i>, 96 LA 1185 (Volz, 1991), the arbitrator held that:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Under the just cause standard for disciplinary action the Company had two burdens: one, show that &lsqb;the employee&rsqb; committed the disciplinary offense with which he was charged &hellip; and two, if this showing is made, to establish that the penalty of the discharge was justified by the seriousness of the offense.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip; A violation of a reasonable disciplinary rule constitutes just cause for discipline but the amount thereof is to be determined by the usual standard of comparing the circumstances in aggravation with those in mitigation.</p></blockquote>
<p>Arbitrator Volz listed four mitigating circumstances: (1) it was the employee's first offense; (2) other employees found to have committed the same or similar violations were less severely penalized; (3) the penalty went directly to discharge without the use of some intervening measure, such as a warning or suspension; and (4) the Company's Drug and Alcohol Policy commonly recognizes the use of rehabilitation and seems to favor it in the usual case. The aggravating factors were that the employee knew the policy against possessing alcohol on company property and knowingly violated it. Nevertheless, the arbitrator concluded that while discipline was warranted the discharge was too severe. The discharge was set aside and the employee was reinstated to his former job.</p>
<p>Officer Hannah has no history of serious discipline with the Division throughout her eleven years. Her awards, commendations, and performance evaluations set her apart from the average officer on the force. Even though the City issued an intervening measure of rehabilitation, it failed to consider Hannah's ultimate success in that rehabilitation when determining her punishment. If the City wanted to terminate Hannah for the March 11, 2012 incident, then why did they have her go through treatment and rejoin the Division for months prior to her termination? The City was aware that Hannah's actions stemmed from her problem with alcoholism and depression after the death of a close family member. Her actions on March 11, 2012 were not a clear and sober reflection of her character.</p>
<p>Even after successfully completing a tremendous amount of counseling and rehabilitation, the City failed to properly consider the fact she had done everything within her power to make right what she had done wrong on March 11th. Hannah does not contend that some discipline is warranted here, but argues that she should be reinstated to her former job based on the past disciplinary actions of the City subject to a suspension from duty.</p>
<p>In <i>CPPA and the City of Cleveland</i>, 53 390 00015 93 (Kasper, 1993), the Arbitrator stated the following with regard to the &ldquo;just cause standard&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">That standard is approached differently by different readers, but in circumstances like this it is ordinarily necessary for the nature and severity of the discipline to be determined by the City so that it is fair, reasonable, and appropriate to its purposes and the specific circumstances. The severity of the discipline must be rational, in the common sense that it must &ldquo;fit the crime,&rdquo; and in accordance with the fault of the offender. Discipline which is otherwise, boarders on the ineffective, capricious, and spiteful; it is improper under the Contract.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">In other words, the issue is not whether the City has the &ldquo;authority,&rdquo; but rather whether it exercised its legitimate authority in a proper manner. Just cause requires that the City after its fair analysis of all the facts, determine for itself, using proper standards, the appropriate discipline under the Contract.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>
<p>After measuring the facts and circumstances of the case with the City's discipline, Arbitrator Kasper upheld the finding of guilt but modified the punishment for not complying with the &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; standard. Here, the termination of Hannah was not fair and reasonable based upon all the relevant material facts and circumstances. Her termination should be reversed or modified in accordance with the &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; standard because it was not fair, reasonable, or appropriate. Her punishment did not &ldquo;fit the crime&rdquo; of her misconduct when comparing it to that of other Cleveland Police Officers described above. Other officers, most commonly male officers, committed domestic violence, violent assaults, discharged their weapon while intoxicated, got in physical altercations while intoxicated, and caused significantly more serious injuries than those of Richardson. Hannah was not provided with a fair analysis of the facts when determining a proper punishment. Richardson was repeatedly adamant about not even pressing criminal charges against Hannah. Only under the threat of parole violation, was the prosecution able to obtain his testimony and ultimately a misdemeanor conviction.</p>
<p>Under the terms of the Agreement, the arbitrator has the legal duty to reach a decision on whether the discipline of the officer comports with the concept of &ldquo;just cause.&rdquo; A review of discipline under &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; involves more than just a determination of whether or not the employee should have been disciplined, but also the duty to determine if the punishment is just and reasonable under the facts of the case. Recently in <i>City of Cleveland and CPPA</i>, No. 53 390 00330 12 (Mancini, 2013), the arbitrator held the &ldquo;just cause standard requires clear proof that an employee has committed a disciplinary offense and that the penalty imposed is warranted under the circumstances presented.&rdquo; In Cleveland Patrol Officer Kirby's termination grievance for excessive force in 2001, the City argued that the termination fit the just cause mandate because Kirby &ldquo;used excessive force and failed to follow proper reporting procedures relative to the use of force.&rdquo; (UX 1, p2) The Union argued that his conduct paled in comparison to conduct the City has determined does not warrant termination. The City argued that termination was proper because the grievant had a disciplinary history and the City had taken previous attempts to instruct and correct the grievant's behavior. The grievant's employment record was severely marred by prior discipline for instances of lack of restraint and improper police protocol. Arbitrator Johnson concluded that the grievant did use excessive force and even after considering the grievant's history, she ultimately concluded termination was not justified and he was reinstated to duty without back pay.</p>
<p>Patrol Officer Scott Marek's grievance for termination after committing an off duty assault had his discharge reversed by Arbitrator Skulina (JX 3, pp45-46). Arbitrator Skulina reviewed the past disciplinary cases of other City of Cleveland Officers when evaluating whether to reinstate the grievant. The grievant was found guilty of assault against his stepson. Specifically, he slapped the child so hard that it left a bruise on his face in the form of an entire hand print. Arbitrator Skulina reinstated him to duty without back pay. The arbitrator found the grievant to be remorseful and that his work record was good to excellent. &ldquo;Just cause incorporated fairness &hellip; and a corrective feature that should redirect the employee and also let other employees know the bounds of the employer's understanding on its management rights.&rdquo; The termination of Officer Marek was inconsistent with past discipline imposed by the City and therefore violated the just cause mandate of the CBA.</p>
<p>Officer Michele Pettry was involved in a confrontation with a worker at a cafeteria at her child's school and punched the woman in the face, causing severe facial bruising and injuries (JX 3, p45). The grievant was convicted of a misdemeanor assault. Arbitrator Barker reinstated her to duty but did not award her back pay. Patrol Officer Noah Jones, while on duty, threatened a young girl on a school bus with &ldquo;cutting her tongue out with a pen knife if the kid didn't quiet down (JX 3, p47). It was alleged that he brought the knife out of his key chain, put it towards the girl's face and cursed at her stating &ldquo;shut up or I'll cut your fucking tongue.&rdquo; (<i>Id</i>.) Arbitrator Barker found the 100-day suspension to be excessive in light of other discipline administered and reduced the suspension to 30 days. The disciplinary comparisons of the Officers listed above for assaults, domestic violence, theft, felony offense, menacing, felonious assault, and other misdemeanor offenses proves that Hannah's termination was for circumstances equal to or much less severe than all of these other officers that were punished but still retained their employment.</p>
<p>Cleveland Police Officer Flannery also had his discharge for off-duty conduct recently overturned by Arbitrator James Mancini. <i>City of Cleveland and CPPA</i>, No. 53 390 00364 12 (UX 5). Officer Flannery engaged in an off-duty altercation with two bar patrons involving his service weapon and failed to report the altercation. There were allegations that he threatened patrons with his weapon while under the influence of alcohol. In regards to disproportional discipline, Arbitrator Mancini stated:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">It is widely recognized arbitrable principle that under the just cause standard the enforcement of rules and assessment of discipline must be exercised in a consistent manner. That is, all employees who engage in the same type of misconduct must be treated essentially the same unless a reasonable basis exists for variations in the kind of punishment.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">It was established that officers like the Grievant who engaged in inappropriate off-duty conduct while under the influence of alcohol were not subjected to being terminated by the City.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">(<i>Id</i>. at 21, 25). The Arbitrator ultimately held that Officer Flannery's termination was disproportional to past disciplinary cases involving similar or even more egregious misconduct by other officers who were permitted to keep their jobs. (<i>Id</i>. at 21). Due to alcohol's clear role in Flannery's off-duty conduct, the arbitrator took into account that Flannery had successfully completed treatment for his alcoholism and was determined fit for duty by Dr. Francis McCafferty's psychiatric evaluation. (<i>Id</i>. at 25). Officer Flannery was ultimately reinstated to duty but was not awarded back wages due to his misconduct.</p>
<p>Officer Hannah's situation is very similar to that of Flannery. She was under the influence of alcohol in an off-duty setting and became involved in a physical altercation. It has been well established that other officers who engaged in off-duty conduct while under the influence of alcohol were not subjected to the same termination that Hannah received. There was not just cause to terminate Hannah in this case and she should be reinstated to duty based on her mitigating factors, notable service record, remorse, and to promote equality and fairness in discipline disbursed in the Division.</p>
<p>Terminating Hannah for her off-duty conduct violates the long-standing precedent that requires an employer to tie conduct outside of the workplace to the duties of the employee. The employer has the burden of proof for off-duty misconduct. The employer must prove the nexus &ldquo;between the employee's conduct and the Employer's business must be real, clear and not simply speculative&rdquo;. 2010 AAA LEXIS 887 (AAA 2010). Arbitrator Tanzman considered the following factors when determining the employer did not have just cause to discipline the officer/employee: (1) that the Grievant admitted his wrong actions; (2) the Grievant had no poor work or attendance record; (3) the Grievant's actions did not affect his work; (4) and there were no Prosecutorial charges. 2010 AAA LEXIS 887, 49-50 (AAA 2010).</p>
<p>Officer Hannah has also admitted her actions, admitted that they were wrong, has done everything possible to correct those actions, had a positive work record, provided ample testimony that her actions did not affect her work, and provided ample testimony and exhibits that showed no sign that she would not be able to perform the duties of her job. Although prosecutorial charges were brought in her case, it was clear the charges were brought against the desires of the victim. The fact that Hannah's off-duty actions and personal issues never impacted her work with the Department is important to show that she was not attempting to slack on her official duties to perform this improper conduct. She treated her job with the respect it required every day. Her supervisors stated that even after this event occurred, Hannah continued to go above and beyond what was required of her, on duty and through her treatment.</p>
<p>The City failed to establish a proper nexus linking her off-duty personal breakdown to any affect it had on her at the job. She did not have excessive force complaints, or missed time from work, was not insubordinate, lazy, or otherwise ever incompetent at her job. Although her off-duty conduct was clearly improper, the discipline she received was not administered in a manner similar to the disciplinary action taken against other officers for similar violations within the City of Cleveland or other police departments for an officer's unrelated off-duty conduct under the influence of alcohol.</p>
<p><i>B. The termination of Officer Hannah is arbitrary, capricious, and disparate in violation of the just cause mandate of Article IV</i>. When comparing the actions of Officer Hannah with the actions of other police officers described above, it is apparent that other officers have engaged in more egregious conduct, have been found guilty of more serious crimes, and have still been afforded the opportunity to keep their jobs. Taking the actions of Hannah, combined with her extensive mitigating factors and treatment, her termination is clearly arbitrary and disparate. It is well established that &ldquo;the degree of the penalty should be in keeping with the seriousness of the offense.&rdquo; <i>Capital Airlines</i>, 25 LA 13, 16 (Stowe, 1955). The party's Agreement stated that the arbitrator has the inherent authority to modify penalties that are found to be improper or too severe. In doing so, the arbitrator should take into consideration: (1) the facts and circumstances surrounding the officer's conduct, (2) the service and background as a member of the Cleveland Police Department, and (3) whether the measure of discipline appears to be punitive in purpose and effect, or corrective in its application.</p>
<p>In <i>City of Cleveland and Fraternal Order of Police</i>, Lodge No. 8, 53 390 0565 89 (Dworkin, 1989), the Arbitrator held:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">The principal task of the Arbitrator is to determine whether the grievant was terminated for just cause. The standard of &lsquo;just cause&rsquo; requires that the action taken by management is supported by the evidence, and consistent with the applicable terms of the agreement. In essence, the discharge action must be deemed fair and reasonable, based on all relevant and material facts and circumstances. According to this standard the decision to discipline and the penalty imposed must take into consideration the grievant's service and background as a member of the Cleveland Police Department, and whether the measure of discipline appears to be punitive in purpose and effect, or corrective in its application.</p></blockquote>
<p>The arbitrator ultimately held that based on the facts and circumstances surrounding the case and the discharged individual, the discipline given was not warranted and was amended accordingly. The City failed to properly take into account Hannah's impressive background and commitment to rehabilitation when imposing her discipline in this case. Termination here was punitive because the City ignored all efforts that Hannah made to correct her improper behavior.</p>
<p>It must be recognized that discharge and suspension are separate, distinct penalties. Suspensions are a corrective measure designed to rehabilitate a miscreant employee, to restore him to acceptable levels of production and/or behavior. Discharge, on the other hand is the extreme severance of the employment relationship. &lsqb;Citation omitted here.&rsqb;</p>
<p>Arbitrator Skulina held:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">I am of the opinion that discharge is tantamount to economic capital punishment. The employee not only loses the job in issue, but &lsqb;also&rsqb;, carries a permanent stigma for future hires. The evidential burden is alleviated to the extent that in the arbitral setting, the rules of evidence are not stringently followed. An employer has a dual burden of proof. Not only must a disciplinary breach be proven beyond a reasonable doubt, but also, it must be proved that just cause has been established to warrant the maximum sanction.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">The significance is that the working environment is entitled to an equilibrium in the application of the employer's justice. Thus, this history of previous decisions is appropriate. The fact that previous Safety Directors were involved does not matter. Continuity and evenhandedness must be maintained by the employer in the public sector, even after changes in the Administration.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i>CPPA and the City of Cleveland</i>, 53 390 00579 96. There are numerous other grievances in further support of the principal that the nature and degree of discipline administered must meet the just cause standard: <i>City of Louisville</i>, 94 LA 243 (Volz, 1989)(Although discipline was warranted under &ldquo;just cause,&rdquo; discharge was reduced to suspension after finding it was unreasonable under the circumstances); <i>State of Ohio</i>, 97 LA 1206 (Rivera, 1991)(While there was just cause for discipline, suspension reduced for sleeping on the job); <i>City of El Paso</i>, 95 LA 201 (Cohen, 1990)(Although just cause existed to discipline officer for using excessive force, suspension reduced from 132 to 88 days); <i>Ohio Dept. of Transportation</i>, 95 LA 1291 (Dworkin, 1990)(Discharge for absenteeism is too harsh under just cause standard, reduced to suspension).</p>
<p>The CPPA has cited numerous past cases where arbitrators have reduced penalties after finding there was not just cause to suspend or terminate. The City's decision to terminate Officer Hannah failed to properly consider the facts of the case, the mitigating factors, Richardson's consistent desire to not pursue criminal charges, her employment history, her commitment to treatment, her remorse and ignored past disciplinary cases and arbitration awards. The City is unable to distinguish Hannah's actions from those of other officers who committed the same or worse actions and were permitted to keep their positions, most specifically male officers charged with domestic violence. The City's discharge of Hannah is not only unreasonable considering the facts and circumstances of the case, but it is also disparate when considering other discipline administered by the City of Cleveland. For the reasons argued herein and at the disciplinary hearing, incorporated herein by reference, Hannah's termination was in violation of the just cause mandate of Article IV of the Agreement.</p>
<p><i><b>Conclusion.</b></i> Based upon the foregoing arguments, Cleveland Police Officer Shani Hannah should have been disciplined for her actions on March 11, 2012 but the City did not have just cause to terminate her employment. When comparing her actions to those of her fellow officers, it is clear that a suspension from duty would adequately set an example for others, properly reflect the severity of her actions, and be equivalent with past discipline given to similar and ever more violent offenses. This was a single disparate act under the influence of alcohol. It was the culmination of the depression Hannah was dealing with after the death of the caregiver that saved her from a horrible childhood.</p>
<p>After the offense, Hannah has gone through alcohol treatment, counseling, therapy, anger management, and taken advantage of numerous other programs to get her life back on track. Most other officers involved in offenses like hers do not do a fraction of the rehabilitation work that Hannah put in. Her consistent longterm effort shows her commitment to rejoining the Cleveland Police Department. Numerous coworkers from her past and present testified that she was an asset to the City of Cleveland and that they had no reservations about her return to work. Officer Hannah had an unblemished 11-year record with the City. She has received commendations, awards, and above average evaluations throughout her career. This off-duty personal incident was not a reflection of how Officer Hannah performs at work.</p>
<p>Based on the many examples of other officers who were involved in off-duty violent incidents, domestic violence, assault, and other criminal acts, it is apparent that termination of Officer Hannah was too extreme. The City failed to present any testimony or evidence that Hannah is at risk to ever do something like this again or had ever acted this way in the past. In fact all of the testimony and evidence provided at the hearing concludes that Officer Hannah is fit, ready, and able to return to the force as a better officer, mother, and citizen of Cleveland. Officer Hannah should be reinstated to duty, subject to a suspension the Arbitrator feels is appropriate based on the facts and suspensions given to other officers for similar acts. Hannah should be reinstated to duty, awarded back pay, and be restored of all his lost benefits as a result of the improper termination.</p>
<p>To not grant the relief requested, is to ignore the unrefuted history of discipline in the Cleveland Division Police. In the hearing thereof, the CPPA presented City records, disciplinary records, arbitrator awards, post hearing briefs with exhibits, past termination cases, and testimony, all of which document a history of conduct and a discipline history that cannot be ignored. The City has elected not to terminate in many cases involving more egregious conduct than that of Officer Hannah. Many officers that have been charged with criminal felonies and misdemeanors have been permitted to retain their employment with the City. Additionally, third party arbitrators in recent and past arbitration awards have reversed terminations regarding officers who have engaged in more egregious conduct that that of Hannah.</p>
<p>If the just cause standard is to have any meaning, if proportionality is to have any meaning, if equal treatment is to have any meaning, and if past arbitrator awards are to have any affect, then Officer Hannah must be reinstated subject to a suspension from duty, together with back pay and restoration of all lost benefits.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Discussion</b></h4>
<p>As set forth above, the issue is whether the City had just cause to terminate Grievant Shani Hannah, and if not, what is the appropriate remedy?</p>
<p><i><b>Facts</b></i>. There is little dispute with respect to the relevant facts. At the time of the incident, Officer Hannah had served eleven years as a police officer for the City. She had an above average record based on her performance evaluations from the beginning of her career in 2001. Her 2002 evaluation (UX 9) included the following: &ldquo;Officer Hannah is progressing at an adequate rate. Her attitude and appearance are excellent&hellip;. This officer shows no signs of deficiencies at this stage &hellip;.&rdquo; In 2004, her evaluation included the following: &ldquo;Officer Hannah &num;1778 is a dependable and reliable veteran officer who often takes on additional duties for the good of the unit. Would make a good supervisor.&rdquo; In 2010, her &ldquo;customer service&rdquo; rating was 4.5/5; &ldquo;total quality of work&rdquo; was rated 4.9/5; and &ldquo;dependability&rdquo; rated 4.7/5. In October 2010, she was awarded a Distinguished Service Medal for her involvement in the apprehension of an armed and dangerous suspect. In short, she had an exemplary record of service up to that point.</p>
<p>About that time she met Mr. Richardson, son of a retired Cleveland Police Officer, and at some point he moved into her apartment. Hannah testified that at that time she was not aware of Richardson's extensive criminal record which included at least five years in prison. At some point, Hannah did become aware of at least some of Richardson's criminal background, but she continued to allow him to live with her. It was apparently during this period that Hannah began to develop an alcohol dependency. In November 2011, about a year after meeting Richardson, Hannah's grandmother died. Her grandmother had been Hannah's primary care giver as a teenager because both Hannah's parents were addicted to cocaine and took no responsibility for her or her younger siblings. Her grandmother's death was a severe blow. Hannah's alcohol dependency grew worse.</p>
<p>About that time Hannah also became aware that although Richardson continued to live with her, he was pursuing relationships with other women. In January 2012, the matter apparently came to a head while Hannah and Richardson were at the home of Richardson's parents. An argument ensued coupled with heavy drinking. The argument and continued through the drive back to Hannah's apartment. Once there, the argument continued to escalate and the Cleveland Police Department was summoned by the local security officer. When they arrived, she threatened suicide. The officers transported her to the hospital for psychiatric evaluation and to detoxify. She remained hospitalized for three days. Hospital staff recommended grief counseling and alcohol treatment. However, she continued to use alcohol excessively until the incident that led to her termination some six weeks later.</p>
<p>The events of the March 11, 2012, off-duty incident for which Patrol Officer Hannah was terminated, are not at all in dispute. Sometime that evening Hannah and Richardson were drinking and got into an argument about Richardson's seeing other women. Hannah had ordered him to move his things out of her home. All of his belongings were apparently in bags and boxes by her apartment door. The dispute escalated and lasted for several hours. Richardson threatened to report Hannah's relationship with him &ndash; a convicted felon &ndash; to her supervisors and thereby put her job in jeopardy. Hannah apparently made equally provoking remarks. About 10 pm, the dispute turned physical. Hannah became enraged and began poking Richardson with two knives apparently in an effort to get him out of her apartment. She inflicted knife wounds, later described by medial staff as superficial, on his hand and leg. Five stitches were required to close one of the wounds.</p>
<p>Hannah then left and police later found her in her car not far from her apartment. When she was located by police, she had a cord wrapped around her neck and it was attached to the ceiling of the car in an apparent suicide attempt.</p>
<p>Hannah was arrested by Internal Affairs officers, charged with felonious assault, and relieved from duty. On March 27, 2012, the Cuyahoga County Grand Jury indicted Hannah for felonious assault and first degree misdemeanor assault. The Cuyahoga County Prosecutor's office later dropped the felonious assault charge and on July 11, 2012, Hannah pled guilty to first degree misdemeanor assault. This is significant because had she been convicted of a felony, she would have been permanently disqualified from being a police officer. Officer Hannah was required to serve 12 months of probation, perform 25 hours of community service, submit to random drug testing, and successfully complete an anger-management program. A six-month jail sentence was suspended.</p>
<p>Officer Hannah effectively completed all of the required counseling and testified that she had not had any alcohol whatsoever since the night of the incident on March 11, 2012. (See for example CX 10, Glenbeigh Certificate of Completion with respect to Anger Management and Alcohol Treatment.) She also successfully completed her court established probation. It is particularly notable that Hannah was returned to work following her July 2012 Court appearance. The City returned her service weapon and for eight months, until just prior to her disciplinary hearing, she worked in restricted duty status. Third District Detective Stephanie Hunter testified at Grievant's disciplinary hearing that Grievant has been &ldquo;a really good worker. I mean, she works hard, I mean, and she's there every day.&rdquo; (JX 3, Tr68) Hunter testified that Hannah does &ldquo;have it together&rdquo; and &ldquo;has no problem being a police officer.&rdquo; (<i>Id</i>. at 69) There were apparently no complaints about Grievant's performance for the eight months she worked prior to her termination.</p>
<p><i><b>Analysis</b></i>. Where, as here, Grievant's action was particularly egregious &ndash; assaulting another person with a knife &ndash; it is tempting to rush to judgment concerning the application &ldquo;industrial capital punishment&rdquo;. The fact is that Officer Hanna did violate the Ohio Revised Code, the Ordinances of the City of Cleveland, the Rules of the Department of Public Safety and the Civil Service Commission. Accordingly, it was clearly appropriate for Public Safety Director Flask to state in his letter of termination that Grievant's conduct &ldquo;raises serious concern about your fitness to continue employment with the Cleveland Division of Police.&rdquo; (JX 2, p13) On the face of the matter, then, discharge does not seem unreasonable.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the standard by which this matter must be assessed is not limited to the single question of whether Grievant behaved as charged. To be sure, there is no question about that. Rather, however, the arbitrator is compelled by the Agreement to assess whether her discharge was proper on the basis of &ldquo;just cause&rdquo;. Proving that an employee actually committed the offense with which he or she is charged is obviously a &ldquo;necessary condition&rdquo; for just cause but it is hardly a &ldquo;sufficient condition&rdquo;. In addition to proving that the offense occurred, &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; requires other elements to show that discharge is appropriate under all the circumstances of the case. Among such elements that are relevant here are clear evidence that (1) there has not been disparate treatment in the application of disciplinary action and (2) the employer has carefully considered all possible mitigating circumstances.</p>
<p><i>Disparate treatment</i>. During Grievant's disciplinary hearing on April 18, 2013, the Union presented evidence regarding the treatment of other police officers employed by the Division of Police who had assaulted family members and others in off-duty situations. Inasmuch as the transcript of that proceeding was entered into evidence here (JX 3), such evidence is also part of the record here.</p>
<p>Three cases involving domestic altercations are particularly relevant. In the first, Officer Eric Roberts was initially charged with felony domestic violence and felonious assault, just as the Grievant here had been charged. Officer Roberts later pled guilty to a reduced charge of disorderly conduct. The photos of his victim (UX 14, pp13-23) show severe facial bruising, lacerations, and a black eye. Officer Robert Sweany inflicted numerous bruises on his teenaged daughter's face, arms, neck, and back based on photos of her (UX 14, pp40-56). She was sent home from school with a black eye. He was criminally prosecuted for domestic violence but plead guilty to a reduced charge and was able to keep his job. Officer Christopher Lane punched his wife in the face causing two black eyes and a bruised lip based on her photos (UX 14, pp7-12). Officer Lane was charged with domestic violence but the charges were reduced to disorderly conduct and he was permitted to keep his job.</p>
<p>Three additional cases involving domestic disturbances are also relevant. Officer Bettis was arrested for domestic violence disorderly conduct and unlawful restraint. He was found guilty of two misdemeanor offenses. Officer Eric Parish became involved in an altercation with a family member and was charged with domestic violence &ndash; a felony. He was found guilty of violating one count of aggravated disorderly conduct, a misdemeanor of the first degree. Officer Monica Phillips also became involved in an altercation with a family member and was found guilty of one count of misdemeanor assault.</p>
<p>The Union introduced ten other cases involving on- and off-duty assault by Cleveland police officers. They were fully described in the Union's brief. (See above at 32-37.) A common occurrence was that more serious felony charges were reduced to misdemeanors. One case in particular, that of Officer Kiggins, is typical. Kiggins was indicted on two counts of felonious assault for firing his gun in a threatening manner. He pled guilty to two counts of aggravated menacing, a misdemeanor of the first degree and kept his job.</p>
<p>In addition to the above, the Union also presented several cases where officers charged with excessive force or assault were reinstated by arbitrators after they had been terminated. Officer Kirby was reinstated without back pay following his termination for use of excessive force (UX 1 &ndash; AAA Case &num;53 390 00166 01, Johnson, Arb., p8). Officer Marek was reinstated without back pay after he assaulted his step son by slapping him on the face leaving his hand print on the boy. Marek had been convicted of first degree misdemeanor assault, the identical charge to which Grievant pled no contest (UX 1 &ndash; AAA Case &num;53 390 00549 96, Skulina, Arb., p4). Officer Pettry was reinstated without back pay after she was found guilty of misdemeanor assault, the same charge to which Grievant pled no contest here (UX 1 &ndash; AAA Case &num;53 390 00434 97, Barker, Arb. p8). In all of these cases, the arbitrators found that discharge was excessive when compared with the resolution of other similar cases by the Employer.</p>
<p>In response to these cases, the City attempted to draw a distinction between them and the Grievant's behavior here. The City noted in its brief that Grievant &ldquo;displayed a pattern of poor decision-making and egregious conduct over an extended period of time&rdquo;. The City contends this distinguishes this case from past cases in which the grievants were reinstated by an arbitrator after the arbitrator found their transgression had occurred due to momentary bad judgment. Moreover, the City sees Hannah's actions as more egregious and severe than those of past officers apparently because of her use of a knife.</p>
<p>There can be little dispute that Hannah did display a pattern of poor decision making beginning with her developing a relationship with Mr. Richardson and becoming dependent on alcohol. Hannah would, herself, no doubt agree with that assessment. The arbitrator must first note, however, that Hannah was not discharged for displaying a pattern of &ldquo;poor decision-making&rdquo;. Rather, all five specifications in her termination letter related to the events of March 11, 2012, and what happened thereafter. None mentioned &ldquo;poor decision making.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Second, based on the arbitrator's careful review of the actual damage done to victims, Richardson was no worse off than many of those suffering broken noses, battered heads, and the like. It is important to remember that most of the cases related to mature men physically beating women or young teens. Moreover, the critical indicator for the arbitrator must be the objective standard of the charge for which the police officer was convicted. There are numerous cases in the record of officers who were either reinstated or who were never terminated in the first place, who, contrary to the City's claim, were convicted of a first-degree misdemeanor, specifically assault &ndash; a criminal offense. This is precisely the charge to which Grievant pled no contest.</p>
<p>Moreover, this was Grievant's first offense. This is relevant because, according to Union witness, retired Sergeant Medlea, some of the officers who were reinstated or not terminated at all have been repeat offenders (Tr 152). Thus, even if their offenses were no worse than Grievant's, one would expect more severe punishment to follow.</p>
<p>The City also tried to distinguish the domestic assault cases by noting that the victim did not want to go forward with the prosecution of the case or agreed to an amendment of the charges to a disorderly conduct because the spouse (i.e. police officer) would get fired. Here, Richardson also expressed a reluctance to testify but did so after he was threatened with parole violations and because Grievant refused to compensate him for his silence. The arbitrator is not persuaded that the motives of victims are at all relevant.</p>
<p>After a careful consideration of the prior cases presented by the Union, the arbitrator is persuaded that the Union has presented a prima facie case that there was disparate treatment of the Grievant. The failure of the City to rebut this evidence with examples of terminated officers whose behavior was comparable to Grievant's compels the arbitrator to conclude that there was disparate treatment in Grievant's case.</p>
<p><i>Mitigating circumstances</i>. Although the finding of disparate treatment above is arguably dispositive, the arbitrator has also considered the City's treatment of mitigating circumstances.</p>
<p>There are a number of circumstances that carry considerable weight in this regard. Foremost for the arbitrator is Grievant's record leading up to her downfall &ndash; the period from her hire date through her receiving her Distinguished Service Medal in 2010. Aside from her exemplary record that was summarized above under the discussion of the facts, Grievant had a spotless discipline record. This is remarkable. As the Union noted it its brief, &ldquo;The City did not present any evidence that Officer Hannah ever performed poorly at her job throughout her eleven years with the Division.&rdquo; Moreover, following her March 2012 incident, and the disposi-tion of her criminal assault charge in July 2012, Grievant was returned to duty in a restricted capacity for eight months. Here again, she performed flawlessly.</p>
<p>Secondly, during the period after she returned to work, she was subjected to two different &ldquo;fitness for duty&rdquo; examinations by Dr. McCafferty (UX 11) and by Dr. Faust (UX 12). The Union's brief dealt extensively with both of these. The conclusions are important. Dr. McCafferty stated, in his October 8, 2012, report (at p8),</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">On the basis of current information, Ms. Shani Hannah, in my professional psychiatric opinion with a reasonable degree of medical certitude, is capable of returning to full time duty without restrictions. Her potential for aggressive acting out is low in view of her being in therapy, on medication and in AA. She is in therapy, attending AA meetings, and is motivated to continue abstinence and treatment&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">Ms. Hannah has improved from her prior state of depression and alcohol abuse and is functioning quite adequately presently. There is no change in my opinion. Psychologically she is able to tolerate the stress of working on the streets, which she as demonstrated previously.</p>
<p class="continued">There is no psychiatric contraindication to Ms. Hannah returning to full time duty without restrictions. It would be helpful for her, however, to continue with therapy with her counselor, he psychiatrist and in the AA program.</p></blockquote>
<p>Dr. Faust, in his March 3, 2013, report is equally supportive of Ms. Hannah's fitness to return to full duty (at p10):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&hellip; Since that time &lsqb;March 2012&rsqb;, she has demonstrated dramatic improvement into her insight and adherence to healthier behaviors and relationships, appears to be internally motivated to continue improving her own physical and emotional health and appears to be genuinely invested and more emotionally available to be involved in her children's personal and academic lives.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;&hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip; &lsqb;O&rsqb;n the basis of the information provided me, and the information gleaned from multiple interviews and psychometric testing, my professional opinion is that Officer Shani Hannah is psychologically fit for full duty and should be considered for return to her previous police duties, contingent on maintenance of her treatment and sobriety.</p></blockquote>
<p>A third mitigating factor is the fact that Grievant Hanna's misbehavior involved off-duty activity. One of the above medical reports marveled at Hanna's capacity to keep her private and professional life as a police officer separate. This simply means that there is even less likelihood that Hanna's work on the streets for the people of Cleveland will be compromised in any way.</p>
<p>Finally, contrary to a statement in the City's brief, Hannah appears to be fully remorseful. She apologized at every opportunity for her behavior. More deeply, on the basis of the fitness-for-duty reports as well as the arbitrator's perception of her at the hearing, she feels even more remorse with respect to allowing herself to slide into the depression and alcohol dependency that led her to her completely anomalous behavior on March 11, 2012. At her disciplinary hearing she said (JX 3, Tr22):</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">What I did was not right and it was definitely not the way it should have been handled, but it happened. I can't take it back. I just want to apologize for it and &hellip; hopefully be able to move forward.</p></blockquote>
<p>In sum, the above mitigating circumstances are substantial and, with all due respect, it appears they did not receive the consideration or weight that they should have when Director Flask made his decision to terminate the Grievant.</p>
<p><i>Continuing concerns</i>. The conclusions and recommendations of Drs. McCafferty and Faust plainly support returning Grievant to full duty, but not without some reservation. Obviously, the recommendations of both contained expectations that Grievant Hannah would continue therapy through the employee assistance plan of the Division of Police and AA attendance. These activities would clearly reduce the potential for Grievant to backslide.</p>
<p>The City's brief, for good reason, noted that Ms. Hannah engaged in a pattern of poor judgment leading to egregious conduct in her personal life. The City has a reasonable concern that such pattern might re-emerge and possibly spill over from her personal life into her professional life. Combined with the reservation implicit in the fitness-for-duty reports, such concerns have led the arbitrator to conclude that certain conditions as outlined in the Remedy, below, should be included in this Award.</p>
<p><i><b>Summary &amp; Conclusion</b></i>. Grievant Hanna was guilty of egregious behavior on the evening of March 11, 2012 which was brought on by great stress in her personal life and a growing dependence on alcohol. Nevertheless her termination was inconstant with the treatment of other Cleveland Police Officers who have committed like offenses. Nor was adequate consideration given to mitigating circumstances before the City reached a decision to terminate her. Accordingly, there was not just cause for the termination of Grievant Hannah on May 22, 2013.</p>
<p><i><b>Remedy</b></i>. Grievant is to be offered immediate reinstatement to her former position as a Patrol Officer for the City's Division of Police. In light of her egregious behavior on March 11, 2012, however, she shall not be awarded any back pay or benefits. Her absence from the City's payroll from the date of her separation (May 22, 2013) until the date she is reinstated shall be recorded as personal leave without compensation or benefits.</p>
<p>In addition, as a condition of Grievant Hanna's continued employment, for the next two years Grievant Hannah shall contact the Employee Assistance Unit at least once each month for counsel concerning her professional and personal life and follow any guidance or referrals the personnel in the Unit prescribe. For the next two years, Grievant Hannah shall make herself available for a reasonable number of random drug and alcohol tests and she shall also attend at least two AA meetings each calendar month and document same to the Employee Assistance Unit. Finally, should Grievant Hannah fail to remain abstinent with respect to alcohol or drugs at any time, <i>on or off duty</i>, within the next two years, she shall be subject to discipline up to and including discharge.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>AWARD</b></h4>
<p>The grievance is sustained in part. Grievant shall be offered immediate reinstatement to her former position as a Patrol Officer. There shall be no back pay. Other conditions of her reinstatement and continued employment are set forth in the discussion of the Remedy, above.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>