<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of a Controversy Between IUE-CWA, Local 89119, Union, And DYN CORP INTERNATIONAL LLC, Employer.</p>
<p>Re: Discharge of Richard Baum.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS NO. 150618-56478-A</p>
<p>January 13, 2016.</p>
<p>Claude Dawson Ames, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ARBITRATOR'S DECISION AND AWARD</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>I. INTRODUCTION</i></b></h4>
<p>This arbitration proceeding arises pursuant to the Collective Bargaining Agreement (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo;) between IUE-CWA, LOCAL 89119 (&ldquo;Union&rdquo;) and DYNCORP INTERNATIONAL LLC (&ldquo;DynCorp&rdquo; or &ldquo;Company&rdquo;), involving the termination of Richard Baum (&ldquo;Grievant&rdquo; or &ldquo;Baum&rdquo;), under which Claude Dawson Ames, Esq. was selected to serve as Arbitrator, and whose Findings, Decision and Award shall be final and binding upon the Parties. This case is being administered under the auspices of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service, Case No. 150618-56478-A. The arbitration hearing was conducted at Reno, Nevada on October 2, 2015. Testimony of witnesses was under oath, however by agreement between the Parties, a stenographic transcript was not taken. Both Parties were afforded full opportunity to present documentary and testimonial evidence and to examine and cross-examine witnesses and for rebuttal. The Parties stipulated that all procedural requirements have been complied with or waived, the matter is properly before the Arbitrator, and that the Arbitrator's notes shall constitute the official record. The Union's and the Company's closing briefs were received on November 17, 2015 and November 16, 2015, respectively. The record was closed by the Arbitrator on November 18, 2015.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>II. STATEMENT OF THE FACTS</i></b></h4>
<p>Grievant Richard Baum was employed by government contractor L-3 Vertex Aerospace in 2014, when that company lost an aircraft maintenance program contract to the Company, DynCorp. The program is the Naval Strike and Air Warfare Center (&ldquo;NSAWC&rdquo;) in Fallon, Nevada and its mission is to support naval pilot training. Baum was offered and accepted employment with the Company as an Aircraft Mechanic-Avionics effective March 26, 2015. The Company's offer states &ldquo;The terms of your employment will be established by&hellip;&rdquo; the CBA between the Company and the Union. (JEx. 5) The Company and the Union entered into a Bridge Agreement effective March 26, 2015, which states that the terms and conditions of the existing CBA between the L-3 Vertex Aerospace and the Union would continue in full force and effect except as to certain modifications. (JEx. 1) Dyn Corp employed approximately 160 aircraft maintenance personnel at the NSAWC site.</p>
<p>For approximately thirteen years prior to 2015, Baum worked for various contractors as an Avionics Mechanic. At one time he was a local union vice president and a shop steward. In 2015 he held nine Collateral Duty Inspector (&ldquo;CDI&rdquo;) certificates, which qualified him to perform inspections &ldquo;as a second set of eyes&rdquo; of the work of his fellow mechanics. The CBA contains an Appendix B which provides that employees can earn hourly incentive pay of up to &dollar;.50/hour for up to three CDIs. (JEx. 12) The qualifications for CDI were for type/model series of F-16, F-18 A-D, Super Hornet E-F/G, E2 and H-60. Baum worked primarily on F-16 and F-18 aircraft. According to a Quality Assurance Representative/Inspector Recommendation/Designation Form of December 2012, the CDIs held by Baum were for F/A-18A/B/C/D Avionics; F/A-18A/B/C/D Ordinance; F/A-18A/B/C/D Corrosion Control; F-16A/B Avionics; F-16A/B Ordinance; F-16A/B Corrosion Control; MH-60S Corrosion Control, Line, and F/A-18E/F Avionics. (UEx. 1) Baum signed the document that indicates, <i>&ldquo;When performing inspections, I am considered to be the direct representative of the Commanding Officer for ensuring safety of flight of the item concerned. I will not permit factors, such as operational desires, maintenance consideration, personal relations&hellip; to modify my judgment. By signing an inspection report, I am certifying upon my own individual responsibility that the work &hellip; has been performed in such a manner that the item is completely safe for flight or use.&rdquo;</i> These CDIs were all obtained following an examination in which Baum qualified as sufficiently knowledgeable to inspect the work of his co-workers. (UEx. 2) A QAR/CDQAR/CDI Brief Form signed by Baum in July 2012 indicates that, &ldquo;Through questioning, the QAM will: a. <i>Ensure candidate is not being persuaded into this position contrary to their will, b. Determine that the candidate feels competent and confident in fulfilling these duties.&rdquo;</i> (JEx. 12) Site Manager William Boykin testified that this is a training document used by the Company. It is part of a larger document titled Initial Quality Assurance Inspector Nomination Form, which was on the Company's website as of the date of the arbitration hearing. (UEx. 2) Further, a Navy document entitled COMNAVAIRFORINST 4790.2B CH-1 indicates that:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><b>7.4.5 Collateral Duty Inspectors (CDIs)</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>NOTE: CDIs shall not inspect their own work and sign as inspector</b>&hellip;<ftnote num="1"><para>Emphasis in original.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">7.4.5.2 QA shall establish minimum qualifications for personnel selected for CDI.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Division officers and the Weapons Officer or the Weapons Department person responsible for QA are responsible for ensuring sufficient qualified personnel are nominated for CDI to comply with required QA inspections during all maintenance activities</i>. <i>Due to the importance and responsibility of duties performed by CDIs, it is imperative division officers and work center supervisors carefully screen all candidates for these assignments</i>&hellip; (JEx. 14)</p></blockquote>
<p>When DynCorp took over the maintenance contract, it instituted a third shift for the mechanics. This changed the shift list and caused Baum to move from Lead on second shift to a non-Lead position on third shift. The lead position pays an hourly premium under the CBA.</p>
<p>On April 6, 2015 Baum provided the Company with a letter addressed to the Quality Assurance Manager<ftnote num="2"><para><quote>QAM.</quote></para></ftnote>, the Phase Supervisor and the Training Coordinator which indicates that &ldquo;&hellip;effective this date, I am dropping my F-16 Avionics CDI Qualification. I request an updated CDI designation letter and change to the Monthly Maintenance Plan&hellip; to reflect this status. I will continue to hold&hellip; the remainder of my multiple qualifications such as F-18A-D Avionics CDI and F-18E-F Avionics CDI. I will continue my support to the &hellip; team as an avionics mechanic on these two platforms as well as work I am assigned to the F-16 under the guidance of a designated CDI.&rdquo; (JEx. 6)</p>
<p>Boykin met with Baum, QAM Jim Campbell, Phase Supervisor Raymond Arvayo and two Union stewards on April 7, 2015. Mr. Boykin's testimony and his internal memo regarding the meeting indicate he asked Baum why he was no longer maintaining his CDI and what issues he was having so that he (Boykin) could possibly help fix the situation. Baum replied, &ldquo;I don't owe you any explanation, my reasons are my own.&rdquo; Boykin advised Baum that his &ldquo;dropping qualifications had a negative impact to the important mission we all play a role in.&rdquo; Baum stated: &ldquo;I don't care to share my reasons if you don't have anything of merit we are finished here.&rdquo; He said he understood Boykin's position and steward Mike Tolzmann stated, &ldquo;Your position is that employees need to maintain qualifications.&rdquo; (JEx. 7)</p>
<p>On April 10, 2015, Baum provided the Company with a letter indicating, &ldquo;I will also drop my F-18E/F avionics CDI&hellip; effective this date&hellip; Rest assured that this action is in no way an indication of lack of support for the&hellip; team. It will rather have the effect of allowing me time to provide my very best effort on my remaining seven collateral duty inspector designations&hellip; I will be more than eager to provide avionics mechanical assistance on F-16A/B and F-18E-G platforms under qualified CDI direction.&rdquo; (JEx. 8)</p>
<p>On April 13, 2015, Mr. Boykin met with Baum, Union steward Jim Lemon and a second steward, along with other management personnel. Boykin's testimony and his internal memo regarding the meeting indicate that he asked Baum if he had had an opportunity to read the Company policy on qualification/certification, to which Baum answered &ldquo;No.&rdquo; Baum was provided a copy of an April 13, 2015 policy and addressed to All Employees with a Subject of Qualifications/Certifications, that states: <i>&ldquo;This is one of many policies that will be issued over the initial period of performance. Since it is of immediate concern, it was necessary to issue this policy vice issuing all policies at once. DynCorp&hellip; offered employment during transition to qualified personnel. The company will determine who is qualified to work on the program and the position functions necessary to remain qualified. The company will determine the necessary certifications for each individual employee with the exception of the requirement of all classes of mechanics who must hold a Plane Captain certification, for which, we have an agreement to meet with the union on the number/mix of Plane Captain certification held by mechanic positions. Until such time, all employees who hold Plane Captain certifications will maintain their Plane Captain certifications. Until the company performs a comprehensive review of the certification programs, such as engine turn up and CDI, employees must maintain all current certifications and re-certify before expiration of said certifications. Further, the company may direct individuals to obtain a specific certification when it is deemed necessary to operate the business. Failure of any employee to do so, will result in disciplinary action.&rdquo;</i> (JEx. 10)</p>
<p>After Baum reviewed the policy, he indicated that he understood that he faced disciplinary action if he turned in his qualifications, his position was unchanged and he believed it was his right to drop his CDIs. He understood he could be terminated. Boykin advised Baum that he was hired in large part because of the qualifications and certifications listed on his resume which made him a highly-desirable candidate. Baum again indicated that it was his right to turn in his certifications.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Boykin's April 13, 2015 memo regarding the meeting indicates:</p>
<p class="continued"><i>&ldquo;I then directed Mr. Baum to maintain the Collateral Duty Inspector certifications that he desired to drop. He refused. At this point I explained to Mr. Baum he was being insubordinate by refusing to follow the Company policy, and this was grounds for termination. I then offered time for him to step outside with his union representatives&hellip; and he refused. I then informed him I was more than willing to give him 24 hours to rethink his position. He&hellip; responded 24 hours is not going to change my mind I'm not maintaining those certifications. At this point I informed Mr. Baum he was being terminated for his insubordinate attitude towards policy and refusal to maintain required qualification/certification&rdquo;</i>. (JEx. 11)</p>
<p>During the meeting that day, Boykin issued a letter of termination which states:</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Effective immediately your employment with DynCorp&hellip; is terminated for insubordination: failure/refusal to follow specific instructions to maintain CDI certifications as required by Company directive</i>. (JEx. 3)</p></blockquote>
<p>On April 14, 2015, the Union filed a timely grievance which states under Reason for Appeal: &ldquo;Rich Baum Termination of employment. Mr. Baum's employment was terminated by the company on 13 APR 2015 without proper justification and in violation of the just cause standard and all relevant articles of the CBA.&rdquo; A Step 3 meeting was held and Boykin issued an April 27, 2015 memo indicating that the Union claims were, &ldquo;&hellip; the Company didn't have the right to terminate Mr. Baum's employment because qualifications were incentivized in the CBA. Furthermore the qualifications Mr. Baum dropped only took him to the level or number of qualifications of other employees on site.&rdquo; (JEx. 4)</p>
<p>When Baum was hired by DynCorp, he signed the Company's Standards and Conditions of Employment New Hire Form, which indicates that &ldquo;insubordination&rdquo; is considered by the Company to be a violation of Company expectations. (EEx. 1) The policy defines Insubordination as <i>&ldquo;Acting in a disrespectful or abusive manner or using disrespectful or abusive language to or about a person in authority, or failure or refusal to follow the direction of a person in authority&rdquo;</i>. Boykin testified that Baum's insubordination was his refusal to follow Boykin's instructions to maintain and not drop his F-16 and F-18 CDIs. The rule violation was in violation of Article 3, the Management Rights clause of the CBA. The Company directive referenced in the termination letter does not refer to the &ldquo;<i>Logan memo</i>&rdquo; of April 13 but only to Boykin's verbal directive to not drop certifications. The purpose of the <i>Logan memo</i> was to issue a policy that maintenance of CDIs is a condition of employment.</p>
<p>Boykin testified that after Baum refused to follow his instructions, he then called Human Resources and asked it to prepare termination papers. But Baum and Union Steward Jim Lemon testified that Boykin never got on the phone and never left the room before handing Baum the termination letter.</p>
<p>Boykin indicated he did not know how many mechanics held nine (9) CDI qualifications but that the average number of CDI certifications held by all mechanics is approximately three. He did not agree that the CBA differentiated between the CDI certification being an incentive versus a requirement. According to Boykin, the fact an incentive is paid does not negate the need for the qualifications. He did agree that Baum would have still received incentive pay for the other CDIs he did not drop. Boykin felt Baum was required to have three qualifications in order to become a Quality Assurance Representative for: F-16, F-18A-C and F-18E&amp;F. Baum could have dropped his other CDIs, but not for the F-16, F-18A-C or F-18E&amp;F. There were ten other mechanics holding similar F-16 avionic CDI certifications. At the time Baum dropped his CDIs, the Company was considering changing from two shifts to three and the ten CDI certificates covering the two (2) areas dropped by Baum would be spread out as 3.3 on each shift. Not all mechanics are required to hold F-18 E&amp;F and F-16 CDIs, but it is the Company's position that every mechanic must have at least one CDI. Boykin agreed on cross-examination that the Company cannot unilaterally create a new job requirement without first negotiating with the Union. He felt that maintaining the CDIs is a condition of employment.</p>
<p>QAM James Campbell testified that as to the Navy Policy Regulation 4790, Chapter 7, he did not feel that Chapter on CDIs applies to Baum being instructed to not drop his CDIs. However, Campbell indicated he would not want a CDI inspecting an aircraft if the CDI did not want to. No CDI should be coerced or persuaded to inspect an aircraft.</p>
<p>Baum testified that he dropped his first CDI certification because he was under pressure of an emotional or psychological nature. The CDI position was voluntary and incentive-based under the QAR/CDQAR/CDI Brief. When he was hired by the Company he initially worked the second shift, which had approximately 35 mechanics. Three to five of them had CDIs for the F-16. He did not think he was being insubordinate by dropping the F-16 since there was no written rule stating he could not drop that CDI. At the April 7 meeting, he felt threatened and felt that it was self-evident that there was a safety issue. When Boykin asked him why he was dropping the certificate he was not under the impression that he had to provide any explanation. He was not aware of anything that needed to be said.</p>
<p>Under the QAR/CDQAR/CDI Brief, the Company cannot coerce an employee to have a CDI qualification. After the first meeting, he then dropped the F-18E&amp;F certification and again did not think he was being insubordinate. He felt his letter dropping the F-18 CDI was an explanation of his reason for dropping the CDI based upon the lack of action by management. At the April 13 meeting, he did not provide a reason for dropping the second CDI. He felt he was being coerced by Boykin and singled out because the Company did not want to lose his CDIs. He had been moved to the third shift but that was not a reason for dropping the two CDIs. He felt he was being persuaded to stay in a position contrary to his will, which threatened naval aviation safety. The Navy allows CDIs to drop their certifications for safety reasons. He disobeyed Boykin's order because it was unlawful, since it involved a pressing safety issue. He felt that the Company had substantially reduced the number of aircraft mechanics when it bid on the maintenance contract. This meant that there was less manpower to perform the same amount of work as before, placing more CDI responsibility on him, adversely affecting his primary job duties as an aircraft mechanic.</p>
<p>Even after he dropped the two (2) CDIs, other aircraft mechanics on his shift had those CDIs, so he felt the Company's mission was not being jeopardized. He did not seek a further meeting or union assistance, because he thought the issue was self-evident. He may have acted prematurely. He had been told to bring union representation to the meeting, which implied disciplinary action might occur. But he felt it was within his purview to drop his CDIs without incurring discipline.</p>
<p>Baum testified he had never been informed that one CDI was preferred over another. He was unaware that his CDIs had to be maintained as a condition of employment. The Parties stipulated at the hearing that Baum was never told that no one else had the CDIs he dropped. The Union now appeals the matter for arbitral review.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>III. ISSUES PRESENTED</i></b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Parties stipulated that the issues for resolution by the Arbitrator are:</p>
<p class="continued">Whether Grievant Richard Baum was discharged for just cause? If not, what shall the remedy be?</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>IV. RELEVANT CONTRACT LANGUAGE</i></b></h4>
<p>This arbitration proceeding is brought pursuant to the relevant portions of the Parties' Bridge Agreement and the CBA between IUE-CWA and L-3 Vertex Aerospace. (JEx. 1 and 2)</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>BRIDGE AGREEMENT WITH DYNCORP</b></i></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Upon achieving the status of successor employer to L-3 Vertex Aerospace, DynCorp International LLC&hellip; agrees to assume the terms and conditions of the Collective Bargaining Agreement between the Union and said predecessor employer dated Effective September 16, 2014. Such assumption applies only to the express terms of said Agreement and not to any bargaining history, side agreements or understandings or past practices between the Union and the predecessor employer.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip; the Company and the Union&hellip; have agreed that the terms of the Agreement effective September 16, 2014, shall continue in full force and effect except as herein modified&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Modify Appendix B to add the following: Fifty percent (50&percnt;) of all Aircraft Mechanics are required to maintain a qualification as a Plan Captain on at least one t/m/s, provided there is an adequate balance across platforms to achieve flight schedules. In order to assure that such a balance is maintained, the Company and the Union will meet in April, 2015 to define adequate balance.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>COLLECTIVE BARGAINING AGREEMENT WITH L-3 VERTEX AEROSPACE</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>ARTICLE 03.00 - MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">03.01 Except as specifically limited by this Agreement, the management of the company, and the direction of the work force, including but not limited to the service performed, the location of the work force, the schedules and fair standards of employee performance, the schedules and hours of shifts, the methods, processes, and means of providing services, materials to be purchased, the right to subcontract out work provided the Company gives the Union prior notice and, it will not directly lead to any bargaining unit people being laid off, the right to hire, promote, demote and transfer employees, the establishment of reasonable rules of conduct, the discharge or discipline of employees for just cause, and the maintenance of efficiency of employees, are the sole and exclusive rights and responsibilities of the Company. All matters not specifically covered by this Agreement are solely functions and responsibilities of management.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>ARTICLE 15 - DISCHARGE AND DISCIPLINARY ACTION</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">15.01 The Company shall have the right to discipline employees for just cause by reprimand, suspension without pay or discharge for violation or infraction of the Company rules <i><b>or Government Instructions such as the NAMP, IETMS and Technical Orders</b></i>.<ftnote num="3"><para>Emphasis in original.</para></ftnote> The Company agrees to notify the Union, in writing, of any action taken under this section.</p>
<p class="continued">15.07 The union and employees shall be notified prior to the enforcement of new disciplinary rules or changes in the existing Corrective Action Guide.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>ARTICLE 19 - ARBITRATION PROCEDURE</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">19.03 The decision of the arbitrator shall be final and binding on all parties. However, the arbitrator shall not have jurisdiction or authority to add to, subtract from, modify or in any way change the provisions of this agreement&hellip;</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>ARTICLE 20 - HOURS OF WORK</b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">20.03 <i><b>Shift Preference. The Company shall have the exclusive right to assign employees to any shift and will honor shift preferences by seniority whenever minimum qualifications by shift are met. Under no circumstances will the provisions of this section be construed to enable an employee, at his insistence and request, to displace a less senior employee from his job and shift.</b></i><ftnote num="4"><para>Emphasis in original.</para></ftnote></p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>APPENDIX B</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>Employee Qualification Incentive Program</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">The Company will pay incentive pay for the following Qualifications: Turns, Plane Captain and CDI/CDQAR.</p>
<p class="continued">&dollar;0.20 per hour for the first qualification in any type/model series (t/m/s)</p>
<p class="continued">&dollar;0.10 per hour for the second like qualification in any type/model series (t/m/s)</p>
<p class="continued">&dollar;0.20 per hour for the third like qualification in any type/model series (t/m/s)</p>
<p class="continued">The type/models series are: F-16, F-18 A-D, Super Hornet #-F/G, E2, and H-60.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>V. POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. <i>Position of the Employer</i></b>:</h4>
<p>Baum was terminated for his insubordination after he refused to follow the Company's lawful and appropriate direction to maintain particular CDI qualifications required to perform his job. The appropriate course of action for an employee who disagrees with management instruction is to follow the instruction and seek recourse by filing a grievance. Following specific instructions or direction from management is a central principle in American Industrial Jurisprudence. A main reason employers agree to include a grievance-arbitration procedure into a collective bargaining agreement is so that they can expect work to get done as directed, while affording employees the right to express their disagreement without interfering with accomplishment of the work. The requirement for an employee to follow a specific direction is reasonably related to business efficiency and performance the employer might reasonably expect from the employee. If an employer cannot rely on employees to perform as directed, the employer cannot accomplish its business objectives.</p>
<p>There was sufficient testimony during the hearing that clearly establishes that the Company has met its burden of proof as required for a discharge case in arbitration. The employee was forewarned of the consequences of his actions. He was told in the presence of union representation that if he refused to follow the direction that he would be considered insubordinate, which was grounds for termination. It was readily evident from the employee's own statements made with representation present that Baum's refusal to follow direction established that the employee was guilty as charged. This was no rush to judgment by the Company. With the exception of a safety concern raised by an employee or if an employee believes he is being asked to participate in illegal conduct, employees with access to a grievance procedure are expected to follow direction and then if necessary file a grievance. None of the exceptions to the &ldquo;obey then grieve&rdquo; rule applies here, where the only reason for resorting to self-help is the desire to have more time on one's hands. There must be zero tolerance for an employee refusing to follow direction and progressive discipline is not required here.</p>
<p>Baum's April 10, 2015 letter states that dropping his two qualifications would allow him time to provide his very best effort on his remaining CDIs. He chose not to bring this reason up during the meetings; instead, he said he did not need to give an explanation. At the hearing he said he did not see the need to express any reason because the letter was self-explanatory and that the letter made it self-explanatory that he wanted to drop the certifications for safety reasons. Safety was not raised in his letters, during the Parties' meetings, or at the Step 3 meeting. Had he been relying on a safety concern, he could have said that. In the absence of a safety concern, there can be no justification for refusing to follow instructions. Whether or not the reason alluded to in the letter was a reasonable basis for dropping the certifications is not for Baum to decide for himself. He should have followed the instruction given and then filed a grievance if he felt the instruction was inappropriate. The Union claimed that an employer cannot enforce an instruction or direction unless it is based on an established/published rule. That is not an exception recognized to the obey then grieve rule.</p>
<p>Whether there was or had to be a specific rule, such as about maintaining or dropping certifications for example, is a matter to be addressed in the grievance procedure, rather than for the employee to rely on his own judgment. Neither the Union or Grievant ever suggested that there did not exist a well-understood rule to follow instructions. Numerous arbitration awards confirm the rule that an employee should obey orders without regard to an existing established rule and then file a grievance if necessary. The Union never claimed that ethics, legal requirements, representational rights or grievance rights were at stake here. The expression of a safety concern was never raised until the hearing and cannot be considered a rationale for refusing the management direction or used to refute that there was just cause for the discharge. The Union raised nine other reasons to justify Baum's refusal to comply with the direction, all of which could have or should have been pursued through the grievance process.</p>
<p>The termination letter was not prepared until after the site manager advised Baum that he was being terminated. There is just cause for discharge and the Company requests the Union's grievance be dismissed.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. <i>Position of the Union</i></b>:</h4>
<p>Just cause requires prior notice to the Union and the employees of any rule to be used by the Company to discipline employees. Article 15 of the existing contract was negotiated to prevent the Company from making ad hoc rules and then contending an employee violated such rules. The Company has failed to carry its burden of proof and to meet the accepted standards for judging whether just cause existed, such as under the seven tests and other arbitral standards; Arbitrator Hepburn states &ldquo;Just cause requires that employees be informed of a rule, infraction of which may result in &hellip; discharge, unless conduct is so clearly wrong that specific reference is not necessary.&rdquo; Here, there was no just cause to discharge, suspend or otherwise discipline Baum. The Company failed miserably with regard to providing prior notice to the Union or Baum that he was required to maintain all nine (9) CDIs and that failure to do so would result in his termination.</p>
<p>The Company cannot create a new job requirement without first negotiating with the Union and the evidence contains no job description stating an aircraft mechanic is required to have a CDI in order to be hired by the Company. Documentary evidence indicates that obtaining and maintaining the CDIs is voluntary. There is nothing in the CBA that requires an employee to become CDI qualified. The CBA does contain language that the employees are &ldquo;incentivized&rdquo; to obtain up to three CDIs. The Company has failed to prove it gave prior notice to Baum and/or the Union that an employee possessing a CDI when hired cannot voluntarily drop it. The evidence is clear that Baum dropped the two (2) CDIs because when he dropped them there was no rule stating he could not do so and he did so for a legitimate reason: that is, Due to the reduction in manpower without a concomitant reduction in workload, he would be better able to perform his mechanic duties if he dropped the CDIs.</p>
<p>Baum was not insubordinate. At the time the April 13, 2015 Company directive was issued, he had already dropped two (2) CDIs. Even the Company has not attempted to argue the directive was published before the dates when he dropped his CDIs. At the time, he indicated his willingness to continue working with team members and perform his duties. The Company has to prove that the order that was given was a &ldquo;valid&rdquo; order and that Baum was given clear prior warning of the consequences. Although there was contradictory evidence on the issue, the evidence establishes that the termination letter was prepared before Baum and the stewards attended the April 13 meeting.</p>
<p>Baum was not required to act now and grieve later when he was directed to reinstate his dropped CDIs. At the time he dropped the CDIs there was no order which would have allowed him to act now and grieve later. That doctrine is generally accepted to be effective when an employee is given a lawful order to perform a job duty which does not jeopardize his safety or health. It is inapplicable here. Following that mantra would have been in violation of the Navy Brief, forcing Baum to work CDI duties against his will. The Site Manager admitted he was trying to &ldquo;persuade&rdquo; Baum to continue those duties, which also violated the Brief. In the hearing, the importance of accurately maintaining valuable aircraft and protecting pilot lives was an overriding safety theme of why a qualified employee was required, as a collateral duty, to inspect and certify maintenance work. No one will ever know if Baum might have made an error in certifying collateral work because of the stress of pressure to accurately perform his job functions, and the risk was too much for him to act now and grieve later. He was under no such duty to do so. The Union respectfully requests that the discharge of Grievant be rescinded and he be reinstated with full back pay and benefits to the date of his discharge.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>VI. DECISION</i></b></h4>
<p>The Company's disciplinary action against Avionics Mechanic Richard Baum concerns his refusal to maintain CDI certifications after being directed to do so by the Site Manager William Boykin. The Company argues that: 1) Grievant has acknowledged refusing to follow Mr. Boykin's instructions and his failure to follow instructions was in violation of the Company's policy against insubordination, 2) the Union cannot now rely on a safety defense since this defense was not raised until the arbitration hearing and, 3) a well-settled arbitrable principle of &ldquo;Obey Now, Grieve Later&rdquo; applies here as to any other affirmative defenses that the Union may raise. According to the Company, Baum was given every opportunity to comply with Management's lawful instruction before being issued its termination decision. The Company has a zero tolerance approach to insubordination and termination of Baum is the only proper penalty here.</p>
<p>The Union disagrees with the Company's position and defends Baum's refusal with claims that: 1) the Company's order was unlawful since compliance would have endangered the safety of Navy personnel if Baum continued to perform his CDI inspections, 2) Baum had the right to drop his CDIs because holding them was voluntary under the existing CBA and, 3) there was no specific instruction by Management to maintain his CDIs until after Baum had already dropped them. According to the Union, when Baum dropped his CDIs there was no order which would have allowed him to act now and grieve later. If Baum followed that mantra he would have been in violation of the Navy Brief by being forced to work CDIs against his will.</p>
<p>Baum was terminated for what the Company alleges was an act of insubordination occurring on April 13, 2015. The termination letter of the same date cites his <i>&ldquo;failure/refusal to follow specific instructions to maintain CDI certifications as required by Company directive&rdquo;</i>. Boykin's memo of the same date cites that <i>&ldquo;&hellip; he was being insubordinate by refusing to follow the Company policy, and this was grounds for termination&hellip; he was being terminated for his insubordinate attitude towards policy and refusal to maintain required qualification/certification&rdquo;</i>.</p>
<p>The order of April 13 came from the Site Manager and there is no dispute as to his authority to issue a directive to Baum. Article 03.00 (Management Rights) of the CBA expressly states that Management has the right to direct the work force as to &ldquo;&hellip; the service performed&hellip; &lsqb;and&rsqb; the methods, processes, and means of providing services.&rdquo; Baum understood that the Company was directing him to maintain his F-16 and F-18 avionic CDI qualifications and understood the consequences of his refusal to comply. The directive was given in a meeting attended by two Union representatives where Baum was given time to comply with the directive, encouraged to consult with the Union and even given 24 hours to reconsider his refusal. Baum testified that he was aware disciplinary action was possible in the meeting since he was advised to bring Union representation to the meeting.</p>
<p>As to whether Baum received a directive that was &ldquo;doable,&rdquo; the Union has argued that Baum was not insubordinate because there was no specific instruction to maintain his CDIs until <i>after</i> he had already dropped his F-16A-B and F-18E&amp;F Avionics CDIs days earlier. It is true that as of April 13, Baum had seven remaining CDIs: F-18 A-D Avionics, F-18 A-D Ordinance, F-18 A-D Corrosion Control, F-16A-B Ordinance, F-16 A-B Corrosion Control, MH-60S Corrosion Control and Line. It is also true that Baum did not indicate on April 13 that he intended to drop any of these remaining seven CDIs. Here, the Union's argument is not persuasive since Baum was given a direct instruction to maintain all of his CDIs, including the F-16A-B Avionics and F-18 E&amp;F Avionics CDIs, on April 13, 2015. The directive was a &ldquo;doable&rdquo; action since there is no indication in the evidence record that the Company ever accepted Baum's notifications that he was dropping the CDIs or that it was impossible for Baum to withdraw his decision to drop the certifications. Baum's letters of April 6 and 10 asked for an updated CDI designation letter and that a change to the Monthly Maintenance Plan be provided to him. This request to the Company to update company records infers that the Company needed to take steps to implement Baum's intention to drop CDIs and there is no evidence they took those steps.</p>
<p>The evidence record remains silent as to whether Baum was required to simply maintain the status he held before April 6, given that the Company was new and not accepting his intention to drop the CDIs. It is important to note that the record also contains no evidence that the Union representatives objected at the April 7 or April 13 meeting to the Company's initial request and the directive that Baum maintain his CDIs, as contained in Boykin's memo regarding the April 7 meeting. Since there is no evidence the Company removed the two disputed CDI designations, it is found that it was &ldquo;doable&rdquo; for Baum to agree to maintain all nine of his CDIs. Therefore, the Arbitrator finds no support for a finding that Baum was not insubordinate because he could not comply with Boykin's April 13 directive.</p>
<p>At first glance, it is found that the Company has met its initial burden in proving that Baum was insubordinate because he violated the Company's Standards and Conditions of Employment policy which indicates that an employee's behavior violates Company expectations where the employee refuses <i>&ldquo;to follow the direction of a person in authority.&rdquo;</i> A well-settled principle of Labor-Management relations does recognize that employees must obey orders given to them by their supervisors and follow the general rule when they disagree; to &ldquo;Work Now and Grieve Later.&rdquo; As stated in <i>Ford Motor Co.</i>, 3 LA 779, 780-81, by Dean Harry Shulman on why the rule is needed, it is because &ldquo;&hellip;<i>an industrial plant is not a debating society.&rdquo;</i> Subject to some exceptions, where an employee refuses to follow a clearly-understood order that is doable and work related, the employee may be appropriately found to be insubordinate, after being given time to reflect and made aware of the consequences for refusing the order.</p>
<p>The core issue in this matter however, is whether there are any recognized exceptions, defenses or mitigating circumstances excusing Baum from his duty to comply with his manager's order. Arbitral authority recognizes two well-defined exceptions which may be considered relevant in the case before me: 1) Where an employee's direct refusal may be protected under a contract provision and/or, 2) Where an employee reasonably believes that in carrying out the order, it will imminently endanger the health or safety of the employee or others. According to the Union, who has the burden of proving that such exceptions exist, Baum's refusal 1) is protected here under the Parties' CBA, and 2) goes beyond health and safety for himself, extending to the safety of others under the Navy Brief.</p>
<p>The evidence is clear that Baum did not state in the April 13 meeting, or at any time after, that he would obey Boykin's directive even under protest. The first defense raised by the Union is that the Parties' CBA protects Baum's position that maintenance of his CDIs was voluntary. Where an employee claims the protection of the CBA, he must still take the necessary action of &ldquo;obeying now and grieving later.&rdquo; The Arbitrator finds that Baum did not obey as instructed and then grieve. As to the CBA protection defense, the next issue becomes, what is the consequence of Baum's refusal to comply? In assessing any potential penalty here, the Arbitrator may consider the evidence record as to whether the CBA provides such protection to him. If it is found that the Company is correct that Baum's action was not justified, it may be appropriate to uphold the termination. However, if it is found that Baum's action was justified, it may be appropriate to consider a lesser penalty applying progressive discipline.<ftnote num="5"><para>At this point, whether there was a related or separate <quote>safety</quote> defense is not yet considered.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Here, the evidence record shows that Baum's refusal to obey is protected under the Parties' CBA. Boykin's memo of the grievance Step 3 meeting expressly documents the Union's claim that CDI qualifications were <i>incentivized</i> in the CBA, and the CDI qualifications Baum dropped took him to the level or same number of qualifications as other employees on site. The Union relies on language of Appendix B in the CBA, indicating that <i>incentive</i> premiums are payable for one, two or three CDI certifications, as proof indicating that obtaining and maintaining CDIs is voluntary on the employee's part. The Union objects to the Company's &ldquo;<i>Logan memo</i>,&rdquo; produced for the first time at the April 13 meeting as being improperly and unilaterally created by the Company to implement a new policy and job requirement without first negotiating with the Union. The Union also asserts a Company violation of Article 15.00 of the CBA by creating a new disciplinary rule without proper notice to the Union and its employees. The Company responds, however, that requiring Baum to maintain all nine (9) of his CDIs is protected under the Management Rights clause of the CBA. The Company maintains that Baum was hired in part, based upon the number of CDIs that he held, including at least one of his CDI's which is a condition of Baum's employment and position. Baum held three (3) important CDIs: the F-16, F-18A-C and F-18E&amp;F, and Baum was attempting to drop two (2) of those important CDIs, that the Company maintains is a condition of employment.</p>
<p>After careful review of the existing CBA, entered into by the predecessor contractor and amended by the Parties' Bridge Agreement, it is found that it does not require Baum to maintain his CDIs as a condition of employment. The Company has pointed to no existing language in the CBA which states that a mechanic must have any designated CDIs or a certain number of CDIs. Rather, the CBA clearly protects Baum's right to drop his CDIs since the CDIs are <i>incentivized</i> and a extra activity that some mechanics voluntarily perform. Baum's protection shielding him against the charge of insubordination for refusing to carry out the directive is found in language contained in the Company's and Navy documents which were entered into the record. The documents address the issue of a safety-defense and include: QAR/Inspector-Recommendation/Designation Form; QAR/CDQAR/CDI Brief/Billet Description; Quality - AssuranceRepresentative/Inspector/Recommendation/Designation, and COMNAVAIRFORINST 4790.2B, Chapter 7.4.5. These documents supports the Arbitrator's finding that participation by Baum in the CDI program was <i>incentivized</i> and voluntary. As such, the Company could not coerce or require his continued participation as a condition of employment. Although Boykin testified that maintaining a CDI was a requirement and condition of employment, there is no corroborating or persuasive evidence to support this claim. The Company has not produced a job description stating that maintaining a CDI is a job requirement for the position of Avonic Mechanic. The Company's letter of employment to Baum makes no mention that its offer is conditioned upon Baum having certain CDI qualifications. Nor does the Company's offer of employment require that Baum continue to possess all of his CDI qualifications.</p>
<p>Notwithstanding the Company's argument that Baum's offer of employment was based on maintaining his nine (9) CDIs, it appears to be based more on an assumption by the Company, rather than a contractual requirement that Baum do so. As a general rule of contract interpretation, an arbitrator may refuse to fill &ldquo;gaps&rdquo; in an agreement where he is convinced that to do so, &ldquo;would constitute contract making&rdquo; rather than contract interpretation. Here, the Employer may not alter or go outside the four corners of its written offer to argue that additional non-written conditions also apply. The employment offer is simply predicated upon the terms and conditions of the CBA and as noted above, the CBA is silent as to any requirement that a mechanic have any number of or any particular CDI. If as Boykin states, having a CDI is a condition of employment, then the expectation should be a subject of bargaining and not unilaterally imposed on the Union. There is no evidence that the Parties negotiated specifics as to the CDI designation or agreed that the Company could do so under its Management Rights clause.</p>
<p>Boykin further testified that: every mechanic must have at least one CDI; a QAR had to hold three (3) CDIs; not all mechanics were required to hold the F-16 and F-18 E&amp;F CDIs; and Baum could have dropped some of his CDIs, but not the F-16, F-18A-C and F-18E&amp;F. It is found based upon the facts set forth in the evidence record, that Baum appears to have complied with the Company requirements as to these CDIs. Baum was not a QAR but was a mechanic, so even under Boykin's description of the Company's desired policy, Baum continued to hold the F-18A-D CDI even after he attempted to drop the F-16 and F-18E&amp;F CDIs. Boykin agreed that by continuing to hold seven (7) CDIs, Baum still would have been eligible for the Company's CDI <i>incentivized</i> payments under the Parties' CBA. If Baum still had his F-18A-D Avionics CDI, the record does not demonstrate why maintaining only that CDI was not sufficient for the Company's mission.</p>
<p>In addition, it is noted that when Baum initially advised the Company by way of his April 6 letter, that he was dropping his F-16A-B Avionics CDI, Boykin met with Baum the next day to discuss Baum's action. The record does not indicate whether Boykin ordered Baum at their April 7 meeting to maintain this CDI. If the Company is correct and Baum was required to maintain all his CDIs held at date of hire, it has failed to explain why he was also not subject to an order on April 7 to maintain his F-16 CDI, similar to the order given by Boykin at the April 13 meeting.</p>
<p>NSA Fallon operation guidelines under which military maintenance contractors perform their duties and carry out their mission contains a mechanism whereby mechanics within the maintenance department perform CDI work, and are designated to act as <i>&ldquo;a second set of eyes&rdquo;</i> for the work done by other mechanics. Certainly, there may be a policy in place that outside of the work performed by the Quality Control Department, mechanics perform certain activities to make sure the work of other mechanics is done correctly. However, this is a more general <i>&ldquo;requirement&rdquo;</i> and does not prove that Baum, as an individual employee, was contractually required to perform this function as a condition of employment or to hold a CDI for a particular type/model series.</p>
<p>As such, the Company has not proven that the CBA required Baum to continue to maintain his F-16 and F-18E&amp;F, or all nine (9) of his CDIs. Baum's refusal to comply with Boykin's order on April 13 is also protected by the language of Appendix B of the CBA.</p>
<p>If the CBA protection defense were the only defense raised by Baum and his Union, this Arbitrator would need only to determine what penalty would be appropriate where Baum refused to comply with a direct order, rather than obey and grieve later where that refusal was in line with the CBA. Baum has also testified that there was a <i>&ldquo;Self-Evident&rdquo;</i> safety issue that protects his refusal to obey from a finding that just cause exists for his removal because he was insubordinate. That issue must now be resolved by the Arbitrator, before moving on to a consideration of the appropriate penalty, if any, in this matter.</p>
<p>Baum asserts that he should be excused from compliance with Boykin's April 13 order because he would have endangered the safety of pilots flying the aircraft if he had done so. But, as argued by the Company, Baum did not raise this defense before the arbitration hearing. At issue then, is whether the safety concern was &ldquo;self-evident,&rdquo; and if not, whether there is other evidence in the record supporting a finding that his safety concern justifies Baum's refusal to obey.</p>
<p>The Company argues that Baum's safety concern cannot be considered by the Arbitrator as a rationale for Baum's conduct because it was not raised until Baum testified at the hearing. Baum testified that he dropped his first F-16 CDI certification because of the emotional and psychological pressure brought on by his increased work load. He indicated that he felt threatened at the April 7 meeting and it should have been &ldquo;self-evident&rdquo; from his April 10 letter that there was a safety issue. Baum's letter indicates that dropping his second CDI will &ldquo;&hellip; have the effect of allowing me time to provide my very best effort on my remaining seven&hellip;&rdquo; designations. Based solely on its face, it is not apparent from Baum's letter that his potential reallocation of time is due exclusively to a safety concern. But there is support in the evidence record for a finding that based on Baum's maintenance duties as an Aircraft Avonic Mechanic, safety concerns must be considered paramount, even if first raised at the arbitration hearing. The safety concerns are therefore found to be valid and a mitigating defense to the charge of insubordination. Baum's safety concerns are clearly distinguishable from and an exception to a charge of insubordination for failure to &ldquo;obey now- grieve later&rdquo; traditionally found in the industrial work place, because it encompasses issues of military readiness, safety concerns about military aircraft and for Navy pilots who fly them. Baum testified without rebuttal that he felt that he was under emotional or psychological pressure which led him to drop his first CDI. This came about when the Company took over for the predecessor contractor and the number of personnel was reduced, but without the workload also being reduced. This raised a safety concern for Baum who felt pressured by the Company to maintain all of his CDIs.</p>
<p>It is therefore found that Baum's April 10 letter is sufficient to raise legitimate safety concerns that are not waived. The Company has offered no evidence to rebut Baum's testimony that by virtue of a reduced number of workers, the mechanics' workload was increased under the new contractor. In a situation where the same work is spread amongst fewer workers as here, and an employee reaction is to drop some of his <i>incentivized</i> duties in order to perform core duties, a safety concern is at least a potential reason for doing so, if not &ldquo;self-evident.&rdquo; But more importantly, documentary evidence in the form of the Initial Quality Assurance Inspector Nomination Form; the QAR/CDQAR/CDI - Brief/Billet Description; Quality Assurance Representative/Inspector; the Recommendation/Designation and the Navy Policy/Regulation COMNAVAIRFORINST 4790. 2B, Chapter 7.4.5; all support Baum's position that a safety issue can be created, where an employee's participation in the <i>incentivized</i> CDI duties is not voluntary, but is coerced.</p>
<p>The evidence further supports a finding that these are all documents known to and used by the Company in its business operation. The Brief/Billet indicates that the QAM must ensure that a potential candidate for CDI certification <i>is not being persuaded into the position contrary to his will</i>. The QAR Recommendation, which is binding on the Company and governs Naval expectations of its contractors and their employees, indicates that a designee must not permit outside factors to modify his judgment and that the designee is the representative of the Commanding Officer to ensure flight safety. Navy Regulation 7.4.5.2, also indicates that the division officers and work center supervisors, must carefully screen all candidates for the CDI assignments. Testimonial evidence by the Company's Quality Assurance Manager, James Campbell, indicates that a CDI certification is voluntary on the employee's part and the employee cannot be coerced or even persuaded to retain the CDI qualifications by the Company, if an employee wants to drop the CDIs. While Mr. Campbell opined that the Navy Policy/Regulation 4790.2B - 7.4.5.2, does not expressly apply to Baum being instructed not to drop his CDIs, Campbell conceded that an employee should not maintain a CDI to inspect Naval aircraft if he does not wish to do so. Although Baum's letters to and meetings with Boykin may not have made it so &ldquo;self-evident&rdquo; that his safety concerns were the rationale behind his determination to drop CDIs, it should have at least been &ldquo;self evident&rdquo; to the Company that by pressuring Baum to continue his voluntary participation in the CDI program under threat of termination, that it was reinforcing his safety concerns and refusal to do so. The voluntary nature of the CDI duty contributes to the Navy's &ldquo;safe for flight&rdquo; culture, even if technically a CDI is not a part of the Quality Assurance Department, it is a part of the aircraft maintenance and overall aircraft safety procedures.</p>
<p>There is no dispute as to the paramount value of pilot lives and that every thing must be done to ensure &ldquo;safe for flight&rdquo;. Thus, it is found Baum did have the right to refuse Boykin's directive based upon the inherent safety concern raised at arbitration. Baum's safety issue is an affirmative defense and exception to the charge of insubordination, and is not waived based on Baum's highly technical and classified nature of his work, requiring Navy aircraft to be &ldquo;safe for flight.&rdquo; Baum's refusal to obey a direct order and grieve later was an exception to the general rule, when balanced against both aircraft being &ldquo;safe for flight,&rdquo;and the potential harm to pilots' lives.</p>
<p>Finally, the Union raises an issue as to whether the termination papers were prepared by the Company prior to the April 13 meeting. The implication being that the Company had already may a decision to terminate Baum before informing him. However, the Union has not shown that either the timing of or manner of the preparation of the Company's papers is either dispositive of or prejudicial to Baum and its case. Even if Management had discussed and prepared potential paperwork before the meeting, this does not prove that the Company's termination decision was a foregone conclusion or prejudicial to Baum or the Union.</p>
<p>Accordingly, under the specific facts of this case, it is found that there is a safety issue present which is a defense and exception sufficient to defeat the charge of insubordination. Baum was not required to &ldquo;obey and then grieve later,&rdquo; since such a requirement may have potentially endangered lives. Based on the reasons stated above, the Company has not met its burden to show just cause existed for the discharge of Avionic Mechanic Richard Baum for insubordinate, based upon his defense of an important safety concern that is directly related to maintenance of his CDI qualifications. The Union's grievance is sustained.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<ol type="lc-letter" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>The Company lacked just cause to discharge Grievant Richard Baum.</p></li>
<li><p>The Union's grievance is hereby sustained.</p></li>
<li><p>The Company's disciplinary termination is hereby rescinded and the Company is ordered to reinstate Mr. Baum to his former position, retroactively to the date of his termination.</p></li>
<li><p>Baum shall be made whole by the Company for all lost wages, less any compensation received during his removal, and related benefits.</p></li>
<li><p>The Company is further ordered to expunge the disciplinary action from its personnel records.</p></li>
<li><p>The Arbitrator shall retain jurisdiction to resolve any disputes regarding implementation and/or interpretation of this Award for sixty (60) days.</p></li></ol>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>