<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION Between WEBSTER MANUFACTURING COMPANY The Company -and- GLASS, MOLDERS, POTTERY, PLASTICS &amp; ALLIED WORKERS INTERNATIONAL UNION, LOCAL 45B The Union</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Grv. &num; 01-WEB-16</p>
<p>FMCS No. 16-54438-6</p>
<p>November 22, 2016.</p>
<p>Jerry A. Fullmer, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>OPINION AND AWARD</i></h4>
<p>This case<ftnote num="1"><para>Webster Manufacturing Company (hereafter referred to as <quote>the Company</quote>) and Glass, Molders, Pottery, Plastics &amp; Allied Workers International Union, Local 458 (hereafter referred to as <quote>the Union</quote>), are parties to a collective bargaining agreement dated April 1, 2013 (Joint Ex. 1). The agreement provides in Article III for settlement of disputes through a grievance and arbitration procedure. A dispute has arisen between the parties concerning a temporary transfer of the Grievant, Don Payne on February 18, 2016.</para>
<para>The Union's grievance (Joint Ex. 2) concerning this matter was dated February 22, 2016. It was submitted to arbitration before the arbitrator under the administration of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service. A hearing was held on September 8, 2016 at the Hampton Inn in Tiffin, Ohio. Both advocates made opening statements and presented and cross-examined witnesses. A transcript was taken. Post hearing briefs were filed by both parties, with the latter being received by the arbitrator on approximately November 9, 2016. It was stipulated by the parties that the grievance was both procedurally and substantively arbitrable; that the time limits in the grievance procedure had either been met or waived and that the arbitrator has been properly chosen and has jurisdiction to hear the case.</para></ftnote> concerns a temporary transfer of the Grievant, Dion Payne, on February 18, 2016.</p>
<h4 align="left">I. FACTS</h4>
<h4 align="left">A. Background Facts</h4>
<p>The Company operates both a foundry and a manufacturing operation in Tiffin, Ohio. The Union represents the employees in the foundry operation. A different union represents employees in the manufacturing operation. There are 35 employees in the former and 165 employees in the latter. (Tr. 10) All the subsequent discussion will be of the foundry bargaining unit.</p>
<p class="continued">As described by the Company witnesses, the &ldquo;job shop&rdquo; aspects of the foundry operation make it susceptible to ups and downs as to its manpower requirements.</p>
<p>Appendix A lists the &ldquo;Classification and Wage Rates&rdquo;. The classifications are five in number, each with sub-classifications. The listing<ftnote num="2"><para>Without the wage rates.</para></ftnote> of those relevant to the case include the following.:</p>
<p><b>&ldquo;FOUNDRY</b></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Pattern Maker &amp; Repair Lead</p>
<p class="continued">Pattern Clerk</p>
</blockquote>
<p><i><b>Foundry Journeyman</b></i></p>
<ul type="none">
<li><p>- Hunter Operator</p></li>
<li><p>- Squeeze Mold</p></li>
<li><p>- Shell Cone</p></li>
<li><p>- Oil Cone</p></li></ul>
<p><i><b>Furnace and Anneal Fireman</b></i></p>
<ul type="none">
<li><p>- Furnace Operator</p></li>
<li><p>- Anneal Fireman</p></li></ul>
<p><i><b>Foundry Operators</b></i></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Clean Up / Sort Bench</p>
<p class="continued">Hunter Shake-out</p>
</blockquote>
<p><i><b>Finishers / Grinders / Inspectors</b></i></p>
<ul type="none">
<li><p>- 30&inch; Grinder Operator</p></li>
<li><p>- Final Inspector</p></li>
<li><p>- Foundry Finisher</p></li>
<li><p>- Foundry Worker (General Labor)</p></li></ul>
<p align="center">(Jt. Ex. 1)</p>
<p class="continued">Vacancies are posted with respect to the classification involved and as to the subclassification as well.</p>
<p>The Grievant has approximately six years seniority with the Company, i.e. since May of 2010. He had been classified as a Foundry Operator. Approximately two years ago there was a vacancy in the Foundry Journeyman classification in the sub-classification of Squeeze Mold. The Grievant bid and was awarded the vacancy on May 3, 2015. He served in that capacity up through the events of this case, apparently without incident.</p>
<p>On the cusp of the facts leading to the grievance there were five employees other than the Grievant who held the classification of Foundry Journeyman, subclassification Squeeze Mold. The Grievant held-more seniority than two of them and less than the other three.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. Facts Leading to the Grievance</h4>
<p>On or about February 18, 2016, the Company felt that the production requirements for squeeze molding were such that a full complement of squeeze molders was not needed. The Grievant was then given a temporary assignment in the Foundry Operator classification in the sub-classification of &ldquo;Clean-Up / Sort Bench&rdquo;. There was no particular discussion of the assignment with the Union, nor was its approval sought. The Grievant performed the transfer as ordered and was paid at his previous rate of pay as a Foundry Journeyman. That rate was the higher of the two.</p>
<p>On February 22, 2016 the Union filed the grievance in this case. It did not include details as to the length of the temporary transfer but succinctly provided in relevant portion that:</p>
<p><b>&ldquo;What happened?</b> Violation of Article VII Seniority &hellip;..</p>
<p><b>Adjustment sought?</b> MAKE WHOLE&hellip;.</p>
<p><b>Union Position</b> MAKE WHOLE&rdquo;</p>
<p align="center">(Jt. Ex. 2)</p>
<p>The grievance was thence processed through the steps of the grievance procedure to arbitration.</p>
<h4 align="left">II. POTENTIALLY APPLICABLE CONTRACT PROVISIONS</h4>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE III</h4>
<h4 align="center">Grievance Procedure</h4>
<p class="continued">&hellip;..</p>
<p class="continued">STEP D</p>
<p>&hellip;.. In making an award, however, the arbitrator shall have no power to alter, add to, or subtract from the expressed written provisions of this Agreement.</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE IV</h4>
<h4 align="center">Wages</h4>
<p class="continued">SECTION 2 &hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued">Additionally, progressive increases of employees who bid or permanently transfer from their original job classification may be delayed by mutual agreement between the Employer and the Union, if the Employee is not progressing satisfactorily as determined by the quality or quantity of work produced and/or his attendance record.</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE V</h4>
<h4 align="center">Hours and Overtime</h4>
<p class="continued">&hellip;..</p>
<p class="continued">SECTION 3. Time and one half (1 1/2) shall be paid for all work performed on Saturday provided 40 straight time hours were worked during the pay period. <i>Whenever said overtime is required, the employee affected shall be advised directly or by posted notice if possible not later than the end of his shift on the prior Thursday, unless practical consideration of customer requirements prevent the Employer from giving such notice.</i> The advance notification requirements specified in this Section shall not be applicable, however, with respect to employees needed for emergency repairs in the plant such as maintenance of machinery or equipment. &hellip;..</p>
<p class="continued">SECTION 12 Temporary Transfers shall not be made by the Employer for a period in excess of forty-five (45) working days without the consent of the transferred employee unless such transfer is made as a replacement for an employee who is absent because of illness or injury.</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE VII</h4>
<h4 align="center">Seniority</h4>
<p class="continued">&hellip;..</p>
<p class="continued">Section 4. In the event it becomes necessary to increase or decrease the working force and in matters relating to transfer or promotion, the following points shall be considered and where factors contained in Sub B are equal length of continuous service shall govern.</p>
<ol type="uc-letter" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Length of continuous service.</p></li>
<li><p>Ability to perform the available work.</p></li></ol>
<p class="continued">Whenever it becomes necessary to reduce the work force within a department, the following procedure shall be followed.</p>
<p>&hellip;..</p>
<p class="continued">SECTION 5 Recall of employees laid off under the provisions of Section 4 herein shall be done in the reverse order of lay off.</p>
<h4 align="left">III. STIPULATED ISSUE</h4>
<p>Did the Company violate the collective bargaining agreement when it transferred the Grievant on February 18, 2016 and if so, what shall be the remedy? (Tr. 4)</p>
<h4 align="left">IV. POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</h4>
<p>The Union Position</p>
<p>The Union summarizes the testimony of the several witnesses. As to the Grievant, it is emphasized that it is Article VII, Seniority which governs and that specifies that &ldquo;length of continuous service&rdquo; is to be taken into account. The testimony of Scott Martin was to the effect that he had been told in the grievance procedure that junior employees had better efficiencies. By Step C the Company had changed its story and was relying on a deviant Webster Qualification Form #2060. The grievance introduced by the Company at that stage was not on point. This shows that the Company will stop at nothing in an effort to frustrate the Grievant's seniority rights.</p>
<p>Mr. Martin also testified as to the bargaining history. He indicated that in the 2013 contract negotiations the language of Article VII, Section 4 was left the same. The <i>Company</i> in that negotiation tried to change the language of Article VII, Section 4 B. to require immediate ability to do the job. This suggested amendment was rejected. This colloquy shows the inconsistency in the Company's position. The Company is trying to get something through the arbitration procedure that it did not get in the course of its negotiations with the Union. Mr. Ken Bentz testified as to how Article VII, Section 4 had been applied in the past. Under that section seniority is to prevail. He cited a case concerning 30 inch grinders which show that the Company accommodated seniority. The testimony of Nick Spurck, the Vice-President of Manufacturing is also cited. He cited a claimed past practice. The Union concedes that this happens from time to time, but not all the time. Sometimes employees acquiesce, but that is their right and does not create a past practice.</p>
<p>Mr. Bentz also highlighted that there is no past practice on the provision and that the Company is twisting the terms of Article V, Section 12. Clearly the word &ldquo;transfer&rdquo; in Article VII, Section 4 covers all transfers.</p>
<p>In summary the Union has met its burden of proof. The Company's position is inconsistent and should not be sustained. Instead the grievance should be sustained and a remedy granted, namely that the Company apply Articl VII, Sections 3 and 4 in accord with its terms.</p>
<p>The Company Position</p>
<p>The Company maintains that the temporary transfer of the Grievant on February 18, 2016 was completely consistent with the Company's management rights and the temporary transfer provision in Article V, Section 12 of the CBA. The Company has exercised this right for years. The &ldquo;restriction&rdquo; of that provision is actually an authorization. That restriction has no application to this case. There is no obligation to confer or to take seniority into account. Similarly it is clear that the &ldquo;pay&rdquo; provision of Article IV, Section 10 was met by the Company in this case. There are no restrictions as to the method by which the Company is to make the temporary transfers. The transfers are made for rational, legitimate operational reasons, nor arbitrarily or punitively.</p>
<p>Even if it is assumed that the provisions of Article V, Section 12 are ambiguous, there is a longstanding past practice in favor of the Company's right to temporarily transfer the Grievant as it did on February 18, 2016. The Company has used its discretion, not seniority, on thousands of occasions over the past years to make transfers on the basis used in this case. Company Ex. 1 is the proof and shows the transfers in question. When faced with these facts, the Union chose to obfuscate. This attempt was unsuccessful and was eventually disproved by the contents of Co. Ex. 1 and the stipulation.</p>
<p>Beyond this, the Union's attempt to assert that the Company has not and cannot temporarily transfer without regard for seniority is not credible and is unequivocally refuted by documented evidence to the contrary. Mr. Martin's testimony on the point was contradictory and even asserted, for a while, that transfers on jobs <i>within</i> a classification were covered by seniority. He also conceded that transfers of the type made in this case were a regular occurrence and that they had never been grieved. He was left with incredibly asserting that each of these temporary transfers was covered by discussions with the Company. His assertions were in direct conflict with the terms of the parties' cba.</p>
<p>All of the Union's assertions about past practice are effectively rebutted by the testimony of Company Vice-President Spurck and its corroboration by Foundry Operations Manager Blott. The Union should not confuse collaboration with control.</p>
<p>Finally, the Union's argument that the seniority article of the cba governs this dispute is belied by a plain reading of the CBA as a whole. The fact is that Article V. Section 12 and the seniority article are two different beasts. The attempt must fall for a number of reasons. One is that a temporary transfer to a lower paid classification is to the employee's advantage because he/she keeps the higher pay, when such is not the case for permanent transfers.</p>
<p>When all is said and done, the contract must be read as a whole. When this is done there can be no other outcome than the denial of the grievance.</p>
<h4 align="left">V. DISCUSSION</h4>
<h4 align="left">A. Introduction</h4>
<p>This is a contract interpretation case concerning the validity of a temporary transfer of the Grievant on February 18, 2016 from his &ldquo;bid&rdquo; classification of Foundry Journeyman; sub-classification Squeeze Mold to a different classification, namely Foundry Operator: sub-classification Clean Up / Sort Bench. Several aspects of the matter are not in dispute. One is that in such a contract interpretation case it is the Union which has the burden of proof. A second is that the cited temporary transfer was actually made. A third is that the temporary transfer was made without any particular discussion with the Union and that the Union's approval was not sought. A fourth is that the Grievant was paid his pre-existing &ldquo;regular&rdquo; wage rate as a Foundry Journeyman for the work in question so that he did not suffer any financial harm from the temporary assignment in question.</p>
<p>The positions of the parties are relatively clear. The Company maintains that it has the largely unqualified right to make temporary transfers. There is no requirement that the temporary transfers be made on the basis of seniority or that they be first discussed with the Union or that the Union's consent be obtained. The Union's argument is that seniority prevails and that it is the junior-most employee who must be assigned to the temporary transfer. Or, the argument continues, the temporary transfer must at least be discussed with the Union and its approval obtained. At the fulcrum of the dispute are the terms of Article V, Section 12, quoted above, which governs &ldquo;temporary transfers&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The methodology for deciding such interpretative disputes is well established in the pantheon of arbitral authority. The arbitrator is first to examine the specific terms which the parties have negotiated. If they are clear and unambiguous, the arbitrator's duty is to apply them to the case as written.<ftnote num="3"><para>This requirement is also set out in Article III, Section 1 STEP D. of the parties' agreement which prohibits the arbitrator from altering, adding to, or subtracting from the <quote>expressed written provisions of this Agreement.</quote></para></ftnote> If they are ambiguous, reference may be had to such aids to interpretation as past practice and bargaining history for such assistance as they may provide in resolving the ambiguity.</p>
<p>We turn first to the express terms.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. The Express Terms</h4>
<p>Article V, Section 12 provides that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;SECTION 12 Temporary Transfers shall not be made by the Employer for a period in excess of forty-five (45) working days without the consent of the transferred employee unless such transfer is made as a replacement for an employee who is absent because of illness or injury.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This provision is one of limitation upon the Company as to the making of temporary transfers. But, there is only one limitation set out, i.e. that of the temporary transfer not exceeding forty-five working days without the consent of the employee.<ftnote num="4"><para>There is an exception to that limitation, i.e. in situations when the transfer is made as a replacement for an employee who is absent because of illness or injury. But, that exception to the limitation is not involved in this case and need not be further discussed.</para></ftnote> It is normally held that where one limitation upon a power is expressed, no other limitations are to be implied .<ftnote num="5"><para>The more erudite expression of the principle is <quote><italic>expressio unius est exclusio alterius</italic></quote> Black's Law Dictionary (West, Sixth Edition 1990) p. 581</para></ftnote> The basic reading then of the terms which the parties have negotiated concerning temporary transfers is that the Company may make them, subject only to the one expressed limitation, i.e. that concerning forty-five working days. There is no expressed limitation concerning proceeding on the basis of seniority or of discussing the proposed temporary transfer with the Union.</p>
<p>Of course the quoted provision of Article V, Section 12 occupies only three lines in the parties' 27 page collective bargaining agreement. Obviously if there is another provision in the agreement which requires that temporary transfers be made by seniority, then that provision would be equally applicable. The most likely place for such a provision would be in Article VII which governs &ldquo;Seniority&rdquo;. These provisions are quoted above.</p>
<p>That Article has provisions making length of service and ability the governing factor when there is to be a decrease in the working force or when there is to be a recall from layoff. But, there is also a provision which makes these factors applicable when there is to be a &ldquo;transfer&rdquo; or a &ldquo;promotion&rdquo;. Thus:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Section 4. In the event it becomes necessary to increase or decrease the working force and <b>in matters relating to transfer or promotion,</b> the following points shall be considered and where factors contained in Sub B are equal length of continuous service shall govern:</p>
<ol type="uc-letter" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Length of continuous service</p></li>
<li><p>Ability to perform the available work.&rdquo;</p></li></ol>
<p align="center">(bold added by arbitrator)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The use of the word &ldquo;transfer&rdquo; as being an occasion for the application of seniority raises an ambiguity. It either means that seniority/ability is applicable in <i>all</i> transfers (the Union interpretation) or it means that seniority/ability is applicable only in &ldquo;permanent&rdquo; transfers because the word &ldquo;temporary&rdquo; is not used. (the Company interpretation).</p>
<p>Given such an ambiguity, we turn to the aids to interpretation.</p>
<h4 align="left">C. Past Practice.</h4>
<p>It is widely accepted that long standing and mutually accepted past practices with respect to ambiguous language may be relied upon in interpreting ambiguous language. Here it is not entirely clear which party is claiming a past practice in its favor. Neutrality urges the conclusion that it is both. We turn to the claims.</p>
<p>On the Union side, the Grievant testified that since being awarded the vacancy as a Foundry Journeyman; Squeeze Mold he had been given many temporary assignments to Foundry Operators; Clean Up / Sort Bench without his seniority being considered. He testified that he had never grieved any of the temporary assignments as being a violation of the parties' agreement. A Past Chairman of the local union, Paul Bentz also testified. He had been Chairman during 32 years, from 1976 to 2008. He indicated that the past practice between the parties had been to discuss temporary assignments when they would result in a transferee's seniority being violated. The current Chairman, Scott Martin, testified that the Company had been abusing temporary transfers, especially with respect to the Grievant. Mr. Martin testified that he would remonstrate with the Company about some of the assignments, claiming that the transferee's seniority was being violated. Oftentimes, after these remonstrances, the Company would be more accommodating and change the assignment so that it was the junior in the classification who was made the subject to the temporary assignment.</p>
<p>The main testimony on the point for the Company was given by Nick Spurck, the Vice-President of Manufacturing. He had been in that position for some six years (Tr. 85) and was involved with the administration of the labor agreement. He said that the provisions of Article V, Section 12 had been in the contract since the creation of the bargaining unit. He testified that in all the temporary assignments which had been made during this period seniority had not been held to be the determining factor. By this, he explained, he did not assert that seniority was not given <i>any</i> consideration, but that it was only one of many factors. He also testified that the &ldquo;transfers&rdquo; which is set out in Article VII, Section 4 refers to &ldquo;permanent&rdquo; transfers not the &ldquo;temporary&rdquo; transfers covered by Article V, Section 12. Other testimony was received from Ed Blott, who has been Foundry Manager since 2012. His testimony was largely consistent with that of Vice President Spurck.</p>
<p>Eventually though, a stipulation was reached between the parties. It was that during the period between the Grievant's successful bid for the Foundry Journeyman Classification;: Squeeze Mold sub classification on May 3, 2015 and the date of the grievance on February 22, 2016 the Grievant and other employees had been temporarily transferred without seniority being deemed to be the controlling factor. (Tr. 96)</p>
<p>In addition to this the Company prepared a one and a half inch thick exhibit (Co. Ex. 1) of print-outs covering temporary transfers made of the Grievant between the dates of December 30, 2012 and January 3, 2016. The exhibit also showed the assignments of two employees junior to the Grievant, Brunthaver and Mangus on the days when the Grievant was being subjected to temporary assignments. The Company points out that there were eleven assignments during this period when the Grievant had a temporary assignment and his junior colleagues remained working in their bid classification of Foundry Journeyman. This exhibit is consistent with the stipulation discussed in the previous paragraph and with the testimony of the Grievant.</p>
<p>The conclusion then is that there is no prevailing past practice of making temporary assignments under Article V. Section 12 on the basis solely of seniority. In fact, there seems to be a widespread practice to the contrary, i.e. of not making them solely on the basis of seniority.</p>
<h4 align="left">D. Bargaining History.</h4>
<p>There is in arbitration a widespread use of bargaining history as an aid to the interpretation of ambiguous language. The impression is made that neither party relies strongly on this argument, even though it was indicated that there would be bargaining history evidence from both sides. (Tr. 19) The fact seems to be that the language of Article V, Section 12 has been in the parties' agreement, unchanged, as long as anyone can remember. There was no evidence with respect to any proposed changes to <i>that</i> language in the course of negotiations.</p>
<p>The main reference to bargaining history was a some testimony by Union Chairman Martin with respect to the course of the 2013 negotiations. (Tr. 53-54).<ftnote num="6"><para>See Union Post-Hearing Brief, p. 19.</para></ftnote> This contention was that in the course of these negotiations the terms of Article VII, Section 4 were not changed. But, the Company had introduced an attempt to amend those provisions to the effect that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Section B. shall be replaced to say:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>B. Previously performed the available work, may do so without training and there have been no changes to the machinery or equipment on which the work is being performed.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Chairman Martin testified that the Union successfully resisted this proposal to change the language. The Company did not dispute these aspects as a matter of fact.</p>
<p>But, proposed changes in the language of Article VII, Section 4 do not necessarily deal with the interpretation of Article V. Section 12. After all, one of the main issues of the present case is as to <i>which</i> of the two provisions is to govern.</p>
<p>The conclusion as to bargaining history is thus that it does not contribute meaningfully to the resolution of any ambiguities in the language under the microscope.</p>
<p>We turn to an overall conclusion.</p>
<h4 align="left">VI. CONCLUSION</h4>
<p>As stated at the outset, this case concerns a temporary transfer to the Grievant, Dion Payne, on February 18, 2016. The claim by the Union is that the parties' agreement, in Article VII, Section 4 requires that such temporary assignments be made on the same basis as layoffs and recalls, i.e. with regard to both seniority and ability to perform work.</p>
<p>Fortunately or unfortunately, the parties have selected an experienced arbitrator with over 51 years of experience in labor law and/or arbitration. In that time the arbitrator has never seen a contract provision or practice requiring that temporary assignments be made on the basis of seniority. This is stated merely to show that the Union has undertaken a heavy burden here to establish its case. It is to be remembered that there is no claim that the Grievant has been harmed financially. He was paid his pre-existing Foundry Journeyman wage for all his work on the temporary assignment.</p>
<p>The conclusion on the basis of the above discussion is that the terms of Article V, Section 12 prevail and there is no requirement that such temporary assignments be made solely on the basis of seniority. The aids to interpretation to not require otherwise.</p>
<p>To the extent that it may not be otherwise clear, the issue concerning the merits is answered in the negative, i.e. the Company did not violate the collective bargaining agreement when it transferred the Grievant on February 18, 2016 The award draws its essence from the arbitrator's interpretation of Articles V and VII of the parties' agreement and from the terms of the stipulated issue itself.</p>
<h4 align="left">VII. AWARD</h4>
<p class="continued">Grievance denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>