<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN ARBITRATION BETWEEN Associated Wholesale Grocers, Inc. and Teamsters Local Union 886</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS No. 15-56616</p>
<p>September 28, 2016.</p>
<p>Benjamin M. Shieber, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center">OPINION AND AWARD</h4>
<h4 align="left">I. Issues</h4>
<p>The Parties stipulated that the issues in this case are:</p>
<p>Did the Company violate the 2012-2020 collective bargaining agreement by the April 2015 shift bid?</p>
<p>If it did, what-should the remedy be? See R. 7.</p>
<h4 align="left">II. Facts</h4>
<p>The Company is a cooperative that provides groceries, frozen foods, and fruits and vegetables to its member stores. It operates a distribution center in Oklahoma City which employs approximately 300 employees of whom 174 are represented by the Union. The Company and the Union have been in a collective bargaining relationship since 1995 with the current contract effective 2012 to 2020. See U. Ex. 2, Article XXXVIII, 2012-2020 Agreement.</p>
<p>In April 2015 the Company posted a shift bid that provided for ten (10) jobs in the perishable area to work four days with a start time of 11:30 p.m., and a fifth day, Saturday with a start time of 9:00 a.m.<ftnote num="1"><para>One employee's start time for the four days was 9:30 p.m. with a Saturday start time of 8:00 a.m. This employee was in the receiver job and the other nine were in the forklift job.</para></ftnote> See Co. Ex. 2, April 2015 bid sheet.</p>
<p>The Union grieved the April 2015 bid &ldquo;on behalf of all employees&rdquo;.</p>
<p class="continued">The grievance stated,</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;AWG April 2015 bid is unfair, unjust and improper. It breaks all past practice of scheduling and bids. There is no history of mixing shifts. Defies common sense and established business practices. There is also an issue with biological clocks and safety concerns&rdquo;. See U. Ex. 1, Grievance No. 100-15-G.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Company denied the grievance and when the Parties were unable to resolve their dispute in the grievance procedure, this arbitration followed. A hearing, which was recorded in a transcript of 133 pages, was held on June 14, 2016. The Arbitrator received the Parties' briefs on September 19, 2016, on which date the case was submitted for decision.</p>
<h4 align="left">III. Decision</h4>
<p>The Company's bid procedure was described by Mr. Brent Warma, Warehouse Operations Manager, as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Basically the company creates a bid that encompasses all the jobs and the needs for the business and breaks it into number of jobs compared to number of people on the seniority roster. And then we post the bid for seven days.</p>
<p>After the seven days, each employee by seniority has the opportunity to come in and bid the position that they want.&rdquo; See Mr. Warma's testimony, R. 85.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The collective bargaining agreement requires the Company to post a bid sheet in the first week of January each year. It also empowers the Company to post other bids during the year at its discretion. See U. Ex. 2, 2012-2020 Agreement, Article XXI, Sections 5 and 6. In the past, in some years there have been as many as four or five bid sheets posted by the Company. See Mr. Warma's testimony, R. 85.</p>
<p>The bid sheet posted by the Company in January 2015 provided that all workers working Shift 1, the day shift, would start work in the morning usually at 9:00 a.m. And all workers working Shift 2, the night shift would usually start work at 10:30 p.m. See Co. Ex. 1, January 18, 2015 Bid Sheet.</p>
<p>The evidence proved that the January 15 Bid Sheet was in accord with a long-standing practice of the Company. The Union President testified without contradiction as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;It's since the inception of the contract, and I wasn't in the &prime;95 agreement, but I &mdash; I have the &prime;95 agreement. And in talking to long-term employees, when AWG took over the Homeland facility in 1995, the practice has been that if you work days and you bid days, that it was five days in a work week and it stayed the same. If you was on nights, it was five nights and the workweek was the same.&rdquo; See testimony of Mr. Ron Cobb, Union President, R. 30-31.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When it issued the April 2015 bid sheet the Company departed from this long standing practice by eliminating all Saturday jobs that would begin at night and by providing for ten Saturday jobs that were formerly night shift jobs to begin at 8:00 a.m. and 9:00 a.m. and end 8 hours later. See Co. Ex. 2, April 5, 2015 bid sheet.</p>
<p>The Union contentions were clearly stated by its counsel in his opening statement. He said, &ldquo;We contend that this is a &ndash; that this 17 plus year practice and custom was part of the CBA, it became part of the CBA as a term and condition of employment. And that Company cannot unilaterally change that because it is a term and condition of employment. That's our main contention.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We have an alternative contention that it is at least a mandatory subject of bargaining, which the Company may not change without negotiating to the point of impasse with the union and they did not do that.&rdquo; See Opening Statement by Mr. McCaffrey, R. 15 and Union Brief.</p>
<p>The Parties' collective bargaining agreement requires the Arbitrator to reject the Union's contentions.</p>
<p>The collective bargaining agreement contains the following provisions:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;The management of the warehouse and the direction of the working forces, including the planning, direction and control of warehouse operations, <i>the scheduling of work and the assignment of employees to such work</i> &hellip; the determination of manpower requirements &hellip; are vested solely and exclusively in the Company &hellip;.&rdquo; See U. Ex. 2, 2012-2020 Agreement, Article XIX (emphasis added).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The agreement also provides:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Hours of work shall be determined by the Company &hellip;.&rdquo; See U. Ex. 2, 2012-2020 Agreement, Article XX, Section 1.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These provisions are unambiguous. They clearly give the Company the power to schedule work of employees and fix the starting time for that work. The existence of a past practice does not empower the Arbitrator to override specific provisions of the collective bargaining agreement. The Arbitrator agrees with the numerous arbitrators who have held that past practice, regardless of how long-standing, does not override unambiguous provisions in the collective bargaining agreement. See <i>Associated Wholesale Grocers. Inc</i>., 81 LA 1126, 1128 (J. M. O'Reilly 1983); and the many cases cited in Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i>, p. 627, notes 119 and 120 (6 ed. 2003).</p>
<p>As for the Union's argument the change was &ldquo;at least a mandatory subject to bargaining&rdquo;, the Arbitrator finds that argument unconvincing. The Parties have bargained about the issue of the Company's power to schedule the work and determine the hours of work of employees, and the collective bargaining agreement sets forth in unambiguous provisions the agreement that they settled on.</p>
<p>The Union does not allege that the Company was motivated by anti-union animus or that the schedule change was arbitrary or unreasonable. As a matter of fact, the evidence proved that the schedule change was adopted for legitimate business reasons that resulted in substantial efficiency and monetary benefits for the Company. Uncontradicted testimony proved that as a result of the April 2015 bid the Company was able to reduce overtime work on Saturdays. See Mr. Warma's testimony, R. 107 and the testimony of Mr. Ellis Luttrull, Director of Distribution, R. 127-128. As a result of the April 2015 bid sheet no employees worked in the warehouse on Saturday nights. The fact that no one was working in the warehouse on Saturday night saved the Company about &dollar;1,600 a month in energy costs. See the uncontradicted testimony of Mr. Warma and Mr. Luttrull, R. 105 and 127. Mr. Warma summarized the result of the shift change by saying that it resulted in a more profitable operation. See Mr. Warma's testimony, R. 111.</p>
<p>Nor was there any evidence introduced showing an adverse effect on employee health and safety as a result of the 2015 shift change.</p>
<p>The unambiguous language of the collective bargaining agreement and the evidence require the Arbitrator to deny the grievance.</p>
<h4 align="left">V. Award</h4>
<p>The grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>