<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF THE ARBITRATION BETWEEN UPMC ALTOONA HOSPITAL AND SERVICE EMPLOYEES INTERNATIONAL UNION, HEALTHCARE PENNSYLVANIA</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Christopher E. Miles, Esquire Labor Arbitrator</p>
<p>DATE OF AWARD: October 10, 2016.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>I. <i>BACKGROUND</i></b></h4>
<p>The class action grievance considered herein was filed by the Service Employees International Union, Healthcare PA (hereinafter referred to as the &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) on behalf of the Registered Nurses employed by UPMC Altoona Hospital (hereinafter referred to as the &ldquo;Hospital&rdquo;). The Grievance Form, dated February 1, 2016, sets forth the following &ldquo;Statement of Grievance&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Only 5 RN's were paid &lsquo;Step bonus&rsquo; for 2015. Numerous other RN's qualified per CBA.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">As the remedy sought, the Union requested &ldquo;compliance with contract side letter regarding Step bonus for 2015. Make all qualified RN's whole in timely fashion.&rdquo;</p>
<p>By letter dated February 10, 2016, Ms. Michele Scanlan, Director of Human Resources, denied the grievance by stating that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Management calculated the payment of this Step Bonus as outlined in the Side Letter under Section 5, (f), which states &ldquo;Payment calculated using the 1/1/11 to 12/31/13 hourly rates for RNI, RNII, III for 1/1/13 on steps in Appendix A, no bonus payment if nurse goes off scale (i.e. achieves step 8 in 2014 then no payment in 2015 &amp; 2016).</p>
<p class="continued">As payment was calculated according to the terms of the Side Letter of Understanding and payment given to those RN's who qualified for this bonus, this grievance is denied.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The grievance was processed in accordance with the procedure contained in the parties' collective bargaining agreement<ftnote num="1"><para>Agreement between The Altoona Regional Health System and SEIU Healthcare Pennsylvania, CTW, CLC, effective January 1, 2011 to December 31, 2013 (hereinafter referred to as the <quote>Agreement</quote>).</para></ftnote> and having been unable to resolve the case, it was appealed to arbitration. The undersigned was selected to hear and decide the issue and a hearing was conducted on July 6, 2016 in Altoona, Pennsylvania. At that time, the parties were afforded full opportunity to present testimony and evidence, to cross-examine the witnesses, all of whom were sworn, and to make arguments in support of their respective positions. Upon receipt and exchange of the parties' post-hearing briefs on August 22, 2016, the record in this case was closed.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>II. <i>SUMMARY OF THE TESTIMONY AND EVIDENCE</i></b></h4>
<p>Mr. Zach Zobrist testified that he is the Treasurer of the Union and he participated as Chief Negotiator during the negotiations for the 2014 Agreement which began in October 2013. He recalled that there were about 35 negotiating sessions and a one-day strike prior to reaching a tentative agreement in February 2014. According to Mr. Zobrist, in the previous Agreement from January 1, 2011 to December 31, 2013, the across the board wage increase was also reflected in the step system. He stated that there was no discussion about the increase not being applied to the step. After the parties reached a tentative Agreement, Management drafted a side letter. The Union wanted to keep the old steps, but the Hospital did not want steps. He conceded that the agreement was that there would be one more year of steps and cash equivalent bonuses would be paid at the end of the year for years two and three. Mr. Zobrist pointed out that there were a lot of nurses who were not at Step 8, so they should be getting bonuses.</p>
<p>On cross-examination, Mr. Zobrist confirmed that this was the first Agreement between the parties. He maintained that with regard to wages the Union wanted three more years of steps but the Hospital wanted only one more year of the steps and there would be a cash equivalent bonus in lieu of the steps. Mr. Zobrist was questioned about his understanding of item (f) of the side letter at Paragraph 5, Wage Steps for 2014. He said the 2013 chart of hourly rates for RN was used as the basis for one more year of the steps in 2014 and a cash equivalent bonus in 2015 and 2016 for employees who were below Step 8. In this regard, the rates of pay would not increase in 2015 and 2016. He stated that employees hired after December 31, 2013 or who reached Step 8 would not get a bonus payment.</p>
<p>Mr. Zobrist made reference to the chart in the side letter and he discussed the various scenarios concerning an increase on an employee's anniversary and then the 2.5&percnt; increase in March. In the Union's view, the person who was still at Step 4 should have gotten the equivalent of the difference between Step 4 and Step 5 and that difference is the amount of the bonus. If the Step system would have continued, the rate of pay would have been higher at Step 5. The Union wanted three more years of Steps but the Hospital would not agree and instead the bonus was settled upon.</p>
<p>According to Mr. Zobrist, the amount of the bonus would be the amount that they would have earned with the 2.5&percnt; pay raise. He stated that Subsection (f) in the side letter means that in 2013 the employees would get one more step and then they would get bonuses for 2014 and 2015. He added that wages would not increase in 2014 and 2015 but the employees would get the bonuses.</p>
<p>Mr. Chris Ricken testified that he was the Chief Negotiating Officer for the Hospital and attended all of the sessions related to the current Agreement. He recalled that the parties agreed that the step increase would continue for one year, after which the employees would be given a bonus, based upon the 2013 hourly rate, if not at Step 8 level. He pointed out that the numbers on the chart included in the side letter reflect the anyone below Step 8 would get the next Step rate of pay.</p>
<p>On cross-examination, he stated that on the date of ratification, the employees got an increased rate of pay and they would receive the 2&percnt; rate increase thereafter. He indicated that at their anniversary date they would go to the rate for the next step just for 2014. In addition, he noted that the employees who reached their anniversary date prior to ratification would get the step increase for 2013.</p>
<p>Ms. Kandy Kelley testified that she is the Human Resources Information Specialist. She prepared the spreadsheet showing the employees who received bonuses in 2014. She explained that she compared these employees with their step and range and what their rate was. Reference was made to employee Musselman on the chart who was a RNI at Step 5 and she was promoted to RNIII and Step 6. Musselman went from &dollar;28.85 to &dollar;31.52 because she got the 2.5&percnt; plus the 4&percnt; for the step increase. The bonus was the difference from &dollar;31.52 and &dollar;31.80. She stated that the same formula was applied to the other employees.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>IV. <i>RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF THE AGREEMENT</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>ARTICLE 20</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>RATES OF PAY</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>SIDE LETTER OF UNDERSTANDING</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>5. Wage Steps for 2014</b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">The following payments are in lieu of the steps being in the contract.</p>
<p class="continued">(b) Payment to each eligible nurse a bonus at the end of each calendar year in successor contract.</p>
<p class="continued">(c) No bonus payment to new employees hired after 12/31/13.</p>
<p class="continued">(d) Eligible nurse on active seniority list on 12/31/13 &amp; on steps.</p>
<p class="continued">(e) Payment based on budgeted hours.</p>
<p class="continued">(f) calculated using the 1/1/11 to 12/31/13 hourly rates for RN I, II, III for 1/1/13 on steps in Appendix A. (no bonus payment if nurse goes off scale, i.e. achieves step 8 in 2014 then no payment in 2015 &amp; 2016)</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>V. <i>CONTENTIONS OF THE PARTIES</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. <i>Union</i></b></h4>
<p>The Union contends that the issue in this case involves a &ldquo;side letter&rdquo; that was negotiated off the record after more than 35 sessions. The Employer sought cost savings. The side letter authored by the Hospital references wage steps for 2014. Traditionally, in the Agreement, employees would advance a step on the anniversary date of hire. The Hospital wanted to eliminate the steps. It maintains that in all previous Agreements, if there was a wage increase, the percentage increase was applied to the steps. The Union contends that the intent was that the wage increases would be applied to the steps as shown in Appendix A. It points out that there are 800 nurses in the bargaining unit; however, only five employees received the step increase at the end of 2014.</p>
<p>According to the Union, the question that needs to be answered is should the percentage increases in the second and third year of the contract be applied to the Step Bonus Scale in the Side Letter of Understanding? The Union argues that the Agreement should be applied to the Wage Steps. The Union calls attention to the analysis of the side letter by Witness Zach Zobrist, who stated that:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>There would be no hiring grid for new hires and the Wage Steps would not be applicable to new hires.</p></li>
<li><p>The Wage Steps were increased by 2&percnt; in the Wage Steps for 2014. The Steps were to be increased by the percentage wage rate.</p></li>
<li><p>Nurses eligible for one step, those below step eight, would be eligible for one more step increase in the first year of the Agreement.</p></li>
<li><p>Wage increases as well as the &ldquo;cash equivalent&rdquo; one of the four big issues as outlined in the union flyer.</p></li>
<li><p>Mr. Rickens indicated that the Hospital was the author and proposer of the language found in the current Agreement concerning casual rates of pay increases, as evidenced in the Tentative Agreement that was reached on February 27, 2014.</p></li>
<li><p>In every prior contract, the percentage increase would be applied to the wage steps.</p></li>
</ol>
<p class="continued">The bonus payments in place of the annual wage steps to affected employees were very important to both parties. The Union wanted to protect some type of compensation through the wage steps. The Hospital wanted to keep future hourly wage increases in check and agreed to the bonuses versus wage steps in the second and third year of the Agreement. Accepting the Hospital's position that there would be no increase in the wage step scale results in the absurd conclusion that the only way to get a step bonus is if an RN moves from RN1 position to an RN2 position. In such a situation, the employee moves from a lower steps scale to a higher step scale whereby the RN is below the step scale for an RN2.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the wage steps were very important and ultimately one of the key pieces that was settled in order to reach a tentative agreement and ultimately the current Agreement. Testimony from Zach Zobrist provided proof that the parties agreed to the side letter prior to the increases in the second and third year and is reflected in Article 20 Rates of Pay. Every previous contract that included the percentage wage increase would be applied to the step wages.</p>
<p>To accept the Hospital's premise that the wage step would not be adjusted by the percentage increase would be unreasonable and only nurses going from RN1 to RN2 would benefit from the contractual language. Considering what the parties went through (over 35 bargaining sessions and a one-day strike), the Union asserts that it would be unreasonable to argue a point that affects only four out of 800 nurses.</p>
<p>Based upon the foregoing, the Union requests that the grievance be sustained and the Hospital be ordered to apply the percentage wage increase to the step Wage for years two and three of the Agreement. The Union also requests that the Arbitrator retain jurisdiction for a period of 60 days in case there is any disagreement as to the Award.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. <i>Hospital</i></b></h4>
<p>The Hospital points out that this is the first Agreement between UPMC and SEIU and there is no history or tradition to apply in this case. It contends that even though the parties were engaged in protracted negotiations and even had a strike, the parties agreed that there would be a final step increase that would be paid out in the form of a bonus to eligible employees at the end of each calendar year of the Agreement. The steps would conclude at the end of 2014 and the bonus would be calculated on the basis of the 2013 steps.</p>
<p>According to the Hospital, the side letter provides that any bonus will be calculated using the hourly rates described in Appendix A of the previous Agreement that was in effect from January 1, 2011 to December 31, 2013. It points out that under the previous wage step system, each nurse was eligible for two wage increases every year of the contract; i.e., on January 1<sup>st</sup> of each year, every nurse would move down one row in the chart to the new annual rates and then, on the nurse's anniversary date, the employee would move over one column on the chart to the next step until the top step (Step 8) was reached. However, the current Agreement provides that each nurse is eligible for one pay increase per year at the beginning of the year and those who were eligible would receive a bonus based on the following criteria: 1) the nurse was hired before December 31, 2013; 2) the nurse was on the active payroll and was on one of the steps (except Step 8) as of December 31, 2013; and the hourly rate based on the 2013 wage scale. Specifically, on January 1, 2014, the nurse would receive a 2&percnt; wage increase and at the end of 2014, the amount of bonus would be the difference between the current hourly rate and the hourly rate for the next step (based upon the 2013 Agreement) multiplied by the budgeted hours of work. In the final year, the hourly wage would be increased by 2.5&percnt; on January 1, 2015 and any bonus would be based upon the same criteria. In this regard, the Hospital asserts that in 2015, only five nurses met the requirements and were paid the bonus.</p>
<p>The Hospital submits that there is no language in the Agreement or the side letter to support the Union's claim that the hourly rates on the step chart should have been increased by the same amount each year. It maintains that the annual bonus is clearly tied to the rates on the chart from the previous Agreement with no reference to increasing those rates. The Hospital suggests that the Union is attempting to gain a benefit through arbitration that was not negotiated. Based on the foregoing, the Hospital requests that the grievance be denied.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>VI. <i>DISCUSSION AND FINDINGS</i></b></h4>
<p>The issue to be resolved herein is whether the Hospital improperly implemented Item 5 of the Side Letter of Understanding concerning Wage Steps for 2014 and thereby violated the provisions of the Agreement by failing to pay bonuses in 2015 to certain nurses who were hired before December 31, 2013.</p>
<p>The record developed in this case reveals that the Altoona Regional Hospital was acquired by UPMC on July 1, 2013 and became UPMC Altoona (the &ldquo;Hospital&rdquo;). The collective bargaining agreement covering the nurses that was in effect at the time of the acquisition, expired on December 31, 2013. Extensive negotiations, which included a one-day strike, resulted in a Side Letter which provided for one final step increase and a bonus to eligible employees at the end of each calendar year of the Agreement. This grievance was filed after only five nurses out of approximately 800 received a bonus payment in 2015. Although the Hospital sought the elimination of the Wage Steps, the Union believes that bonuses should be based upon an annual increase in the rates of pay for each Step, in accordance with the past practice which would provide bonuses to more nurses.</p>
<p>The Side Letter of Understanding was not included in the Agreement. Nevertheless, the Side Letter does not say what the Union is arguing as there is no reference whatsoever to increasing the rates for the Step Wages. Reference is specifically made to Appendix A as far as the bonus calculation using the &ldquo;1/1/11 to 12/31/13 hourly rates for RN I, II, III for 1/1/13 on steps in Appendix A&rdquo;. There is no mention of any continuing Step increases going forward. Indeed, the parties agreed that the bonuses would be based upon the rates reflected in Appendix A of the Agreement which expired on December 31, 2013. It appears that the Union assumed the Steps could be increased each year based upon the percentage increase, but that is not what it states.</p>
<p>Consequently, it is found that the Union did not meet its burden of proving a violation in this case and the grievance is denied.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>The grievance considered herein challenged the Hospital's implementation of the Side Letter of Understanding regarding the Step Wages and the calculation of bonus payments. However, the Union failed to establish that the parties agreed that the rates for the Step Wages should be increased each year as was the practice under the previous Agreement. Consequently, the grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>