<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>UNITED STATES STEEL CORPORATION Keetac Plant and UNITED STEELWORKERS Local Union No. 2660</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No. USS-47,931</p>
<p>Grievance No. KEE-12-0064</p>
<p>August 23, 2016.</p>
<p>David A. Peterson, Arbitration</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>BACKGROUND</i></h4>
<p>1/ This grievance from Keetac claims Grievant, a Labor Grade 4 Maintenance Technician - Electrical, was improperly denied overtime pay for hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours during workdays when he was on a 12-hour Alternative Work Schedule. Violations of Article 5 and Appendix 0 of the September 1, 2012 Minnesota Ore Operations Basic Labor Agreement are alleged.</p>
<p>2/ Article 5 and Appendix 0 of the 2012 Basic Labor Agreement provide in part as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE FIVE - WORKPLACE PROCEDURES</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">Section C. Hours of Work</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">6. Alternative Work Schedule</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Company may adopt alternative work schedules consisting of ten (10) or twelve (12) hour per day scheduling with the approval of the Local Union President/Unit Chair, the Grievance Chair, the District No. 11 Director and sixty percent (60&percnt;) of the Employees who are impacted by the alternative schedule.</p>
<p class="continued">Approval of an alternative work schedule may be revoked at any time more than six (6) months after its implementation by a simple majority vote of the Employees who are impacted by the schedule. Following such revocation, the Company shall reinstate a normal schedule as promptly as possible.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Section D. Overtime</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">2. Conditions Under Which Overtime Rates Shall Be Paid</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Unless worked pursuant to an agreed upon Alternative Work Schedule, overtime at the rate of one-and-one half times the Regular Rate of Pay shall be paid for:</p>
<p class="continued">a. hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday;</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">APPENDIX O - SPECIAL PAY CALCULATIONS</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">APPENDIX O-2: USS-USW UNDERSTANDING ON ALTERNATIVE WORK SCHEDULES,</p>
<p class="continued">Alternative Work Schedules (AWS), as contemplated by the Basic Labor Agreement, involve the use of ten (10) and twelve (12) hour per day scheduling without the payment of daily overtime. The process through which such schedules may be adopted is set forth in Article Five, Section C-6 of that Agreement. In addition, the parties herewith express their understanding of how certain other contractual matters, impacted through the use of AWS, are to be handled when. an AWS is utilized.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Overtime</i></h4>
<p class="continued">An Employee on an AWS shall only receive overtime pay for hours worked in excess of their scheduled shift or hours worked in excess of forty (40) hours in a payroll week, subject to the non-duplication provisions.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>3/ According to the evidence presented at the hearing Grievant was among the group of Maintenance Technician - Electrical employees who voted on whether or not to approve the adoption of this 12-hour AWS, although prior to the actual implementation of this AWS in July 2011 Grievant was displaced to a regular 8-hour day shift position as the result of other employees exercising their greater seniority to secure a place on this AWS. Subsequently, in November 2012, one of the employees on this AWS who possessed greater seniority than Grievant sustained an off-duty injury and went off work on Sickness and Accident (S&amp;A). The injured employee was expected to be off work for a number of months. Grievant was asked to fill-in on this AWS temporary, but extended, vacancy and Grievant agreed to do so. In November 2012 Grievant was then reassigned from his 8-hour day shift position, where he received overtime for hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday and a meal if he worked more than ten (10) consecutive hours, to this extended temporary vacancy on the 12-hour AWS, where he was treated the same as other employees on the AWS: he received overtime only for hours worked in excess of his scheduled twelve (12) hours in a workday and he received a meal allowance if he worked more than fourteen (14) consecutive hours. Grievant filed this December 2012 grievance seeking daily overtime pay for hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday on this AWS.</p>
<p>4/ Grievant testified that at the time this 12-hour AWS was being considered by the Electrical Group he attended an informational meeting with Company and Union representatives and, based on the presentation, he understood that whenever an employee on an 8-hour schedule was assigned to fill-in for a temporary vacancy on the 12-hour AWS the employee so assigned would still get overtime after eight (8) hours and would still get a meal if the employee worked more than ten (10) hours. Grievant stated that, prior to this case, he had in fact received overtime after eight (8) hours and a meal after ten (10) hours when he was assigned to this AWS to fill-in for vacation-related vacancies. He also stated that he has received overtime after eight (8) hours and a meal after ten (10) hours when he has been assigned to this AWS to fill-in for temporary vacancies subsequent to this case. Grievant recalled that the only reason he was given for why he had been treated differently in the present case is that Management determined the S&amp;A vacancy he was filling was a &ldquo;long term vacancy&rdquo; and thus justified paying him as an AWS employee.</p>
<p>5/ The Local Union President testified that when the parties at Keetac discussed the adoption of Alternative Work Schedules they made reference to the May 6, 2004 Garraux/Conway USS-USWA Understanding on Alternative. Work Schedules (now basically set forth in Appendix 0-2) and had meetings to review all the issues involved. The President said the parties ultimately agreed on the terms for an Alternative Work Schedule - 12 Hour Shift Agreement. That Agreement, dated September 24, 2010 and signed the same day by the then President of Local 2660 and the current President who was the Local 2660 Grievance Committee Chairman at the time, reads in relevant part as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">In addition to the May 6, 2004 Garraux/Conway USS-USWA Understanding on Alternative Work Schedules, the following are additional clarifications on the proposed implementation of an Alternative Work Schedule (AWS) in accordance with Article 5 Section C-4 as follows:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Full Week Guarantee - The Company shall be deemed to have met its obligations under Article Five, Section C-4 provided an Employee scheduled to work an AWS has an opportunity to work as scheduled or take vacation and is paid in accordance with these guidelines. The Company reserves the right to schedule employees off who otherwise would have been working on a holiday(s) and will still be deemed to have met the full week guarantee.</p></li>
<li><p>Additional Hours - The Company retains the right to schedule additional hours as it deems necessary. The Company also reserves the right to temporarily schedule an 8-hour pattern.</p></li>
<li><p>Meal Allowance - The Company agrees to provide a meal allowance for employees working more than fourteen (14) consecutive hours. The Union acknowledges that no overtime meals will be provided to employees working more than 10-hours on an AWS regardless of whether the employee(s) are working a scheduled shift or an extra shift. The parties agree the Company will have met its obligations under Article 5-C-7 and Article 5-D-5 of the 2008 BLA.</p></li>
<li><p>21-Turn Rotating Shift Reinstatement The parties agree in the event of a majority vote to revoke the AWS, the Company will discontinue scheduling on the basis of the AWS within 60-90 days. The parties further agree that the current agreed to 21-turn rotating shift patterns may be reinstated and considered an approved pattern. The Company retains the right to return to a 21-shift pattern in the event the Company determines the AWS is not meeting the needs of the operation.</p></li>
<li><p>Applicability - Initially, the Company intends that the AWS would apply to Mine and Crusher operating employees currently on a 21-shift rotation. In the event the Company chooses and the parties agree to offer an AWS to other groups of employees, this agreement may be used to implement an AWS in those locations as well.</p></li>
<li><p>Vacations - The Company agrees to allow the daily increment option for calendar year 2011 if elected by more than <i>50&percnt;</i> of the affected employees as a group in Mine and Crusher operations.</p></li>
<li><p>Hot Relief/Staggered Shifts - The Company retains the right to incorporate the hot relief and/or staggered shifts as deemed necessary.</p></li>
<li><p>Sunday Premium - The parties agree that any potential for increased costs due to an AWS versus the current 21 shift rotation is undesirable. Therefore, notwithstanding anything to the contrary, the parties agree that for any Employee regularly working an AWS pattern, any hours worked on Sunday in excess of eight (8) shall be paid as overtime.</p></li></ul></blockquote>
<p>6/ The President stated that the parties' understandings and agreements on the AWS were explained to the bargaining unit employees by the Department Manager of Labor Relations via a PowerPoint presentation. The President, offered a series of thirty-seven pages of slides or screenshots from this PowerPoint presentation, and the witness noted that a portion of the slide or screenshot on page twenty-seven of this exhibit directly addressed the AWS temporary vacancy issue in the following language:</p>
<blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><i>VACANCIES</i></h4>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Employees (from outside area) backfilling AWS pattern will be required to work entire shift but will receive OT per existing rules.</p></li></ul></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The President insisted this language reflected the parties&rsquo; mutual understanding and agreement that only incumbents of an AWS were giving up the right to receive overtime for working in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday, and that the employees who were used to fill temporary vacancies on an AWS, regardless of the duration of the temporary vacancy, were to retain the right to receive overtime for working in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday. The President contended that, with the exception of this case, the Company had and has consistently paid regular shift employees filling temporary vacancies on an AWS in this manner. He offered some of Grievant's pay records to support this contention.</p>
<p>7/ The President acknowledged, on cross-examination, that the agreement being relied on here (to the effect that employees not incumbent to an AWS who are used to fill temporary vacancies on an AWS retain their right to receive daily overtime for hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday) is a 2010 verbal agreement between the local parties. When the witness was questioned how such a verbal local agreement could be considered enforceable in light of Article 5, Section A-6-a (which requires that &ldquo;After May 20, 2003, all Local Working Conditions must be reduced to writing and signed by the Plant Manager and the Local Union President/Unit Chair&rdquo;), he answered that other than in the present case Management has consistently complied with this local agreement and has thus recognized its existence. The witness noted, too, that the Alternative Work Schedule - 12 Hour Shift Agreement at Keetac does not specify that regular shift employees filling temporary vacancies on the AWS are to be considered as AWS employees whereas the Alternative Work Schedule, 12 Hour Shift Agreement at Minntac, dated February 16, 2016 and signed by the President of Local 1938 and by the Local 1938 Grievance Committee Chairman on February 24, 2016, does contain the following language: &ldquo;Vacancies: To clarify any misunderstanding in prior AWS agreements, Employees filling in for temporary vacancies, of any duration, on the AWS will be considered to be an AWS employee, for all purposes including overtime and meal allowance purposes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>8/ The Department Manager of Labor Relations testified the local parties bargained for the adoption of this AWS at Keetac, consistent with the May 6, 2004 Garraux/Conway USS-USWA Understanding on Alternative Work Schedules, and that the mutual understandings and agreements ultimately reached between the local parties were reduced to writing in the Alternative Work Schedule - 12 Hour Shift Agreement dated September 24, 2010. The Department Manager stated there is no written agreement to the effect that an employee not on an AWS who is used to cover a. temporary vacancy on an AWS at Keetac is entitled to receive overtime for hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday, and he noted that Appendix 0-2 expressly specifies that an employee on an AWS is only to receive overtime for hours worked in excess of their scheduled shift or in excess of forty (40) hours in a payroll week. Appendix 0-2 does not exclude an employee on an AWS who may be there on a temporary vacancy from this overtime limitation. With regard to the PowerPoint slide reading in part &ldquo;Employees (from outside area) backfilling AWS pattern will be required to work entire shift but will receive OT per existing rules&rdquo;, the witness claimed the &ldquo;from outside area&rdquo; language referred to instances of &ldquo;resource sharing&rdquo; with other unrelated departments and not to all employees outside this AWS and certainly not to Grievant who is a Maintenance Technician - Electrical in the Electrical Department.</p>
<p>9/ The Union contends Grievant was entitled to have been paid overtime for all hours he worked in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday on this AWS, and to have received an overtime meal after working ten (10) hours, on the dates at issue despite the fact he was on an AWS where other employees received no overtime unless they worked in excess of twelve (12) hours in a workday and received a stipend rather than an overtime meal if they worked more than fourteen (14) consecutive hours. The Union insists Grievant was so entitled because he was on the 12-hour AWS as a fill-in to cover a temporary vacancy and he was not an incumbent to the AWS. The Union asserts the parties had an understanding and an agreement that employees not incumbent to an AWS who were used to fill-in on an AWS temporary vacancy would not be considered an AWS employee and would continue to receive overtime after eight (8) hours and an overtime meal after ten (10) consecutive hours. The Union notes Grievant's case was, to its knowledge and belief, the first time the Company treated an employee who was not an incumbent to an AWS in the same manner for overtime and overtime meal/stipend purposes as if the employee was an incumbent to the AWS; the Company was said to have otherwise followed the parties&rsquo; understanding and agreement on how regular shift employees filling AWS temporary vacancies were to be treated for overtime purposes, both before and after this case, including paying Grievant overtime after eight (8) hours and providing him with an overtime meal after ten (10) hours when he filled-in on AWS temporary vacancies subsequent to this incident. The Union requests the grievance be sustained.</p>
<p>10/ The Company maintains Grievant was not entitled to have been paid overtime for all hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday, or to have received an overtime meal after ten (10) hours rather than a stipend when he may have worked more than fourteen (14) consecutive hours, because on the dates at issue he was on a 12-hour AWS which, pursuant to Article 5, Section C-6, had been adopted with the approval of the District 11 Director, the Local Union President, the Grievance Chair and at least sixty percent (60&percnt;) of the impacted employees. The Company asserts that, in accordance with Appendix 0-2, employees on an AWS receive overtime pay only for hours worked in excess of their scheduled twelve (12) hours in a workday or in excess of forty (40) hours in a payroll week. The Company rejects the notion that Grievant may properly accept an assignment to an AWS pattern, knowing what it entails and enjoying the additional days off, and yet expect to be treated differently than other employees in the AWS group with respect to overtime and overtime meals because he is filling a temporary vacancy. The Company denies the AWS process contemplates such exceptions or that any enforceable practice exists which would compel this result. The Company requests the grievance be denied.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>FINDINGS</i></h4>
<p>11/ Grievant claims he was improperly denied overtime pay for hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours during workdays when he was filling a temporary, but extended, vacancy on a 12-hour Alternative Work Schedule beginning in November 2012. It was represented that this was the first instance at Keetac where a regular shift employee was used to fill a temporary vacancy on an AWS and did not receive overtime pay for hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday and did not receive a meal after working more than ten (10) consecutive hours.</p>
<p>12/ Article 5, Section C-6 of the 2012 Basic Labor Agreement authorizes the adoption of Alternative Work Schedules consisting of twelve (12) hour per day scheduling with the approval of the Local Union President/Unit Chair, the Grievance Chair, the District No. 11 Director and sixty percent (60&percnt;) of the employees who are impacted by the alternative schedule. It was undisputed that the 12-hour Alternative Work Schedule in this case received the required approvals, including the approval of at least sixty percent (60&percnt;) of the Electrical Group employees impacted by the alternative schedule, and that this AWS was then properly implemented. Grievant, a Maintenance Technician - Electrical, was among the impacted employees and had a vote, although he was displaced to a regular 8-hour shift position by the time this AWS was implemented in 2011.</p>
<p>13/ When Grievant accepted the assignment to this 12-hour AWS to cover for the temporary, but extended, vacancy resulting from an S&amp;A related absence of another employee on this AWS, Grievant received overtime pay for hours worked in excess of twelve (12) hours in a workday and in excess of forty (40) hours in a payroll week and he received a meal allowance if he worked in excess of fourteen (14) consecutive hours as did other employees on this AWS.</p>
<p>14/ Article 5, Section D-2 of the 2012 Basic Labor Agreement provides that overtime shall be paid for hours worked in excess of eight (8) hours in a workday unless such excess hours are &ldquo;worked pursuant to an agreed upon Alternative Work Schedule&rdquo;. In this case Grievant was working pursuant to an agreed upon 12-hour AWS. Notably, too, Appendix 0-2 of the 2012 Basic Labor Agreement expressly recognizes that an AWS may &ldquo;involve the use of &hellip; twelve (12) hour per day scheduling without the payment of daily overtime&rdquo; and further provides: &ldquo;An Employee on an AWS shall only receive overtime pay for hours worked in excess of their scheduled shift or hours worked in excess of forty (40) hours in a payroll week, subject to the non-duplication provisions.&rdquo; The Board finds Grievant to have been an employee &ldquo;on an AWS&rdquo; while he was filling this extended temporary vacancy. The Board does not find Appendix 0-2 to distinguish between an employee on an AWS filling such a temporary vacancy and an employee on an AWS filling a permanent vacancy, and nothing in the Alternative Work Schedule - 12 Hour Shift Agreement signed by the local parties on September 24, 2010 is found to support this distinction for overtime purposes. Moreover, regardless of the interpretation of the cited PowerPoint slide referring to vacancies which the impacted employees were shown prior to voting on whether to approve this AWS, which was ultimately implemented in 2011, the Board cannot reasonably conclude that this PowerPoint slide constitutes an enforceable local agreement in light of the fact Article 5, Section A-6 of the Basic Labor Agreement plainly requires that after May 20, 2003 all local working conditions must be in writing and be signed by the Local Union President and the Plant Manager.</p>
<p>15/ The Board acknowledges there was credible evidence offered at the hearing that the manner in which Grievant was treated for overtime purposes while on this AWS during the period in question was not consistent with how he and others had and have been treated while filling apparently shorter or day-to-day temporary vacancies on this AWS both before and after the time this grievance arose, but the Board does not find it to have been shown on this record that Grievant was contractually entitled to be treated differently than other employees on this AWS for overtime purposes during the period in question. The Board finds no contractual violation to have occurred here, and under Article 5, Section I-6-b of the Basic Labor Agreement the Board lacks the &ldquo;jurisdiction or authority to add to, detract from or alter in any way&rdquo; the provisions of the Agreement. In the absence of a proven violation of Grievant's contractual rights this grievance can only be denied.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>AWARD</i></h4>
<p>16/ The grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>