<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION BETWEEN CITY OF CLEVELAND AND CLEVELAND POLICE PATROLMEN'S ASSOCIATION</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>CASE NO. 53 390-00330 12</p>
<p>July 31, 2013.</p>
<p>James M. Mancini, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>OPINION AND AWARD</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>SUBMISSION</b></i></h4>
<p>This matter concerns a grievance filed by Police Officer Nikolai Przybylski. The grievance alleged that Officer Przybylski had been improperly given a two day suspension in violation of the Collective Bargaining Agreement between the City of Cleveland (hereinafter referred to as the Employer or City) and the Cleveland Police Patrolmen's Association (hereinafter referred to as the Union or CPPA). The arbitration hearing was held on April 19, 2013 at Cleveland City Hall. The parties subsequently submitted post-hearing briefs.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>BACKGROUND</b></i></h4>
<p>The Grievant, Nikolai Przybylski, has been employed as a Cleveland Police Officer for approximately fifteen years. He is currently assigned to the City's Fourth Police District.</p>
<p>On January 1, 2012, Officer Przybylski was working a traffic detail at a Cleveland Browns versus Pittsburgh Steelers home game. Officer Przybylski was assigned with another officer to direct traffic at a pedestrian crossing near the stadium.</p>
<p>As numerous fans were leaving the game, two police cars approached the Grievant's intersection with their lights and sirens activated, escorting a third vehicle. Officer Przybylski stopped pedestrians on both sides of the street to allow the police vehicles to proceed through the intersection. However, one individual, later identified as Jason Currie, stepped off the curb and started to walk across the street in violation of Officer Przybylski's order. Mr. Currie did not stop and walked across the street as the police vehicles made their way through the intersection.</p>
<p>The Grievant stated that he ordered Mr. Currie to stop but he kept on walking. He then pointed his flashlight at him because it had gotten dark outside and the area under the bridge is not well lit. The Grievant further indicated that because of Mr. Currie's non-compliance, he physically grabbed and pulled him out of the street so that the police vehicles could go through the intersection. At that point, he told Currie to stay on the curb until the vehicles passed. However after the first police vehicle made it through the intersection, Mr. Currie once again stepped off the sidewalk into the street. Officer Przybylski testified that he ordered Currie to get back on the sidewalk and again shined his flashlight at him. Instead, Mr. Currie continued to walk into the street, approaching the police car that was going through the intersection with his lights and sirens activated. Officer Przybylski stated that he attempted to grab Currie but he actually went in front of the moving police vehicle and ran to the sidewalk on the other side of the street.</p>
<p>After the police vehicles had passed through and the pedestrians were now able to cross the street, the Grievant stated that he chased after Mr. Currie. When he caught up with him, he noticed that Currie had red glassy eyes, a staggered stance, and alcohol on his breath. As a result, the Grievant stated that he told Mr. Currie that he was under arrest for disorderly conduct and intoxication. The Grievant asked Currie to place his hands behind his back so that he could be handcuffed. However as the Grievant attempted to place the handcuffs on him, Currie walked away from the Grievant.</p>
<p>Officer Przybylski once again chased after Mr. Currie who continued to fail to comply with his orders. The Grievant then pulled out his pepper spray and told Currie that he would have to pepper spray him if he did not comply. He warned him that he had to stop resisting. At that point, Mr. Currie put his hands behind his back and allowed the Grievant to cuff him. The Grievant indicated that Currie was about six foot two inches and weighed about 275 pounds.</p>
<p>As Officer Przybylski began to escort Mr. Currie to his police vehicle, Currie kept pulling back and started to complain about the handcuffs. He also yelled that he was not going to jail. As they approached the police car, Currie dropped to one knee and yelled again that he was not going to jail. Officer Przybylski ordered Currie once again to stop resisting and told him that he needed to have a seat in the police car. However as they approached the police vehicle Currie again dropped to his knees and stated that he was not going to jail.</p>
<p>The Grievant testified that when he attempted to pull Mr. Currie up and place him in his police vehicle, Currie continued to pull back from him. At that point, Officer Przybylski told Currie &ldquo;If you don't stop resisting, I'm going to have to pepper spray you.&rdquo; The Grievant indicated that this warning was given twice to Mr. Currie who responded by saying &ldquo;Go ahead and pepper spray me. Spray me in the mouth.&rdquo; Mr. Currie was still on his knees and opened his mouth after making that statement. The Grievant stated that as Currie started to close his mouth, he took his pepper spray and sprayed him. As he attempted to spray in the eyebrow area, Currie lifted his head and opened his mouth wide. As a result, instead of hitting him in the eyebrow area, the pepper spray hit Currie in the mouth. Mr. Currie immediately put his head down and spit out pepper spray. At this time, three off-duty officers from another jurisdiction helped the Grievant get Mr. Currie into the backseat of the police vehicle. Officer Przybylski further testified that due to the size of the crowd, and the intoxicated condition of Currie, he decided that the best method for him to comply with his orders would be the use of his pepper spray. Officer Przybylski testified that he did not intend to pepper spray Currie in the mouth.</p>
<p>Subsequently, the Grievant called Sgt. Michael Richardson who was assigned to the police department's traffic division and who was the detail supervisor on duty that day. It took Sgt. Richardson between five and ten minutes to get to Officer Przybylski's location. When he arrived at the scene, the Grievant told him that Mr. Currie was drunk and disorderly, and was not listening to his orders. When Sgt. Richardson asked the Grievant about his use of pepper spray, the Grievant responded by stating that he had warned Mr. Currie that he would be pepper sprayed if he continued to resist arrest. The Grievant told Sgt. Richardson that Mr. Currie stated &ldquo;If you are going to spray me, spray me in the mouth.&rdquo; The Grievant then stated that he took out his pepper spray and warned Currie that he would be sprayed if he continued to resist arrest. According to Sgt. Richardson, Officer Przybylski indicated that he sprayed Currie in the mouth.</p>
<p>The police department requires that officers complete a Record Management System (RMS) report if non-deadly force is used in an incident. In this case, Officer Przybylski completed his RMS report immediately after he and the other officers transported Mr. Currie back to the station for booking. In that RMS report, the Grievant indicated that he told Currie several times to stop resisting arrest and to have a seat in his cruiser. However, he refused and when he attempted to push Currie, Mr. Currie then knelt down on the pavement. He then pulled out his pepper spray and warned him to stop resisting arrest or he would have to pepper spray him. In his RMS report, the Grievant indicates that Currie then &ldquo;told me to spray him in the mouth. He then opened his mouth and I sprayed him.&rdquo; Mr. Currie immediately spit it on the ground.</p>
<p>Sergeant Richardson was charged with investigating the Grievant's use of force incident. Sgt. Richardson testified that Officer Przybylski's decision to use force was correct because it was done to bring about compliance from a drunk and disorderly individual. Although Sgt. Richardson indicated that he did not believe that the use of pepper spray was done in a reckless manner, he did find that the procedure followed by the Grievant was wrong and improper. Sgt. Richardson stated that he believed that Officer Przybylski had allowed Mr. Currie to goad him into pepper spraying him in the mouth. Sgt. Richardson indicated that he reached his conclusion because the Grievant acknowledged that after Mr. Currie opened his mouth and said spray me he pepper sprayed him in the mouth. In his investigative report, Sgt. Richardson indicated that the Grievant used bad judgment in spraying Currie in the mouth just because he was asked to do so. Based on the conclusions which he reached, Sgt. Richardson counseled Officer Przybylski on the proper use of pepper spray. Sgt. Richardson stated that he did not believe that any further action should be taken.</p>
<p>Sgt. Richardson indicated that the use of non-deadly force reports like the one he prepared in this case are reviewed through the chain of command in the police department. In the instant matter after further review by the department, Sgt. Richardson was ordered to submit charge papers on Patrolman Przybylski. In the April 16, 2012 charging letter, there were four specific charges made against the Grievant. The first three dealt with equipment which was entrusted to his care. These charges are not at issue here. The fourth charge stated as follows: &ldquo;On Sunday, January 1, 2012, you were assigned to traffic detail. You, Patrol Officer Nicolai Przybylski, No. 1185 encountered an intoxicated male who walked towards on-coming traffic and/or on-coming emergency response vehicle. You used an unnecessary use of force by pepper spraying the male in the mouth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A pre-disciplinary conference was held on April 25, 2012 before Deputy Chief Leroy Morrow. Deputy Chief Morrow concluded that under the totality of the circumstances, the use of force on Mr. Currie was necessary but the manner in which the Grievant used the pepper spray was improper. He determined that the Grievant had been provoked into pepper spraying Currie in the mouth. The Chief stated that he based this conclusion on the Grievant's RMS report which indicated that Mr. Currie opened his mouth and then the Grievant pepper sprayed him in the mouth.</p>
<p>Sgt. Stephen Merrifield, Officer-In-Charge of the Cleveland Police Academy, testified that after reading Sgt. Richardson's investigative report and the RMS report, he concluded that the Grievant's use of pepper spray on Mr. Currie was justified. However, he believed the manner in which Officer Przybylski deployed the pepper spray in the mouth of Currie was not in line with the training received by officers at the Police Academy. Sgt. Merrifield stated that police officers are currently trained to spray at the forehead area because gravity would bring that down to the eyes, the nose, and eventually into the mouth. He acknowledged that spraying someone in the mouth does not cause any more harm then spraying the person in the eyes. Sgt. Merrifield could not express an opinion as to whether or not Officer Przybylski was provoked into spraying Currie in the mouth.</p>
<p>Deputy Chief Morrow recommended a two day suspension for Officer Przybylski. Deputy Chief Morrow believed that such a suspension would be sufficient to deter the Grievant from committing similar acts in the future as well as to put others on notice that such similar activity would be taken seriously by the department. The Deputy Chief indicated that there were no other comparable situations in the past that he could rely upon in determining the appropriate remedy. However, he indicated that he believed that a verbal or written warning would not have been sufficient to get the Grievant's attention and to deter such activity from occurring in the future. The Deputy Chief acknowledged that the use of pepper spray in this case did not constitute excessive force but rather it was the Grievant's use of &ldquo;bad judgment&rdquo; in allowing Mr. Currie to provoke him into spraying him in the mouth. Subsequently on May 10, 2012, Police Chief Michael McGrath, notified the Grievant that he was being suspended for two days for the &ldquo;improper use of pepper spray.&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>POSITION OF THE CITY</b></i></h4>
<p>The City contends that it had just cause to impose a two day suspension on Officer Przybylski because his pepper spraying of an individual in the mouth violated divisional rules and regulations. The evidence clearly shows that the manner in which the Grievant used the pepper spray on Mr. Currie was improper and subject to discipline. Deputy Chief Morrow properly determined that a two day suspension would be the proper deterrent for similar misconduct in the future not only for Officer Przybylski but also for other police officers as well.</p>
<p>The City contends that Officer Przybylski intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in the mouth after he was provoked and goaded by Mr. Currie into doing so. The Grievant allowed Mr. Currie to dare him into pepper spraying him directly in the mouth which is what occurred. It is evident that the Grievant's actions constituted bad judgment on his part.</p>
<p>Moreover, the City argues that the Grievant's intentional pepper spraying of Mr. Currie in the mouth did not comply with divisional rules and regulations. The City points out that it does not maintain that the Grievant's use of pepper spray was inappropriate. Rather, the evidence clearly demonstrates that the manner in which the Grievant used pepper spray was not in compliance with existing division rules and regulations. It was also not in compliance with the training provided the police officers at the academy. In that the Grievant's use of pepper spray violated division rules and regulations, he was properly subjected to discipline.</p>
<p>The City claims that Officer Przybylski's after the fact testimony should be disregarded because it contradicts what he had written in the RMS report. It was only when the Grievant was faced with the prospect of receiving discipline that he attempted to tell a different version than what he stated in his RMS report and from what he told Sgt. Richardson when he arrived at the scene within minutes after the incident occurred. The City emphasizes that the RMS report makes no mention of Mr. Currie jerking his head up at the last moment which resulted in his being pepper sprayed in the mouth. In his RMS report, the Grievant stated that Mr. Currie &ldquo;opened his mouth and I sprayed him.&rdquo; What is stated in the RMS report was corroborated by Sgt. Richardson who testified that Officer Przybylski never mentioned Mr. Currie jerking his head up or that spraying him in the mouth was inadvertent. Based on the RMS report as well as the testimony of Sgt. Richardson and Deputy Chief Morrow, it was reasonable for them to conclude that Officer Przybylski had intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in the mouth because he was provoked into doing so.</p>
<p>The City concludes by stating that police officers are required at all times to conduct themselves in a manner which fosters public confidence in the integrity of the department. Officer Przybylski's actions on January 1, 2012 exhibited a disregard for his duty to conduct himself both professionally and competently when he intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in the mouth because he was goaded into doing so. It is clear therefore that a two day suspension was justified in this case for the Grievant's failure to use pepper spray in a proper manner in accordance with divisional rules and regulations.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>POSITION OF THE UNION</b></i></h4>
<p>The Union argues that the evidence does not support the conclusion the Grievant intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in the mouth. Moreover, the use of pepper spray was justified under the department's use of force policy. In that the Grievant did not intentionally pepper spray Mr. Currie in the mouth and his use of pepper spray was a reasonable use of force, it must be held that the two day disciplinary suspension imposed was improper.</p>
<p>The Union cites Officer Przybylski's numerous statements made throughout the investigation of this matter that he did not intentionally administer the pepper spray in Mr. Currie's mouth. At the pre-disciplinary hearing held on April 25, 2012, the Grievant stated that the spraying of Mr. Currie in the mouth was inadvertent. Moreover, the Grievant has explained how his RMS report was not meant to contain every fact or circumstance regarding the incident. As the evidence indicated, patrol officers prepare their reports at the end of their tour and then their sergeants review their reports. In this case, Sgt. Richardson reviewed the Grievant's report and did not find that it showed that Officer Przybylski had intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in the mouth. The Union points out that Sgt. Richardson did not believe that Officer Przybylski should be disciplined in any way for his actions. The CPPA argues that therefore there were no facts surrounding the incident which warranted a finding that the Grievant improperly used force against Mr. Currie or that he had allegedly intentionally pepper sprayed him in the mouth.</p>
<p>The Union claims that the use of force policy does not prohibit an officer from pepper spraying a suspect in the mouth. In addition, Officer Merrifield in charge of training at the Cleveland Police Academy, stated that the manner in which Officer Przybylski used the pepper spray was not improper. It is clear therefore that the Grievant's actions of pepper spraying Mr. Currie in the mouth did not constitute an improper or unreasonable use of force.</p>
<p>The Union also points out that there is no indication that Mr. Currie ever suffered any adverse reaction as a result of being pepper sprayed in the mouth. Mr. Currie did not file an improper use of force complaint against Officer Przybylski. Moreover administering pepper spray in the mouth of an individual actually constitutes a reduced use of force as compared to other methods of force such as the taser. The fact that the Grievant used a lesser means of force in this case supports the conclusion that Officer Przybylski did not administer the pepper spray in Mr. Currie's mouth because he got under his skin or was taunting him. Officer Przybylski warned Mr. Currie numerous times before he used the pepper spray. The facts did not support the conclusion that Officer Przybylski was retaliating against Mr. Currie when he administered the pepper spray in his mouth.</p>
<p>The Union submits that there was no just cause for the two day suspension in this case. Officer Przybylski acted reasonably when he used pepper spray to subdue the intoxicated and non-compliant Mr. Currie on the day in question. The Grievant followed the use of force continuum during the situation and as a result the finding that he was guilty of using improper force was not warranted. The evidence does not show that Officer Przybylski intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in the mouth. The CPPA argues that the Deputy Chief's interpretation of the Grievant's RMS report was unreasonable and insufficient to conclude that the Grievant's actions in pepper spraying Mr. Currie in the mouth were intentional. As a result, it must be held that there was no just cause to support the two day suspension imposed.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>OPINION</b></i></h4>
<p>The basic issue presented herein is whether there is just cause for the discipline imposed and if not, what is the appropriate remedy. The just cause standard requires clear proof that an employee has committed a disciplinary offense and that the penalty imposed is warranted under the circumstances presented. Therefore, the City had to satisfy the burden of proving by clear and convincing evidence that the Grievant engaged in the alleged misconduct and that the two day suspension was justified under the circumstances.</p>
<p>The City in this case did not find that the Grievant's use of pepper spray in the instant manner was inappropriate. The evidence establishes that Officer Przybylski used his pepper spray to bring about Mr. Currie's compliance with his orders. As stated by the Grievant, Mr. Currie was drunk, disorderly and refused to get into his police cruiser. As a result, the Grievant properly warned Mr. Currie that he would be pepper sprayed if he continued to be non-compliant. As acknowledged by both Sgt. Richardson as well as Deputy Chief Morrow, the use of pepper spray on Mr. Currie was necessary and appropriate.</p>
<p>However, the City has alleged in this case that it was the manner in which Officer Przybylski used the pepper spray which was not in compliance with existing division rules and regulations. Specifically, the Grievant was charged with intentionally pepper spraying Mr. Currie in the mouth after Currie had provoked and goaded him into doing so. As a result, as stated in Police Chief McGrath's letter to the Grievant dated May 10, 2012, he found the Grievant &ldquo;guilty&rdquo; of &ldquo;the improper use of pepper spray.&rdquo; Chief McGrath then imposed the two day or twenty hour suspension without pay. The CPPA on behalf of the Grievant has denied that he intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in the mouth. According to Officer Przybylski, he intended to spray Currie above his eyebrows and he inadvertently sprayed him in the mouth when he raised his head. Therefore, the question becomes one of determining if the Grievant intentionally administered the pepper spray in Mr. Currie's mouth.</p>
<p>After a careful review of the record, this arbitrator must find that it was not clearly demonstrated that Officer Przybylski intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in the mouth on the day of the incident. Officer Przybylski stated throughout the department's investigation of the matter that he did not intentionally administer the pepper spray into Mr. Currie's mouth. At the predisciplinary conference held on April 25, 2012, he clarified the statement that he made in his RMS report and stated that the spraying of Mr. Currie in the mouth was inadvertent and not done intentionally. At the arbitration hearing, the Grievant's testimony was that he went to spray Currie &ldquo;in the eyebrow area&hellip;but at that time he lifted up his head and opened up his mouth wide.&rdquo; The Grievant stated that as a result, instead of hitting Mr. Currie in the eyebrow area he &ldquo;hit him in the mouth.&rdquo; Even on cross-examination, Officer Przybylski again reiterated that as he was pepper spraying Mr. Currie, he suddenly lifted his head up and as a result the spray inadvertently went into his mouth. It should be noted that when this occurred the Grievant stated that he immediately stopped using the pepper spray. Based on the Grievant's consistent statements made throughout this matter, this arbitrator is compelled to find that the evidence does not support the City's contention that Officer Przybylski intentionally administered the pepper spray in Mr. Currie's mouth.</p>
<p>This arbitrator does not find any merit to the City's claim that Officer Przybylski's RMS report which was prepared soon after the incident shows that the Grievant intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in his mouth. In his RMS report, the Grievant indicates that Mr. Currie refused to move and told him to spray him in the mouth. Officer Przybylski then states that Currie &ldquo;opened his mouth and I sprayed him and he immediately spit it out on the ground.&rdquo; The RMS report does not mention Mr. Currie jerking his head up and Officer Przybylski inadvertently pepper spraying him in the mouth. However during his testimony, Officer Przybylski offered a reasonable explanation as to why he did not include such a statement in his RMS report. The Grievant indicated that at the training academy, he had been told to be as concise as possible while still including necessary facts. The Grievant stated that he did not mean to imply in his report that he intentionally pepper sprayed Currie in the mouth. Considering the Grievant's explanation as to the lack of details in his RMS report and his consistent testimony throughout this matter, it once again must be held that Officer Przybylski did not intend to pepper spray Mr. Currie in the mouth. Other than the RMS report, there is no other evidence of any kind which even suggests that the Grievant intentionally administered the pepper spray in Mr. Currie's mouth. As a result, this arbitrator must find that the evidence does not support the City's claim that Officer Przybylski was provoked by Mr. Currie into pepper spraying him in the mouth.</p>
<p>This arbitrator also does not find that Officer Przybylski's use of pepper spray in this case violated division rules and regulations. At the predisciplinary conference, Deputy Chief Morrow concluded that Officer Przybylski's actions did not constitute an excessive use of force. He indicated that the department's use of force continuum allowed the Grievant to deploy his pepper spray in order to get Mr. Currie to comply with his orders. It is apparent that the City's issuance of a two day disciplinary suspension in this case was based on the department's finding that the Grievant was guilty of improperly pepper spraying Mr. Currie in the mouth. However as previously discussed, the record before this arbitrator does not support such a finding. Rather, the evidence presented clearly shows that Officer Przybylski did not intentionally spray Mr. Currie in the mouth. As a result, it cannot be said that an inadvertent pepper spraying of an individual in the mouth in any way violated departmental policy or the use of force continuum. Moreover, it was not shown that the Grievant's actions were not in compliance with the training which he has received. Officer Merrifield who is in charge of training at the Cleveland Police Academy, stated that although Officer Przybylski's use of pepper spray in this case in hitting Mr. Currie in the mouth was contrary to the way officers are currently trained, he found that the Grievant's actions were not improper. He also stated that spraying an individual in the mouth would not cause any more damage than spraying that person in the eyes.</p>
<p>There was also no clear showing made that the Grievant's actions in this case diminished the esteem of the Division of Police in the eyes of the public. The evidence indicates that Officer Przybylski conducted himself in a proper manner on the day in question and acted reasonably without any malicious intent when he used pepper spray to subdue the non-compliant Mr. Currie. Sgt. Richardson concluded that the Grievant did not act in a reckless manner. Officer Przybylski testified credibly that he was not thinking about hurting Mr. Currie when he pepper sprayed him. It should be noted that there is no indication that Mr. Currie suffered any injury or was harmed in any way by the Grievant's actions. Mr. Currie did not file a complaint regarding the incident. There simply was no showing made in this case as claimed by the City that the Grievant's actions were unprofessional or inappropriate.</p>
<p>In summary, this arbitrator must find that the two day disciplinary suspension imposed in this case was not justified. The City failed to clearly and convincingly demonstrate that Officer Przybylski intentionally pepper sprayed Mr. Currie in the mouth on the day of the incident. The Grievant's consistent and credible testimony throughout this matter was that the spraying of Mr. Currie in the mouth was inadvertent and not done intentionally. Contrary to the City's claim, the evidence establishes that Officer Przybylski's use of pepper spray on the non-compliant Mr. Currie was proper and in accordance with the department's Use of Force Policy. As a result, this arbitrator must hold that the evidence does not support the City's contention that the Grievant was guilty of the improper use of pepper spray. For that reason the two day disciplinary suspension imposed must be set aside with the Grievant being made whole for all lost wages incurred.</p>
<p>Although this arbitrator has determined that the two day disciplinary suspension cannot be upheld, he does find that Officer Przybylski's actions in this case warranted a verbal warning. First, although the evidence shows the Grievant did not intentionally pepper spray the non-compliant Mr. Currie in the mouth, the fact remains that he did so. As even the Grievant acknowledged during his testimony, he should have been &ldquo;extra vigilant&rdquo; when using the pepper spray to aim at the forehead of Mr. Currie. The Grievant indicated that he could have done &ldquo;better&rdquo; in this case by aiming higher at Mr. Currie's forehead, and if he had done so most of the pepper spray would have landed in that area rather than in Currie's mouth. Support for a verbal warning in this case is found in the testimony of Sgt. Richardson who counseled Officer Przybylski at the scene and later provided instruction to the Grievant as to the proper use of pepper spray. In effect, Sgt. Richardson was providing a verbal warning to the Grievant that he had to make sure that he administered pepper spray at the forehead as opposed to the mouth area.</p>
<p>Moreover, this arbitrator finds that it would be appropriate to impose a verbal warning for the Grievant's failure to more fully describe the incident in his RMS report. Because Officer Przybylski failed to specifically state that he did not intend to spray Currie in the mouth, it led Sgt. Richardson as well as Deputy Chief Morrow to conclude, albeit incorrectly, that the use of pepper spray on Mr. Currie was improper. The Grievant should bear some responsibility for precipitating the chain of events which led the department to impose a two day disciplinary suspension. This once again supports this arbitrator's conclusion that a verbal warning be given to the Grievant for his actions in this case.</p>
<p>Therefore, this arbitrator has determined that the two day disciplinary suspension imposed shall be set aside and expunged from the Grievant's record. The Grievant is to be compensated for all lost wages incurred as a result of the improper suspension. However, the Grievant is to be given a verbal warning for his actions in this case.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>The grievance is sustained in part. There was no just cause established for the imposition of the two day disciplinary suspension. That suspension is to be set aside and removed from the Grievant's file. Officer Przybylski is to be compensated in full for any and all lost wages incurred. However, the Grievant is to be given a verbal warning for his actions in this case.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>