<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>Haynes International, Inc. Kokomo, Indiana -and- United Steelworkers, Local 2958</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS No. 16-54399</p>
<p>Grievance No. 5A-010-16</p>
<p>December 15, 2016.</p>
<p>Colman R. Lalka, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><small-cap>Opinion and Award</small-cap></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i>INTRODUCTION</i></h4>
<p>This arbitration proceeding was conducted pursuant to Article IX of the July 1, 2013 <i>Agreement between Haynes International, Kokomo, Indiana and United Steelworkers, Local No. 2958</i>. Hearing was held in Kokomo, Indiana on October 4, 2016. At the hearing, sworn testimony was taken with the parties being provided an equal opportunity to examine and cross-examine witnesses; exhibits were offered and made part of the record. Both parties submitted Post Hearing Briefs.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>STATEMENT OF THE CASE</i></h4>
<p>The Grievant was discharged from employment for failure to wear a seatbelt while operating a forklift. The Union grieved the discharge as being in violation of the parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement. The grievance was processed, without resolution, through the steps of the parties' contractual grievance procedure, and the matter is now before this Arbitrator for final and binding determination.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>ISSUE</i></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Did the Company have Just Cause to discharge the Grievant from employment? If not, what is the appropriate remedy?</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i>COLLECTIVE BARGAINING AGREEMENT</i></h4>
<p>In addition to Article IX providing for a grievance and a final and binding arbitration procedure, the following provisions of the parties' Labor Agreement are applicable to these proceedings:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE I &ndash; Agreement</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">1.3 Responsibilities</p>
<p>The Company and Union and their officers and representatives at all levels and all employees of the Company are bound to observe the provisions of this Agreement.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE X - SUSPENSION AND DISCHARGE</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">C. If it is determined by the parties hereto or in arbitration that the employee has been discharged or suspended unjustly, the Company shall reinstate the employee and reimburse him/her, at his/her regular rate of pay, provided, however, that if justified by the circumstances involved, the employee may be reinstated with a lesser amount or with no reimbursement for wage loss.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE XV - SAFETY AND HEALTH</p>
<p class="continued">15.1</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">A. The Company shall continue to make reasonable provisions for the safety and health of its employees at the plant during the hours of their employment. &hellip;</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE XVII - MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</p>
<p class="continued">A. Except as specifically limited or modified by this Agreement all of the rights, powers, prerogatives, and authority involved in the management of the business, the operation of the plants, and the employment and direction of the work force are vested exclusively in the Company.</p>
<p class="continued">B. Among the rights and responsibilities reserved to Management are the right &hellip; to discipline, suspend, and discharge employees for just cause; &hellip;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In addition to the Collective Bargaining Agreement, the following provision of the parties' negotiated Employee Conduct Policy, containing a total of thirty-eight items, are applicable to these proceedings:</p>
<h4 align="center">EMPLOYEE CONDUCT POLICY</h4>
<p class="continued">PURPOSE:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Safe, orderly and efficient operation of our Kokomo facilities require that all employees observe proper standards of conduct. This is necessary to protect the safety and health of all employees &hellip; To this end the following, but not necessarily all inclusive, list of improper acts or failures to act is posted for all employees. Such improper conduct or violation of other generally accepted standards of decent industrial conduct will subject the employee to disciplinary action, up to and including discharge. &hellip;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">PROCEDURE:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Please refer to the Corrective Rehabilitation procedures that will be used as guidelines to ensure fair and consistent application of discipline when an employee fails to comply with an item or items on this list.</p>
<p class="continued">The following actions illustrate what are considered failure to observe proper standards of employee conduct:</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">7. Using vile, abusive, or threatening language and engaging in obscene behavior.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">19. Loitering, wasting time, or sleeping during working hours.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">24. Insubordination: &ldquo;employee refusing to comply with a direct order after being informed that his/her refusal would be considered insubordinate.&rdquo;</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">33. Failure to obey all safety rules, committing unsafe acts, &hellip;</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">36. Bringing radios, cameras, televisions, cellular phones, or pagers on company property without special authorization.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The following provisions of the parties' negotiated Corrective Rehabilitation Policy apply to this matter:</p>
<blockquote>
<p align="center">CORRECTIVE REHABILITATION POLICY</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">2.0 PROCEDURE:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The following corrective rehabilitation procedures shall apply to the thirty-eight items, or any combination of items, that are considered to be improper employee conduct &hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">The following procedures incorporate a five step process that will be used to rehabilitate employees in the event an employee fails to comply with Haynes' general rules on employee conduct. &hellip; The degree of discipline in each case, up to and including discharge, will be determined by the severity of the situation involved. Any employee without counseling at any level for a twelve (12) month period can only be referred to as a counseling meeting. As always, management has the ultimate responsibility to ensure consistency of these procedures and must work extra hard to use these procedures to rehabilitate employees.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">3.0 PRIMARY PROCEDURE:</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">3.1 COUNSELING MEETING:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The employee shall be counseled concerning his/her improper conduct. &hellip;</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">3.2 LEVEL 1:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Subsequent to a counseling session and in the event an employee continues to violate proper conduct, the employee shall receive the First (1st) warning that his/her conduct is still unacceptable and future acts of improper employee conduct will lead to Level 2.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">3.3 LEVEL 2:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Subsequent to counseling and Level 1 notification and in the event an employee continues to violate proper conduct, the employee shall receive the 2nd warning that his/her conduct is still unacceptable and that he/she will be suspended for five (5) working days without pay for any future acts of improper employee conduct.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">3.4 LEVEL 3:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Subsequent to counseling, Level 1 and Level 2 notification and in the event an employee continues to violate proper conduct, the employee shall receive a five (5) working day suspension without pay. The employee shall also be informed that his/her job is in serious jeopardy and that any future acts of improper employee conduct will lead to termination from Haynes International Inc.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">3.5 TERMINATION MEETING:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Subsequent to counseling, level 1, 2 and 3 notification and in the event an employee continues to violate proper conduct, the employee shall be informed that his/her employment with Haynes International Inc. has been terminated.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">4.0 OVERVIEW OF FORM:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">This form has been developed to provide consistency and fairness in applying counseling or disciplinary procedures for employees. It is essential and expected that supervisors and/or management representatives utilize this form or format when discussing or administering discipline to employees. &hellip; This form can and should be used for all formal discussions between an employee and supervisor, whether counseling or discipline.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center"><i>DISCUSSION</i></p>
<p>Haynes International produces high-performance, nickel- and cobalt-based heat- and corrosive-resistant alloys. With the use of furnaces at temperatures of 3,000 degrees, raw material is melted into the desired alloy. The alloys are then formed into sheets, plates, coils, bars, and wire, as ordered by the Company's purchasers. During the processes where the alloys are formed into the various configurations, the material is often at 2,000 degrees.</p>
<p>Dick Foster, North Plant Superintendent, explained that safety is the foremost objective at the plant. Mr. Foster indicated the goals of Company are safety, quality, productivity, and cost, in that order. At the beginning of every shift, Mr. Foster continued, a ten- to fifteen-minute Toolbox Talk is conducted. Each Toolbox Talk covers a safety topic.</p>
<p>Employees are required to wear personal protective equipment, or PPE, as, for example, hard hats, safety goggles, hearing protection, and metatarsals. Other PPE specific to the different operations in the plant is also mandatory. Mr. Foster stated that seatbelts must be worn when operating a forklift, and employees are trained in forklift operation, including the requirement that seat belts be worn.</p>
<p>The Grievant, when questioned on cross-examination, agreed that the work environment is dangerous, that there are monthly safety meetings, and that Toolbox Talks are conducted at the beginning of every shift. The Grievant also agreed that he received forklift training on three occasions, and admitted being aware of the requirement of wearing a seatbelt.</p>
<p>Mr. Foster testified that on March 29, 2016 he was working in the Pickle Area on the north end of the facility, and left that area to proceed south toward the area where the Savage Saw is located. As he was proceeding toward the Savage Saw, Mr. Foster was stopped by several managerial and supervisory employees to address business matters. The distance where stopped was later measured to be sixty-four feet from a pilaster located at the northwest corner of the Savage Saw.</p>
<p>Mr. Foster first observed the Grievant from the sixty-four-foot distance. The Grievant was working near the pilaster, with a forklift parked nearby. Mr. Foster continued in the southerly direction, around the Grievant and the pilaster. Once past the Pilaster, Mr. Foster could not be seen by the Grievant. In that the Savage Saw was in operation, tarps along the side of the saw were closed, obstructing Grievant's view of that area.</p>
<p>Maintenance had previously moved the Savage Saw, installed a new style float system to prevent overfilling, and Mr. Foster proceeded to the area of the floats. After observing the floats, Mr. Foster proceeded to a location alongside the pilaster, but on the opposite side from where the Grievant was working. Mr. Foster testified he then discussed with Scott Sholty, Savage Saw Operator, problems encountered with a roller table.</p>
<p>Mr. Sholty confirmed that he was working on the saw when he was approached by Mr. Foster. As Mr. Sholty continued working on the saw, the two men conversed. Mr. Foster stated that toward the end of his conversation with Mr. Sholty, he observed the Grievant, at a measured fifteen feet away, driving the forklift. Mr. Foster testified he was looking directly at the Grievant, and observed the seatbelt buckle hanging down. As the Grievant drove by, Mr. Foster concluded his conversation with Mr. Sholty and started in pursuit of the Grievant.</p>
<p>The Grievant proceeded to the area of the Pacific Shear, stopped the forklift, and got off. As the Grievant got off the forklift, Mr. Foster was directly behind him. Mr. Foster stated he did not see the Grievant take the seatbelt off to exit the forklift. Mr. Foster asked the Grievant why he was operating the forklift without a seatbelt, and the Grievant responded that he had a bit of a situation and felt like he needed to get out of the way.</p>
<p>The Grievant never indicated what the situation was. The Grievant, according to Mr. Foster, also stated, &ldquo;Well, it wasn't that far.&rdquo; The Grievant at no time indicated to Mr. Foster that he was wearing the seatbelt. At that point, Mr. Foster testified, he threw up his hands and said, &ldquo;Ryan, you don't get it, do you?' and walked away. Mr. Foster then sought out the Grievant's supervisor to have him address the matter further.</p>
<p>Cory Reed, Production Supervisor, is the Grievant's direct supervisor. Mr. Reed summoned the Grievant and his Union Committeeman to his office, and informed the Grievant that he was suspended pending further investigation. Mr. Reed testified that the Grievant responded not by claiming he was wearing the seatbelt, but by indicating that he didn't know how Dick Foster could have seen that he wasn't using a seatbelt. Mr. Reed accompanied the Grievant to his locker, and then to the plant exit. At no point from the office to the exit did the Grievant indicate that he was wearing his seatbelt.</p>
<p>Lynn Smith, Senior Labor Relations Manager, testified that the parties have a negotiated Employee Conduct Policy containing thirty-eight rules. The violation of any of the rules triggers the parties' Corrective Rehabilitation Policy, also negotiated, outlining progressive steps of employee discipline. Pursuant to the Corrective Rehabilitation Policy, discipline remains active on an employee's record for twelve months, provided another rules infraction does not occur within the twelve months. In the event of another infraction within the twelve months, the level of discipline in the progression continues from the previous level.</p>
<p>In addition to the above two policies, relevant to these proceedings is a Job Safety Analysis (JSA) specific to forklifts. At two points the JSA admonishes, &ldquo;Climb into seat and fasten seatbelt,&rdquo; and &ldquo;Be sure to fasten seatbelt.&rdquo; The JSA is used to train employees in forklift operation at the time of hire, and when an employee is transferred into a new department or work group. Company records indicate the Grievant was trained in forklift safety devices, and Ms. Smith indicated the training in forklift safety devices includes use of seatbelts. The JSA is also available online for employees to review.</p>
<p>Ms. Smith also noted that every three years forklift drivers must be reevaluated and recertified. A document entitled Driver's Performance Evaluation Checklist indicates that on September 30, 2013, the Grievant was evaluated in forklift operation. The Grievant received an Excellent rating under &ldquo;Uses Seat Belt.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Grievant's disciplinary record, in chronological order includes: November 24, 2014, counseling for use of cell phone on shop floor in violation of Rule 36; February 25, 2015, Level 1 discipline for &ldquo;vile, abusive or threatening language&rdquo; toward a supervisor, rules 7 and 19; September 15, 2015 Level 2 discipline, not wearing safety glasses, rule 33; October 29, 2015 Level 3 for use of cell phone inside the plant, rule 36; December 11, 2015, Coaching for not wearing his hard hat; and the infraction of March 29, 2016 leading to the termination of his employment. The Employer points out that four of the five violations were for infractions of Safety Rules.</p>
<p>On the form required by the Corrective Rehabilitation Policy, at each level of discipline the Grievant was admonished in writing that future violations will result in a progression to the next level of discipline. The admonition on the Level 3 discipline of October 29, 2015 reads, &ldquo;This is to inform employee that his/her job is in serious jeopardy. Any future violation of employee conduct rules will lead to termination from Haynes International, Inc.&rdquo; The employee also receives the same admonition verbally.</p>
<p>Ms. Smith testified that she becomes involved in the disciplinary process at Level 3, and reads to the employee the language required by Paragraph 3.4 of the Corrective Rehabilitation Policy. This paragraph contains the admonition that any future infractions will lead to termination. Level 3 also provides for a five-day unpaid suspension, which the Grievant received.</p>
<p>Regarding the December 11, 2015 coaching, Ms. Smith testified that during a meeting in her office, Mr. Foster knocked on her door, and stated he really needed to speak to her. Mr. Foster then explained that he had found the Grievant not wearing his hard hat, and they were at the point of the Grievant's termination. Ms. Smith testified that they made the decision to provide the Grievant one more opportunity to modify his behavior.</p>
<p>They discussed the fact that the Grievant was a twenty-year employee, and that they did not want to discharge the Grievant. It was determined to have the Grievant's supervisor conduct a coaching session and impress upon the Grievant the severity and seriousness of his actions, and that termination would result if the infractions continued. The Coaching Form specifically provides, &ldquo;Any future violation of the employee conduct rules will lead to a further movement in the corrective rehabilitation policy which will be termination level.&rdquo; The coaching was conducted by Mr. Reed, and Mr. Reed read the admonition to the Grievant.</p>
<p>Regarding the seatbelt infraction of March 29, 2016, it was Ms. Smith's role to investigate the incident. Ms. Smith interviewed the Grievant in the presence of his Union Representative, Rex Ambrose, Local President. During the interview, Ms. Smith testified, the Grievant stated there was no way Mr. Foster could have seen his seatbelt from where he, Mr. Foster, was located. It was the Grievant's impression that Mr. Foster was still at the point sixty-four feet distant where he was having the discussion with other company personnel.</p>
<p>The Grievant also stated during the interview that he was sure he buckled up, that during the last four or five months he had really been paying attention to wearing his seatbelt, and that he had gotten on and off the forklift approximately twenty times that day and buckled up every time.</p>
<p>Ms. Smith then accompanied the Grievant to the shop floor, along with Mr. Ambrose and Jim Sturgeon, Company Labor Counsel, where the Grievant reenacted the events of March 29. During the reenactment, the Grievant indicated that Mr. Foster was at the location sixty-four feet distant. The Grievant also stated that he was banding and needed to move the forklift out of the way. The Grievant never stated seeing Mr. Foster by the pilaster. The Grievant did indicate that when he got off the forklift, he grabbed a piece of cardboard, and Mr. Foster was right there.</p>
<p>During the investigation, Ms. Smith interviewed Mr. Sholty, who concurred that Mr. Foster was standing by the pilaster. After interviews of the witnesses, it was Ms. Smith's belief that Mr. Foster's version of events was more credible than the Grievant's. After the investigation, Ms. Smith discussed the matter with supervisory and managerial personnel, and it was determined to terminate the Grievant's employment. Upon being terminated, the Grievant responded, &ldquo;Terrible acts, I'm a menace to society.&rdquo; He was very sarcastic toward her, Ms. Smith testified, and this indicated to her that he still did not understand the seriousness of his actions and the importance of safety. Mr. Reed, also present at the meeting, corroborated Ms. Smith's account of the Grievant's remarks.</p>
<p>In its post hearing brief, the Union contends, &ldquo;This case involves what the Union believes to be a penalty for an infraction that simply did not take place.&rdquo; Evidence of record, however, convinces the Arbitrator that, on March 29, 2016, the Grievant was in fact operating a forklift without wearing the seatbelt.</p>
<p>On March 29, the Grievant was unaware of Mr. Foster's location on the opposite side of the pilaster, in a position to clearly see the Grievant from a distance of fifteen feet as he drove by. Mr. Foster was able to clearly see the Grievant's seatbelt dangling off to the side, unused. Mr. Foster had no reason to prevaricate, and testified that by his having had Mr. Reed process the form for the next disciplinary step, which Mr. Foster knew was termination, a rift resulted in a personal relationship he had with the Grievant's father. The Grievant, on the other hand, to save his job, had reason to prevaricate.</p>
<p>Moreover, documents support Ms. Smith's belief that Mr. Foster's version of events was credible. On March 29, Mr. Foster prepared a memorandum of the incident. That memorandum reads:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>On 3-29-16 at 8:58AM I observed Mr. Ryan Miles operating one of the 880lb Combi lift trucks. Ryan was working with a skid of material on the northwest end of the Savage saw. When he completed his work he climbed back on to the Cornbi fork-lift and proceeded to transport the lift of material to the back side of the Pacific shear.</p>
<p>I was located at the north side of the Savage saw talking to Scott Sholty about the Savage saw table rolls. I looked up and observed Mr. Miles driving by and not wearing his seat belt. I saw the buckle of the seat belt dangling down from the side of the seat on the Combi fork lift. I was no more than 15 feet away from the Combi fork lift when I saw Mr. Miles without his seat belt fastened while operating the Combi fork lift.</p>
<p>I followed Mr. Miles to the Pacific shear and asked him why he was not wearing his seat belt while operating the fork lift. Ryan responded by saying he was in a bit of a situation where he was and felt he needed to get out of the way. He continued to say that it wasn't that far.</p>
<p>I said, &ldquo;Ryan, you just don't get it, do you?&rdquo; He said, &ldquo;Yes, I do get it!&rdquo; I turned and walked off to find Ryan's supervisors to inform them of the infraction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Mr. Foster testified that had the Grievant stated he was wearing the seatbelt, he would have noted that statement in his memorandum.</p>
<p>In addition to Mr. Foster's memorandum, on the Suspension Form used by Mr. Reed on March 29, Mr. Reed noted, in the section provided for employee comments, the following statement made by the Grievant, &ldquo;I do not see how Foster could have seen that I did not have my seat belt.&rdquo; The Grievant initialed the form. At the arbitration hearing, the Grievant testified that what was written on the form was only a summary of what was stated, and that he did say that he was wearing his seatbelt.</p>
<p>It is noteworthy that on March 29 the Grievant was not yet aware of the location of Mr. Foster at the time he observed the Grievant. Being unaware of Mr. Foster's location, it was his contention only that Mr. Foster could not have seen whether he was wearing his seatbelt. Considering that the Grievant is a former Committeeman, it is not credible that he would have initialed the Suspension Form without adding such an important &ldquo;fact&rdquo; as that he was using his seatbelt. His only contention at that point was that Mr. Foster was not in a location observe the seatbelt.</p>
<p>At the arbitration hearing, then knowing that Mr. Foster was at a location to have observe him, the Grievant, for the first time, added that he was wearing a black jacket on March 29, and perhaps Mr. Foster mistook the zipper for the seat belt. That contention, having been raised for the first time at the arbitration hearing, appears as nothing more than an afterthought to escape the consequences of his rules violation.</p>
<p>There is no question that the Grievant was aware of the requirement of wearing a seatbelt. The Grievant admitted knowing the requirement, as well as having undergone three training sessions on forklift operation, which included the requirement of seatbelt use, and the forklift JSA indicating at two locations that seatbelt use is required.</p>
<p>There is also no question that the Company takes its safety rules very seriously, and consistently disciplines employee infractions. Scott Pulsipher, Union Committeeman, testified that intermittently since 2001 he has served as a Committeeman and Assistant Committeeman, and that he never experienced an employee facing discipline for a seatbelt violation. The Company, in contravention, produced documentation of five disciplines for seatbelt violations, none of which included the Grievant. The disciplines involved five different employees, and were dated from February 25, 2009 through September 7, 2016.</p>
<p>Ms. Smith testified that she was employed by the Company since mid-2008, and after her arrival began scanning discipline documentation in order that they could be retrieved electronically. Upon an electronic retrieval of disciplines for seatbelt violations, the five were recovered. Ms. Smith also noted that in the seatbelt discipline of February 25, 2009, Mr. Pulsipher attended the disciplinary session as that employee's Committeeman.</p>
<p>This record of seatbelt disciplines supports the argument that the Company takes safety at its facility seriously, and that the Grievant was not somehow singled out for discipline and discharge. In fact, the Grievant having been subject to termination on December 11, 2015 for a safety rules infraction, but receiving coaching instead, indicates that the Employer was attempting to rehabilitate the Grievant's behavior, rather than terminate.</p>
<p>It also is to be noted that the Grievant's employment was terminated pursuant to the negotiated Corrective Rehabilitation Policy. Emphasis must be placed on negotiated. That is, the Union agreed to the Rules and the consequences of Rules violations. The Corrective Rehabilitation Policy provides for Employer discretion in the level of discipline to be issued, and it also must be noted that, pursuant to that discretion, the Employer used Coaching rather that termination on the Grievant's infraction of December 11, 2015. No further exercise of discretion is required.</p>
<p>The Company emphasizes that while it helps employees perform their jobs safely through training, it is, in the end, up to the individual employee to act in a safe manner. In that the Employer's attempts at rehabilitation of the Grievant's behavior failed, the Employer had Just Cause, as mandated by Article XVII, Paragraph A, for the termination of the Grievant's employment.</p>
<h6 align="center"><i>CONCLUSION</i></h6>
<p>Based upon the foregoing, the above identified issue is answered in the affirmative. That is, the Employer had Just Cause to terminate the Grievant's employment, the Arbitrator is unable to find a violation of the parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement, and the grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>