<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of the Arbitration between THE CITY OF CLEVELAND and CLEVELAND POLICE PATROLMEN'S ASSOCIATION &lsqb;CPPA&rsqb;</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Grievant: DONALD MEEL AAA&num; 01-14-0000-4846</p>
<p>January 9, 2015.</p>
<p>Hyman Cohen, Esq. Impartial Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center">SOCIAL MEDIA POLICY</h4>
<p>The hearing was held on September 18, 2014 at Burke Lakefront Airport, Cleveland, Ohio, before HYMAN COHEN, Esq., the Impartial Arbitrator,selected by the parties pursuant to the Rules and Regulations of the American Arbitration.</p>
<p>The hearing began at 10:00 a.m. and was concluded at 11:00 a.m. Post-hearing briefs were submitted on or about November 14, 2014.</p>
<p>The <b>CITY OF CLEVELAND, the &ldquo;City&rdquo; and CLEVELAND POLICE PATROLMEN'S ASSOCIATION</b>, the <b>&ldquo;Association&rdquo;</b>, have been and continue to be, parties to a Collective Bargaining Agreement. An undated grievance, on behalf of <b>DETECTIVE PATROL OFFICER 1, DONALD MEEL</b>, was filed by the Association with the City in which it claimed that the three (3) day disciplinary suspension imposed against the Grievant for &ldquo;inappropriate social media behavior&rdquo; was &ldquo;arbitrary, disparate, excessive and unreasonable and in violation of the just cause standard&rdquo; of the Agreement.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>FACTUAL DISCUSSION</b></h4>
<p>The Grievant is assigned to the Crime Scene and Records Unit. His duties consist of processing crime scenes throughout the City of Cleveland. The Grievant is also assigned to the Use of Deadly Force Investigation Team.</p>
<p>The Grievant authored a post to the editor of The Plain Dealer on or about August 6, 2013, which states as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;As police officers in Cleveland, we take our share of abuse. We are spat upon, urinated on, punched, kicked, stabbed, shot and we even die to maintain the thin blue line between anarchy and the general public. We do so with our chins held high. Lately, however, we have had to endure another indignity, one imposed by politicians with no apparent sense. Now, we recognize discipline as a necessity. But when it is applied with a view to political expediency and not as a means of maintaining order within the ranks, we tend to begin to question why we take the abuses I've mentioned here. When our mayor and police chief call career criminals victims, they demonize us to the public at large and embolden those who would do us all harm. This is just wrong This needs to be corrected. But it won't, because in Cleveland, pandering to the criminals is more important than seriously dealing with their actions.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The post which was updated on the internet, <i>cleveland.com</i>, on August 7, 2013 was entitled by The Plain Dealer editorial staff as follows: &ldquo;Cleveland police take abuse from the public and politicians&rdquo;. A complaint with respect to the Grievant's post was brought to the attention of the Cleveland Division of Police. Sergeant James E. Mangan of the Inspection Unit was assigned to determine whether there were any Police Division policies or procedures related to the posting, and if so, were any of them violated.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>a. FORM 1 TYPE ORDER</b><ftnote num="1"><para>Described by the City as a <quote>basic memo used to pass information throughout the Division of Police</quote>.</para></ftnote></h4>
<p>After reading the post, Sgt. Mangan issued a &ldquo;Form 1 Type Order&rdquo;. In response to the Form 1 Type Order, the Grievant stated that he posted the blog when he was off-duty and by using his personal laptop computer. He stated that he did not name an individual mayor; nor did he name an individual police chief. He went on to state that he deliberately left the names of the mayor and the police chief to the interpretation of the reader. The Grievant added that there are &ldquo;several&rdquo; police chiefs in the Cleveland area.</p>
<p>Continuing with the Grievant's responses to the &ldquo;Form 1 Type Order&rdquo;, is that his use of the pronoun &ldquo;we&rdquo; referred to &ldquo;&lsqb;A&rsqb;ll police officers who work within the City of Cleveland&rdquo; Moreover, the Grievant explained his statement in the post, that &ldquo;when our mayor and police chief call career criminals victims, they demonize us to the public at large and embolden those who would do us all harm&rdquo;. He said that he &ldquo;did not name any persons and &lsqb;he&rsqb; deliberately left this to the interpretation of the reader&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Based on the Grievant's responses in his Form 1, and his claim that his post is &ldquo;protected concerted activity&rdquo; under the &ldquo;Fair Labor Standards Act&rdquo;, Sgt. Mangan requested that all the paperwork in connection with the incident be forwarded to the City's Law Department to determine if the Grievant's statements are &ldquo;protected under the Fair Labor Standards Act or that of the First Amendment&rdquo;.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>b. ISSUANCE OF DISCIPLINE</b></h4>
<p>On January 27, 2014, an administrative pre-disciplinary hearing was held before the Deputy Chief of Police. By letter to the Grievant dated January 29, 2014, Chief of Police Michael McGrath stated that an Inspections Unit Report determined that the Grievant &ldquo;posted, transmitted or otherwise disseminated, disrespectful information on social media that would reasonably tend to diminish the esteem of the Division of Police or its personnel in the eyes of the public.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Chief McGrath accepted the recommendation of the pre-disciplinary Hearing Officer in finding that there was just cause to impose discipline. He issued a three (3) day (twenty-four (24) hours) suspension without pay with two (2) of the days (sixteen (16) hours) held in abeyance until January 27, 2016.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>DISCUSSION</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>1. Issues of Law</b></h4>
<p>At the outset of this discussion a threshold issue raised by the parties must be addressed. In their post-hearing briefs, the parties have commingled the issues of whether the Grievant was disciplined for just cause, with the question of whether the discipline violated the Grievant's First Amendment Rights. Thus in its brief, the City argues that &ldquo;it has met its burden of proof and disciplined the Grievant for just cause&rdquo;. In support of its claim that the test of just cause was satisfied, the City relies on decisional law of the Federal Court (6th Circuit), that the Grievant's post &ldquo;is not protected under the First Amendment and that the post was not protected concerted activity&rdquo;,</p>
<p>The Union states that the issue to be resolved includes both First Amendment rights and just cause under the Agreement: &ldquo;Whether the City &ast; &ast; violated the &ast; &ast; Agreement when it disciplined &lsqb;the Grievant&rsqb; in violation of his First Amendment Rights and without just cause to impose a three (3) day suspension from duty&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Obviously, the U.S. Constitution is to be distinguished from the parties&rsquo; Collective Bargaining Agreement. Clearly, the test of &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; refers solely to the Agreement between the parties. I believe that it is best that I fulfill my responsibility as an Arbitrator acting under the Agreement rather than under the U.S. Constitution. It is more appropriate that the interpretation and application of the First Amendment to public sector employees be left to the Courts rather than to arbitration which is a private dispute resolution process of the parties. See, e.g. <i>USM Corp</i>., 69 LA 1050, (Feller, 1977).</p>
<p>My role as an Arbitrator is to be a reader of the Labor Agreement rather than a reader of the First Amendment and the federal decisional law which gives it meaning. Before proceeding to consider the Agreement, it is important to set forth several well established principles involving the employment relationship of public sector employees.</p>
<p>As a first and obvious principle, &ldquo;Public employees do not enjoy any constitutional right to be employed by the government&rdquo;. Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works, Seventh Edition (K. May, Ed.-in-Chief), (BNA, 2012) at page 19-3, Moreover, in City of Wooster. Ohio</i>, 111 LA 1167, (Richard), the Arbitrator stated:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;&ast; &ast; When citizens enter into an employment relationship with the government, they voluntarily acknowledge and accept that in its role as an employer, the government is endowed with all rights normally reserved to employers, including the right to maintain discipline and promote morale, harmony and efficiency in the work place.&rdquo; At page 1172</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Having set forth these well recognized principles, I turn to the Agreement between the parties, which provides for my authority and jurisdiction. Pursuant to Article XXII, Paragraph (51), the parties defined a &ldquo;grievance&rdquo; as &ldquo;any dispute arising out of or connected with the subject matter of the Contract, or the interpretation, application or enforcement of any of its terms&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Underscoring the primacy of the Contract, is Step 4 of Article XXII, which in pertinent part, provides: &ldquo;In the event a grievance goes to arbitration, the arbitrator shall have jurisdiction only over disputes arising out of grievances as to the interpretation and/or application and/or compliance with the provisions of this Contract including all disciplinary actions and in reaching his decision, the arbitrator shall have no authority (1) to add or subtract from or modify in any way any of the provisions of this Contract; (2) to pass upon issues governed by law, (3) to make an award in conflict with law.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Step 4 clearly limits my jurisdiction by providing that it is &ldquo;only over disputes arising out of grievances as to the interpretation and/or application and/or compliance with the provisions of this Contract, including all disciplinary actions &ast; &ast;.&rdquo; The parties reinforced the limits of my jurisdiction by stating in Step 4 that I have no authority &ldquo;(1) to add or subtract from or modify in any way any of the provisions of this Contract; and (2) pass upon issues governed by law&rdquo; which obviously includes the issue as to whether the Grievant's post is protected speech under the First Amendment.</p>
<p>The prohibition in (3) of Step 4 that I am not authorized to issue an award in conflict with law is not at variance with any of the views I have just stated. Indeed, in light of the agreed upon definition of a grievance, and the lack of authorization in (1) and (2) of Step 4, I am limited to consideration of whether the City has violated any provision of the Contract, leaving to the Courts the decision as to whether my award is in conflict with law.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>I</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>General Police Order 1.3.39; Social Media, Social Networking, Internet Use &amp; Medium.</b></h4>
<p>The City or Division of Police promulgated General Police Order 1.3.39: &ldquo;Social Media, Social Networking, Internet Use &amp; Medium&rdquo; which provides as its &ldquo;Purpose&rdquo;, &ast; &ast; &ldquo;guidelines for Division members' use of social media, social networking sites, internet use and any other medium&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;Policy&rdquo; of the General Police Order is as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Members of the Cleveland Division of Police shall adhere to all Division rules and regulations as they relate to personal conduct and communications that may diminish the esteem of the Division or its personnel in the eyes of the public. Members are prohibited from engaging in any action (involving social media or otherwise) that has the potential to negatively impact the law enforcement function of the Cleveland Division of Police or any other law enforcement agency or ancillary government function.</p>
<p class="continued">This directive applies regardless of the medium involved or whether the conduct or communications occur on-duty or off-duty. In an internet based culture characterized by hyper-connectivity and worldwide access to information, members shall be particularly mindful of their activities or information that they cause to enter the networks of the World Wide Web.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The General Policy Order sets forth the following &ldquo;Definitions&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Medium is any means of mass communication or information transfer including print, radio, television, or the internet.</p>
<p class="continued">Social media is any variety of online sources that allow people to communicate and share information, photographs, videos, audio, text, and other multimedia files with others via some form of online (internet) or cellular network platform.</p>
<p class="continued">Social Networking is any act using social media to communicate with others.</p>
<p class="continued">Post is the act of electronically publishing content on an internet site. Blogging is the equivalent of posting.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The &ldquo;Procedures&rdquo; in pertinent part, provide as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;PROCEDURES:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">1. When not necessitated by a legitimate law enforcement activity or function, members who use social media or other internet-based function shall not post, transmit, or otherwise disseminate information that:</p>
<p class="continued">A. Contains any text, photograph, audio, video, or any other multimedia file:</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">B. Impairs working relationships within the Division for which loyalty and confidentiality are important, or impairs discipline or harmony among coworkers.</p>
<p class="continued">H. Would reasonably tend to diminish the esteem of the Division of Police or its personnel in the eyes of the public.</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">VI. This policy shall not prohibit a member from posting or publishing content on the internet that already exists in the public realm to the extent that such postings do not diminish the esteem of the Division or its personnel in the eyes of the public. &ast; &ast; &ast;.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>The issue to be resolved is whether by his post on August 6 and 7, 2013, the Grievant violated General Police Order 1.3.39. At this point, I believe it is useful to repeat the Grievant's post.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;As police officers in Cleveland, we take our share of abuse. We are spat upon, urinated on, punched, kicked, stabbed, shot and we even die to maintain the thin blue line between anarchy and the general public. We do so with our chins held high. Lately, however, we have had to endure another indignity, one imposed by politicians with no apparent sense. Now, we recognize discipline as a necessity. But when it is applied with a view to political expediency and not as a means of maintaining order within the ranks, we tend to begin to question why we take the abuses, I've mentioned here. When our mayor and police chief call career criminals victims they demonize us to the public at large and embolden those who would do us all harm. This is just wrong. This needs to be corrected. But it won't, because in Cleveland, pandering to the criminals is more important than seriously dealing with their actions.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>According to the Association, the Grievant's post was prompted by a high speed police chase on November 29, 2012, which ended in the death of two (2) suspects. These events received extensive media coverage and resulted in several investigations of the Cleveland Police Division.</p>
<p>Before proceeding further, it is significant that the Grievant did not disclose in his Form1 responses that he authored the post because of the events of November 29 and its aftermath. Nor does the post itself refer to the November 29 incident.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>NOVEMBER 29, 2012 INCIDENT</b><ftnote num="2"><para>Based upon the Association's brief and various news media reports.</para></ftnote></h4>
<p>In its brief, the Association claims that the Grievant's post was prompted by the 23 minute high speed police car chase and shooting of two (2) suspects during the evening of November 29, 2012. There were 59 police cars and 104 police officers involved in pursuing the two (2) suspects. It was reported that 13 officers fired 137 bullets at the suspects during the chase.</p>
<p>Some of the officers involved reported seeing a gun held by a suspect. However, when the bodies of the suspects were removed from their vehicle no gun or shell casings were found.</p>
<p>The events of November 29, 2012 generated widespread news, and was highly publicized in the United States. Following the incident, there were criminal investigations by the City of Cleveland, the Attorney General of Ohio and the U.S Department of Justice.</p>
<p>A Sergeant was fired. Two (2) supervisors were demoted and various officers were disciplined for their roles in the chase and deadly shooting on November 29.</p>
<p>The Cuyahoga County Medical Examiner found cocaine in the blood of the two (2) suspects. One (1) suspect tested positive for amphetamines, and the other for marijuana. Both had previous criminal convictions and failed to stop or pull over during the high speed chase. Yet, according to the Association, the suspects were called &ldquo;victims&rdquo;.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>THE POST</b></h4>
<p>Initially, the Grievant states that police officers are subject to various forms of abuse by the very people they are required to protect. Thus, police officers are &ldquo;spat upon, urinated on, punched&rdquo;, etc. They take the abuse to maintain the thin and fragile line between anarchy and the general public. The Grievant goes on to state, that the police officers take such abuse with pride &ndash; with &ldquo;their chins held high&rdquo;. In these sentences, I find no violation of the Division's Social Media policy,</p>
<p>The Grievant than states that in addition to such abusive conduct, the police officers are subject to another &ldquo;indignity&rdquo; which is &ldquo;imposed by politicians with no apparent sense&rdquo;. The additional &ldquo;indignity&rdquo; or the affront to their self respect, which police officers are subjected to, is that discipline is applied with a view to &ldquo;political expediency&rdquo; rather than as a &ldquo;means of maintaining order within the ranks&rdquo;. When this occurs the Grievant states, &ldquo;we&rdquo;, as police officers &ldquo;tend to begin to question why we take the abuse by the general public&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The Grievant is stating in effect, that discipline is dictated by what is advantageous politically, without regard to fundamental principles of law enforcement, integrity and candor. Thus, discipline is applied for politically advantageous motives which undermine the means of maintaining order within the ranks, which is proper and necessary.</p>
<p>The Grievant's comment that discipline is applied with a view to &ldquo;political expediency&rdquo; is highly disparaging of the chain of command in the Police Division. Discipline can only be applied by supervisors who are vested with such authority by contract or under law.</p>
<p>The intentional dissemination by the Grievant of his personal views about the reasons for discipline is addressed to a wide reaching audience &ndash; to readers of the most widely read newspaper in Cleveland &ndash; The Plain Dealer. They are personal opinions which are misleading and injurious to those officers vested with authority to impose discipline. These personal views reflect unfairly upon officials within the Division who are authorized to make decisions about personnel and the operations of the Police Division.</p>
<p>Assuming that the Grievant was referring to the events of November 29, 2012, he impugned the motives of the officials of the Police Division for issuing discipline to the officers for &ldquo;political expediency&rdquo;, rather than as a means of maintaining order within the ranks. Although there may be differences with respect to the views of reasonable people concerning the events of November 29 and its aftermath, it is unreasonable to conclude that &ldquo;political expediency&rdquo; was the motive for the discipline of the officers,</p>
<p>Accordingly, the Grievant's personal criticism that discipline was issued with a view based on &ldquo;political expediency&rdquo; is demeaning to the Police Officials and &ldquo;may diminish the esteem of the Division or its personnel in the eyes of the public&rdquo;; in addition, the Grievant has engaged in an action, by his use of social media, which has the potential to negatively impact the law enforcement function of the Division contrary to the Social Media &ldquo;Policy&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The Grievant then stated that &ldquo;when our mayor and police chief call career criminals victims, they &ldquo;demonize us&rdquo;, meaning the police &ldquo;to the public at large and embolden those who would do us all harm&rdquo;. The Grievant said in response to the Form 1 interrogation, he deliberately left the identity of the Mayor and Police Chief to the interpretation of the reader.</p>
<p>A reasonable interpretation by the reader or third party is that the Grievant is referring to the current Mayor of Cleveland, Frank G. Jackson, and Police Chief Michael McGrath. Support for this conclusion is based on the possessive word &ldquo;our&rdquo; which immediately precedes &ldquo;mayor and police chief&rdquo;. In addition, the coupling of &ldquo;police chief&rdquo; with &ldquo;mayor&rdquo; establishes that the Grievant is referring to Chief McGrath and no other police chiefs.</p>
<p>The demonization of the police and emboldening criminals, will not be corrected according to the Grievant because &ldquo;in Cleveland&rdquo; which is a shorthand expression for the Mayor and Police Chief, &ldquo;pandering to the criminals is more important than seriously dealing with their actions&rdquo;. By describing the Mayor and Police Chief as &ldquo;demonizing&rdquo; the police because they called &ldquo;career criminals victims&rdquo;, the Grievant has disseminated his personal view that &ldquo;in Cleveland&rdquo;, or in other words, the Mayor and Police Chief have referred to the police as evil and cruel.</p>
<p>The Grievant adds that the Mayor and Police Chief will not correct the wrong of calling career criminals victims, because it is &ldquo;more important&rdquo; for them to &ldquo;pander to criminals&rdquo; rather than seriously deal with their actions. By &ldquo;pandering to criminals&rdquo;, the Grievant, in effect, is stating that the Mayor and Police Chief are taking special pains to satisfy the views and needs of the lowest and most dishonorable persons, namely criminals.</p>
<p>Thus, the Grievant's accusations against the Mayor and Chief of Police of demonizing the police to the public and pandering to criminals which is more important than dealing seriously with their actions, are both harmful and destructive. The Grievant's attack of the two (2) City officials is based solely on the Grievant's characterization of &ldquo;career criminals&rdquo; and the use of the word &ldquo;victims&rdquo; by the City officials. The accusations by the Grievant that the Mayor and Police Chief &ldquo;demonize&rdquo; the police to the public and &ldquo;pandering to the criminals&rdquo; constitute a sharp, public disparaging attack upon the leadership of the Police Division. The wide dissemination of such criticism in a post to The Plain Dealer, was in a manner reasonably calculated to harm the reputation of the leadership of the Police Division and the Mayor.</p>
<p>Indeed, the provocative characterizations of demonizing the police to the public and &ldquo;pandering to criminals&rdquo; has the potential of sowing discord within the ranks of the Division of Police and the chain of command. Such views, widely disseminated by the Grievant who identifies himself as a Police Officer in the post, undermine the integrity and command structure of the Police Division; and seriously interfere with the harmonious relationship based upon loyalty which is required to exist in order to carry out the vital duties of officers to serve and protect. &lsqb;e.g. Section B of the Social Media &ldquo;Procedures&rdquo;. In this discussion, I have not exercised a judgment or evaluation with respect to the events of November 29, 2012.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the Grievant has violated the Social Media &ldquo;Policy&rdquo; by failing to adhere to all Division rules and regulations as they relate to personal conduct and communications that may diminish the esteem of the Division or its personnel in the eyes of the public&rdquo;. In addition, contrary to the &ldquo;Policy&rdquo;, the Grievant has engaged in an action (involving social media or otherwise) that has the potential to negatively impact the law enforcement function of the Cleveland Division of Police &ast; &ast;&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Moreover, the following &ldquo;Procedures&rdquo; of the Social Media Policy have been violated by the Grievant:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;B, Impairs working relationships with the Division for which loyalty and confidentiality are important, or impairs discipline or harmony among coworkers.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>SOCIAL MEDIA POLICY</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>a. Off-Duty</b></h4>
<p>The Grievant acknowledged that his post was performed off-duty. Although the post states it is authored by &ldquo;Don Meel, Cleveland&rdquo;, there is no doubt that he also identifies himself among &ldquo;police officers in Cleveland&rdquo; and by using the pronouns &ldquo;us&rdquo; and &ldquo;we&rdquo; in the post.</p>
<p>Turning to the issue of off-duty conduct, the following is well established:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Employers may issue work rules that penalize off-duty conduct of their employees that reflects adversely on the employer, impairs relations with the public and customers, or creates friction within the workforce.&rdquo; <i>How Arbitration Works</i>, Seventh Edition, at page 13-161.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reinforcing this well established principle are the following terms of the Division's Social Media Policy. This directive applies regardless of the medium involved or whether the conduct or communications occur on-duty or off-duty&rdquo;. It is sufficient to state that the Grievant's off-duty post reflects adversely upon the Cleveland Division of Police and creates friction within the ranks and the chain of command.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>b. Procedures - Section VII</b></h4>
<p>Pursuant to the category of &ldquo;Procedures&rdquo; in the Social Media Policy, Section <b>VII</b> provides: This policy is not intended to prohibit or inhibit a member's exercise of their constitutional rights as established and as interpreted by case law&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Contrary to the Association's claim, &ldquo;Section VII does not authorize the Arbitrator to determine whether the Policy prohibits or inhibits the exercise of Constitutional rights as established and interpreted by case law. As I have previously discussed, the terms of the Agreement prevail over an employer's unilateral policy. Thus, the definition of a &ldquo;grievance&rdquo; and the Arbitrator's jurisdiction is clearly defined by Article XXII of the Agreement. Clearly, the bargained for terms of the Agreement trump the U.S. Constitution in determining whether an employer has disciplined an employee for just cause.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>c. PROCEDURES&ndash;SECTION VI</b></h4>
<p align="center">Section VI of the Procedures provides as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;This policy shall not prohibit a member from posting or publishing content on the internet that already exists in the public realm to the extent such postings do not diminish the esteem of the Division or its personnel in the eyes of the public&rdquo;.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There is nothing that has been brought to the attention of the Arbitrator that &ldquo;in the public realm&rdquo; the discipline of the Officers involved in the November 29, 2012 incident was issued with a view to &ldquo;political expediency&rdquo;; nor is there in the public realm that the police were demonized because the suspects in the November 29 incident were called &ldquo;victims&rdquo;. Moreover, there is also nothing &ldquo;In the public realm&rdquo; that the officials of the Division pander to criminals rather than seriously addressing the actions of criminals. Clearly, the Grievants post diminishes &ldquo;the esteem of the Division or its personnel in the eyes of the public&rdquo;, in violation of Section VI of the &ldquo;Procedures&rdquo; in the Social Media Policy.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>DICTUM</b></h4>
<p>By way of dictum which is not essential to resolving the instant dispute, I believe it would be useful to briefly consider the claims by the Association that the Grievant engaged in concerted protected activity and his post is protected by the First Amendment.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>a. &ldquo;Concerted Protected Activity&rdquo;</b></h4>
<p>I assume that the issue with respect to &ldquo;concerted protected activity&rdquo; implicates the Public Sector Collective Bargaining Law in the State of Ohio. Based on the evidentiary record, the Grievant did not engage in concerted activities for the purpose of collective bargaining or other mutual aid or protection&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Although the Grievant referred solely to his name at the end of the post, in the text of the post he acknowledges that he is a Police Officer by the use of the following words: &ldquo;as police officers&rdquo;, &ldquo;us&rdquo; and &ldquo;we&rdquo;. However, the comments were made solely on his own behalf.</p>
<p>There is no language to suggest that the Grievant sought to initiate or induce other Officers to engage in concerted activity. In order for concerted activity to be protected under the Ohio Public Sector Collective Bargaining Law, the Grievant is required to seek or initiate or induce or prepare for group action.</p>
<p>Nor is there any intent by the Grievant to engage Officers in a discussion over the terms and conditions of employment. The Grievant's claim that the discipline of Officers who were involved in the November 29, 2012 events were based upon &ldquo;political expediency&rdquo; does not fall within a discussion with fellow Officers over terms and conditions of employment.</p>
<p>By submitting the post to The Plain Dealer, the Grievant did not have in mind fellow Officers; clearly, he personally had in mind the readers of The Plain Dealer, and in general, the public.</p>
<p>The Grievant's additional comments that the Mayor and Police Chief &ldquo;demonize us to the public&rdquo; because of his claim that they describe the suspects in the November 29, 2012 incident as &ldquo;victims&rdquo;; and that this attitude will not change because &ldquo;in Cleveland pandering to criminals is more important &ldquo;than seriously addressing the actions of criminals are beyond the scope of &ldquo;concerted protected activities&rdquo;. These personal comments seriously disparage and undermine the esteem, respect and public perception of the Cleveland Division of Police.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>b. First Amendment</b></h4>
<p>At the outset of this brief discussion, it bears repeating as a threshold matter, that in the text of the post the Grievant identified himself as a Police Officer, rather than as a &ldquo;citizen&rdquo;. Moreover, in his post, the Grievant does not merely address a matter of political, social or other concern to the community. Rather than belabor what has already been stated, the Grievant's dissemination of his post, is harmful and highly disparaging of the officials in the Police Division. In light of the Social Media Policy, which was familiar to the Grievant, his comments undermine the esteem and respect of the Division of Police, and its Officers who, day and night carry out the essential and dangerous job of serving and protecting the public.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>AWARD</b></h4>
<p>Based upon the evidentiary record, the City proved by clear and convincing evidence that the Grievant was disciplined for just cause under the Agreement. The three (3) day suspension without pay, with two (2) of the days (16 hours) to be held in abeyance until January 16, 2016, is both fair and reasonable.</p>
<p>The grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>
