<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>UNITED STATES STEEL CORPORATION Granite City Works and UNITED STEELWORKERS Local Union No. 50</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case Nos. USS-48,177 -48,178 -48,179</p>
<p>Grievance Nos. GCI-15-0085 -0086 -0087</p>
<p>October 25, 2016.</p>
<p>Terry A. Bethel, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>BACKGROUND</i></h4>
<p>1/ This case from Granite City Works concerns Grievant's discharge for an event that occurred on October 28, 2015. On that date, Grievant, a Utility Person, had been assigned to clean around a conveyer belt using a Bobcat. Grievant, who was working the 2:00 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. shift, finished the job at about 4:30 p.m. Grievant said he needed to urinate, so he started toward the rest room at the yard labor shack on his Bobcat. The route required him to travel east on a road running parallel to, and on the south side of, the high line railroad. Once Grievant reached a crossing, he would make a 90 degree turn heading north, cross the tracks, and then go west on a road running along the north side of the track.</p>
<p>2/ A video of the event showed Grievant traveling east on the road parallel to the track. At one point he stopped for a few seconds, which, Grievant said, was when he considered using the rest room at the nearby coal handling shack. However, Grievant thought it was probably locked, so he continued on the route to the yard shack. As Grievant approached the crossing, there was a train on the adjacent track, heading in the same direction as Grievant. When Grievant reached the crossing, he made the 90 degree turn and proceeded into the crossing without stopping. The train struck Grievant's Bobcat broadside. The collision damaged the engine brakes, so the train pushed the Bobcat along the track for about 200 yards before it could stop. Grievant was injured by the collision, although not seriously. Neither of the train operators was injured. Both the locomotive and the Bobcat were damaged.</p>
<p>3/ Grievant was issued three discharges on November 3, 2015: Unsatisfactory Work; Safety Violation; and Damage to Company Property, all covering the same event. Grievances over all three discharges were filed on November 6, 2015.</p>
<p>4/ Area Manager of Maintenance Frank Townsend pointed to Mobile Equipment Standard Practices 11.32 and 11.33, which read, in relevant part:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">11.32. The operator shall approach all railroad crossings with caution and stop at all railroad crossings having a stop sign, activated crossing signal, lowered crossing gates, flare or any other sign, signal, or barrier meant to stop traffic.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">11.32.1. The operator shall not proceed through a crossing when a train is approaching.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">11.33. The operator shall bring the equipment to a full stop, look both ways, listen for warning signals and approaching rail traffic, and then proceed when the crossing is clear of traffic in both directions&hellip;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Grievant had been trained on the procedures, Townsend said. He also pointed to a safety contact Grievant received on September 14, 2015, concerning stops and the use of blue lights,&rdquo; and another one on September 9, 2015 that covered &ldquo;mobile equipment hazards.&rdquo; There is no dispute that Grievant did not stop at the crossing. Townsend said locomotives weigh about 200,000 pounds, have blind spots, and cannot stop quickly; they have the right of way at all crossings. Anyone approaching a track crossing, Townsend said, has to expect there is a locomotive in the area.</p>
<p>5/ The crossing Grievant used did not have any signs, crossing gates, or signals. However, another crossing about two hundred yards farther down the track had crossing gates, signs, lights, and bells. Grievant said he should have gone to the crossing with the gates, and he acknowledged that the crossing he used was unauthorized; however, he said all employees use it, and that he had seen managers use it. The incident report prepared by Emergency Services says the train operator told the security officer that the crossing gates were down and lights were flashing at the approved crossing, although it is not clear from the report whether they were down when the locomotive struck Grievant or whether they activated as the locomotive traveled down the track after the collision.</p>
<p>6/ Grievant said he was in a hurry to get to the restroom, and he agreed that he should have stopped. He'said he looked to his left a number of times while he was traveling parallel to the track, but did not see the train. He looked to his right as he made the turn toward the crossing, he said, but did not look to his left. The video from the locomotive indicates that the locomotive operator sounded the horn twice before the collision; however, Grievant said he did not hear it. He said the Bobcat's engine is loud and that its tracks make a loud noise when he drives on the road. In addition, Grievant said he was wearing hearing protection.</p>
<p>7/ Townsend testified that the train operators did nothing wrong; they were not speeding and they blew the horn to let Grievant know they were approaching the crossing. According to Townsend, the collision would not have occurred if Grievant had stopped and looked both ways before crossing the track. Townsend said he believed discharge was appropriate because even though Grievant was not badly injured, the potential for a fatality was just &ldquo;off the charts.&rdquo; Not many people who are hit by a train, Townsend said, can sit at a table afterwards and talk about it. Townsend said he felt he could no longer trust Grievant to work safely.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</i></h4>
<p>8/ The Company contends there is no significant factual dispute, and the only issue is whether the discipline was too harsh. The Company says the Board has been consistent in holding that it cannot substitute its judgment about appropriate discipline for the Company's. The Board can only modify the discipline, the Company insists, when it bears no reasonable relationship to the offense. This is more than a reasonable person standard, the Company says; in order to modify the discipline, the Board has to find that no person could ever impose it. This is like an arbitrary and capricious standard, the Company says, which applies when the Company's decision about the proper discipline makes no sense. The Company relies on USS-43,780, where the Board applied the reasonable relationship test.</p>
<p>9/ The discipline in the instant case bears a reasonable relationship to the offense Grievant committed, the Company argues. The rules Grievant broke are very basic &mdash; he has to stop, look both ways, and listen before crossing a railroad track. If the rules are ignored, there is great potential for a &ldquo;horrible result&rdquo; because of the mass of the train. On October 28, 2015, Grievant failed to stop before he crossed the track. He also failed to look both ways; had he done so, he could not have missed seeing the train. Grievant either failed to look, the Company says, or he knew the train was there and tried to beat it across the tracks. Finally, Grievant did not listen. Grievant may have been wearing hearing protection, but even so he was responsible for knowing what was going on around him.</p>
<p>10/ The Company says only Grievant knows whether he was hurrying to the shack because he had an urgent need to urinate. But even if he did, the Company contends, that would not excuse his obligation to use good and safe judgment. In essence, the Company says, the Union is arguing that Grievant should get a second chance &ldquo;because he had to pee.&rdquo; The Company also urges the Board to ignore the Union's claim that Grievant's need to urinate caused him to exercise poor judgment. If that were a defense, the Company contends, then every employee who uses poor judgment would make the same claim.</p>
<p>11/ The Company cites USS-44,719;-44,720, where the Board upheld the discharge of a mine production truck driver who took her eyes off the road while she was driving and leaned over to pick up her radio microphone. The employee's inattention resulted in an accident that capsized the 850,000 pound truck, causing the Company to pay &dollar;580,000 to recover the truck and repair the damage. The employee was not seriously injured. The employee had fifteen years of service and no disciplinary record, and the Board noted that she was an honest and credible witness, and that she had made one disastrous mistake. Nevertheless, the Board said the result of the accident could have been &ldquo;devastating.&rdquo; The employee lost control of a very large and dangerous truck and there was a reasonable relationship between the penalty and the offense.</p>
<p>12/ The Board also quoted from its decision in USS-26,770, in which a crane operator failed to notice that a hook was not properly engaged to a ladle hauling molten steel. The ladle spilled, causing significant damage, injuries, and a fatality:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The task Grievant had to perform was relatively simple, but critical&hellip;. Due to the known potential for great damage and harm to others if she failed to perform this task properly, her duty of care was extremely high. There was no acceptable margin of error. The evidence in this case convinces us that she failed to live up to the duty.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Company argues that the Board's language should apply to the instant case as well.</p>
<p>13/ The Board refused to apply any mitigating factors in USS-44,719; 44,720, the Company says, and it contends the Board should take the same position here. Grievant had about eighteen years of service and a disciplinary record that included only two warnings for attendance. However, the Company insists that Grievant violated the most basic of safety rules and then tried to use his bladder to excuse his conduct. Moreover, Grievant claimed he looked to the left while traveling parallel to the track, which cannot have been true, unless Grievant looked, saw the train, and then tried to outrun it to the crossing. Given these facts, the Company concludes, the Board must find that there was a reasonable relationship between Grievant's conduct and the discipline imposed.</p>
<p>14/ The Union says there is no evidence in the record that Grievant had received training on the safety procedures the Company relies on, or, for that matter, that he had even seen them. Nor was there any evidence about the content of the two safety contacts. This means, the Union argues, that the Board should disregard the Company's claim that Grievant violated those rules. The Union also contends that there was no testimony that it was improper for Grievant to use the crossing where the collision occurred. The Company did not rebut Grievant's testimony that it was common for employees to use the crossing, or that managers also used it.</p>
<p>15/ The Union disputes Townsend's conclusion that it would have been unsafe to allow Grievant to return to work. There was no evidence of past incidents or of any kind of pattern. Moreover, the Company did not ask Grievant to take a medical examination testing his cognitive ability, his hearing, or his vision. Yet the Company imposed the most severe discipline on an employee with eighteen years of service and a good disciplinary record. The Union notes the Company's reliance on USS-43,780, but what the Company did not mention, the Union says, is that the Board said the reasonable relationship analysis included consideration of &ldquo;the length and nature of the employee's service,&rdquo; although the Company refused to consider those factors in the instant case.</p>
<p>16/ The Union says it is not trying to excuse Grievant's conduct because he needed to use the rest room; rather, its point is that an urgent need to urinate could have affected Grievant's judgment, something that has to be taken into account. The same is true, the Union says, of the fact that. Grievant was trying to do the right thing by obeying the rule that prohibited him from relieving himself outside. These factors must be weighed, the Union says, in determining that the discipline imposed on Grievant was too harsh. The Union also points out that there is nothing in the grievance minutes contending that Grievant tried to outrun the train, which was an argument that did not surface until the arbitration hearing.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>FINDINGS</i></h4>
<p>17/ Townsend testified that Grievant had been trained on Standard Practices 11.32 and 11.33, which Grievant did not deny. Nor did he claim he was unaware of the rules. To the contrary, Grievant said he knew he was supposed to look in both directions before crossing the track and that he did not look to the left, although he claimed to have done so while driving parallel to the track. This evidence is sufficient to justify the Company's reliance on both 11.32 and 11.33.</p>
<p>18/ Grievant clearly violated the rules. He did not stop before he crossed the tracks and he did not look to his left. Nor is it likely that Grievant looked to his left while traveling on the road running parallel to the tracks. Had he done so, he could not have missed seeing the locomotive. The more likely scenario is that Grievant was in a hurry and simply did not take the time to check his surroundings before he crossed the tracks. As the Company points out, only Grievant knows whether he actually felt an urgent need to urinate, which caused him to hurry. But even if that was true, it is not an excuse for the accident and cannot be considered as a mitigating factor. Even in exigent circumstances, employees crossing railroad tracks in a steel mill must exercise caution to avoid exactly what happened in this case.</p>
<p>19/ The critical issue to be decided is whether there was proper cause for Grievant's discharge. If not, then the Board's authority to modify the discipline under Article 5-I-9-e would come into play. As indicated in prior Board decisions cited by the Company, in determining whether there was proper cause for discharge or rather only for some lesser degree of discipline, the Board has looked at whether &mdash; in the Board's judgment there was a reasonable relationship between the offense committed by the employee and the penalty imposed by the Company. This necessitates a case-by-case determination taking into account all relevant facts and circumstances, including an employee's length of service and prior disciplinary record. Where the Board finds no reasonable relationship, it will set aside the discharge.</p>
<p>20/ Grievant's misconduct did not cause serious injuries or property damage. The potential for both, however, was substantial and, as the Board said in a similar context in USS-44,719; -44,720, the absence of serious consequences &ldquo;was only a matter of happenstance.&rdquo; Grievant did nothing on his own to minimize the risk of harm. Instead, Grievant drove directly into the path of an oncoming train, in the process endangering the well-being of two train operators, but also putting his own life in significant peril. As Townsend testified, few people can get hit by a train and live to talk about it.</p>
<p>21/ The Board recognizes that Grievant was a long service employee with a good work record, and that these are factors the Board must consider in making a determination of whether there was proper cause. Nevertheless, when weighed against the severity of his misconduct, Grievant's length of service and his work record do not compel a conclusion that the Company lacked proper cause for discharge. Grievant was oblivious to his surroundings &mdash; even though there was clear visibility and even though the train sounded its horn twice.&mdash; and his lack of attention could easily have resulted in serious injury or death.. This conclusion is consistent with the decision in USS-44,719; -44,720, in which the Board upheld the discharge of an employee who had fifteen years of service and an unblemished record. As in the instant case, that employee's negligence endangered her own well-being, and, &ldquo;by barreling into the left lane,&rdquo; she also put the lives of other employees in jeopardy.</p>
<p>22/ The Union correctly points out that the Board cited the employee's length of service as a factor in its decision to reinstate the employee in USS-43,780. However, that employee had worked for the Company for thirty-three years, and, perhaps more important, the Board said there was a lack of proof that the employee's actions, while they violated a significant safe job procedure,. &ldquo;directly caused or could reasonably have been foreseen to cause&rdquo; the accident. That cannot be said about Grievant's misconduct, which was the sole cause of the accident.</p>
<p>23/ Although Grievant characterized the crossing he used as unauthorized, the Union correctly points out that the Company did not rebut Grievant's testimony that employees and managers regularly used the crossing. The Company did not contend in its final argument that Grievant's decision to use the unauthorized crossing influenced the discharge decision. It is worth noting, however, that Grievant testified he should have gone to the other crossing. Had he done so, he would have encountered gates and other signals warning him not to cross the tracks. Use of the unprotected crossing only heightened the need for caution on his part, as did the fact that his ability to hear the approaching train was negatively impacted by the noise of the Bobcat and his use of hearing protection.</p>
<p>24/ Finally, the Board rejects the Union's claim that the Company should have had Grievant's vision, hearing and cognitive ability examined before concluding that he could not be trusted to work safely. Grievant did not claim he had problems hearing or seeing. The problem was not that Grievant could not see, but, rather, that he did not look. Similarly, there is no reason to doubt Grievant's cognitive ability; he knew what he was supposed to do, but he simply chose not to do it.</p>
<p>25/ Based on all the circumstances discussed above, the Board concludes that there was a reasonable relationship between Grievant's conduct and the penalty assessed and there was proper cause for discharge. Thus, the Board must deny the grievances.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>AWARD</i></h4>
<p>26/ The grievances are denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>