<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of the Arbitration between International Union of Operating Engineers, Local 487, Union, and Titan America, Inc., Employer.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No. 16-53073-3</p>
<p>November 1, 2016.</p>
<p>Michael G. Whelan, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Opinion and Award</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Introduction</b></i></h4>
<p>The instant matter arises under the 2013-2016 collective bargaining agreement (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo;) between Tarmac, a Titan America Business (&ldquo;Employer&rdquo; or &ldquo;Titan&rdquo;), and the Operating Engineers Local No. 487 (&ldquo;Union&rdquo;). The parties to the CBA selected Michael G. Whelan as the Arbitrator to decide a grievance submitted by the Union. The parties presented evidence and argument on August 5, 2016, in Deerfield Beach, Florida. At the close of the evidentiary hearing, the parties agreed to submit post-hearing briefs on or before September 9, 2016. After two requests for enlargement of time submitted by the Union were approved, post-hearing briefs were timely submitted by the parties on or before September 30, 2016. On that date, the hearing record was deemed to be closed.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Issues</b></i></h4>
<p>The parties stipulated to the arbitrability of the grievance and to the following statement of the issues:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Was the discharge of Grievant in violation of the CBA? If so, what is the proper remedy?</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Relevant Contract Language</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i>ARTICLE II</i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i>MANAGEMENT PREROGATIVES</i></h4>
<p>1. The Union recognizes that the management of the Employer's business, the assignment and direction of the working force, the determination of the number to be employed or retained by the Employer, the right to make reasonable rules and regulations, the right to hire, promote and transfer employees; the right to discipline, suspend, discharge and demote employees for just cause; the right to layoff employees because of lack of work or other just or proper reasons, shall be the exclusive responsibility of the Employer, but it is understood that such rights shall not be arbitrarily exercised and the Union shall have the right, under the grievance procedure set forth in this Agreement, to question any action deemed unjust.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>ARTICLE XV</i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i>INDEFINITE LAYOFFS, TERMINATIONS AND RECALL</i></h4>
<p>1. Employees can be discharged by the Employer for just and proper cause.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Addendum &ldquo;C&rdquo;</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Company Rules</b></i></h4>
<p class="continued">We wish to call your attention to certain Company rules. These are listed below. Enforcement of these rules in addition to those outlined in the Employee Handbook will be as follows:</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Major Company Rules</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The following is intended to be an illustrative list rather than an exhaustive list of the</p>
<p class="continued">type of behaviors for which immediate discharge may result:</p>
<blockquote>
<p align="center">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">4. Punching another employee's time card or intentional falsification of a time card or any other Company record.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Facts</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>The parties</i></h4>
<p>The Employer produces cement at its Pennsuco plant in Medley, Florida. The Employer hired CH (&ldquo;Grievant&rdquo;) into the position of machine operator on March 2, 2004, and he was promoted to loader operator about four years later. Grievant remained employed with Titan as a loader operator until his termination on February 3, 2016.<ftnote num="1"><para>All dates refer to 2016, unless otherwise noted.</para></ftnote> The Union represents a unit of forty-four equipment operators at the Pennsuco plant. Grievant was a member of that unit at all times relevant to this case.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>Grievant's job</i></h4>
<p>As a loader operator working in the cement-making process, Grievant used heavy equipment to move material around a yard. Specifically, Grievant used a Komatsu front-end loader (the &ldquo;Loader&rdquo;) to move raw materials that go into the cement recipe and to clean the Internal Wastewater Management System (&ldquo;IWW system&rdquo;). The IWW system includes a series of three cells or pits used to drain water off waste material that accumulates during the cement-making process. To clean the IWW system, Grievant drives the Loader into the cells to remove material. When driving the Loader into the cells, the water level is not supposed to reach the wheel of the Loader.</p>
<p>Each day after reporting for work, Grievant was responsible for inspecting the Loader prior to using it. Grievant was required to document these pre-trip inspections on a &ldquo;Front End Loader Safety and Operational Checks&rdquo; form (the &ldquo;inspection form.&rdquo;). The inspection form lists twenty-six specific points of inspection and contains a &ldquo;Remarks&rdquo; section where miscellaneous comments may be made. Among those specific points of inspection are &ldquo;engine oil level&rdquo; and &ldquo;hydraulic oil level.&rdquo; Listed next to each point of inspection is a series of three boxes that should be checked after the inspection: the box farthest to the left should be noted as &ldquo;OK&rdquo; if the inspection is satisfactory; &ldquo;NR&rdquo; if the item needs repair; or &ldquo;N/A&rdquo; if an inspection of that item is not applicable. After the inspection form is completed and signed by the operator, it must be turned in to a supervisor who is supposed to review and sign off on the form.</p>
<h4 align="left">C. <i>The Loader fails</i></h4>
<p>On January 14<sup>th</sup>, Grievant started up the Loader, and the gear light came on. Grievant informed his supervisor about the problem, and the supervisor called a technician from Linder, a third-party vendor that services the Loader. The Linder technician came to the Pennsuco plant to check out the problem. The technician performed many, but not all, of the items on the 250-hour and 1000-hour planned maintenance schedule, but did not perform any items on the 500-hour and 2000-hour planned maintenance schedule. The technician also noted that the &ldquo;battery box was full of sand.&rdquo;</p>
<p>On January 29<sup>th</sup>, Grievant arrived at the Pennsuco plant between midnight and 2:00 a.m., and he performed the required inspections on the Loader. He had a number of copies of pre-filled out inspection forms in the Loader that had all the boxes already marked. On all of these forms, the &ldquo;OK&rdquo; box is checked for most points of inspection. Grievant took one of those forms, added the date, and he went into the building and placed the completed form on his supervisor's desk. At some point, one of Grievant's supervisors signed the appropriate box on the form indicating that the supervisor had reviewed the form. When Grievant returned to the Loader, he began to do his rounds. At that time, Grievant noticed the Loader was making a whining noise. He stopped the machine and told his supervisor about the noise.</p>
<p>Titan supervision again contacted the Linder technician, who came to the Pennsuco plant to check it out. After Linder's initial inspection, it informed Titan's Operations Manager SK (&ldquo;SK&rdquo;) that the Loader did not have adequate oil, that the hydraulic oil was contaminated such that its consistency was like molasses, and that the Loader was covered in mud. Linder supplied SK with photographs of the underside of the Loader showing it to be covered with mud, and a photograph of several pre-filled out inspection forms that were found in the cab of the Loader. After learning this, SK reviewed the inspection forms submitted by Grievant from January 14<sup>th</sup> through January 29th. All the forms during this period, except the one for January 14<sup>th</sup>, derived from the same photocopy and had the same entries, except for the date and the number of gallons of fuel added. After learning this, SK concluded that Grievant must not have conducted the pre-trip inspections because if Grievant had done so, Grievant would have observed the low fluid levels, the contaminated hydraulic oil, and the mud-covered components. SK consulted with a Titan human resources representative, who advised that Grievant should be suspended pending further investigation into the incident. Grievant, who had finished his shift on January 29<sup>th</sup>, was on his way home when he received a phone call from Titan informing him that he was suspended until further notice.</p>
<h4 align="left">D. <i>Further Investigation and Grievant's termination</i></h4>
<p>On February 1<sup>st</sup>, SK visited the Linder facility, where he took possession of the pre-filled out inspection forms, and he spoke to a Linder representative about the condition of the Loader and the estimated cost of repairs. That same day, SK also requested his security department to provide him with video footage of the plant yard from January 14<sup>th</sup> through 29<sup>th</sup>, so that he could determine if the Loader was submerged in water in the IWW cells at any point. A meeting was also arranged with the Union and Grievant to hear Grievant's side of the story.</p>
<p>On February 3<sup>rd</sup>, Titan representatives met with Grievant and his Union representatives for that purpose. After that meeting, Titan concluded that Grievant falsified his pre-trip inspection forms, which caused the condition of the Loader to go undetected and cost Titan thousands of dollars to repair. On this basis, Titan terminated Grievant's employment. Pursuant to the grievance procedure in the CBA, the Union filed a timely grievance challenging Grievant's termination. The Employer denied that grievance, which led to the Union initiating the instant arbitration proceedings.</p>
<h4 align="left">E. <i>Repairs to the Loader</i></h4>
<p>The Linder technician initially reported the problem with the Loader as &ldquo;Transmission noise.&rdquo; He reported the cause as &ldquo;&lsqb;f&rsqb;ound sand in the gear box.&rdquo; Further, the technician reported the &ldquo;correction&rdquo; as the following:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">1/29/16 Traveled to the machine location. Found transmission not working and the engine had to be revved a lot before machine would start moving as if the clutch was slipping. Checked for gear box oil and found no oil on dipstick. Took oil sample and found that it looked slushy. Per customer water and sand get into the batteries and gear box while in the reclaiming area. Removed drain plug and found no oil came out but sand did. Removed the strainer and found it was worse. Replaced transfer case oil. Machine is going to the shop for repairs. 39/16 &lsqb;sic&rsqb; Removed steering pump and installed new pump. Replaced o-rings on machine.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Another page of the service invoice reads as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Customer complaint was machine would not move in 1st or reverse. Dispatched tech to machine, upon diagnosing unit there was a fan noise evident, trans was not shifting properly, engine revolution was high before any movement at all and whining noise high, pulled dipstick for trans case and no oil, sample of oil was slushy looking as if it had concrete/sand and water intrusion,.&lsqb;sic&rsqb; removed drain plug to find more sand than oil, strainer was plugged with as well, att &lsqb;sic&rsqb; least 3 to 4 inches of sand in trans and pump case, unit needs to be in shop to tear down and see extent of internal damages, cause of this could be due to excessive water height in reclaiming pit, battery boxes also show evidence of sand from water intrusion there. Can attempt a drain and clean before shop bound.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Over the course of several days in March, Linder repaired the Loader. According to the service invoice, the following work was performed:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">3/7/16 Reassembled parts and brackets. Installed parts on transfer case.</p>
<p class="continued">3/8/16 Assembled transmission and hydraulic motor. Installed hoses and harness. Pressure washed hydraulic pump.</p>
<p class="continued">3/15/16 Installed HST on the machine and pumps. Installed fron &lsqb;sic&rsqb; drive shaft and rear shaft. Set-up the HST.</p>
<p class="continued">3/17/&lsqb;sic&rsqb; Installed the transfer case and hoses.</p>
<p class="continued">3/18/16 Finished installing transfer case hoses and installed cabin, harnesses, and hoses.</p>
<p class="continued">3/21/16 Connected harness, hoses and cabin attachments. Tested machine and found working properly at this time.</p>
<p class="continued">3/22/16 Finished installing hoses. Added HST oil. Ran machine under load. Drained and assed&lsqb;sic&rsqb; fresh fluid. Cleaned machine.</p>
<p class="continued">3/23/16 Washed and tested machine. Evacuated a/c system and charged with Freon.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The total cost of the repairs to the Loader was &dollar;38,390.77. The largest single expense was a new transfer case, which alone cost &dollar;26,386.90, not including labor.</p>
<h4 align="left">F. <i>Video footage of Grievant's operation of the Loader</i></h4>
<p>After Grievant's termination, SK received video footage showing that Grievant had submerged the Loader into water in the IWW cells on January 26<sup>th</sup>. None of Grievant's inspection forms after that date include any mention of submerging the Loader in water past the wheel rim.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Discussion</b></i></h4>
<p>The term &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; in the employment context is used to stand for the notion that there are limitations on managerial discretion to discipline employees. In determining the question of just cause, an arbitrator is called upon to interpret that phrase as a term of art that is unique to collective bargaining agreements. While an arbitrator may refer to sources other than the collective bargaining agreement for enlightenment as to the meaning of just cause in the context of the facts of the particular case, the essential role of the arbitrator is to interpret the collective bargaining agreement. In interpreting the meaning of just cause in the instant case, this Arbitrator draws the essence of the meaning of that phrase from the CBA.</p>
<p>It is well-established in labor arbitration that when, as in the present matter, an employer's right to discipline an employee is limited by the requirement that any such action be for just cause, the employer has the burden of proving by clear and convincing evidence that the discipline was for just cause. Therefore, the Employer has the burden of persuading the Arbitrator by clear and convincing evidence that there was just cause for Grievant's termination.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>The Just Cause Standard</b></i></h4>
<p>A determination of whether just cause exists for discipline requires at least two primary determinations. The first is whether there is a reasonable basis under the collective bargaining agreement to impose discipline on the employee in the first instance. If there is a reasonable basis upon which to impose discipline, the second determination is whether the penalty imposed is reasonable under the totality of the circumstances. These are two distinct inquiries and must be dealt with separately.</p>
<p>The determination of whether there was a reasonable basis to impose discipline consists of a number of substantive and procedural elements. Primary among the substantive elements is the existence of sufficient proof that the employee engaged in the conduct for which he or she was disciplined. Other elements include a requirement that an employee know or reasonably be expected to know ahead of time that engaging in a particular type of behavior will likely result in discipline; and a requirement that discipline be administered even-handedly &ndash; that is, that similarly situated employees be treated similarly and disparate treatment be avoided.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>Whether There was a Reasonable Basis to Impose Discipline</b></h4>
<p>The first issue for determination is whether Grievant engaged in the conduct for which he was terminated. Although there was some discussion at the hearing about whether Grievant violated policies or practices related to the use of the Loader, it was established that Grievant was terminated for falsification of company records. Specifically, the Employer maintains that Grievant was terminated for falsifying the inspection forms he submitted in late January. Thus, the disposition of this matter comes down to whether there is clear and convincing evidence that Grievant falsified the inspection forms he turned in during this period.</p>
<p>It is clear that most of the inspection forms Grievant turned in to his supervisors after January 14<sup>th</sup> had been filled out prior to the day they were submitted, as those forms are all photocopies of the same form. The forms turned in during this period are also part of the same batch of copied forms that were found in the loader after it was taken to Linder on January 29th. On all of these forms, all points of inspection and the remarks section are identically marked, and the &ldquo;OK&rdquo; box is checked for most points of inspection. The only difference between any of these forms is the date and the number of gallons of fuel added.</p>
<p>On the matter of whether Grievant actually performed the required inspections, Grievant testified that he did perform the required inspections and everything on the inspection forms was accurate. The Employer did not present any direct evidence that Grievant did not perform the required inspections, instead reasoning that if Grievant had performed the inspections then the Loader would not have sustained damage. For this type of circumstantial evidence to be convincing, it is necessary to prove that the damage to the Loader resulted from some condition that would have been revealed in the required pre-trip inspections.</p>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>Whether pre-checking fluid levels could have prevented Loader damage</i></h4>
<p>On this issue, the Employer claims that it learned from the Linder technician that the Loader &ldquo;did not have adequate oil, the hydraulic or transmission oil that was present was contaminated such that its consistency was like molasses.&rdquo; The Employer also claims that Linder informed it that the Loader was &ldquo;covered in mud.&rdquo; Based on this information, the Employer concluded that Grievant did not complete the pre-trip inspection, because if he had done so, he would have &ldquo;observed the low fluid levels, a contaminant in the hydraulic oil and the mud covered components.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Analysis of this issue requires consideration of whether pre-trip inspections of the various types of oil used in the Loader could have prevented the damage. The Loader uses engine oil, gear oil, and hydraulic oil. Engine oil used to lubricate the moving parts within the engine is of medium viscosity, or thickness. Gear oil is used to lubricate the transfer case and is of heavy viscosity. Hydraulic oil, sometimes referred to as fluid, is of low viscosity. Hydraulic oil is pumped through various systems in the loader &ndash; including steering, brakes, transmission, and the loader controls &ndash; to lubricate and power them.</p>
<p>There was no damage to the engine so the level or consistency of the engine oil is not central to the Employer's argument here. The Linder technician noted that the problem with the Loader was &ldquo;transmission noise&rdquo; due to &ldquo;sand in the gear box.&rdquo; The technician's description of the &ldquo;correction&rdquo; to this problem suggests that it was primarily due to contamination of the gear oil. According to the Linder technician, when he checked the oil, it did not register on the dipstick, and when he did drain the gear box he found sand and &ldquo;slushy&rdquo; oil. The Employer submitted a photograph of the oil into evidence, and it appears dark and thick with the appearance of molasses. According to the testimony of MS (&ldquo;MS&rdquo;), a former mechanic, this is how contaminated gear oil used in a transfer case would appear. The technician then noted that he removed the drain plug and drained the oil, and then he replaced the transfer case oil. This evidence, as well as MS's testimony, establishes that the technician was describing contaminated gear oil from the transfer case, not hydraulic fluid. Thus, the vast majority of the damage to the Loader was caused by lubrication failure in the transfer case. This conclusion is supported by Linder's service invoice, which shows that the majority of the cost of repairs involved the transfer case, where over &dollar;26,000 of a total of about &dollar;29,000 in parts alone was attributable to the transfer case.</p>
<p>The transfer case is a sealed metal box under the Loader containing gears lubricated by heavy viscosity gear oil. At various service intervals, the transfer case oil is changed by a mechanic by going under the Loader and removing metal plugs to drain the old oil and refill with new oil. There is no hourglass gauge or attached dipstick on it that would permit eyeball inspection, and Grievant was not required to conduct a pre-trip inspection of the amount or consistency of the gear oil in the transfer case. For this reason, Grievant cannot be held responsible for falsification of the inspection form as it relates to the gear oil because he was not required to check or document the level or consistency of the gear oil during the pre-trip inspection.</p>
<p>The Linder technician also performed some repair work to the Loader's hydraulic system, including replacing a steering pump and some o-rings. On January 29<sup>th</sup>, while at the Pennsuco plant, the technician also added two gallons of hydraulic fluid to that system. So, there is also an issue here concerning whether damage to the Loader's hydraulic system could and should have been prevented by a pre-trip inspection of that system. The Loader's hydraulic system is inspected by viewing an hourglass gauge to check the fluid level. There are also specific functions of the hydraulic system, such as brakes and steering, that must be inspected by starting up the machine and checking the operation of those functions.</p>
<p>Grievant testified that he performed the required inspections, which would have included a check of the transmission oil on an hourglass gauge. Based on the record evidence, it is difficult to conclude that he did not do so. The technician only added two gallons of fluid while on-site, which is not a lot in the context of the 47.6-gallon capacity of the Loader's hydraulic system. There is no record evidence upon which to conclude that a shortage of two gallons of hydraulic fluid would have been noticeable on the hourglass gauge.</p>
<p>Also, hydraulic fluid may be refilled though a fill tube, and once the cap on the fill tube is closed, the operation of the pump creates a seal. If water were to mix with the hydraulic fluid, the resulting compound would be a white milky material, not black and slushy as noted by the technician. There was no evidence presented that the hydraulic oil appeared milky. Further, if the hydraulic fluid was contaminated with sand and water, it raises unaddressed questions about why so little new hydraulic fluid was added. Thus, it cannot be concluded that the hydraulic fluid in the loader was at a level that would have registered as unsatisfactory on the hourglass gauge.</p>
<p>Another aspect of the pre-trip inspection of the Loader's hydraulic system involves starting up the machine to check the operation of the various hydraulic functions. Clearly, the Loader failed to operate properly towards the beginning of Grievant's shift on January 29<sup>th</sup>, but it is not sufficiently clear from the record that Grievant did not check the operation of the hydraulic components prior to submitting the inspection form. In other words, the steering, brakes, and other hydraulic functions initially may have worked when Grievant performed the pre-trip inspections, and then the transmission could have started to whine shortly thereafter when he began to use the Loader. In sum, there is insufficient evidence upon which to conclude that Grievant did not do a pre-trip inspection of the hydraulic system that would have revealed the potential for the damage done to that system.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>Whether checking the Loader for mud could have prevented damage</i></h4>
<p>The Employer also contends that Grievant's failure to report mud-covered components establishes that he did not perform the pre-trip inspections. Initially, it must be noted that there is no specific box to check for mud-covered components. There is a box labeled generally &ldquo;inspect truck for damage,&rdquo; but it is not clear that a muddy Loader should be treated as &ldquo;damage&rdquo; within the meaning of that phrase.</p>
<p>Titan's operations supervisor testified that if a Loader operator saw the underside of the Loader in the condition shown in the photographs taken by Linder, the Loader operator should have reported the condition to his supervisor and documented the condition on the &ldquo;Remarks&rdquo; section of the inspection form. At that point, it would be up to the supervisor to decide whether to keep the Loader in service or to have maintenance address the condition. Certainly, this procedure makes sense, but the evidence shows that on November 6, 2015, and January 24<sup>th</sup>, Linder had noted on its Planned Maintenance Program forms after servicing the Loader that the battery box was &ldquo;dirty&rdquo; and &ldquo;full of sand.&rdquo; These forms should have alerted Titan supervision to the dirty condition of the Loader, yet there is no evidence that it was addressed after Titan received that documentation. Also, during this period of several weeks prior to January 29<sup>th</sup>, Grievant and other drivers operated the Loader, and there is no evidence that anyone documented or reported that the underside of the Loader was dirty. It appears that the operations supervisor's view of Grievant's responsibility to report the dirty condition of the Loader is not consistent with the operators' inspection practice. In sum, there is too much ambiguity on the inspection form and uncertainty in the operator's practice concerning the reporting of mud to conclude that additional documentation about the mud-covered components would have prevented the damage to the Loader.</p>
<p>Titan also argues that the reason Grievant did not do the required inspections and report the water damage is that he knew he would get into trouble for driving the Loader too deep into the water.<ftnote num="2"><para>There is clear evidence that Grievant drove the Loader into water past the rim of the wheel while cleaning the IWW system. However, Grievant was not discharged or otherwise disciplined for violation of rules regarding operation of the Loader.</para></ftnote> That possible motivation is too speculative to serve as a basis to conclude under the clear-and-convincing evidence standard that Grievant did not perform the required pre-trip inspections.</p>
<h4 align="left">C. <i>Whether using pre-filled out forms is evidence of falsification</i></h4>
<p>Finally, Titan submits that using a pre-filled out form is itself evidence of falsification. Use of a pre-filled out form is not the best practice. There is more room for error in using a pre-filled out form because employees may forget where they left off during a series of inspections, which could easily happen, especially if they are interrupted. Making an entry after each check helps ensure that all the required checks are made and eliminates that risk. However, the mere fact that Grievant filled out the forms in advance does not show falsification. The point at which Grievant took responsibility for the contents of the form is the point at which he submitted it to supervision. Up until that time, Grievant could make changes to the form, as is shown by the varying dates and number of gallons on the forms submitted during January. Certainly, the Employer could require that employees not use a pre-prepared form, and discipline employees for doing so, but there is no evidence that such a policy or practice had been established here prior to this incident.</p>
<p>For the above-stated reasons, the Employer has not shown clear and convincing evidence that Grievant falsified company records, the conduct for which he was discharged. Because this required element of just cause has not been established, it is unnecessary to reach the other elements of the just cause standard.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Conclusion</b></i></h4>
<p>The Arbitrator determines that the Employer lacked just cause to terminate Grievant's employment. As a remedy, Grievant shall be reinstated and otherwise made whole for all lost pay and benefits as provided in the Award below.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>Award</b></i></h4>
<p>For the above-stated reasons, I, the undersigned Arbitrator, hereby AWARD, as follows:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>The grievance is SUSTAINED.</p></li>
<li><p>Grievant shall be reinstated forthwith. His termination shall be rescinded, and all documentation showing that he had been terminated shall be removed from his personnel file.</p></li>
<li><p>Grievant shall be paid for all lost pay and benefits and otherwise made whole from the date his termination until the date of his reinstatement, less all interim earnings he may have received from other employment and unemployment compensation.</p></li>
</ol>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>