<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the matter of arbitration between Arthur F. Schultz Company and the General Teamsters Local Union No. 397</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No. 16-53796-1</p>
<p>July 15, 2016.</p>
<p>Louis V. Imundo, Jr. Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>1.0 <i>Introduction</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">1.1 Appearing For Management</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Edward J. Betza, Esq., Attorney at Law</p></li>
<li><p>Melanie Hoover, Esq., Attorney at Law</p></li>
<li><p>John Blakeslee, President &amp; Co-owner</p></li>
<li><p>Daniel F. Schultz, Chairman of the Board &amp; Treasurer</p></li>
<li><p>Tom Ohmer, General Manager</p></li>
<li><p>Nicholas R. Gerlach, Delivery/Warehouse</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">1.2 Appearing For The Union</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Ernest B. Orsatti, Esq., Attorney at Law</p></li>
<li><p>Stephen B. Getz, President &amp; Business Agent</p></li>
<li><p>Douglas A. Youngs, Secretary Treasurer &amp; Business Agent</p></li>
<li><p>Brandon P. Pappas, Grievant</p></li>
</ul>
<h4 align="left"><b>2.0 <i>Nature Of The Case</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">This case pertains to two interrelated issues. The first is whether the instant grievance is properly before the Arbitrator. The second is whether the Grievant, Mr. Brandon Pappas, should have been discharged for his misconduct on February 24, 2016.</p>
<p class="continued">It was Management's position that the grievance was untimely filed and as a consequence it is not properly before the Arbitrator. It was Management's position that pursuant to Article XV, Section C of the Agreement the grievance should have been filed within the five day period of initial suspension and it was not filed until the sixth day.</p>
<p class="continued">It was Management's position that given the seriousness of Mr. Pappas venting his frustration over the GPS misdirecting him by hitting the unit with a clenched fist, which caused the windshield to crack, his failure to complete his scheduled route and his failure to report what had happened to anyone in Management his discharge was warranted.</p>
<p class="continued">It was the Union's position that the grievance is arbitrable. It was the Union's position that the Grievant was suspended on February 25, 2016 and that because the normal work schedule is five consecutive days from Monday through Saturday the grievance was timely filed on March 1<sup>st</sup>. The Union argued that the Grievant does not normally work on Sunday and he was not scheduled to work on Sunday, February 28<sup>th</sup>. It was the Union's position that there is no bargaining history or past practice to support Management's interpretation of the arbitration clause in the Agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">It was the Union's position that the penalty of termination was grossly disproportionate to the seriousness of the offense and that the appropriate discipline was a written warning. It was the Union's position that Mr. Pappas was denied due process because he was never given an opportunity to explain his actions before he was discharged. It was the Union's position that Mr. Gerlach, the only person Management interviewed, seized on the opportunity to retaliate against Mr. Pappas because of Mr. Pappas having reporting him for drinking on the job, which resulted in him being given a &ldquo;Last Chance Agreement.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">It was the Union's position that Management failed to consider that Mr. Pappas was a long term employee and that his action that caused the windshield to crack was unintentional.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>3.0 <i>Applicable Articles And Sections Of The Agreement</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article V &ndash; Hours Of Work, Section A (in part)</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The normal hours of work for all full-time employees shall be not more than eight (8) hours per day nor more than forty (40) hours per week. The normal schedule for full-time employees shall be five consecutive days from Monday through Saturday.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article XV &ndash; Discipline And Discharge, Section B</b></h4>
<p class="continued">In the event that the Company deems it necessary to discharge an employee, it is agreed that the employee will be placed on a suspension subject to discharge for a period of five (5) days during which time the Company will review the facts to determine if discharge is appropriate. Unless the Company changes its decision, the discharge shall be final at the end of the five (5) day period.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article XV &ndash; Discipline And Discharge, Section C</b></h4>
<p class="continued">During the five (5) day period of initial suspension, the employee may file a grievance or submit any information he wishes the Company to consider before making a final decision.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article XV &ndash; Discipline And Discharge, Section D</b></h4>
<p class="continued">Any grievance contesting the discharge may be filed within this five (5) day period of initial suspension or it shall be deemed untimely filed and it shall not be recognized or processed under this Agreement.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article XXIII &ndash; Grievance Procedure, Section B1</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The aggrieved employee or employees shall take the matter up first with the Shop Steward within five (5) working days of the date on which the grievance arises who in turn will take the grievance up with the Department Manager in charge, employees shall have the Shop Steward present on any grievance. If a satisfactory settlement is not effected with the Department Manager within three (3) working days, the employee shall submit such grievance to the Union's business representative in writing.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article XXIII &ndash; Grievance Procedure, Section B2</b></h4>
<p class="continued">If no satisfactory adjustment is agreed upon, the matter shall be referred by the business representative to the General Manager of the Company or some other executive officer of the Company with authority to act, who shall review the alleged grievance and offer a decision within five (5) working days after receipt of same.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article XXIII &ndash; Grievance Procedure, Section B6</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The decision of the Arbitrator shall be final and binding as to all matters within the limits of his jurisdiction.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article XXIII &ndash; Grievance Procedure, Section B7</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The fees and expenses in connection with the services of the Arbitrator shall be shared equally by the parties.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article XXVIII &ndash; Management Rights</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Company has the sole and exclusive right to manage its facility and to direct its workforce except as provided for in this Agreement.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>4.0 <i>Issues</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Parties agreed in principle to the Issues to be decided by the Arbitrator. Their specific wording was left to the Arbitrator's discretion. The Arbitrator has determined the Issues to be as follows:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Is the grievance properly before the Arbitrator?</p></li>
<li><p>If yes, was the Grievant's discharge the appropriate discipline?</p></li>
<li><p>If no, what was the appropriate discipline?</p></li>
</ul>
<h4 align="left"><b>5.0 <i>Relevant And Pertinent Information From The Record</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">The following was taken from the Arbitrator's notes, recording of the Hearing, testimony of witnesses, documentary evidence, and the briefs.</p>
<p class="continued">In his opening statement with respect to arbitrability Issue Mr. Betza made the following points to support Management's position:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>On Wednesday, February 24<sup>th</sup> the Grievant was working as a delivery driver delivering furniture. On his shift he became angry, punched his GPS, which resulted in a cracked windshield. He did not complete his shift.</p></li>
<li><p>It was reported to Management that Mr. Pappas had damaged a company vehicle and failed to finish his shift.</p></li>
<li><p>On February 24<sup>th</sup>, Mr. Blakeslee made the decision that Mr. Pappas should be terminated.</p></li>
<li><p>Under Article XV, Section B of the Agreement unless the Company changes it's position the discharge shall be final at the end of the five day period.</p></li>
<li><p>Under Section C the suspended employee may file a grievance during the five day period of initial suspension.</p></li>
<li><p>Under Section D any grievance contesting the discharge must be filed within the five day period of the initial suspension or it shall be deemed untimely and not recognized or processed.</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant was suspended on Wednesday, February 24, 2016. He was terminated on February 29<sup>th</sup>.</p></li>
<li><p>The grievance is dated March 2, 2016, which was day six. Based on that information the grievance was untimely.</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">In his opening statement with respect to the arbitrability Issue Mr. Orsatti made the following points to support the Union's position:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>The Grievant was notified on the morning of February 25<sup>th</sup> that he was being placed on suspension.</p></li>
<li><p>The Agreement states that a grievance must be filed within five working days. February 28<sup>th</sup> was a Sunday.</p></li>
<li><p>The grievance was filed March 1<sup>st</sup> within five working days.</p></li>
<li><p>Mr. Getz will testify that the Union received notification of Mr. Pappas' termination on March 1<sup>st</sup>. The grievance was timely filed.</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza called Mr. John Blakeslee as Management's first witness. Mr. Blakeslee testified that on Wednesday evening, February 24, 2016, he received a telephone call from Mr. Ohmer informing him of the incident that had occurred. Mr. Blakeslee said Mr. Ohmer told him that Mr. Gerlach had told him what had happened. The witness said that based on what Mr. Ohmer told him Mr. Pappas had to be suspended. Mr. Betza asked the witness if Mr. Pappas completed his shift on the 24<sup>th</sup> and he answered no. Mr. Betza asked the witness when he decided to suspend Mr. Pappas and he answered: &ldquo;On Wednesday night.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) The witness said he told his warehouse manager to call Mr. Pappas and tell him not to report for work on Thursday. The witness said that Mr. Pappas did not report for work after the 24<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza submitted into the record, a copy of the termination letter dated February 29, 2016 from Mr. Blakeslee to Mr. Pappas informing him that he was being terminated and the reasons for the decision. (Mgt No. 1) Mr. Blakeslee said the letter was mailed to Mr. Pappas on February 29<sup>th</sup> by certified mail.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti cross-examined. Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Blakeslee if he knew when the termination letter was received by Local 397? (Mgt. No. 1) The witness said he did not know for certain. Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Blakeslee when Mr. Pappas was notified of his suspension? Mr. Blakeslee answered: &ldquo;I imagine; I think it was that morning on Thursday the 25<sup>th.</sup>&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) Mr. Orsatti made the point that the Company's workweek, under Agreement, goes from Monday through Saturday. (Jt. No. 1) The witness agreed, but said there is a provision for Sunday work. Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Blakeslee if Mr. Pappas had been scheduled to work on Sunday and he answered no.</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator questioned Mr. Blakeslee. The Arbitrator asked Mr. Blakeslee how and when Mr. Pappas was told on the 25<sup>th</sup> he was being suspended? The witness answered that his warehouse manager did such early in the morning. The Arbitrator, referring to Article XV, Section C of the Agreement, asked the witness if he had any memory regarding if the five day period has been treated as work days or calendar days? (Jt. No. 1) The witness said this was the first occasion that he is aware of since the language has existed.</p>
<p class="continued">Management rested.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti called Mr. Stephen Getz as the Union's first witness. Mr. Getz testified that at the time the incident in question arose he was responsible for administering the Agreement and had been doing such since 2009. (Jt. No. 1) Mr. Getz said this case is the first ever between the Parties to be arbitrated. Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Getz when he first heard about Mr. Pappas' suspension? Mr. Getz said that late in the morning on the 25<sup>th</sup> Mr. Blakeslee notified him by telephone about the incident involving Mr. Pappas and that the Company was doing their due diligence.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti, referring to the grievance read: &ldquo;Brandon Pappas was unjustly terminated from his position at Arthur F. Schultz by letter received on March 1, 2016&rdquo;, and asked him who he was referring to having received the letter? (Jt. No. 2) Mr. Getz answered: &ldquo;I received from Attorney Betza in an email at approximately 11:00 a.m. that morning the termination letter along with another document. We were in the process of negotiating a new agreement so there were a couple of documents attached to that email. (Arbitrator's recording) Mr. Getz testified that the grievance was timely filed because March 1<sup>st</sup> was the fifth day. (Jt. No. 2) Mr. Getz said his belief is based on Article V's definition of a work week. (Jt. No. 1) The witness said that Sunday is not a scheduled work day.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza cross-examined. Mr. Betza pointed out that under the Agreement Sunday work can be scheduled. (Jt. No. 1) The witness agreed, but made the point that Sunday is not a regularly scheduled work day or considered to be included in the normal work week.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union rested.</p>
<p class="continued">In his closing argument Mr. Betza made the following points to show the grievance is not arbitrable.</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>There is nothing in the Agreement that excludes Sundays from the work week.</p></li>
<li><p>The argument that Sundays are not normally a work day does not rise to a level where anyone could conclude that you cannot count that day.</p></li>
<li><p>If Sundays or any other days are not to be counted the Contract needs to say so. The language is very clear regarding that a grievance must be filed within five days.</p></li>
<li><p>The Union's claim that they did not learn of the discharge is irrelevant. Mr. Pappas was discharged on the 29<sup>th</sup> and the Union knew his discharge was coming.</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">In his closing argument Mr. Orsatti made the following points to show that Management had failed to prove their case:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>The Agreement is very clear that Sundays are not part of the work week. While Sundays can be worked they are not part of the regular work week.</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant could not have been suspended on Sunday.</p></li>
<li><p>When we are talking about a five day suspension it is reasonable for the Union to conclude that the suspension was five working days. The requirement to file a grievance in terms of the suspension would have been the five days he was not working. You do not suspend people on days when they are not working.</p></li>
<li><p>On it's face the Contract is clear. The Grievant was suspended for five work days, which did not include Sunday.</p></li>
<li><p>The grievance was timely filed and is properly before the Arbitrator.</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">In his opening statement with respect to the merits Mr. Betza made the following points to support Management's position:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>On Wednesday, February 24<sup>th</sup>, while working on his shift, Mr. Pappas, who was driving and paired up with Mr. Gerlach got very angry, punched a GPS unit, which then shattered the windshield of the vehicle.</p></li>
<li><p>Mr. Pappas then refused to complete the rest of his shift and went home.</p></li>
<li><p>Given the violent nature of his actions and subsequent refusal to complete his shift the decision was made to terminate Mr. Pappas' employment.</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">In his opening statement with respect to the merits Mr. Orsatti made the following points to support the Union's position:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>The Union does not dispute the fact that Mr. Pappas' conduct caused the windshield to fracture.</p></li>
<li><p>The Union disputes Management's claim that it was done in a violent manner. Mr. Pappas did not intend to break the windshield. It was an unfortunate incident.</p></li>
<li><p>Mr. Pappas deserves nothing more than a warning letter.</p></li>
<li><p>The GPS in the truck was Mr. Pappas' personal GPS. Mr. Pappas was frustrated by the circumstances. His actions were not in a violent rage.</p></li>
<li><p>He reached for the GPS in the dark and it resulted in the windshield fracturing. For this he deserved some minor discipline.</p></li>
<li><p>The discharge action was grossly disproportional to what happened.</p></li>
<li><p>The assertion that Mr. Pappas refused to complete his assigned work that day is grossly inaccurate. It was the end of the day. It was 7:00 o'clock at night.</p></li>
<li><p>Mr. Pappas had one remaining pickup to do that day, but could not do it because he had a broken windshield. It would have been improper for him to have kept on driving his vehicle with a broken windshield.</p></li>
<li><p>Mr. Pappas brought his vehicle back to the store and punched out. He worked a full shift that day with one minor exception.</p></li>
<li><p>The Company was not harmed in any way. He was not directed to continue working that day.</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza called Mr. Nicholas Gerlach as Management's second witness. Mr. Gerlach testified that in addition to his position as Warehouse/Delivery he is a Union steward. Mr. Gerlach testified that he was in the truck with Mr. Pappas when the incident occurred. Mr. Gerlach testified that Mr. Pappas became visibly frustrated after he drove on the wrong road. Mr. Gerlach said: &ldquo;He quickly and violently made a motion toward the GPS and the windshield became damaged as a result of that.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) Mr. Betza asked the witness if Mr. Pappas punched the windshield and he answered yes. Mr. Betza asked the witness what happened to the windshield. The witness answered: &ldquo;Well, surprisingly it left a very large I guess you would call it spider web track across it.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) Mr. Betza asked the witness if Mr. Pappas said anything to him and the witness answered: &ldquo;Immediately after that, no.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) He said they sat there for 10 to 20 minutes and nothing was said between them. Mr. Gerlach said that eventually Mr. Pappas drove to the next stop and after that stop they doubled back to the store as opposed to finishing their route. The witness said he asked Brandon if he should call the last stop and his response was: &ldquo;Fuck it I'm done anyways.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) Mr. Gerlach testified that insofar as he knew Mr. Pappas did not, while they were out in the truck, notify anyone at the Company that he had damaged the vehicle.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza asked Mr. Gerlach if Mr. Pappas said anything else to him after the event and if so, what did he say? Mr. Gerlach answered yes and recalled Mr. Pappas saying: &ldquo;I can't believe I wasted it on a windshield.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) Mr. Betza asked the witness how he interpreted Mr. Pappas's remark? The witness answered: &ldquo;As a threat.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) Mr. Betza asked as a threat of what and towards who? The witness answered: &ldquo;As a threat of violence towards myself or towards other employees at Arthur F. Schultz.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording)</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Gerlach testified that after they returned to the store he proceeded to tell Mr. Ohmer, who was at the store, about what had occurred. The witness said he met with Mr. Blakeslee the next day. Mr. Betza submitted into the record, a copy of the handwritten statement that at Mr. Blakeslee's request the witness prepared. (Mgt. No. 2) The witness said he freely wrote the statement.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti cross-examined. Mr. Gerlach said that Mr. Pappas punched the GPS and this took place sometime between 6:00 p.m. and 6:30 p.m. Mr. Orsatti asked the witness if the cracked windshield got worse over time and he answered no.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Gerlach said he became a Union steward shortly after the incident. Mr. Orsatti said to the witness that he does not like Mr. Pappas and he answered yes. Mr. Orsatti said to Mr. Gerlach that Mr. Pappas had reported him twice for drinking on the job. The witness said he believed that to be accurate. The witness said that although he does not particularly like Mr. Pappas he conducts himself as a professional on the job. Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Gerlach if he received any discipline as a result of Mr. Pappas having reported his drinking on the job? The witness said he was given a last chance agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza redirected. Mr. Betza submitted into the record, a copy of the &ldquo;Final Written Warning&rdquo;, i.e., last chance agreement that Mr. Gerlach was given on March 23, 2015. (Mgt. No. 3) Mr. Betza asked the witness how much time passed from when he consumed alcohol during scheduled work time on Company property and when Mr. Pappas reported it to the Company? Mr. Gerlach answered: &ldquo;At least a year if not more than that.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording)</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator questioned Mr. Gerlach. The Arbitrator asked Mr. Gerlach if it was light, getting dark, or dark when, on February 24<sup>th</sup>, Mr. Pappas and he made the last delivery? The witness said it was dark. The Arbitrator asked the witness if, at anytime Mr. Pappas said it was dangerous or getting dangerous to be driving with a cracked windshield and he answered no. The Arbitrator asked the witness if, at anytime he told Mr. Pappas that it was unsafe to be driving in the dark with a cracked windshield? The witness answered: &ldquo;No sir, I didn't say much of anything after this incident occurred.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording)</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Gerlach testified that the driver is typically in charge when they are delivering and/or picking up furniture. The Arbitrator asked Mr. Gerlach if, on the 24<sup>th</sup>, either Mr. Pappas or he was carrying a cell phone while they were out on delivery? The witness said the truck has a Company cell phone. The witness they also typically had their personal cell phones with them. The Arbitrator asked Mr. Gerlach if employees had ever been given any direction with respect to who is responsible for reporting an unanticipated event that occurs during the course of making deliveries? The witness said no direction has ever been given and that he did not say anything because at the time he felt threatened. The Arbitrator asked the witness to elaborate on why he felt threatened. The Arbitrator asked Mr. Gerlach if Mr. Pappas directed the remark to him in some manner? Mr. Gerlach answered: &ldquo;When he removed the GPS from the windshield in what I deemed to be a violent motion of action that made me feel uncomfortable and threatened.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) The witness said that when Mr. Pappas hit the GPS with his fist the unit with the suction mounting bracket came off the windshield.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza recalled Mr. Blakeslee. Mr. Betza submitted into the record, a color copy of the photo that Mr. Blakeslee said he took off the cracked windshield early on Thursday morning, February 25<sup>th</sup>. (Mgt. No. 4) Mr. Betza submitted into the record, a copy of the receipt for the replacement of the cracked windshield. (Mgt. No. 5)</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza asked the witness why he decided to terminate Mr. Pappas? Mr. Blakeslee said it was based on three criteria. They were: 1. The violent nature of the action; 2. the damage to the Company vehicle; 3. not finishing the deliveries for the day.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti cross-examined. Mr. Orsatti asked the witness if there are occasions when a driver fails to complete his deliveries on a given day and he answered yes. The witness said that such seldom occurs. The witness said he could not remember the last time such happened.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Blakeslee if he spoke with Mr. Pappas to get his side of the story and he answered no. Mr. Orsatti asked the witness when he made the decision to terminate the Grievant? The witness said it was probably on Friday. Mr. Blakeslee testified that before he made the decision he had knowledge of Mr. Pappas' side of the story because Mr. Pappas had communicated by text messages with his direct supervisor about what had occurred. The witness said that Mr. Pappas did not deny that his action resulted in a damaged windshield. Mr. Blakeslee said that Mr. Pappas should have made the scheduled pickup with the damaged windshield on his truck.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza redirected. Mr. Betza asked Mr. Blakeslee if, after he informed Mr. Getz of his decision, the Union ever provided him with any information regarding Mr. Pappas and the February 24<sup>th</sup> event and he answered no.</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator questioned Mr. Blakeslee. The Arbitrator asked the witness if drivers are required to report damage to a vehicle within a specified period of time? The witness said there is a daily inspection report. The Arbitrator asked Mr. Blakeslee if, unless a vehicle is inoperable, drivers are required to immediately report any damage that the vehicle has sustained and he answered no.</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator, referring to the termination letter and noting that reference was made to: &ldquo;&hellip;prior issues with failure to control your temper, most recently February 2015.&rdquo; asked Mr. Blakeslee what he meant? The witness spoke about some prior incidents. The Arbitrator asked how long prior discipline remains active in an employee's record and Mr. Blakeslee said the practice is one year. (Mgt. No. 1) The Arbitrator asked Mr. Blakeslee if the reference to the February 2015 incident was within or after one year and his response was that it was after. The Arbitrator, again referring to the termination letter asked Mr. Blakeslee what he was referring to when he wrote: &ldquo;Over the past 5 days the Company has considered your comments, &hellip;?&rdquo; (Mgt. No. 1) Mr. Blakeslee said he was referring to the text messages between Mr. Pappas and the Warehouse Manager regarding the incident. The text messages were not introduced at the Hearing.</p>
<p class="continued">Management rested.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti called Mr. Brandon Pappas as the Union's second witness. Mr. Pappas said he first started working at the Company as a temporary employee and became a regular full time employee in April 2002. The Grievant testified about his job duties and responsibilities.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti asked the Grievant what were his shift hours on February 24, 2016? The Grievant answered: &ldquo;8:00 a.m. until I'm done.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) The Grievant said his typical workday was from 8:00 a.m. to 5:00 p.m.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Pappas how many delivery drivers there were on February 24<sup>th</sup>? The witness estimated there were three or four.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti directed Mr. Pappas to Mgt. No. 3 and asked him if, in 2015 that was the first time he reported Mr. Gerlach for consuming alcohol? The Grievant testified that he reported such to Mr. Ryan Turbechewski, the Warehouse Manager in 2014 and in a subsequent meeting around the time the final warning was issued he brought it up again.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Pappas to explain what happened late in the day on February 24<sup>th</sup>? The Grievant said the GPS was mounted on the windshield with a suction cup bracket. Mr. Pappas said he got frustrated because the GPS had been misdirecting him. The Grievant, referring to the GPS said: &ldquo;I went to grab it, an open hand and not a fist and when I went to grab it I bumped the mount. I (unintelligible) because of the darkness I couldn't quite see where the mount was. I bumped it a little harder than I meant to.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) The Grievant said he did not intend to damage the windshield and that he was surprised when he saw the damage.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Pappas testified that after making the next delivery because of the darkness and the light reflection on the cracked windshield it was difficult to see. The Grievant said he decided that it was no longer safe to drive the truck and he decided to not make the scheduled pickup and to return to the warehouse. The Grievant testified that when he returned to the warehouse he followed his normal routine when checking back in at the end of the day. The Grievant said he did not speak to any supervisor before he left for home.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Pappas if he said anything to the effect that: &ldquo;I can't believe I wasted it on a windshield?&rdquo; The Grievant said he could not recall making such a statement. He further denied saying anything that Mr. Gerlach could have interpreted as a threat.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti asked Mr. Pappas if, after the incident, anyone from the Company interviewed him after the incident and he answered no. The Grievant said that on the 25<sup>th</sup>, early in the morning he got a call from Ryan (Turbechewski) telling him not to report for work that day. The Grievant said he was told that John or Dan would be contacting him and such never occurred until he was notified that he was terminated.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza cross-examined. Mr. Betza asked Mr. Pappas how far it was and how long it took to make the delivery with the cracked windshield? The Grievant said he could not recall, but it was close.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant testified that when he returned to the warehouse with the damaged windshield he assumed that Mr. Gerlach would tell Mr. Ohmer about what had happened.</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator questioned Mr. Pappas. The Arbitrator asked the Grievant if he would agree with Mr. Gerlach's testimony that after the windshield had been damaged they sat in silence for 10 to 20 minutes? The witness said it was more like 10 minutes. Mr. Pappas said he was shocked by the amount of damage to the windshield. Mr. Pappas maintained that he did not punch the GPS and opined that the damage occurred when he removed the GPS bracket from the windshield.</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator asked Mr. Pappas why he did not report to supervision that he had missed a stop and that the windshield was damaged? Mr. Pappas answered: &ldquo;I think that I was upset at that point. I knew that Nick was already reporting it. I felt that it was going to be mis-reported and I basically assumed that this was going to be the end of my job once they saw the window.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording)</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Orsatti redirected. Mr. Pappas said he did not intend for the windshield to be broken. Mr. Pappas said he saw Mr. Gerlach talking with Mr. Ohmer and assumed he was telling him about the damaged windshield.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza recross-examined. Mr. Betza said to Mr. Pappas: &ldquo;Didn't you think this should be reported?&rdquo; Mr. Pappas answered: &ldquo;I supposed that would have been one way to go.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) Mr. Pappas said that the Company needed to be told about the damaged windshield and missed pickup and he believed that Mr. Gerlach did such.</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza asked Mr. Pappas if, at any point in time, he decided to send a letter, email, or text message to the Company regarding what had happened. Mr. Pappas answered: &ldquo;When I got the message from Ryan do not report and that John or Dan would get a hold of me I took that strongly as to not bother until they contacted me.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording) John is Mr. Blakeslee and Dan is Mr. Schultz and they co-own the Company.</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator requestioned Mr. Pappas. The Arbitrator asked Mr. Pappas how he would characterize or describe his working with Mr. Gerlach during the six months preceding the February 24<sup>th</sup> event. Mr. Pappas answered: &ldquo;Intolerable.&rdquo; (Arbitrator's recording)</p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Betza recross-examined. Mr. Betza asked Mr. Pappas if he notified anyone in Management that there was a problem with Mr. Gerlach? The Grievant said he did nothing about the situation after the February 2015 argument he had with Mr. Gerlach in front of a customer. The Grievant said he was told to get along with Mr. Gerlach.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union rested.</p>
<p class="continued">The Parties rested and made closing arguments in written briefs.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>6.0 <i>Opinion</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">ISSUE NO. 1</p>
<p class="continued">IS THE GRIEVANCE PROPERLY BEFORE THE ARBITRATOR?</p>
<p class="continued">The record establishes that Mr. Blakeslee made the decision to suspend the Grievant sometime during the evening of February 24<sup>th</sup> very shortly after Mr. Ohmer called and told him what Mr. Gerlach had reported. The record establishes that Mr. Pappas learned that he was being suspended early in the morning on February 25<sup>th</sup> when he received a telephone call from his immediate supervisor, Mr. Ryan Turbechewski, telling him not to report that day. In the Arbitrator's opinion, the time line for all subsequent actions relating to this matter started to roll on February 25<sup>th</sup> when Mr. Pappas was officially informed that he was suspended.</p>
<p class="continued">The establishment of mutually agreed on time lines for the full spectrum of actions relating to the disciplining of employees are essential to maintaining the integrity of the process. The Parties recognized such when they agreed on the applicable language in the Agreement. (Jt. No. 1)</p>
<p class="continued">In the Arbitrator's opinion, when Management decides to suspend employees for misconduct the time off from work is normally scheduled work time. Suspending an employee for one day when the following day is not a regularly scheduled work day and he/she had not been previously scheduled to work that specific day would service no useful purpose whatsoever. A suspension with the resultant loss of pay is meant to impress on the individual that there is a price to pay for misconduct.</p>
<p class="continued">At the Hearing, and in his brief Mr. Betza asserted that: &ldquo;There is nothing in the Agreement that excludes Sunday from being counted for grieving a suspension, and nothing that states that the five day suspension excludes certain days.&rdquo; (Mgt. brief pg. 5) The record establishes that there is no past practice to show how the Parties have interpreted Article XV, Sections B, C and D &lsquo;s language. (Jt. No. 1) Nor is there anything in the record to show whether the referenced language's time line was meant to include Sundays when such was memorialized in an agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">As noted, a relevant part, Article V, Section A of the Agreement states: &ldquo;The normal schedule for full time employees shall be five consecutive days Monday through Saturday.&rdquo; (Jt. No. 1) The record establishes that while it was not unusual for Mr. Pappas to work more than eight hours in a day it was unusual for him to work on Sunday. He was not scheduled to work on Sunday, February 28<sup>th</sup>. In the Arbitrator's opinion, unless the Parties had agreed that non scheduled work days would be included in suspension time off such cannot be included because to do such would contravene the purpose of a suspension.</p>
<p class="continued">Article XV, Section C of the Agreement states: &ldquo;During the five (5) day period of initial suspension, the employee may file a grievance or submit information he wishes the Company to consider before making a final decision.&rdquo; (Jt. No. 1) As stated the suspension started on February 25<sup>th</sup>. As concluded, Sunday cannot be included in the five day period. This year February has 29 days. The fifth day was March 1<sup>st</sup> the day the grievance was filed. (Jt. No. 2)</p>
<p class="continued">In conclusion, for the aforementioned reason the grievance was timely filed and is properly before the Arbitrator.</p>
<p class="continued">ISSUE NO. 2</p>
<p class="continued">IF YES, WAS THE GRIEVANT'S DISCHARGE THE APPROPRIATE DISCIPLINE?</p>
<p class="continued">In the Arbitrator's opinion there are two critical elements that go to the heart of this Issue. The first is whether Mr. Pappas was denied his right to due process. The second is the credibility of the Grievant and Mr. Gerlach the only two people who know what actually happened at the time of and after the event occurred. As will be discussed, Mr. Pappas and Mr. Gerlach had different recollections.</p>
<p class="continued">In the Arbitrator's opinion, due process for the accused is at the heart of the determination of whether just cause exists to discipline. Due process requires that a timely, thorough and impartial investigation be conducted. Due process also requires that the accused be interviewed and allowed to present his/her side of the case before Management makes a final decision on what discipline, if any, to impose. It is well-established that if neither or both of these essential requirements are not satisfied arbitrators will, with infrequent exceptions, fail to sustain any imposed discipline no less a discharge.</p>
<p class="continued">The principals in this matter are the Grievant and Mr. Gerlach. The record establishes that the Grievant and Mr. Gerlach do not like each other. This fact was most certainly known to Management. In the Arbitrator's opinion, considering that Mr. Pappas played a big part in Mr. Gerlach being given a &ldquo;Final Written Warning&rdquo; it is very apparent that Mr. Gerlach could take advantage of any opportunity to get Mr. Pappas in trouble. (Mgt. No. 3) The belief that he could does not mean that he definitely would do such. In the Arbitrator's opinion, Management's decision to solely rely on Mr. Gerlach's version of the events was a serious error in judgment.</p>
<p class="continued">An important element in deciding this Issue is the credibility of Mr. Pappas and Mr. Gerlach. In the Arbitrator's opinion, both of them were not very credible witnesses. After a thorough review of the record the Arbitrator has determined that Mr. Gerlach was a far less credible witness than the Grievant.</p>
<p class="continued">In the Arbitrator's opinion, the record clearly shows that before, during and after Mr. Pappas' action caused the windshield to crack he did not in any way whatsoever do anything that can be considered to be threatening to Mr. Gerlach. Mr. Pappas did not direct any threatening remark to or about Mr. Gerlach. Mr. Pappas' physical action on the GPS was not directed to or at Mr. Gerlach.</p>
<p class="continued">In the Arbitrator's opinion, unless the windshield had a small unnoticeable crack, or was inherently defective, which there is nothing in the record whatsoever to prove such, to cause the windshield to crack Mr. Pappas had to have hit the GPS unit with considerable force. Striking it with a clenched fist, or even an open hand with considerable force would far more likely to have caused the unit to come either off the suction mount, or with the suction mount still attached to hit the windshield with sufficient velocity to crack it than the Grievant's claim that he grabbed it (GPS) and bumped the mount. In the Arbitrator's opinion, Mr. Pappas' version of what caused the windshield to crack was not credible.</p>
<p class="continued">In the Arbitrator's opinion Management erred when they elected not to interview Mr. Pappas and believed Mr. Gerlach's version of the events when they most certainly knew that he had a clear motive to capitalize on the opportunity Mr. Pappas gave him. In conclusion, Mr. Pappas was denied his right to due process.</p>
<p class="continued">In the Arbitrator's opinion, there is nothing in the record to show no less prove that Mr. Pappas intended to damage the windshield. In the Arbitrator's opinion Mr. Pappas became very frustrated when the GPS kept misdirecting him and he vented his frustration by punching the GPS with sufficient force with or without the mount still attached to the unit to cause it to strike and crack the windshield.</p>
<p class="continued">In the Arbitrator's opinion, given the damage to the windshield and the fact that the final stop of the day, a pickup, would have done after sunset it is understandable why Mr. Pappas decided not to make it. What is not understandable nor excusable is the fact that Mr. Pappas did not call the Company on the cell phone in his truck and tell Mr. Ohmer who was on the premises of the situation.</p>
<p class="continued">The record establishes that when Mr. Pappas realized that his action had resulted in a cracked windshield he believed he would lose his job over it. In the Arbitrator's opinion, Mr. Pappas was unprofessional and irresponsible when, after returning to the warehouse, instead of speaking with Mr. Ohmer he clocked out and went home. In the Arbitrator's opinion, although Mr. Gerlach reported the event to Mr. Ohmer such did not excuse the Grievant from doing the same. In the Arbitrator's opinion, considering the animus that existed between Mr. Pappas and Mr. Gerlach, Mr. Pappas had a strong reason to make sure that his version of the event was heard too.</p>
<p class="continued">The record shows that Mr. Blakeslee was the individual who made the decision to terminate Mr. Pappas. (Mgt. No. 1) As concluded, Mr. Blakeslee erred when he failed to either personally, or have a designated member of Management interview Mr. Pappas before the decision was made. However, this begs the question: why didn't Mr. Pappas take affirmative action to tell his side of the story? The answer to this question is that Mr. Pappas gave unrebutted testimony that when Mr. Turbechewski called him on February 25<sup>th</sup> telling him not to report that day he was also told that John or Dan would be contacting him and such never occurred until he received notification that he was terminated. In the Arbitrator's opinion, Mr. Pappas had good reason not to call Mr. Blakeslee and/or Mr. Schultz because of what Turbechewski had told him. In the Arbitrator's opinion, while, as the five day period was coming to an end Mr. Pappas could have called Mr. Ohmer, Mr. Blakeslee or Mr. Schultz and asked to be heard. Management, for the reasons discussed, had a far greater responsibility to contact Mr. Pappas.</p>
<p>The record establishes that Mr. Pappas was a long term employee with no current discipline on his record. As stated, his action that resulted in a cracked windshield was unintentional. Mr. Pappas had good reason not to make the last pickup. Mr. Pappas erred when he did not call the Company to report that because of the cracked windshield he could not finish his route. He again erred when he did not join Mr. Gerlach in telling Mr. Ohmer what happened. In the Arbitrator's opinion, Management's assertion that Mr. Pappas willfully refused to complete his assigned work shift is a mischaracterization. (Mgt. brief pg. 6) Willful refusal implies a direct refusal or disregard of a direct order. This is not what happened. As stated, Mr. Pappas had good reason not to offer any explanation for his behavior during the period of his suspension. (Mgt. brief pg. 7)</p>
<p class="continued">In the Union's brief Mr. Orsatti wrote:</p>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;6. The penalty is grossly disproportionate to the offense.</p>
<p class="continued">Management established a precedent for the level of discipline appropriate for this type of conduct. On March 23, 2015, the Employer decided that a Last Chance Agreement was the appropriate penalty for an employee drinking on the job &ndash; an offense which they characterized as &lsquo;both illegal and in violation of Company expectations.' (Management Exhibit No. 1). Mr. Pappas' conduct on February 24, 2016 pales in comparison to Mr. Gerlach's conduct, yet Management decided to terminate Mr. Pappas. In order for the punishment to be consistent, no more than a written warning should have been imposed on Mr. Pappas.&rdquo; (Union brief pg. 14)</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator agrees with the above quoted with the exception of the suggested discipline. In the Arbitrator's opinion, Mr. Pappas' frustration with his GPS did not justify his hitting it with his fist with such force that it resulted in a large spider web cracked windshield. (Mgt. No. 4) In the Arbitrator's opinion, although the event was properly reported to Management by Mr. Gerlach, Mr. Pappas had a responsibility to do the same. As discussed, Management denied Mr. Pappas any semblance of due process. For all of these reasons the penalty of discharge was far, far too severe.</p>
<p class="continued">In conclusion, after a thorough review of the record and in consideration of all of the aforementioned it is the Arbitrator's decision that the discharge should be reduced to a one day suspension.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>7.0 <i>Award</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">The discharge is hereby rescinded and reduced to a one day suspension. The Grievant is to be reinstated to his former position without any loss of seniority or benefits and returned to work as soon as practical. The Grievant is to be compensated for all lost wages after the one day suspension including any lost overtime. The Grievant is to be reimbursed for any out of pocket healthcare expenses that would have been paid by the Company's healthcare insurance provider had he not been discharged. Any monies earned or paid to the Grievant including unemployment compensation benefits monies, except earnings from investments and income streams he was receiving before he was discharged from any sources that continued after his discharge are to be deducted from the wages owed to him.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant is hereby directed to fully cooperate with the Management in providing relevant requested information pertaining to monies paid or earned out of pocket healthcare costs incurred during the aforementioned time frame. Failure to fully cooperate in providing relevant requested information will nullify the claim for monies owed. Any proven withholding or falsification of relevant requested information will also nullify the claim for monies owed.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>