<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>City of Twinsburg Public Employer and Ohio Patrolmen's Benevolent Association Employee Organization</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>AAA No: 01-16-0001-7191</p>
<p>September 19, 2016.</p>
<p>Gregory P. Szuter, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>ARBITRATION DECISION AND AWARD</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>I. INTRODUCTION</b></h4>
<p>The parties to this arbitration are City of Twinsburg, Ohio (&ldquo;Employer&rdquo; or &ldquo;City&rdquo;) and Ohio Patrolmen's Benevolent Association (&ldquo;Union&rdquo; or &ldquo;OPBA&rdquo;). This arbitration arises from a grievance filed on April 13, 2016 by Tom Austin (&ldquo;Grievant&rdquo;) under the collective bargaining agreement between the parties for the Sergeant Unit, effective, 2014, through 2016. (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo; or &ldquo;Agreement&rdquo;). Other identical collective bargaining agreements for members of the Patrol and Dispatch Units having the same language were cited in the grievance and the parties stipulated the three units would be comprehended in the grievance and considered together in arbitration under this grievance.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>II. RECORD OF HEARING</b></h4>
<p>An arbitration hearing was held in Twinsburg, Ohio, on August 4, 2016 at which both parties presented their evidence and arguments. The parties submitted four Joint Exhibits (&ldquo;JX&rdquo;). The Union offered seven exhibits (&ldquo;UX&rdquo;), two duplicating the JX. The Employer offered two exhibits (&ldquo;EX&rdquo;). The parties filed post hearing briefs in lieu of argument. The testimony, which is noted herein, with the exhibits and stipulations together with the briefs constitute the record of hearing.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>III. THE GRIEVANCE</b></h4>
<p>The written grievance was filed on April 13, 2016 citing the provision violated as &ldquo;Article 32 (all OPBA CBA's)&rdquo; and charged:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Statement of Facts: On or about 4/8/16 the City reduced the amount paid to employee (OPBA members) who participate in opting out of the City's healthcare plan. This modification and redaction violates clear CBA language and past practice of the parties. Remedy Sought: Rescind the modification, calculate the correct opt out payment going forward and cease and desist from future reductions including retroactive.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Employer responded denying the grievance. The Union appealed to arbitration.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>IV. PROVISIONS OF THE COLLECTIVE BARGAINING AGREEMENT</b><ftnote num="1"><para><italic>Italics</italic> are inserted in the quoted matter in this section IV and in the next, V, are not for emphasis but for ease of location for the reader. Italics used elsewhere are for emphasis added except when noted as being in the original. Any <italic>underscoring</italic> shown appears in the original.</para></ftnote></h4>
<p>Because the language of the other agreements is identical with respect to the issue on the merits, the Patrol Agreement (JX A, 2014-16 CBA) was referred to on the record exclusively. Unless noted otherwise that agreement is cited herein by any reference to the CBA. The provisions shown below indicate some of the terms considered or construed herein by the parties or by the Arbitrator. As to the merits:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE 32 HEALTH CARE &amp; INSURANCE</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 2</p>
<p class="continued">The parties agree that the current employee contributions for the health care offerings shall remain in effect until March 1, 2015; effective March 1, 2015 the employee shall pay <i>fourteen percent (14&percnt;) of the COBRA rate for the lowest deductible plan and ten percent (10&percnt;) of the COBRA rate for all other non-HSA offerings</i>, including Prescription Drug coverage, offered by the Employer through payroll deduction.</p>
<p class="continued">Effective March 1, 2016 the Employer shall offer at least one PPO Plan and the Employee shall pay <i>ten percent (10&percnt;) of the COBRA rate for the PPO Plan, including prescription drug coverage</i>, offered by the Employer through payroll deductions for the duration of this Agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">Also effective March 1, 2015, and throughout the term of this Agreement the City shall offer a &ldquo;High Deductible Health Plan&rdquo; (HDHP). The City shall make an annual contribution, by March 1, 2015, and throughout the term of this Agreement, of no less than &dollar;1,000 to the HSA account for those employees choosing a family coverage HSA health care option and &dollar;500 to the HSA account for those employees choosing a single coverage HSA health care option. Annually during the open enrollment period, employees will be permitted to cash out accrued sick time at 100&percnt; of the employees hourly wage in an amount equal to the maximum deductible of the HSA selected by the Employee less the City contribution. The City shall only increase the current maximum deductible for the HDHP in an amount as required by the I.R.S. However, should the deductible increase as contemplated herein, the City shall not be obligated to increase its annual contribution to employees set forth above.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 6</p>
<p class="continued">Health care insurance under other medical care entities and their plan may be offered to employees by the Employer. Employees shall have the option of enrolling in such plan on a voluntary basis. Members of the Bargaining Unit hired prior to April 1, 2014 are eligible to participate in <i>the City's &ldquo;Opt-Out&rdquo; program wherein employees may be eligible for a cash incentive to waive health coverage. Such &ldquo;Opt-Out&rdquo; amount shall be thirty percent (30&percnt;) of the Non-HSA option premium</i> (Family or Single) for which the employee would otherwise be eligible. Employees hired on or after April 1, 2014 of this Agreement shall be entitled to the amount provided for by City Ordinance for non-bargaining unit employees of the City</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">The parties put in evidence the predecessor agreements showing the language since 2006. In receding order they show the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE 32 HEALTH CARE &amp; INSURANCE (2012-2014 Patrol CBA CX 2)</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 2</p>
<p class="continued">The parties agree that effective March 1, 2012; The employee shall pay nine percent (9&percnt;) for the first year; twelve percent (12&percnt;) for the second year; and fourteen percent (14&percnt;) for the third year<i>, of the COBRA rate for plan A Medical and Prescription</i> through payroll deduction for the duration of this agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 3.</p>
<p class="continued">The parties agree that effective March 1, 2012; The employee shall pay five percent (5&percnt;) for the first year; eight percent (8&percnt;) for the second year; and ten percent (10&percnt;<i>) for the third year, of the COBRA rate for plan B Medical and Prescription</i> through payroll deduction for the duration of this agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 7</p>
<p class="continued">Health care insurance under other medical care entities and their plan may be offered to employees by the Employer. Employees shall have the option of enrolling in such plan on a voluntary basis.</p>
<p class="continued">Members of the Bargaining Unit are eligible to participate in the City's &ldquo;Opt-Out&rdquo; program wherein employees may be eligible for a cash incentive to waive health coverage. Such &ldquo;Opt-Out&rdquo; amount shall be thirty percent (30&percnt;) of the Plan A premium for the plan (Family or Single) for which the employee would otherwise be eligible.</p>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE 32 HEALTH CARE &amp; INSURANCE (2011-2014 Patrol CBA UX 2)</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 2</p>
<p class="continued">The employee shall pay <i>six percent (6&percnt;) of the premium for Plan A</i> of the Hospital/Medical/Prescription plan through payroll deduction for the. duration of this agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 3</p>
<p class="continued">The employee shall pay <i>two percent (2&percnt;) of the premium. for Plan B</i>. of the Hospital/Medical/Prescription plan through payroll deduction for the duration of this agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 7</p>
<p class="continued">Health care insurance under other medical care entities and their plan may be offered to employees by the Employer. Employees shall have the option of enrolling in such plan on a voluntary basis. Members of the Bargaining Unit are eligible to participate in the City's &ldquo;Opt-Out&rdquo; program wherein employees may be eligible for a cash incentive to waive health coverage. Such &ldquo;Opt-Out&rdquo; amount shall be thirty percent <i>(30&percnt;) of the Plan A premium</i> for the plan (Family or Single) for which the employee would otherwise be eligible.</p>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE 20 INSURANCE (2006-2009 Patrol CBA UX 1)</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 2.</p>
<p class="continued">The employee shall pay <i>five percent (5&percnt;) of the premium for Plan A</i> of the Hospital/Medical/Prescription plan through payroll deduction during plan year 2006-2007, and six percent (6&percnt;) for Plan A for plan year 2007-08 and for the duration of this agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 3.</p>
<p class="continued">The employee shall pay <i>three percent (3&percnt;) of the premium for Plan B</i> of the Hospital/Medical/Prescription plan through payroll deduction during plan year 2006-2007, and four percent (4&percnt;) for Plan B for plan year 2007-08 and for the duration of this agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 7</p>
<p class="continued">Health care insurance under other medical care entities and their plan may be offered to employees by the Employer. Employees shall have the option of enrolling in such plan on a voluntary basis. Members of the Bargaining Unit are eligible to participate in the City's &ldquo;Opt-Out&rdquo; program wherein employees may be eligible for a cash incentive to waive health coverage. Such &ldquo;Opt-Out&rdquo; amount shall be <i>thirty percent (30&percnt;) of the Plan A premium</i> for the plan (Family or Single) for which the employee would otherwise be eligible.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">As to the arbitration proceeding the following appear in the Sergeants Unit agreement:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE 42 ARBITRATION PROCEDURE (2014-2016 Sergeants CBA JX C)</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 2.</p>
<p class="continued">The arbitrator shall have no power or authority to add to, subtract from, or in any manner alter the specific terms of this Agreement, or to make any award requiring the commission of any act prohibited by law, or to make any award that itself is contrary to law or violates any of the terms and conditions of this Agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 3.</p>
<p class="continued">The arbitrator shall not decide more than one (1) grievance on the same hearing day or series of hearing days, except by the mutual written agreement of the parties.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 4.</p>
<p class="continued">The hearing(s) shall be conducted pursuant to the Rules of Voluntary Arbitration of the American Arbitration Association.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 5.</p>
<p class="continued">The fees and expenses of the arbitrator and the cost of the hearing room, if any, shall be borne by the party losing the grievance. All other expenses shall be borne by the party incurring them. Neither party shall be responsible for any of the expenses incurred by the other party.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Section 7. The arbitrator's decision and award will be in writing and delivered within thirty (30) days from the date the record is closed. The decision of the arbitrator shall be binding upon the parties.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>V. STIPULATIONS ON ARBITRABILITY</b></h4>
<p>The parties agreed that there a valid arbitration contract as between the parties, and that the grievance was processed in procedural compliance with it and is properly before the arbitrator for the consideration of the merits. The parties stipulated the language of the three current agreements as to Article 32 is identical and that the grievance filed in the Sergeant unit is sufficient to consider the same issue for all three units notwithstanding any limitation otherwise in the Agreements.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>VI. STATEMENT OF THE ISSUES FOR DECISION</b></h4>
<p>The parties agreed that the Arbitrator would decide the framing of the issues subject to their proposals. The issue is:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><i>Whether or not the City violated the Articles 32 of collective bargaining agreements when it modified the health care opt out amount in 2016 for all three units and if so, what should the remedy be?</i></p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>VII. FINDINGS OF FACT ON THE RECORD AS A WHOLE</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><small-cap>A. Background</small-cap></h4>
<p class="continued">The City of Twinsburg is located in the exurban area of Northeast Ohio between cities of Cleveland and Akron Ohio. Its Mayor is Ted Yates who was preceded by Kathleen A Procop. The Finance Director is Karen Howse who held the position since 2008. The Human Resource Director is currently Kolette Woloszynek, who was preceded by Clayton D. Morris.</p>
<p class="continued">The City employs approximately 400 persons of which half or slightly less than half are nonbargaining personnel. The bargaining unit personnel are represented by six employee organizations with six collective-bargaining agreements. Among those six are the three police units, one each for the patrol unit, sergeants unit and dispatch unit all represented by the OPBA. In addition on the record were mentioned a Fire unit, an AFSCME unit, and a Teamster unit.</p>
<p class="continued">The City has provided health care coverage for its employees over a long period. The plan year for the healthcare coverage begins March 1. The evidence presented at hearing related to the healthcare coverage of the past 10 years, 2006 through 2016 through Medical Mutual of Ohio. The healthcare coverage of the City had been reviewed by the City's insurance cost-containment committee consisting of one representative from each bargaining unit with an equal number of nonbargaining unit employees appointed by the City. It functions in an advisory capacity to evaluate the current plans and to explore options in healthcare coverage in order to maintain or reduce costs. The committee, working through the insurance broker employed by the City, begins by obtaining quotes from carriers starting in November. Before 2016 there is no effort to consider carriers other than Medical Mutual. When the costs and schedule of benefits for various plans are obtained and evaluated, they are passed on to the Human Resources and then to the Finance Director. When a selection is made, a general meeting of all the employees is held by the broker before March 1 in which all the available options for the plan year are shown. The employees are provided with a form to indicate their choices of plan including the opt out option.</p>
<p class="continued">Another feature of the healthcare program described by the Finance Director Howse was &ldquo;shared funding.&rdquo; She testified that some form of shared funding was present since she began her employment in 2008. Shared funding was a method by which the carrier, Medical Mutual, would receive healthcare claims from providers, adjudicate them and send a bill in an appropriate amount to the City for payment. The City would then make a check for payment on a claim by claim basis payable to Medical Mutual until the agreed maximum limit of the shared funding was reached. Medical Mutual in turn pays the providers. The effect of shared funding is to reduce the number of claims by having the City take on the risk of those claims before Medical Mutual begins funding them under its policy. The maximum amount of shared funding has varied since 2008 when it was &dollar;2000 single / &dollar;5000 family and later &dollar;3000 single / &dollar;6000 family. In 2016 shared funding limit is &dollar;5000 single / &dollar;10,000 family coverage. Shared funding is not an item negotiated with the unions but is a determination on pricing made between Medical Mutual and the City. The employees are aware of it only in the most general terms.</p>
<p class="continued">Until the 2014 plan year the City provided two plans referred to as Plans A and B. Both plans were preferred provider organizations (PPO) available as single and family policies. Both involve the a monthly shared cost between the employee and employer that varied over time. The chief difference between them is that the high-level plan, Plan A, had generally lower deductibles, coinsurance limits and co-pays which comes at a higher cost than Plan B. Another difference is the amount the employee contributed towards the monthly cost of the plan with Plan B being lower in consideration of its lower cost. In addition the City provides a prescription drug program that is identical for both plans and provides dental and vision coverage at no cost to the employees.</p>
<p class="continued">Effective March 1, 2014 the City instituted a &ldquo;high deductible health plan&rdquo; (HDHP). This plan funds the healthcare coverage of claims a through a health savings account (HSA) until high deductible is met and then the HDHP pays the claims. It is referred to on the record as the &ldquo;HSA Plan.&rdquo; The City continued to offer the two PPO plans, Plan A and Plan B. Such plans pay a different reimbursement to providers depending on whether the provider has a contract to be in the carrier's &ldquo;network&rdquo; or not. Beginning plan year 2016, March 1, 2016, only one PPO plan was offered alongside the HSA Plan.</p>
<h4 align="left"><small-cap>B. Bargaining History</small-cap></h4>
<p class="continued">Officer Ronald Fruscella had been a patrol officer for 20 years and served as an OPBA Director for the patrol unit from 1997 to 2015. He participated in the negotiations during that period. Sgt. Thomas Austin had been a patrol officer for the City since 1995 until he was promoted to sergeant in 2012. He participated in the patrol negotiations until his promotion. He participated in the sergeants' negotiations for the 2014 &ndash; 2016 agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">The 2006 &ndash; 2008 negotiations were conducted by the IBB method of the FMCS which is a collaborative or problem-solving style. As incentive to reduce participation in the City's health care and thereby reduce costs, during the negotiations the parties agreed to add an &ldquo;opt out&rdquo; provision. It became Article 20 Section 7. (In later agreements it was Article 32 Section 7 then Article 32 Section 6.) During the annual enrollment it allowed employees to voluntarily opt out of the City's program in exchange for receiving a monthly payment in the amount of 30&percnt; of the plan a premium either family or single whichever is applicable. At that time the employee monthly contribution was 5&percnt; of the premium for plan A (3&percnt; for plan B) for the first year, then 6&percnt; of the premium for plan A (4&percnt; for plan B) for the balance of the term of the agreement. These were in Article 32, Sections 2 and 3 respectively in that agreement and all others until 2014 &ndash; 16.</p>
<p class="continued">During the negotiations for the 2011 &ndash; 2014 agreement, taking place in 2010 at which Officer Fruscella was present, the opt out provision continued without change. At that time the employee monthly contribution continued at 6&percnt; of the premium for Plan A but plan B became 2&percnt;.</p>
<p class="continued">During the term of the 2011 &ndash; 2014 agreement, Officer Fruscella testified that in the winter of 2012 when the City was experiencing the effects of the Great Recession, he approached the City on behalf of the Union offering to consider cost-containment issues. One of the proposals made by the City was a revision of the employees' contribution to the healthcare program. The HR Director Clayton Morris on behalf of the City presented Officer Fruscella with a proposal that the employee monthly contribution for healthcare be increased from 6&percnt; of the premium for Plan A to 9&percnt; (2012) of the COBRA rate for the Medical Mutual Plan A, then 12&percnt; (2013) and then 14&percnt; (2014). Similarly the Plan B share paid by the employee would increase from 2&percnt; of the premium, to 5&percnt; of the COBRA rate, then 8&percnt;, then 10&percnt;.</p>
<p class="continued">In their discussions Officer Fruscella testified that he questioned the meaning of the COBRA rate. He said that it was explained to him it that it was the total actual cost of the health care program. He also testified that he requested that the opt out payment be made to employees be on the same basis. His testimony was that Mr. Morris agreed. Mr. Morris did not testify and was not present for the hearing. Sgt. Austin testified that he was present in those discussions when the COBRA rate was introduced to the agreement in 2012 and agreed with Officer Fruscella.</p>
<p class="continued">Finance Director Howse was also questioned about the changes made in 2012 on the method of calculating the employee share of the payment for the monthly cost of healthcare. She acknowledged the increase in the percentage and the change to the COBRA rate for the employee payments. With respect to the opt out amount she testified she was instructed by Mr. Morris that the employee share of the opt out would be calculated at 30&percnt; of the COBRA rate. Mr. Morris showed her a printout of an email that confirmed that. She testified that the words &ldquo;COBRA rate&rdquo; were not in the email but that the COBRA rate amount was stated there. Neither party put this email in evidence. Her testimony was that in response to HR Director Morris she said he should get the agreement in writing. Director Howse was not present during the testimony of Officer Fruscella . Although she had been present in some negotiations, she was not present in the 2012 discussions with the Union.</p>
<p class="continued">The City put in evidence an excerpt of the amended patrol unit agreement for 2012 to 2014 showing Article 32. CX 2. It was stipulated that the provisions of Article 32 were the same for the other two OPBA units. It was also stipulated that the effective dates which were not shown in the excerpt were from January 1, 2012 to March 31, 2014. Those effective dates are a variation from parties' pattern of duration clauses from January to December. It was made for the purpose of having the agreement on health care cover the plan years 2012, 2013 and 2014. Officer Fruscella testified he signed an agreement with HR Director Morris revising the healthcare provision. The agreement also reduced the wage increase to 0&percnt; for 2012 which does not appear in the CX 2 excerpt.</p>
<p class="continued">In the negotiations for the 2014 &ndash; 2016 agreement no provision was made for the 2014 healthcare plan year because the duration of the 2012 &ndash; 2014 modification had ended after the 2014 plan year began. In the 2014 &ndash; 2016 negotiations which were concluded in April 2015 several changes were made for the 2015 and 2016 plan years. In particular the HSA plan was written into the agreement and only one PPO plan was offered. The employee monthly contribution for healthcare was stated in Article 32 Section 2 for all plans. It decreased for Plan A in 2015 from 14&percnt; of the COBRA rate to 10&percnt; . On the other hand for 2015 the Plan B share paid by the employee increased from 8&percnt;of the COBRA rate to 14&percnt; . In 2016 Plan B ceased and the HSA plan became the only alternative to the PPO form of policy. The monthly contribution was not applicable to the HSA Plan due to its different type of funding.</p>
<p class="continued">The opt out provision for 2014 &ndash; 16 CBA became Article 32 Section 6. Other changes were made. The employees hired beginning in the term of the agreement were excluded from the opt out formula in favor of the opt out amount that is provided under the codified City ordinances for all other employees. That amount was a flat sum of &dollar;250 per month. The opt out for the employees hired before the 2014 &ndash; 16 agreement remained at 30&percnt; of the &ldquo;non-HSA option premium (Single or Family) for which the employee would otherwise be eligible.&rdquo; Officer Fruscella and Sgt. Austin testified that there were no other discussions about how the opt out was calculated for incumbent employees.</p>
<p class="continued">Sgt. Austin saw the COBRA rate language when it was presented in the sergeants negotiations in 2015 for the 2014&ndash;16 agreement. He recognized that it the came from the interim 2012 agreement between Officer Fruscella and Director Morris. He understood that the COBRA rate was the total cost of healthcare, the price that an employee would have to pay if he bought the coverage directly from Medical Mutual &ldquo;off the street.&rdquo; The sergeants' negotiations took place after those of the patrol unit and the agreement was signed in June 2015 to be retroactive.</p>
<p class="continued">Finance Director Howse had experience with healthcare in her prior employment as well. She agreed that the COBRA rate was the &ldquo;off the street&rdquo; price. The words &ldquo;fat cost&rdquo; was also used in her testimony. She testified it was used under the COBRA statute as the sum charged to former employees who wish to continue to purchase coverage from the City. Since 2008 the City had never used that rate to collect premium payments from former employees because none had chosen to purchase COBRA coverage. The formal definition used by Director Howse was that the COBRA rate was &ldquo;the full liability of the City for the type of plan that is being provided including administrative charges.&rdquo; It was not published by the carrier; she received it from the broker. Without the City's shared funding arrangement, Director Howse testified the difference between the premium and the COBRA rate would probably only be the 2&percnt; administrative fee.</p>
<p class="continued">Finance Director Howse discussed COBRA rates in connection with the shared funding feature of the City's plans. She explained that the monthly charge by Medical Mutual per employee did not include the claims that were administered through the shared funding procedure. Nonetheless the administration of the shared funding feature was part of the charges that were included in the Medical Mutual billing. Because the shared funding allows the City to pay claims direct, only the claims included by Medical Mutual in the monthly invoiced charges were those that Medical Mutual paid plus its administrative costs. The administrative costs included the cost to adjudicate both the policy claims and the self funded claims. The difference between the 2016 monthly invoice amounts from Medical Mutual (&dollar;1, 944.15) and the COBRA rate (&dollar;2,452.59) is &dollar;508.44. Since the COBRA rate was meant to represent the cost of the full program, it included the value of the shared funding feature and possibly administrative costs in that amount.</p>
<p class="continued">Employees receiving the opt out payment were not participants who could have their initial claims presented through the shared funding with medical mutual.</p>
<h4 align="left"><small-cap>C. The Grieved Event: 2016</small-cap></h4>
<p class="continued">Officer Fruscella had never used the opt out provision. Sgt. Austen had used the opt out provision from time to time more frequently since his wife participated in the State Highway Patrol healthcare program. Every year at the City's healthcare meeting when the options were presented to all the employees, he had received a form identifying in the options on which he could make a selection. The forms and evidence for 2014 and 2015 show Plan A, Plan B and an HSA plan. The form for 2016 showed only &ldquo;PPO Plan&rdquo; and &ldquo;HSA Plan.&rdquo; The same form is used each year for all City employees both nonbargaining and bargaining unit. Sgt. Austin used these forms to opt out of the healthcare program for both the plan years 2014 and 2015.</p>
<p class="continued">All the forms identified the employee's cost per plan and the type of plan with the HSA plan being &dollar;0. In 2014 and 2015 the monthly rates of the employee cost showed the employer's full monthly cost and the employee's cost after the applicable percentage from the agreement was applied. For example 2014 showed Plan A: Family &dollar;2, 372.55; Employee Cost &dollar;332.16, which is 14&percnt;. (UX 6) The percentage was not stated but when calculated is the same as provided in the 2012 &ndash; 2014 modification agreement. Sgt. Austen testified that the figure used for the employer cost on the forms was not identified on the form and was not explained at any of the meetings. It was simply understood to be the cost of the plan on a monthly basis for which the employee pays a monthly percentage. Finance Director Howse explained that, although not identified on the forms, the stated amount was the COBRA rate. The form concluded with identifying the coverage details and a list of check boxes for the employee's choice of plan including the opt out. The amount to be paid for the opt out was not stated or defined anywhere on the form.</p>
<p class="continued">The last form for healthcare options under the 2012 &ndash; 14 modified agreement is in evidence. The form for the prior year under that agreement is not in evidence and will be assumed to be similar otherwise it would have been offered.</p>
<p class="continued">The same format was used in the 2015 enrollment forms except that the effects of the health insurance opt out was explained in a text legend concerning taxes and the reenrollment procedure. As in the prior years, the employee's monthly contribution was as a stated number without an explanation or the percentage or the basis. (UX 7) This was the first form for healthcare options under the 2014 &ndash; 16 agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">For the 2016 plan year the City chose a different broker. The healthcare committee began it is work as usual in the fall but this time it looked to other carriers. The result was that for the 2016 Plan year Medical Mutual was retained with a PPO Plan and HSA Plan.</p>
<p class="continued">The annual healthcare meeting for the 2016 plan year took place in February 2016 with the options required to be returned by March 1. The form changed in so far as it identified the employees' cost next to the employer's monthly figure as &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; for the first time. (UX 3) For example the PPO plan shows under &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; &dollar;2,452.59 and under &ldquo;Employee cost,&rdquo; &dollar;245.26 which is 10&percnt; of the COBRA figure. The percentage is not stated but the basis on which it is applied was identified as the COBRA rates. The rest of the form is similar to past ones. It refers to dental and vision coverage followed by a group of check boxes for the employee's selection of healthcare plan or the opt out choices. The text is different from 2015 legend. It addresses the opt out which states that the employee understands that &ldquo;I will receive monthly payments in lieu of coverage which is subject to all applicable taxes.&rdquo; The balance of the text is similar to the past legends that referred to the requirement of having alternative coverage and reenrollment. The basis for the opt out and the percentage are not stated and neither is the amount. This was the second form for healthcare options under the 2014 &ndash; 16 agreement.</p>
<p class="continued">Sgt. Austen had elected the opt out for the plan years 2014, 2015 and 2016. The timecard entries for his payroll from January 2015 through July 2016 (UX 4) show the detail of his by a weekly payroll in terms of regular hours, paid time off, comp and premium time all shown in hours with hourly rate, effective rate, and gross earnings. In the detail for the weekly payroll is included the line item, &ldquo;opt out pay.&rdquo; For the 2014 plan year Sgt. Austen's monthly opt out pay was &dollar;711.76 shown in the February 27, 2015 and March 13, 2015 payrolls. Beginning with the new plan year the amount increased to &dollar;714.79 which was paid beginning in the payroll of April 24, 2015 through the end of the plan year. In comparison to the Health Insurance Option Forms for the respective plan years, these amounts are three times the employee cost for the high-level plan in each case. The employee costs in that period were 10&percnt; of the employer's cost listed on the Health Insurance Option Form making the employee's opt out pay 30&percnt; of the monthly employer figure. Although not stated on the form, the employer figure is the employer's COBRA rate. Although not stated on the form the employee's opt out cost was as agreed in 2012 a percentage of the COBRA rate that was three times the employee's monthly cost.</p>
<p class="continued">Sgt. Austen enrolled in the opt out for the plan year 2016. The timecard entries show beginning with the payroll of April 8, 2016 that the opt out pay was &dollar;583.25 which continued through date of hearing. The timecard entries in evidence and received by the Union from the City (UX 4) show an identical pattern with respect to the timecard entries for Patrol Officer Jeffrey Hayes and Dispatcher Chris Fried both of whom had opted out during this same period under their respective agreements.</p>
<p class="continued">In February 2016 Finance Director Howse was participating in collective bargaining negotiations for the first time in the City beyond the occasional visit such as in 2008 with the Fire Department. In this case she was meeting with the AFSCME bargaining unit along with other members of the City team including the Law Director. In a discussion about the opt out, the Law Director stated that the police department paid 30&percnt; of the premium charged by Medical Mutual. Director Howse interjected that the amount paid was 30&percnt; of the COBRA rate. Afterwards Director Howse met with the Law Director and now Mayor Yates to study the agreements. They found &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; appeared In Article 32 Section 2 for the employee monthly payments and &ldquo;premium&rdquo; appeared in the Article 32 Section 6 for the opt out pay.</p>
<p class="continued">Finance Director Howse explained that the Medical Mutual premium appears on a monthly statement from the carrier which identifies employees by a reference number, coverage type (medical/drug), contract(family/single), and amount due for each. Each monthly statement also makes adjustments for additions and cancellations. The monthly amounts due are stated per employee for 2016 as family &dollar;1944.15 per employee and single, &dollar;756.43 per employee. (CX 1) After consulting with the Law Director and the Mayor, Finance Director Howse prepared a letter to be sent individually to all employees in the opt out program. It identified the City's premium on which the contractual 30&percnt; would be applied as the amount stated in Medical Mutual monthly invoices. It read as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Dear Tom Austin,</p>
<p class="continued">Following up on our open enrollment in March, we reviewed each employee's healthcare plan selection, dependents, costs, and opt-out amounts. During this audit, it was discovered that the City has been overpaying your opt-out amount in previous plan years per the language in the bargaining agreement, Article 32, Section 6 which says:</p>
<p class="continued"><i>&ldquo;Such &ldquo;Opt-Out&rdquo; amount shall be thirty percent (30&percnt;) of the Non-HSA option premium (Family or Single) for which the employee would otherwise be eligible.&rdquo;</i></p>
<p class="continued">The City's premium for Non-HSA plan for 2016 is &dollar;194.15. Therefore, going forward your monthly opt-out amount will be &dollar;583.25. Payment will be received the first pay of each month. At this time, the City is reviewing the legal obligation to recover the overpayment you have received in previous plan years. We will get back to you once we've fully investigated our fiduciary responsibility to recoup these public funds.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Finance Director Howse testified that the change announced in the letter was made because of the City's belief that the use of the COBRA rate since 2012 for the opt out pay had been a mistake. It changed as a result of the email and the discussion with Human Resource Director Morris about the discussions with the Union in 2012. Prior to that time, Finance Director Howse had used the monthly billing amount from Medical Mutual for both the employee monthly contribution and the opt out payments. In 2016 she reverted to that formula for the opt out payment after the discussions with the rest of the administration.</p>
<p class="continued">Although the letter concluded with the a statement that a recoupment of past overpayments of the opt out amount might be necessary, no action had been taken with respect to that before the hearing.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>VIII. POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><small-cap>A. The Union's Position</small-cap></h4>
<h4 align="left"><i>1. Intent of the Parties.</i></h4>
<p class="continued">The issue is whether the employer violated the CBA when it unilaterally modified the administration of the Employee Opt-Out payment. The Union asserts the parties had a clear and uncontroverted understanding of the application of the opt-out language of Article 32 of the three CBAs.</p>
<p class="continued">Prior to 2012 was the City paid the monthly &ldquo;premium&rdquo; rate as that term was defined by the parties which was the monthly rate the City paid to the insurer per employee. In addition the City paid claims under the shared funding arrangement with the carrier.</p>
<p class="continued">The language that appeared in the relevant CBAs previous to 2012 specified that the Employee Contribution was based on the Plan A or Plan B &ldquo;premium&rdquo; but the Employee Opt-Out was calculated based on the Plan A &ldquo;premium.&rdquo; According to Officer Frusella and Howse, Plan A constituted the highest cost plan to the City. The City had agreed to calculate the Employee Opt-Out based on the most expensive plan. According to Officer Frusella, the Employee Opt-Out was a win-win. The City was unburdened from highest monthly charge in addition to noy having to pay claims under shared funding.</p>
<p class="continued">Officer Frusella testified that he negotiated the healthcare provision for the 2012-2014 CBA.The Union agreed to calculate the Employee Contribution based on the higher &ldquo;COBRA rate.&rdquo; The COBRA rate constituted the true cost for the City of the healthcare plan for each employee plus the administrative costs and fees. Thereby the Union agreed to pay for some of the cost of the shared funding. According to Officer Frusella, the parties specifically agreed that since the Employee Contribution was based on the COBRA rate, the Employee Opt-Out would also be based on the COBRA rate. Thus to be consistent with the previous win-win scenario, the Employee Opt-Out was based on the highest figure. Officer Frusella's testimony was uncontroverted.</p>
<p class="continued">In the 2012-2014 CBAs (EX 2) the language of the Employee Healthcare Contribution was modified to include the &ldquo;COBRA rate.&rdquo; Although Article 32, Section 6 on the opt out was not modified, the City's actions confirmed the parties understanding. Director Howse testified that, in 2012, she received an email from the Human Resources Director stating the amount calculated for the Employee Healthcare Contribution and the Employee Opt-Out. The Employee Opt-Out was specified at thirty percent (30&percnt;) of the COBRA rate. Director Howse confirmed that prior to March 2016, the Employee Opt-Out payment under all the relevant CBAs was calculated at thirty percent (30&percnt;) of the COBRA rate. This was based on a clear meeting of the minds.</p>
<p class="continued">Officer Frusella and Sgt. Austin testified the parties negotiated the language related to the Employee Opt-Out in the 2014-2016 CBA to reflect the elimination of the &ldquo;Plan A&rdquo; option and substituted the term &ldquo;Non-HSA option.&rdquo; (JX A, B and C). The Employee Opt-Out was still calculated based on the highest cost plan, the &ldquo;Non-HSA option.&rdquo; The parties also agreed to eliminate the Employee Opt-Out for employees hired after April 1, 2014. (Id.). There was no discussion about modifying the calculation of the Employee Opt-Out amount based on the post-shared funding cost. Therefore, there was no agreement to modify the mutual understanding of the term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; within Section 6.</p>
<p class="continued">The 2014 Health Insurance Plan Option sheet specified the &ldquo;Monthly Rates&rdquo; that the Employee Contribution and the Employee Opt-Out were based on.(UX 6.). These were the COBRA Rates. The City applied the contribution and opt-out calculations to the same figure.(UX 4). The 2015 Health Insurance Plan Option sheet specified the &ldquo;Employee cost.&rdquo; (UX 7). The City applied the contribution and opt-out calculations to the same figure. (UX 4).</p>
<p class="continued">Therefore, it is uncontroverted that the mutual understanding of the parties during the term of the existing CBAs, based on a clear meeting of the minds, was that the terms &ldquo;monthly rate,&rdquo; &ldquo;COBRA rate&rdquo; and &ldquo;Non-HSA option premium&rdquo; all meant the same figure.</p>
<p class="continued">The 2016 Health Insurance Plan Option sheet specified the &ldquo;COBRA Rate&rdquo; for the first time. Employees contributed ten percent (10&percnt;) of the monthly COBRA cost but employees who opted out of coverage for 2016 received 30&percnt; of the monthly charges of the carrier to the City per employee not 30&percnt; of the COBRA rates. The City unilaterally decided beginning in March 2016, and in contravention of the parties agreement, to misinterpret the language. The City decided it was no longer going to abide by the parties' mutual intent and agreement. As a result, the City's actions constitute a violation of the relevant CBAs.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>2. The Employer's Conduct</i></h4>
<p class="continued">Assuming the Arbitrator finds the term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; ambiguous, the conduct of the City, the bargaining history, the past practice, the reasonable interpretation of the language and other standard factors in interpreting the ambiguous language all support the Union's position.<ftnote num="2"><para>In deciding whether more than one reasonable interpretation renders the language ambiguous, the arbitrator determines whether each proposed interpretation is reasonable. <italic>Clark v. Hartley</italic> (1982), 7 Ohio App. 3d 147, 150. If the parties propose more than one reasonable interpretation, arbitrators seek an interpretation that reflects the intent of the parties from sources including the language used, contract negotiations, bargaining history and past practice. <small-cap>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, <italic>How Arbitration Works</italic></small-cap>, 5thEd. 1997, p. 479.</para></ftnote> Unquestionably custom and past practice constitutes one of the most significant factors in labor-management arbitration.<ftnote num="3"><para>Jaffe, Ira, 1-10 <small-cap>Labor and Employment Arbitration</small-cap> &sect;10.02, (2011, Matthew Bender &amp; Company, Inc.).</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">However, the term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; in this context can mean many options. In regard to this case, the dictionary definition of &ldquo;premium&rdquo; is &ldquo;The price of insurance; the amount paid for insurance; a price that is higher than the regular price.&rdquo; <small-cap>Mirriam-Webster Learner's Dictionary</small-cap>, 2016. The City focuses on the monthly bill received from the insurance company for each employee. (EX. 1). The parties themselves have defined &ldquo;Non-HSA option premium&rdquo; to have the same meaning as the &ldquo;monthly rate&rdquo; or &ldquo;COBRA rate.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">Premium can also mean the total price of insurance per employee, which in this case can also mean the monthly cost plus the &dollar;10,000 shared funding amount for family coverage. If defined in that manner, the annual cost to the City for coverage would equal &dollar;10,000 (shared funding) plus &dollar;23,329.80 (&dollar;1,944.15 x 12). The total amount paid for insurance by the City would equal &dollar;33,329.80. That would also be consistent with the dictionary definition. The Employee Opt-Out would equate to &dollar;833.25 per month for a family plan. Would the City prefer that the Union unilaterally modify the parties interpretation to mean this higher amount?</p>
<p class="continued">Since 2012, the parties mutual definition as reflected in the City's own conduct and practice without interruption, deviation or modification was for the opt out that &ldquo;premium&rdquo; meant &ldquo;COBRA rates.&rdquo; From 2008 until the present, the City had a shared funding program with the health insurer. The City utilized the shared funding arrangement in 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015 and 2016. This was not a new program or a new method of calculating the premium beginning in 2016. This arrangement was in effect when the City negotiated the 2012 agreement. This remained true in 2013 and when the parties negotiated the CBAs for the three units for 2014, 2015 and 2016.</p>
<p class="continued">Director Howse confirmed that prior to March 2016, the Employee Opt-Out payment under the CBAs was thirty percent (30&percnt;) of COBRA rate. All the payroll records reflect the same payment across the patrol, dispatch and sergeants CBAs confirm the City had applied the intent of the parties every year since 2012, consistently across all units and based on the same figure from year-to-year. All the City's conduct and the evidence demonstrates exactly the parties understanding of how the Employee Opt-Out would be and has been calculated. For the City to now argue that they were unaware of the language or how the long-standing practice had effected the monthly cost is disingenuous.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>3. Estoppel</i></h4>
<p class="continued">Before March 1, 2016 employees selected their plan option or elected to opt-out of coverage, signed the sheet and returned it to the City prior for coverage beginning March 1. The Employee could not re-enroll in coverage unless a qualifying event occurred. (UX 5). The City's notification that its application of the formula would change came March 25, after the open enrollment period. The employees were precluded from selecting any other options. The employees relied on the parties' agreement, past practice and the City's representations on the sheets in forming their decisions. The City's actions in unilaterally modifying the calculation resulted in a detrimental effect on the employees who could not un-ring the bell. Thus, the City should be precluded from modifying the parties agreement after the open enrollment period.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>4. Remedy</i></h4>
<p class="continued">For all the forgoing reasons, the Union requests that the Arbitrator sustain the grievance and find the City violated the relevant CBAs, the parties mutual agreement and the long-standing practice. The OPBA requests that the Arbitrator sustain the grievance and award compensatory damages<ftnote num="4"><para>The compensatory damages for the period from March 2016 through the date of the Arbitrator's Award is the <quote>make whole</quote> remedy to place the grievant where the employee would have been but for the contractual violation. <quote>Remedies,</quote> 2-39 <small-cap>Labor and Employment Arbitration</small-cap> &sect;39.03 (Greenbaum, Marcia, Matthew Bender &amp; Company, Inc., 2008).</para></ftnote> consistent with the Arbitrator's Award and that the City be ordered to immediately cease and desist from future violations. Employees who elected to Opt-Out of healthcare coverage beginning in March 2016 should have received, pursuant to the mutual agreement of the parties, an amount of &dollar;286.10 for single coverage and &dollar;735.77 for family coverage. Through August 2016, employees who opted-out of coverage were denied &dollar;175.02 for single eligible employees and &dollar;1,095.12 for family eligible employees.</p>
<h4 align="left"><small-cap>B. The City's Position</small-cap></h4>
<p class="continued">The Union and the City negotiated an amendment to the language regarding Article 32 as reflected in 2012-2014 CBA (CX 2). For the first time, the CBA distinguished between using the COBRA rate for calculation of employee contributions (Sections 2 and 3) and continuing to use the premium rate for the calculation of employee's opting out (Section 7). Prior to that change, the employee's contribution to his/her health insurance cost and the &ldquo;opt-out&rdquo; provision were both calculated off the per employee &ldquo;premium&rdquo; charged monthly by the carrier. The City acknowledges that it began paying the &ldquo;opt-out employees&rdquo; at the higher COBRA rate by error in 2012 after Article 32 of the CBA changed by making reference to the COBRA rate in Section 2. (CX 2) The City's Finance Department discovered this error in 2016 and took corrective measures.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union argues that past practice should control and the City should be obligated to continue to pay the much higher opt-out rate irrespective of the language in the CBA. Past practice should not control when the sole reason for the past practice was mistake. The language of the contract is clear. A miscalculation should not entitle a group of employees to a significant windfall.</p>
<p class="continued">To be binding on parties to a collective bargaining agreement (CBA), a past practice must be:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="paren" bind-to="left-right">
<li><p>unequivocal,</p></li>
<li><p>clearly enunciated, and</p></li>
<li><p>followed for a reasonable period of time as a fixed, and established practice accepted by both parties.<ftnote num="5"><para><italic>Association of Cleveland Fire Fighters, Local 93 v. City of Cleveland</italic>, 793 N.E.2d 484 (2003).</para></ftnote></p></li></ol>
<p class="continued">In most cases that claim &ldquo;past practice&rdquo; the CBA was silent as to the issue and it was therefore reasonable for the arbitrator to look at past practice to fill the gap. Here the CBA is not silent but is very clear that the employee who elects to opt-out of the City's health insurance shall be entitled to &ldquo;30&percnt; of the Non-HSA option premium.&rdquo; Payment of any different amount is an error that differs from the clear and unambiguous terms of the CBA.</p>
<p class="continued">The concept of opt-out language is that it should be mutually beneficial to the parties. The employee benefits by receiving additional compensation for not accepting the benefit of health insurance and the employer benefits by not having to pay the premium for the health insurance not accepted by the employee. Logic would dictate that the City should only be obligated to compensate the employee the percentage of the premium the City saved by not having that employee on its group health care. The only amount the City saved for each employee that opts out is &dollar;1,944.15 (family) and &dollar;756.43 (single). The Union wants to be compensated at the much higher COBRA rate which factors in the City's shared funding. To award any amount higher than the premium inappropriately benefits the employee for the City's willingness to assume &dollar;10,000.00 of risk through shared funding. The amount of money the City expends for any given employee annually through shared funding differs greatly per employee and from year to year. To make any award on such a variable figure is speculative and contrary to the plain language of the CBA.</p>
<p class="continued">The City would respectively request the grievance be denied. Furthermore, the City would request a finding that since April 2012 Article 32 provide that the employees who opt out are only entitled to 30&percnt; of the premium that the City pays for that employee's coverage not the COBRA rate. Finally, the City has an obligation to the taxpayers to seek to recoup the money paid out in error and contrary to the terms of the contract.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>IX. DISCUSSION AND DECISION</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><small-cap>A. Standards for Contract Interpretation</small-cap></h4>
<p>The party alleging breach on an issue bears the burden of proof by a preponderance of the evidence, which is, that its reading is the more probable.<ftnote num="6"><para><italic>Certainteed Corp</italic>., 88 LA 995, 998 (Nicholas, 1987); <italic>Shepard Niles Inc.</italic>, 115 LA 1447, 1451 (Fullmer, 2000); <italic>City of Jackson</italic>, 121 LA 1582, (McDonald, 2005).</para></ftnote> It must persuade the Arbitrator that the position it has taken is correct and consistent with the language of the Agreement.<ftnote num="7"><para><italic>Avaya, Inc</italic>., 05-2 ARB Par. 3264 (CCH) at p. 4697-4698. See also <italic>Dresser Industries</italic>, 96 LA 1063 (Nicholas, 1991) and <italic>Gates Robert Co.</italic> 96 LA 445 (Sergeant, 1991).</para></ftnote></p>
<p>The primary duty of the Arbitrator is to determine and carry out the mutual intent of the parties.<ftnote num="8"><para>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, <italic>How Arbitration Works</italic> (5th Ed.), at p. 471 and <italic>L &amp; S Products</italic>, 97 LA 582 (1990.)</para></ftnote> The mutual intent must be first be drawn from the language itself. Unambiguous language must be given its plain meaning.<ftnote num="9"><para><italic>National Service</italic>, 95 LA 829 (Abrams, 1990) <italic>Potlach Corp</italic>., 95 LA 737 (Goodstein, 1990) and <italic>Metro Transit Authority</italic>, 94 LA 349 (Richard, 1990). Also: <italic>North Carolina Association of Educators</italic>, 125 LA 114 (Pritzker, 2008); <italic>US Food Service</italic>, 124 LA 114 (Fitzsimmons, 2008).</para></ftnote> A writing is unambiguous where the meaning can be determined the without more than the facts and the language.<ftnote num="10"><para><italic>Community Memorial Hospital</italic>, 95 LA 581 (1990).</para></ftnote> Plain meaning of contract language augmented by dictionary definitions is often sufficient to resolve interpretation issues. Initially the interpretation of a writing should be possible without resorting to any extrinsic evidence, i.e. any source other than the four corners of the Agreement.<ftnote num="11"><para>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, <italic>How Arbitration Works</italic> (6<superscript>th</superscript> Ed. 2003), Sec. 9.2, <quote>Ambiguity and Exclusion of Extrinsic Evidence</quote> 434-35 and cases cited therein particularly <italic>Primeline Industries, Inc.</italic>, 88LA 700 (1986).</para></ftnote></p>
<p>If the disputed contract language is reasonably susceptible to more than one meaning, the language may be considered ambiguous and the Arbitrator may rely on other interpretative aids such as bargaining history or past practice of the parties.<ftnote num="12"><para><italic>Inland Empire Paper Company</italic>, 88 LA 1096 (Levak 1986). See Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, <italic>How Arbitration Works</italic>, (6th ed. 2003) at p. 434.</para></ftnote> To sum up:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;The arbitrator will declare an agreement to be clear and unambiguous where he is able to determine its meaning without any other guide at than a knowledge of the simple facts on which, from the nature of the language, in general, it is meaning depends. Where, however, the simple facts allow both sides to advance plausible contentions for conflicting interpretations, the arbitrator will declare the language to be unenforceable, and will make reference to precontract bargaining history, past practice and other applicable rules of construction in order to arrive at the true meaning of the disputed provision.&rdquo;<ftnote num="13"><para><italic>Keego Harbor, Michigan, Police Department</italic> 114 LA 859, 863, (Roumell, Jr. 2000) quoting <italic>Inland Empire Paper Company</italic> 88 LA 1096, 1102 (Levak, 1987). See <small-cap>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, <italic>How Arbitration Works</italic></small-cap>, (6th ed. 2003) at p. 434.</para></ftnote></p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Ambiguity must appear to the interpreter <i>from the facts and the contract term</i>. Ambiguity is <i>patent</i> if it arises from the document alone. That is, the term has different meanings to each party. If it arises out of the circumstances to which the document applies, then it is a <i>latent</i> ambiguity.<ftnote num="14"><para><quote>Latent ambiguity</quote> is Judge Posner's term for a <quote>mutual misunderstanding.</quote> See discussion by Chief Judge Posner in <italic>Colfax Envelope Corp v Graphic Communications, Local &num;458-3M</italic>, 20 F.3d 750, 145 LRRM 2974 (7<superscript>th</superscript> Circuit 1994) quoted at length in ELKOURI &amp; ELKOURI, 6<superscript>th</superscript> Ed. Interpreting Contract Language, pp 429-430. Some arbitrators analogize ambiguity to <quote>filling the gaps</quote> in contract language. Actually the <quote>gap</quote> between the intent and the words is patent ambiguity, and the <quote>gap</quote> between the words and facts to which they apply is latent ambiguity.</para></ftnote> In this case the parties agree that the terms appear to each of them to be clear but in fact are not when they come to be applied to the facts after the contract is agreed.</p>
<h4 align="left"><small-cap>B. Did the City violate Article 32 of the Collective Bargaining Agreements when it Modified the Health Care Opt out Amount for Incumbent Employees in 2016?</small-cap></h4>
<p>The contract provides two formulas relating to health care payments. One is the formula for the employees' payment for coverage the other is the formula for the Employer's payment to employees to waive coverage. The employee's contribution is a percentage of the &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; and the Employer's opt out payment to employees is a percentage of &ldquo;premium.&rdquo; Since 2012, although the two sections used two different words, they were administered as if the terms were identical. Both formulas were applied to the &ldquo;COBRA rates.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Union argues that it is simply a matter of past practice to explain an ambiguity. The Employer made its payments for years as if the terms were identical and then changed its mind. The Employer sees it as simply the plain reading of a contract which is not ambiguous. There are two words that have two different meanings hence two different formulas. That is, past practice cannot alter unambiguous language.</p>
<p>However in this case there is an ambiguity. It is a latent ambiguity. In 2012 the employee contribution uses the words &ldquo;COBRA rate&rdquo; and the employee opt out payment uses the word &ldquo;premium.&rdquo; However it is uncontroverted that both calculations were administered the same way. The uncontroverted mutual intent of the parties is supposed to be apparent from the words they use in the Agreement. Hence a latent ambiguity arises <i>from the facts and the contract term</i>.</p>
<p>The City claims it is a mistake but that rests on no evidence other than the words on paper. The Union says the ambiguity was clarified by the City's conduct. The Union has the evidence from both parties in support of its position. The Employer does not. The Union's reading of the contract is more probably correct.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>1. Patent Ambiguity pre 2012</i></h4>
<p>The focus of the grievance is whether the term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; in the opt out provision became ambiguous as a result of the negotiations of 2012. Did a latent ambiguity arise from the application of the contract to the facts in evidence after 2012? The Employer is comfortable that the monthly amount charged per employee per month in the carrier invoice should constitute meaning of the &ldquo;premium&rdquo; as used in the CBA's since 2012 just as it did beforehand. However, the term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; was also ambiguous before 2012.</p>
<p>The CBA term, &ldquo;premium&rdquo; of Article 32 Sections 2,3 and 7 was not defined anywhere in the contract before or after 2012. It was simply used in the form of &ldquo;premium for plan A (or B).&rdquo; Every conceivable dictionary defines it as a consideration for a policy of insurance often paid periodically in installments usually monthly.<ftnote num="15"><para>West's Encyclopedia of American Law, edition 2. Copyright 2008 The Gale Group, Inc.; <quote>premium.</quote> Merriam-Webster.com. Merriam-Webster, n.d. Web. 23 Aug. 2016; <quote>premium</quote>. Dictionary.com Unabridged. Random House, Inc. 23 Aug. 2016. &lt;Dictionary.com http://www.dictionary.com/browse/premium&gt;; <quote>premium</quote>. Collins English Dictionary - Complete &amp; Unabridged 10th Edition. HarperCollins Publishers. 23 Aug. 2016. &lt;Dictionary.com http://www.dictionary.com/browse/premium&gt;</para></ftnote> The periodicity of the payment was not defined in the CBA. It could have been the monthly invoice, i.e. the consideration for the policy benefits alone, or 1/12 of total annual costs (i.e. policy plus shared funding), or an annual amount or even something else.</p>
<p>The invoice for the monthly charges from the carrier uses the term &ldquo;Amounts Due&rdquo; which are listed per employee. The term &ldquo;Premium&rdquo; appears in only one place, at the bottom of the form. It is part of an apparent running tab or reconciliation chart that begins with &ldquo;Previous Balance Total,&rdquo; then &ldquo;Current Premium&rdquo; and &ldquo;Pay This Amount.&rdquo; From its format alone it is obvious that to the carrier the &ldquo;premium&rdquo; as an annual running figure on which monthly installments are made as in &ldquo;Pay this Amount.&rdquo; In the example given it was blank. This extraneous evidence does not assist in defining the CBA term&rdquo;premium.&rdquo; It lists the monthly amounts charged per employee but uses the technical term in an unclear manner.</p>
<p>Viewed from the dictionary definition standpoint (&ldquo;total consideration&rdquo;), before 2012 the total of all the monthly installments per employee was not the&rdquo;premium&rdquo; paid by the City for the healthcare insurance. The monthly amount charged by the carrier does not pay for the benefits provided through the self funding program even though that arrangement had been a feature of the City's healthcare since at least 2008.</p>
<p>Director Howse explained the shared funding program. The City is in effect self insuring the claims between the employee's out-of-pocket costs (coinsurance, co-pay, deductibles) and the indemnities offered by the carrier. The carrier adjudicates the claims under its indemnity formulas, pays the providers, and then bills the City for reimbursement. By self insuring part of the claims the City is piggy backing on the carrier's benefit schedule and its arrangements with the providers. The Employer pays periodic invoices to the carrier throughout the year for the cost of claims under this shared funding program <i>in addition</i> to the monthly invoices. While the Employer takes the risk, currently of an additional &dollar;10,000 in claims, for each employee, it does not endure that level experience in the vast number of cases each year. Some budgeted or actuarial factor to account for that exposure could be computed. The CBA term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; could have been interpreted to take that into account before 2012. In fact it partially did so.</p>
<p>The monthly charge by the carrier was also explained in the testimony of Director Howse in response to the Arbitrator's questions. She said it includes the indemnities paid for the claims by the carrier under its policy and the cost of the administration of those claims <i>plus</i> the cost of administration of the claims processed through the shared funding arrangement.<ftnote num="16"><para>The Arbitrator's questions probed whether the carrier's monthly charges might also include other charges such as retention fees, catastrophic or stop loss insurance coverage, and reinsurance. Director Howse was only aware of generally of administrative fees and unaware of anything more specific such as these charges.</para></ftnote> Although before 2012 employees were contributing monthly towards &ldquo;premium&rdquo; as stated in the CBA, they were not contributing towards the value of the self funded benefits. However they did contribute toward the administration of the shared funded benefits. This interpretation of &ldquo;premium&rdquo; made by the City to be the monthly invoice amount was a savings to them. They paid only for the administration of the self funded portion not for the self funded claims. On the other hand the employee opt out payment calculated by the City compensated the opt out employee for the administrative fee for the self funded portion of the policy and did not compensate the employee for the loss of the value of the self funded benefits themselves. There is no rational consistency to that aside from a mutual intent of the parties that the two groups of employees be treated alike.</p>
<p>The carrier's invoice offers no instruction on what the term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; means in the collective bargaining agreement before 2012. By past practice it was interpreted as the monthly per employee charge shown on the carrier's invoice. That is one way to go, but other interpretations could have been reasonable as well. Suffice it to say before 2012 the patently ambiguous CBA term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; had become defined by past practice.<ftnote num="17"><para>For a past practice to be binding, it must be 1) unequivocal, 2) clearly enunciated and acted upon, and 3) readily ascertained over a reasonable period of time as an established practice accepted by both parties. <italic>Celanese Corp. of America</italic>, 24 LA 168, 172 (Justin 1954); followed in <italic>Association of Cleveland Fire Fighters, Local 93 v. City of Cleveland</italic>, 793 N.E.2d 484 (2003). Also <italic>City of Salem</italic>, 125 LA 1317 (Reeves 2008). All of these conditions have been met. Once settled as practice it cannot be unilaterally changed. ELKOURI &amp; ELKOURI, (6th Ed.), Section 12.8, <quote>Role of Custom and Practice in Interpreting Ambiguous Language,</quote> at p. 623</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="left"><i>2. Latent Ambiguity post 2012</i></h4>
<p>While the patent ambiguity in the interpretation of the same word in three contacts had been resolved by practice earlier, during the negotiations in 2012 it became a latent ambiguity. The evidence from Officer Fusella and Director Howse show the narrative of the origins of the intent giving rise to this new ambiguity.</p>
<p>The occasion for the 2012 change in the CBA was the particularly draconian effects of the Great Recession during 2011 for many municipalities. The Union approached the City to consider cost savings. Director Morris proposed a savings by using the full cost of the health plan, ie. the COBRA rate, for the employees' subsidy of the Employer cost of healthcare. It was explained to Officer Fusella that the COBRA rate is the &ldquo;true cost&rdquo; of the plan to the Employer. It is the true cost because that is what an employee would need to pay for similar coverage &ldquo;on the street.&rdquo; Thus the proposal was to have employees participate in paying part of that figure, ie the &ldquo;COBRA rates.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The term &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; is the healthcare industry shorthand for the cost of &ldquo;continuation coverage&rdquo; under the COBRA legislation. The statute provides that a plan may charge a premium for the cost of continuation coverage not to exceed 102&percnt; of &ldquo;the applicable premium.&rdquo;<ftnote num="18"><para>The 2&percnt; represents the statutory administrative fee. There is a separate rule for disabled employees.</para></ftnote> &ldquo;Applicable premium&rdquo;is defined in the statute as the &ldquo;cost to the plan&hellip; of the coverage for similarly situated beneficiaries.&rdquo;<ftnote num="19"><para>19 ERISA &sect;604, 29 USC &sect;1164; also 42 USC &sect;300 bb-4.</para></ftnote> The cost of continuation coverage must be a reasonable estimate of the cost of providing the coverage on either an actuarial analysis or taking into account factors prescribed by the IRS regulations.<ftnote num="20"><para>ERISA &sect;604(2), 29 USC &sect;1164(2); also 42 USC &sect;300 bb-4(2).</para></ftnote></p>
<p>The City's shared funding exposure had grown from 2008 at &dollar;2000/&dollar;5000, to &dollar;3000/&dollar;6000, to &dollar;5000/&dollar;10,000 by 2016. The &ldquo;reasonable estimate&rdquo; of the cost of those benefits for purposes of calculating the COBRA rate must have grown over time also. Hence the request for relief by Director Morris for employee monthly contributions to be based on the COBRA rate includes the reasonable estimate of the cost to provide shared funding benefits. It is the &ldquo;true cost&rdquo; because it includes a value for the shared funding. The &ldquo;on the street&rdquo; policy similar to what the Employer offered had to include these benefits paid by the Employer.</p>
<p>The cost of continuation coverage under COBRA must be calculated on the &ldquo;reasonable estimate&rdquo; of providing self funded benefits. That risk according to the broker has an assigned value of approximately &dollar;500, the difference between the monthly charge and the COBRA rate. The &ldquo;applicable premium&rdquo; for setting the COBRA rate is more than the monthly per employee charge by the carrier as Director Howse explained. The difference is that the COBRA rate reflects some value given to the shared funding arrangement. As she testified the monthly charge and the COBRA rates would only be 2&percnt; different if the shared funding <i>were not</i> a feature of the City plan.<ftnote num="21"><para>See also Employer's Post Hearing Brief p. 6.</para></ftnote> Since the &ldquo;applicable premium&rdquo; and the &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; would be off by 2&percnt; had there <i>not</i> been a shared funding feature, the COBRA rate approximates the Employer's true cost of the plan.</p>
<p>Understanding the &ldquo;true cost,&rdquo; Officer Fusella requested the opt out be calculated the same way. Director Morris agreed. In doing so Director Morris did not agree to a windfall for the opt out employees. The opt out employees were intended to receive part of the amount that represented the City's savings by their nonparticipation. Using the COBRA rate was appropriate because it included the shared funding benefits they were waiving. This is the win-win as Officer Fuscella described. Since the modification caused a savings to the City on the employee monthly contributions, this agreement provided the same benefit to the opt out payments. It was quid pro quo.</p>
<p>Stated another way, once the COBRA rates were explained as the true cost of the plan, why would the employee opt out be calculated at anything other than the true cost? Failing to do so treats the two classes of employees unequally. Before their 2012 agreement, the interpretation of &ldquo;premium&rdquo; intended to treat the two groups the same. Equal treatment is undoubtedly part of the mutual intent of the parties.<ftnote num="22"><para>By contrast in 2016, the opt out for all non-police employees and for new hired police was had become agreed to be &dollar;250.00, based on the City ordinance. Based on comparison of that figure with the COBRA rates, that amount is an approximation of some (lower) percentage of the true cost. That part of the 2016 agreement was motivated by a mutual intent to towards uniformity at the expense of equal treatment. Not so the 2016 agreement for the incumbent police employees and also not so before 2016.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Officer Fusella said he remembered something was written up and that he signed an agreement. Sgt. Austen seemed to be vaguely aware of it also. Director Morris did not testify to the contrary. He did not even appear. Mayor Procop, in office at the time, was not called. The inference is that they would not disagree with Officer Fusella.</p>
<p>Finance Director Howse did testify. She was not present for the testimony by Officer Fusella but even so she corroborated it. She confirmed that there was indeed a writing, in her testimony, a copy of an email, and a verbal instruction from Director Morris to her that the opt out payment be calculated on the basis of the COBRA rates.</p>
<p>Undoubtedly there was an agreement among Fuscella-Morris-Howse to use the COBRA rates for the employee opt out. The City submitted the 2012 CBA in evidence which showed &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; for the employee contribution but not for the opt out. It said &ldquo;Plan A premium&rdquo; (later &ldquo;Non HSA option premium.&rdquo;) Based on the evidence there is no question that the &ldquo;Plan A premium&rdquo; for the opt out meant the use of the &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; but the contract did not say that. The contract appeared clear to both parties for years. Not until it was questioned was the latent ambiguity observed. The City argues now in 2016 that it expected in the parties' pre-2012 definition of the CBA term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; was to continue for the opt out provision. That was clearly not the intent in 2012 based on the bargaining history. Other extraneous and practice evidence contradicts that also.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>3. The Extraneous and Past Practice Evidence</i></h4>
<p>The source for defining the CBA term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; after 2012 is COBRA which allows charges of 102&percnt; of the &ldquo;applicable premium.&rdquo; The Employer's definition of the CBA term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; as the monthly charge for employees <i>sans</i> the self funded benefits quite obviously is not the &ldquo;applicable premium&rdquo; on which the COBRA rate is calculated. The effect of the 2012 negotiations by clarifying the &ldquo;true cost&rdquo; was to make the CBA term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; of Article 32 Section 7 (later 6) synonymous at least with the &ldquo;applicable premium&rdquo; under COBRA.</p>
<p>The term &ldquo;Plan A premium&rdquo; appears nowhere in the evidence submitted aside from the CBA. The carrier invoice for the monthly charges as shown above does not assist in defining the CBA term &ldquo;premium.&rdquo; The other documents in evidence are the Health Insurance Plan Options for 2014, 2015 and 2016. Those refer to the employee monthly contributions using the terms &ldquo;Monthly Rates&rdquo; (2014) and &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; (2015 and 2016). Although not identified as such in 2014 when the form used the term &ldquo;Monthly Rates,&rdquo; it is nonetheless also the COBRA rate by another name. Hence the only extraneous documentary evidence as to what the CBA term &ldquo;premium&rdquo; meant for the opt out is &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo;since 2012.</p>
<p>Officer Fusella and Director Howse agree on how the ambiguity was resolved by practice. The Finance Director complied with HR Director Morris' instructions to use the COBRA rates. She did so for four years afterwards, for all three bargaining units, for numerous employees. That is 104 bi-monthly pay periods per year for three units, or effectively 312 pay periods in all. The number of employee checks per pay period is not in evidence. The payrolls in evidence confirm the use of COBRA rates for calculating the opt out for all three units prior to the March 25, 2016 letter. There is simply no contrary evidence.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>4. The Mistake Defense</i></h4>
<p>The Employer claims this is a case of a unilateral mistake. That is that the Finance Director used the wrong basis for the calculation for many years, for many employees under several agreements. A contract is not avoided by <i>unilateral mistakes</i>, only by <i>bilateral or mutual mistakes</i> of fact.<ftnote num="23"><para><quote>The distinction between <quote>mutual</quote> mistake and <quote>unilateral</quote> mistake has some importance. In the matter of the remedy to be granted, it may be a decisive factor&hellip;. The American Law Institute states the law to be that the contract is not made avoidable by a unilateral mistake, however material it may be to the interest of the mistaken party. Without doubt, this has been the prevailing form of statement, along with the even more common form that mistake is not operative unless it is mutual.</quote> <small-cap>Corbin on Contracts</small-cap> (West Publishing, 1952) &sect;609. Also: 69 O. Jur 3d <small-cap>Mistake</small-cap>, Sec. 5 and 6; 15 O. Jur 3d <small-cap>Compromise, Accord and Release</small-cap>, Sec. 59.</para></ftnote> An agreement is enforceable by its terms notwithstanding the mistaken position taken by one of the parties on a pre-contract circumstance.</p>
<p>The evidence does not assist the City. It did not make a unilateral mistake. The City agreed with the Union to the opt out formula. That was confirmed by the City implementing it on the instruction from the City's bargainer to the Finance Director that COBRA rates would be used. Given its origin this is not a unilateral mistake to use COBRA rates. It was intended. If there were a mistake it was made by both parties in failing to better memorialize what both parties clearly had agreed. The writing failed to reflect the agreement. Hence this is a case of mutual mistake.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&ldquo;A mutual mistake exists when both parties sign off (on) contract language that does not correspond with their actual agreement. In this limited circumstance, an arbitrator may reform the contract to reflect the true intent of the parties.&rdquo;<ftnote num="24"><para><italic>Los Angeles County Social Services Union</italic>, 89-1 ARB &para;8189, at &para; 3923 (Knowlton 1988). In <italic>Hibbing Ready Mix</italic>, 97 LA 248 (Imes, 1991) the arbitrator refused to enforce a contract where both parties conceded a mutual mistake. See also <italic>Down River Forest Products</italic>, 94 LA 141, 145 (Gangle, 1989).</para></ftnote></p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Reformation, that is revising the agreement to reflect the true (not mistaken) intent, is the remedy for mutual mistake. &ldquo;Reformation is not a proper remedy for the enforcement of terms to which the defendant never assented; it is a remedy the purpose of which is to make a mistake in writing conform to the antecedent expressions on which the parties agreed.&rdquo;<ftnote num="25"><para><small-cap>Corbin on Contracts</small-cap> (West Publishing, 1952) &sect;614.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>The other remedy for mutual mistake is recision of the agreement which leaves the parties where they stood before contracting, ie. without an agreement. Recision arises if neither party can be assigned a greater blame for the pre-contract circumstances.<ftnote num="26"><para><small-cap>Restatement 2D of Contracts</small-cap>, Sec.20(1)(a),(b)(1981).</para></ftnote> If both are equally blameless the agreement can only be set aside. It does not appear recision would serve the purposes of these parties by putting them back where they were before 2012. More to the point, the parties are not equally blameless. Both parties agreed and the Employer implemented the agreement. It behooves the Employer, a body politic, to carefully supervise the scrivening if that were important as it now claims that it is. Director Howse testified that her reaction to Director Morris's instruction to use COBRA rates was &ldquo;Get that in writing.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There may be times when an arbitrator should reform a contract but they should be few and far between.<ftnote num="27"><para>See <small-cap>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, <italic>How Arbitration Works</italic></small-cap>, (6th ed. 2003) at Ch. 18 3K. 18.3.K.i, <quote>Remedies for Mistake,</quote> and Ch.9.2.A.ii, <quote>Exceptions</quote> and cases cited.</para></ftnote> One reason for that is the clarity or lack thereof of what the original intent may have been. That is certainly not the case here. The parties' intent could not be clearer. Had this case not been resolvable by the interpreting a latent ambiguity, the Employer's argument of mistake would have led to a reformation and the same result. The CBA would be administered both prospectively and retroactively to apply the opt out formula to the COBRA rates for the qualifying employees.</p>
<h4 align="left"><small-cap>B. What Shall the Remedy Be?</small-cap></h4>
<p>The employees who opted out during the plan year 2016 shall be made whole. The Employer shall cease from applying the opt out percentage to any but the COBRA rates for the applicable employees.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>X. CONCLUSION</b></h4>
<p>The Union proved on the evidence taken as a whole that its reading of the Agreement is more probably correct that since 2012 the interpretation of &ldquo;premium&rdquo; in Article 32 Section 6 for incumbent employees is identical to &ldquo;COBRA rates&rdquo; found in Article 32 Section 2. The grievance is granted and the Grievants shall be made whole as set out in the Award.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><small-cap>Award</small-cap></b></h4>
<p>I, The undersigned Arbitrator, having been designated in accordance with the arbitration agreement entered into between the above named parties, and having duly heard the proofs and allegations of the parties, hereby AWARD as follows:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>The Arbitrator finds for <small-cap>Ohio Patrolmen's Benevolent Association</small-cap> and against <small-cap>City of Twinsburg, Ohio</small-cap> on the Grievance of April 13, 2016 on behalf of all three OPBA units.</p>
<ol type="lc-letter" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p><i>Cease and desist.</i> The City is ordered to as soon as practicable to cease and desist from the using any but the COBRA rates used for calculation of the employee monthly healthcare contribution in calculating the employee opt out payments under Article 32 of the respective OPBA collective bargaining agreements for eligible employees.</p></li>
<li><p><i>Affirmative order.</i> The City is ordered as soon as practicable to calculate the employee opt out payments under Article 32 of the respective OPBA collective bargaining agreements for eligible employees using the COBRA rates used for calculation of the employee monthly healthcare contribution.</p></li>
<li><p><i>Compensatory damages.</i> The City shall compensate all employees who opted out of health care coverage beginning with the 2016 plan year, the difference between the actual amount of the opt out payments made and the opt out payment amount as calculated using the prevailing COBRA rates for calculation of the employee monthly healthcare contribution until the full implementation of the remedy in the payroll system.</p></li></ol></li>
<li><p>The Agreement requires that cost and expenses of the arbitration shall be borne by the non prevailing party which in this case is the City of Twinsburg.</p></li></ol>
<p class="continued">The foregoing is in full settlement of all disputes presented in the hearing of this matter.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>