<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between, Teamsters Local 848, Union And, Transdev Transportation, Inc., Employer.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>January 31, 2017.</p>
<p>William S. Schilling, Arbitrator</p>
<p>The parties selected the Arbitrator pursuant to the terms of their Collective Bargaining Agreement dated January 1, 2012 - December 31, 2016 (JX1)<ftnote num="1"><para>Union, Company, and Joint exhibits are referenced as UX, CX, and JX.</para></ftnote>. The matter was heard on May 25, 2016 at 16501 Ventura Blvd. in Encino, California. The Grievant was present, and the parties were afforded the opportunity to examine and cross-examine witnesses under oath, introduce relevant evidence, and propound arguments in support of their respective positions. The hearing record was closed and the matter submitted for award as of October 3, 2016, following the receipt and exchange of the post-hearing briefs.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>BACKGROUND</b></h4>
<p>Transdev Transportation Services Inc. contracts with cities and counties, including in Northern Los Angeles County, to operate transportation systems. Transdev was previously incorporated as Veolia Transportation Services, and some historic policies and materials still display the older name as the transition has only recently been completed. In and around the Northern Los Angeles metropolitan area the employer contracts with the Antelope Valley Transit Authority (AVTA) to perform transit services. AVTA employees under the Transdev contract are represented by Teamsters Local 848.</p>
<p>The grievant, Charlean Jones, was employed as a Bus Operator and was originally hired by Veolia Transportation on August 1, 2007.</p>
<p>In January 2015, Road Supervisor, Terrence Cloud, was reviewing bus videos pursuant to his conduct of an equipment check. The busses involved were part of a new fleet of electric buses for the AVTA contract. There had been some issues with the video system on these busses and that is what he was checking. During that review he noticed a driver engaging in several behaviors that he considered unsafe and in violation of the Company's safety policy. Upon researching the bus number, route, date and time of day; he determined that the driver was Ms. Jones. The observed behaviors occurred on January 20, 21 and 22, 2015.</p>
<p>The Company suspended Ms. Jones, pending further investigation, on January 22 for &ldquo;Conduct&rdquo; (JX3). In a document dated January 26 (JX4), she was notified that the results of the investigation were that she had committed &ldquo;Unsafe Acts &amp; General Safety Principles&rdquo;; specifically &ldquo;Carrying customers off the established route without authorization, Listening to unauthorized sound equipment (radio, tape player, etc.) while operating a vehicle, Operators are not permitted to eat or drink while operation a Company vehicle.&rdquo; She was terminated on January 28 and handed a notice stating: &ldquo;During the investigation, it was confirmed that on January 20, 2015 and January 21, 2015 you failed to follow the training and guidelines of the Veolia Transportation World Class Safety Policies and Procedures provided to you&hellip;Your poor job performance and unsafe acts&hellip;due to using your electronic device while operating a Company vehicle&hellip; You have violated the Veolia Transportation Policies and Procedures&hellip;You also violated the Veolia Transportation Communication Device Policy&hellip;As a result, your employment with Veolia Transportation has been terminated effective January 28, 2015.&rdquo; (JX5)</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>ISSUES</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The parties could not agree upon an Issue and stipulated that the Arbitrator has the authority to frame the Issue. Following are the issues proposed by each party.</p>
<p class="continued">Employer: &ldquo;Did the Collective Bargaining Agreement prohibit the discharge of the grievant? If so, what is the proper remedy?</p>
<p class="continued">Union: &ldquo;Did the Company have just cause to terminate the grievant Charlean Jones? If not, what is the appropriate remedy?</p>
<p class="continued">After reviewing the Collective Bargaining Agreement (JX1) and the parties two submissions, the Arbitrator determines the Issue to be as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did the Company violate Article 21, Section 1 of the Agreement, requiring just cause, when it discharged Charlean Jones? If so, what is the appropriate remedy?&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>STIPULATIONS</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The case is properly before the Arbitrator for decision.</p>
<p class="continued">The parties agreed that the Arbitrator has the authority to frame the Issue.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>RELEVANT LANGUAGE</b></h4>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 2 - RECOGNITION</h4>
<p class="continued">Section 2 - Union Responsibilities: The Union recognizes the responsibilities imposed upon it as the exclusive bargaining agent for the bargaining unit employees and realizes that in order to provide maximum opportunities for continuing employment, good working conditions and good wages, the Company must be in a strong competitive position. The Union, therefore, agrees that it will assist the Company's efforts to maintain a strong competitive position by ensuring its support of programs for the efficient utilization of the work force, safety in its operations, including accident prevention programs, a high degree of on-time performance, proper and courteous service by its driver-members, the wearing of designated dress, and the maintenance of good grooming. It further agrees to promote the Company's business and support it is its efforts to strengthen good will between the Company, the employees, AVTAAntelope Valley Transportation Authority, and the public.</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 10 - MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</h4>
<p class="continued">Section 1 - Company Rights: It is not the intent of this Agreement to include matters of management, and the Company reserves to itself the management, conduct, and control of the operations of its business, including but not limited to:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The prescribing of reasonable Company rules, instructions, and regulations for safe, proper, and effective conduct of its business in a competitive environment;</p>
<p class="continued">The company also reserves the right to change decisions within the scope of this Article at any time.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 12 - MINIMUM SAFETY POLICIES AND PROCEDURES</h4>
<p class="continued">The Company and the Union recognize that safety is of primary concern to all parties and are committed to uphold the Veolia World Class Safety Policies and Procedures. These policies may be revised with proper and timely notification to the Union. The Union reserves the right to grieve all discipline resulting from this article that does not meet &ldquo;just cause.&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 21 - DISCIPLINE AND DISCHARGE</h4>
<p class="continued">Section 1 - Just Cause: Employees will be disciplined or discharged for just cause as outlined in the Employee Handbook.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 2 - Progressive Discipline: A progressive disciplinary procedure will be used for the no fault attendance policy and poor job performance. The Drivers shall be allowed a three (3) minute grace period on their sign-on time. Progressive discipline may consist of a verbal warning, written warning, and a suspension, although all of these steps are not a prerequisite for termination. However, no employee may discharged under this section unless he has had a previous written warning within twelve (12) months of the instant infraction. Warnings must be for similar infractions to support termination, however, an employees' entire work history may be considered prior to termination.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 5 - Termination: If the Union determines that the Company has violated the Collective Bargaining Agreement by disciplining or discharging an employee without just cause, the Union shall have the right to file a grievance under Article 22 of this Agreement.</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 22 - GRIEVANCE/ARBITRATION PROCEDURE</h4>
<p class="continued">Section 3 - Grievance Arbitration: If the grievance is not resolved in the written response provided in Section 2, Step 3 above, and if the defending party has processed the grievance in strict adherence with the express time limits in this article, the aggrieved party may file for arbitration. Such filing must take place not later than thirty (30) calendar days after the date on which the written response from the defending party is due under Section 2, Step 3,</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">(a) The arbitrator shall be appointed by the Company and the Union.</p>
<p class="continued">(b) The arbitrator shall have no authority to:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">(1) add to, delete from, amend or in any way disregard any of the terms in this Agreement</p>
<p class="continued">(2) accept for submission any issue other than factual questions as to whether or not a specific, written provision of the</p>
<p class="continued">Agreement has been violated by the Company;</p>
<p class="continued">(3) fashion a remedy in any grievance in which he fails to find that the specific written provision of the Agreement has been violated by the other party.</p>
<p class="continued">(4) accept for submission or render an award in a grievance in which the specific procedures of the Article, including the express time limits at each step, have not been adhered to:</p>
<p class="continued">(5) fashion a remedy in any grievance that is inconsistent with any of the terms or condition of one of the Company's revenue contracts or;</p>
<p class="continued">(6) fashion a remedy in any grievance which back pay is awarded retroactively for more than ten(10) days prior to the date on which the grievance was filed.</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>ANALYSIS AND OPINION</b><ftnote num="2"><para>To concentrate on the determinative and avoid the cumulative, the analysis does not summarize all evidence or contentions raised by the parties and considered by the Arbitrator.</para></ftnote></h4>
<p>In order to address the Issue at hand, the language in the Collective Bargaining Agreement, CBA, (JX1) must first be considered. Article 21, Section 1 requires just cause for discipline or discharge. The just cause standard is also referenced in Section 5 - Termination of Article 21 and in Article 12 - Minimum Safety Policies and Procedures.</p>
<p>Ultimately, it is the task of the Arbitrator to determine whether such just cause standard has been met. In doing so, there may be other sections of the CBA for consideration. Such is the case here. Article 21, Section 2 - Progressive Discipline provides further insight into the intent of the parties regarding discipline.</p>
<p>The first sentence of that Section is key and is in some dispute between the parties. It reads: &ldquo;A progressive disciplinary procedure will be used for the no fault attendance policy and poor job performance.&rdquo; The Union contends that the &ldquo;attendance policy&rdquo; and &ldquo;poor job performance&rdquo; are two separate and distinct sets of circumstances. Union Business Representative, Joe Pimentel, testified to the intent of the language, based on his involvement in the negotiations. He was the co-chair for the Union in negotiations and attended all sessions. His testimony was unrebutted. On cross examination, it appeared that Company counsel was trying to establish that ALL progressive discipline referenced in Section 2 should fall under the &ldquo;no fault attendance policy&rdquo; and that &ldquo;poor job performance&rdquo; was actually included as part of the attendance policy. However, in its post-hearing brief, the Company made no such argument. Conversely, Mr. Pimentel did NOT testify that ALL discipline must be progressive, no matter how serious. And, the Union did not argue in its post-hearing brief that ALL discipline must be progressive. Instead, it argued that the specifics of Jones' violations were such that they required progressive discipline. That contention will be addressed later in this Analysis.</p>
<p>It is my determination, based on the contract wording and the testimony, that the &ldquo;no fault attendance policy&rdquo; and &ldquo;poor job performance&rdquo; are two separate sets of circumstances. And that both require progressive discipline as outlined in Section 2. It is also my determination that there are certain actions, behaviors, violations, etc. that are NOT subject to progressive discipline because of the nature of their severity.</p>
<p>Article 21, Section 2 further reads that &ldquo;no employee may be discharged under this section unless he has had a previous written warning within twelve (12) months of the instant infraction. Warnings must be for similar infractions to support termination, however, an employee's entire work history may be considered prior to termination.&rdquo; In the case of Ms. Jones, she had not been issued a written warning within the previous twelve months for similar infractions. The Union contends that because she had not received a previous warning, she should not have been terminated. The Company contends that her policy infractions were not subject to progressive discipline because they could not be categorized as &ldquo;poor job performance.&rdquo; They believe that the infractions were more serious and therefore subject to immediate dismissal. To address this, the specifies of her violations must be examined.</p>
<p>The actions of Ms. Jones, resulting in her termination, took place over a three day period; January 20, 21 &amp; 22, 2015. All of the allegations involved violations of the Veolia Transportation World Class Safety Policies and Procedures, WCSP (JX9). The specific sections at issue appear under the heading &ldquo;General Safety Principles&rdquo;. They are:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;E.6 Operators are not permitted to eat or drink while operating a Company vehicle.</p>
<p class="continued">E.8 When driving a Company vehicle, the use of cellular phones, other personal communications devices (Bluetooth, hands free and ear buds), and other electronic devices is limited to the following situations:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">(a) Cellular phone use while operating a motor vehicle is prohibited in any jurisdiction that prohibits said use by law.</p>
<p class="continued">(b) Transit Operators: The use of cellular phones, personal communications devices, and other electronic devices while operating a transit vehicle is prohibited. Cellular phones and other personal communications devices must be powered off at all times when an Operator is seated behind the wheel, regardless of whether the vehicle is powered on or off.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>Additionally, the Communication Device Policy, CDP (JX12) states, in part: &ldquo;(a) Veolia Employees: The use of cellular phones and other personal communication devices while operating a vehicle on Company business is prohibited. Cellular phones or other personal communication devices must be powered off at all times except when the vehicle is in park and the engine turned off&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ms. Jones signed for receipt of the CDP (JX13) and the Policies and Procedures (JX14, JX15). She testified. that she had been trained on and was fully aware of these policies.</p>
<p>So, what specifically happened on these three days in January 2015. The evidence presented is contained in CX4 (a CD/DVD &amp; memory stick), CX7, CX8, CX9, CX10 &amp; CX11; in addition to testimony from witnesses. The latter five documents are screen shots taken from the videos that were used to generate CX4. The Union objected to all of these documents arguing that the Company could not establish that the grievant was the individual pictured in each. Based on the testimony of Terrance Cloud, who physically took the videos from each vehicle and then matched the vehicle with the driver by reviewing the date, time of day, route sheet, etc., I am persuaded that Ms. Jones was the driver shown in each of the video segments and screen shots.</p>
<p>The best evidence for determining Ms. Jones' actions is the CD/DVD (CX4) containing several segments of videos. Since I am an Apple/MAC user, try as I might, I was unable to get either the CD/DVD or the memory stick to work in my computer. However, I do still have a PC laptop and was able to get CX4 to work on it. The exhibit contains six segments of video; 3 from 1/20/15, 2 from 1/21/15, and 1 from 1/22/15. Based on my comprehensive, lengthy, and careful review, I was able to clearly see a number of actions relevant to the charges against Ms. Jones.</p>
<ul type="none">
<li><p>- On 1/20/15 from 6:22:32 to 6:22:39 she was operating her phone while the vehicle was in motion. Company witness, Hector Fuentes testified to observing the same actions (TR p.85, 19-25)</p></li>
<li><p>- On 1/21/15 from 11:32:42 to 11:33:13 she was reaching for and handling her purse which was hanging on the fare box, while the vehicle was in motion.</p></li>
<li><p>- On 1/22/15 from 15:33:31 to 15:34:33 she was again reaching for and handling her purse which was hanging on the fare box, while the vehicle was in motion.</p></li>
<li><p>- Throughout the various segments there were numerous incidents of her eating and drinking, then holding the food and drink between her legs.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>With respect to the charges against her, Ms. Jones admitted that she violated the Policies. On JX2 she wrote &ldquo;I understand that what I did was wrong and if given a second chance I will prove that I can and will follow company rules and policies.&rdquo; On UX7 she wrote &ldquo;I understand that I violated company policy with having the phone on. I regret and understand what I did was wrong. I will not violate company policies and rules again.&rdquo; On cross examination, Ms. Jones testified as follows (TR p.166, 4-13):</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Q In your words, what do you think you did that was wrong?</p>
<p class="continued">A Having the cell phone turned on.</p>
<p class="continued">Q Anything else?</p>
<p class="continued">A Listening to music.</p>
<p class="continued">Q Anything else?</p>
<p class="continued">A Humm, handling the cell phone while at a layover.</p>
<p class="continued">Q Anything else?</p>
<p class="continued">A No.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Basically, Ms. Jones admits to listening to gospel music while driving, in an effort to take her mind off of her personal issues regarding her son. What she didn't admit to was handling the phone and her purse while the vehicle was in motion. She also didn't admit to eating and drinking while she was behind the wheel. Her testimony amounts to only a partial admission, in my opinion, and is therefore very troubling to me. It does not demonstrate complete remorse. If she doesn't acknowledge all of the actions she took, she can't show remorse for actions she doesn't admit happened. And therefore, she can't correct those actions going forward, because she hasn't admitted that they even took place.</p>
<p>What is even more troubling, and harmful to her credibility, is the issue of a previous five (5) day suspension she received in July 2008 (CX12). It was her contention and testimony that she had a totally clean work record. However, when confronted with CX12, she had to admit she had been previously suspended (TR p.158, 6-19):</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Q And do you remember being suspended in 2008 because you tried to cover some drive cam equipment, some cameras inside, with some gum?</p>
<p class="continued">A Yes. I recognize this. This is when Martin Tompkins was the manager. I thought you were relating to when Hector was, Hector was the manager.</p>
<p class="continued">Q Okay. I thought your testimony before, and correct me if I am wrong, was during the entire period of time of your employment with Transdev, you have never been suspended: wasn't that your testimony?</p>
<p class="continued">A Yes.</p>
<p class="continued">Q You didn't limit your testimony to when Hector was General Manager versus Marty Tompkins; correct?</p>
<p class="continued">A Right.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In addition, she had a written warning notice dated 1/28/14 for a passenger complaint (CX13, p.4).</p>
<p>How do all these policy violations stack up against the terms of the CBA (JX1)?</p>
<p>The Company contends in its brief that Article 21, Section 1 &ldquo;states that discipline and discharge shall be determined by the Employee Handbook.&rdquo; That is not quite accurate. What that Article and Section actually states is: &ldquo;Employees will be disciplined or discharged for <i>just cause</i> (emphasis added) as outlined in the Employee Handbook.&rdquo; The inclusion of the words &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; are a significant difference. To state that the Employee Handbook is what determines discipline and discharge is to ignore many of the provisions of the CBA. For example, on page 7 of the Employee Handbook (JX11) it states: &ldquo;All Company employees are employees &ldquo;at will.&rdquo; This means employment with the Company can be terminated by the employee or by the Company at any time without cause.&rdquo; Obviously, &ldquo;at will&rdquo; employment is NOT consistent with the terms of the CBA (JX1).</p>
<p>The Company's brief further states &ldquo;In fact, Article 12 of the CBA specifically incorporates the WCSP (JX9) and the WCSP specifically states that violation of the policy regarding cell phones can result in immediate termination.&rdquo; What the Company fails to include from Article 12 is &ldquo;The Union reserves the right to grieve all discipline resulting from this article that does not meet &ldquo;just cause.&rdquo; Additionally, the Company has misstated what is contained in the WCSP by stating &ldquo;can result in immediate termination.&rdquo; The actual wording is &ldquo;Failure to comply with any portion of this policy will result in disciplinary action, up to and including dismissal.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The third contention from the Company is that the Communication Device Policy (JX12) incorporates &ldquo;zero tolerance&rdquo; for any violation of the policy. Company witness Cloud testified as follows (TR p.40, 15-20):</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Q What was your understanding of the policy at the time?</p>
<p class="continued">A Zero tolerance.</p>
<p class="continued">Q And what does that mean?</p>
<p class="continued">A If you are caught using your cell phone, it is immediate termination.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Later, while being asked about this policy on cross examination, Cloud testified (TR p.76, 4-10):</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Q You used the phrase &ldquo;zero tolerance&rdquo; in your direct testimony.</p>
<p class="continued">A Uh-huh.</p>
<p class="continued">Q But that phrase is not included in this document; right? The phrase &ldquo;zero tolerance&rdquo; is not included in this document, right?</p>
<p class="continued">A No.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What JX12 actually states is: &ldquo;Failure to comply with any portion of this policy may result in immediate termination of employment.&rdquo; The use of the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; is significant versus the use of another word, like &ldquo;will&rdquo; or &ldquo;shall&rdquo;. Based on the document itself (JX12) and the testimony, it is my determination that &ldquo;zero tolerance&rdquo; does NOT apply to any and all violations of the Policy. If &ldquo;zero tolerance&rdquo; was the intent, then that is what would be stated. Instead, the level of discipline must be determined by a standard of &ldquo;just cause.&rdquo; That means that the individual circumstances of any usage must be examined to determine &ldquo;just cause&rdquo;. Some of those circumstances might warrant progressive discipline and some might not be subject to progressive discipline, since outright dismissal is one explicit option.</p>
<p>The Union argues that the individual circumstances regarding Ms. Jones do not meet a just cause standard for termination. They believe that she should have received progressive discipline as outlined in Article 21, Section 2 of the CBA (JX1), specifically with respect to the end of the Section, which states: &ldquo;&hellip;an employees' entire work history may be considered prior to termination.&rdquo; The Union's argument that Ms. Jones had a &ldquo;clean record&rdquo; is just not factual. They further argued in their brief that: &ldquo;Neither the CBA nor the Safety Policy mandate termination under the facts that have been presented.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I agree that neither the CBA nor the Safety Policy mandate termination for any and all phone usage. That determination must be made based on the specific facts of any individual case. Where, then, does Ms. Jones' phone usage fall with respect to the CBA and Safety Policy?</p>
<p>First, is the consideration of her entire work history as outlined in Article 21, Section 2. This consideration does not mitigate her circumstances or help her. She had a 5 day suspension in 2008 and a written warning in 2014. That is NOT a clean work record.</p>
<p>Second, is her credibility. As stated previously, I am troubled by her lack of acknowledgement of all her violations of the Safety Policy. I am even more troubled about her initial denial of the 5 day suspension in 2008. While I am empathetic about her personal issues with her son, that does not mitigate the credibility issues.</p>
<p>Third, is the severity of the instances. By handling her purse and her phone while the bus was in motion, plus eating and drinking, she created serious distractions from her driving. It demonstrated prohibited conduct expressly proscribed in the safety policies. Such behavior clearly jeopardized the safety of herself, her passengers, pedestrians, other vehicles, and her vehicle. As discussed earlier, there are certain violations that are severe enough to warrant termination even without having received a written warning within the last 12 months for a similar infraction. The actions of Ms. Jones in January 2015 fall into that category.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>AWARD</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Company did not violate Article 21, Section 1 of the Agreement, requiring just cause, when it discharged Charlean Jones.</p>
<p class="continued">The grievance is denied.</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator retains jurisdiction, should any dispute arise pertaining to this Award.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>