<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of the Arbitration of a Dispute Between THE CITY OF SARTELL (POLICE DEPARTMENT) and LAW ENFORCEMENT LABOR SERVICES, INC.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>BMS Case &num;16 PA0712</p>
<p>January 6, 2017.</p>
<p>Sharon A. Gallagher, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ARBITRATION AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>In accord with the 2015-17 collective bargaining agreement between these parties, the parties jointly selected Arbitrator Sharon A. Gallagher to hear and resolve a dispute between them through the Minnesota BMS concerning holiday pay for Officers Broda and Lundquist. Hearing was held on November 29, 2016 at Sartell, Minnesota by agreement of the parties. No stenographic transcript of the proceedings was made. The Union called two witnesses and the City called three witnesses, all of whom were first sworn on oath or affirmation by the Arbitrator.</p>
<p>The parties submitted ten Joint Exhibits and the Union submitted nine Union Exhibits, all of which were received into the record.<ftnote num="1"><para>The City objected to Union Exhibits 4 and 5 on relevancy. These exhibits were received over objection with the understanding that the objection would be dealt with in this Award.</para></ftnote> The parties made opening statements and had a full and fair opportunity to present documentary and testimonial evidence and to make objections and arguments in support of their positions. The hearing was completed on November 29<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<p>The parties agreed to submit post-hearing briefs postmarked by the close of business on December 19, 2016, with full copies of any case precedents enclosed that the parties wish the Arbitrator to consider. The parties' briefs were received on December 19, 2016, whereupon the record was closed.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>ISSUES</i></b></h4>
<p>The parties were unable to stipulate to the issues to be decided herein. However, they agreed that the Arbitrator could frame the issues based on the relevant evidence and argument herein as well as the parties' suggested issues.</p>
<p>The Union suggested the following issues:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Did the City of Sartell violate Section 14.3 of the Collective Bargaining Agreement by requiring Investigator Tim Broda to take days off on holidays that coincided with his regularly scheduled work days, and to use hours from his holiday pay bank on those days?</p></li>
<li><p>Did the City of Sartell violate Section 14.3 of the Collective Bargaining Agreement by requiring School Resource Officer Jill Lundquist to take days off on holidays that coincided with her regularly scheduled work days, and to use hours from her holiday pay bank on those days?</p></li>
<li><p>If so, what is the appropriate remedy?</p></li></ol>
<p>The City offered the following issues for determination:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Does the City have the right to order an employee not to work on a holiday when the holiday falls on a regularly scheduled workday?</p>
<p class="continued">If not, what is the remedy?</p></blockquote>
<p>Based on my review of the relevant evidence and argument, and having considered the parties' suggested issues, I believe the Union's issues more accurately describe the dispute in this case,<ftnote num="2"><para>The City's issues contain argument.</para></ftnote> and they shall be decided here.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>RELEVANT CONTRACT PROVISIONS</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>ARTICLE V. Employer Authority</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">5.1 The Employer retains the full and unrestricted right to operate and manage all staff, facilities and equipment; to establish functions and programs; to set and amend budgets; to determine the utilization of technology; to establish and modify the organizational structure; to select, direct, and determine the number of personnel; to establish work schedules; and to perform any inherent managerial function not specifically limited by this Agreement.</p><p align="center">&hellip;</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>ARTICLE X. Work Schedules</b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">10.1 The sole authority in the work schedule is the Employer's. The normal workday for an employee shall be no less than eight (8) nor more than twelve (12) consecutive hours. The normal work period shall be 160 hours in a twenty-eight (28) day period.</p>
<p class="continued">10.2 Service to the public may require the establishment of regular shifts for some employees on a daily, weekly, seasonal, or annual basis other than the normal 8 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. day. The Employer will give the maximum amount reasonably possible, but not less than twenty-four (24) hours advance notice to the employees affected by the establishment of work days different from the employee's normal work day. Scheduled days off will not be charged with less than two weeks notice unless agreed to by the employee and employer.</p>
<p class="continued">10.3 In the event that work is required because of unusual circumstances such as, but not limited to, fire, flood, snow, sleet, or breakdown of municipal equipment or facilities, no advance notice need be given. It is not required that an employee working other than the normal workday be scheduled to work more than the normal work day; however, each employee has the obligation to work overtime or call backs, if requested, unless unusual circumstances prevent him/her from so working.</p>
<p class="continued">10.4 Service to the public may require the establishment of regular workweeks that schedule work on Saturdays, Sundays and/or holidays.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>ARTICLE XIV. Holidays</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">14.1 <i>Definitions</i>. Twelve (12) normal work days during the calendar year shall be considered holidays; defined as a paid non-work day.</p>
<p class="continued">14.2 <i>Holidays Observed</i>.</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>New Year's Day</p></li>
<li><p>Martin Luther Kings Birthday</p></li>
<li><p>Presidents' Day</p></li>
<li><p>Good Friday</p></li>
<li><p>Memorial Day</p></li>
<li><p>Independence Day</p></li>
<li><p>Labor Day</p></li>
<li><p>Veterans Day</p></li>
<li><p>Thanksgiving Day</p></li>
<li><p>Floating Holiday</p></li>
<li><p>Christmas Eve Day</p></li>
<li><p>Christmas Day</p>
<p>Employees who work Easter Sunday will be paid time and one half.</p></li></ol>
<p class="continued">14.3 <i>Holiday Pay</i>. The Employer will credit the officers 120 hours per year (12 holidays x <b>10</b> hours) in a holiday bank. These hours can be scheduled like vacation. These hours must be used or scheduled by November 1<sup>st</sup> of each year. All unused and unscheduled hours will be paid out to employees in their first paycheck of November. Employees who work on a holiday shall receive time and one-half for the hours worked. If an employee is required to work the holiday on a scheduled day off, the employee has the choices described above and shall also receive one (1) additional day off within the following thirty (30) days. Employees required to work overtime during scheduled time off on a holiday will receive time and one-half plus time off for an equivalent compensation rate of two and one-half time.</p>
<p class="continued">14.4 <i>Work Force</i>. For the purposes of scheduling time off, the work force in the Police Department on any given day shall not be below four (4) employees per day.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>ARTICLE XV. Vacation Leave</b></i></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">15.1 <i>Allowances</i>. Employees shall earn and accumulate vacation leave monthly from the date of hire in accordance with the provisions as follows:</p>
<table width="585" columns="1">
<tr>
<td width="34%"><p></p></td>
<td width="33%"><p></p></td>
<td width="33%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>0-2 years</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>40 hours</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3.334 hours per month</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>After 2 years</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>80 hours</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>6.667 hours per month</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>After 5 years</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>120 hours</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>10 hours per month</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>After 11 years</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>160 hours</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>13.334 hours per month</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>After 18 years</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>200 hours</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>16.667 hour per month</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
<p class="continued">15.2 <i>Vacation Periods</i>. Every practical effort shall be made by the Employer to schedule employees' vacations at a time selected by the employee, insofar as adequate scheduling permits. If it is necessary to limit the number of employees on vacation at the same time, the vacation schedule shall be established on the basis of seniority in the event of any conflict over requested vacation. Vacation selections shall be granted by seniority until April 1<sup>st</sup> of each year. After April 1<sup>st</sup>, requests will be granted on a first come first serve basis.</p>
<p class="continued">15.3 <i>Vacation Use and Carry Over</i>. Employees shall be allowed to carry up to one and one half times their annual accrual rate at any given time. Any amount carried in excess of one and one half year's accrual must be used within 30 days of exceeding the accrual amount. The City shall pay an eligible employee for unused, accrued vacation leave if an employee request to use carried vacation leave is denied by the Employer and cannot be rescheduled within the subsequent one-hundred eighty (180) days.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>ARTICLE XVI. Sick Leave</b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">16.1 <i>Allowances</i>. All employees in the bargaining unit shall earn sick leave at the rate of eight (8) hours per month, ninety-six (96) hours per year, and will be permitted to accumulate leave to a total of six hundred (600) hours.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>ARTICLE XXIV. Grievance Procedure</b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">24.5 <i>Arbitrator's Authority</i></p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">A. The arbitrator shall have no right to amend, modify, nullify, ignore, add to, or subtract from the terms and conditions of this Agreement. The arbitrator shall consider and decide only the specific issue(s) submitted in writing by the Employer and the Union, and shall have no authority to make a decision on any other issue not so submitted.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;</p></blockquote></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>BACKGROUND</b></i></h4>
<p>The City of Sartell and its Police Department have grown and changed since the 1990's. Chief Jim Hughes stated that he was hired by the City in 1991 as a police officer, promoted to Sergeant in 1994, and then to Lieutenant in 2000. In 1991 the City employed the Chief of Police, one Captain and four officers.</p>
<p>In 1995, the Department added one School Resource Officer (SRO), The SRO was a licensed City police officer specially assigned to the school district. Since 1995, the SRO has had the same duties: Security in the schools, mediation with parents and students, counseling of students and investigation of crimes in the schools. Also since 1995, the School Board has had a major role in selecting SROs. The Board requires that when there is an SRO opening, interested licensed City police officers must submit applications and be interviewed. The Board then approves the applicant they select and the Chief of Police has then approved that officer for the SRO position.</p>
<p>Since 1995, City officers assigned as SROs have worked 8 hours per day, 5 days per week and they have not worked in the schools when the school district is closed on holidays and their winter and spring breaks because the schools are closed. No job description exists for the SRO position. Traditionally, during these times when school is closed during the school year, the SROs have been scheduled to work 8 hours on a patrol shift or other duty at holiday pay to complete their 40 hours per week regular schedules. SROs do not receive additional pay due to their different position. They are paid on the contractual salary grid which is based on years of service. During the longer school break for summer, the SROs have either been assigned to a regular 10 hour patrol shift or to other 8 hour shifts, for example as Community Safety Officers in the City.<ftnote num="3"><para>Community Safety Officers' duties include code enforcement, unlocking car doors for citizens, performing community outreach duties for seniors and children. No job description exists for the Safety Officer position.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Chief Hughes stated that for many years, the Department was under a hiring freeze and this resulted in the Department being significantly understaffed, even as the City grew from a bedroom community of St. Cloud to a larger commercial and residential center with increasing crime. Chief Hughes stated that this situation made it difficult for the Department to grant all time off requests made by officers.</p>
<p>In 1995, an Investigator position was added to the Department roster. Traditionally, the Investigator has been paid on the contractual salary grid and no additional pay is granted for the position. No job description exists for the Investigator position. From 1995 to 2016, the Investigator position worked the same schedule as patrol officers, a 7 week (28 day) rotation, working 5 ten hour days with 3 days off for 4 weeks and then working 4 ten hour days with 4 days off for 3 weeks so that each officer works 2080 hours per year.</p>
<p>For many years, the City has had a goal of having two patrol officers on the street at all times, to protect the public and answer calls for assistance/service. When the Department was seriously understaffed, the Investigator's primary duties were to fill in on open patrol shifts and to act as a back-up for patrol officers on duty. During these years, the Investigator's secondary duty was to investigate crimes and process evidence therefrom.</p>
<p>In 2004, Jim Hughes was appointed Chief of Police upon the retirement of the prior Chief. It should be noted that the language of Article 14 has been the same at least since the 2004 contract was in effect. (U. Exh. 1). In 2005, a second SRO was authorized. The incumbent of that position has consistently worked the same schedule and has had the same duties as the initial SRO. As time passed, the Investigator has worked fewer patrol shifts and had a heavier caseload of criminal investigations.</p>
<p>Officer Wayne Schreiner became Sergeant in 2004. Since this time, Schreiner stated he has done all the scheduling for the Department. Schreiner stated that he staggers the start day of the patrol officers' 7 week rotating shifts so that he can maintain two patrol officers on the street at all times. Schreiner stated that when he took over as scheduler, the SRO (Officer Whitson) would look at the annual schedule in advance and list the holidays he was going to take for each year, so Schreiner never had to deal with the issue. Whitson retired in 2014 and Grievant, Officer Jill Lundquist was selected and approved as an SRO.<ftnote num="4"><para>Lundquist did not testify herein as she was on maternity leave prior to November 29<superscript>th</superscript>. Officer Jarod Cooper, Union Steward, testified herein regarding Lundquist's duties.</para></ftnote> The other SRO is Officer Vandevrede.<ftnote num="5"><para>Officer Adam Vandevrede was not a grievant herein and he did not testify herein.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Lindquist's timesheets for 2015 through October 19, 2016 showed that Lindquist worked 8 hours on Presidents' Day and Veterans' Day, 2015, which occurred on her regularly scheduled work days during the school year. She received time and one-half pay on those days (U. Exh. 2). Those days are not school holidays. For all other contractual holidays that occurred on her regular work days, Lindquist took 8 hours holiday bank time. Lindquist worked a patrol shift during the Summer of 2015, 10 hours a day on the 7 week rotation. In 2016, Lindquist worked the Presidents' Day holiday and received time and one-half pay. For all other holidays that fell during the school year on her regular work days, Lindquist took off using either holiday bank time or accrued vacation time (U. Exh. 3). No evidence was provided to indicate whether Lindquist chose to take these holidays off or whether she was forced to do so.</p>
<p>Schreiner stated that until January 1, 2016, Investigator Tim Broda (the incumbent of the position since 1999) normally worked on the holidays that fell on Broda's regular 10 hour work days on the 7 week rotation, mostly as Investigator, although Schreiner stated he used Broda to fill in the patrol schedule if Schreiner was short on patrol officers on a holiday. Schreiner stated that when the Department was very understaffed he scheduled Broda's workdays that fell on holidays as patrol shifts more than he has in more recent years.</p>
<p>In approximately 2005, Officer Dan Miller became the City's Violent Offender Task Force (VOTF) officer. This position was funded through a State grant and the contribution of three cities, including Sartell. Miller's regular work schedule and hours of work s well as his normal duties were set by the State VOTF Commander. Chief Hughes stated that Miller worked 10 hour days, Tuesday through Friday for a number of years, but he also worked weekends and 8 hour days to meet the needs of the Task Force and that if a holiday fell on one of Miller's work days, he was allowed to work as a plainclothes detective for the City at time and one-half.</p>
<p>For example, on President's Day, Good Friday and Thanksgiving in 2013 and 2014, for part of Labor Day, Veteran's Day and part of Thanksgiving, Miller worked those contractual holidays and received time and one-half pay for the hours worked (U. Exhs. 4 and 5).<ftnote num="6"><para>The City objected to this evidence on relevancy grounds. In my view, this evidence is relevant to flesh out the facts of this case, although I note that the City did not set Miller's work hours or work week, the VOTF Commander did this, which set Miller's position apart from those involved here.</para></ftnote> On all other contractual holidays in 2013 and 2014, Miller either had a regular off day or he took compensatory time or vacation to fulfill his Task Force assigned regular week work schedule. Miller quit in 2015 to take a Deputy Chief position at the County Sheriff's Department.</p>
<p>Investigator Broda's time sheets for the years 2013 through 2015 showed that he worked the following contractual holidays:</p>
<p align="center">President's Day 2013</p>
<p align="center">Good Friday 2013</p>
<p align="center">Memorial Day 2013</p>
<p align="center">Martin Luther, King, Jr. Day 2014</p>
<p align="center">Good Friday 2014</p>
<p align="center">Veteran's Day 2014</p>
<p align="center">Thanksgiving (8 hours) 2014</p>
<p align="center">President's Day 2015</p>
<p align="center">Good Friday 2015</p>
<p align="center">Easter 2015</p>
<p align="center">Memorial Day 2015</p>
<p align="center">Independence Day 2015</p>
<p align="center">Veteran's Day 2015</p>
<p align="center">Thanksgiving 2015</p>
<p align="center">Christmas Day 2015</p>
<p class="continued">On all other workdays that fell on contractual holidays in 2013-2015, Broda either had a regular off day or he voluntarily took vacation or other time off. (U. Exhs. 6-8).</p>
<p>It is undisputed that work on contractual holidays is not specifically assigned, that holidays simply fall on some patrol officers' regular work days due to the 7 week rotation. And when a holiday falls on an officer's regular work day, the patrol officers must either work the day or take time off and get a replacement off-duty officer to work the day in order to patrol the City and cover calls for service. Neither Sergeant Schreiner nor the Chief check the schedule and make special holiday assignments. Chief Hughes stated that answering calls for service are essential services every day of the year 24/7, but that the SRO and Investigator duties are non-essential. Hughes noted that the Investigator can perform his duties during a 40 hour work week and that patrol officers can perform investigatory duties (such as taking witness statements) if necessary on a holiday. Hughes stated that the SRO has no regular work to perform when schools are closed.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>FACTS</b></i></h4>
<p>In 2014, the Department was seriously short-staffed due to SRO Whitson's retirement, and the fact that a City patrol officer was killed and, Chief Hughes stated, due to increases in the residential and commercial populations in the City. Chief Hughes stated fewer requests for time off could be granted in 2014 because the Department was so understaffed and that Summer, the SROs were assigned to work 10 hour days on the 7 week rotation. Hughes stated that it took all of 2015 to fill the three open positions in his Department and that the City Council later authorized him to hire two more officers in 2016, for a total of 17 bargaining unit employees (19 total with the Chief and Deputy Chief included).</p>
<p>Chief Hughes stated that in 2014 and 2015, the number of criminal investigations also grew in the City. Hughes stated that it became difficult and inefficient for Broda to continue to work the 10 hour work days on the 7 week rotation with the other officers because he would have 3 days off for 4 weeks and then 4 days off for 3 weeks which made it harder for him to properly and timely investigate his criminal cases. The Chief stated he decided to make Broda a full-time Investigator and told Broda this in 2015. Hughes wanted to change Broda's work schedule to five 8 hour work days per week, Monday through Friday, in 2015 but he could not do so due to the Department being so understaffed.</p>
<p>On or about March 7, 2016, Chief Hughes issued a memo seeking City officers interested in a part-time Patrol/Investigator assignment, to submit letters of interest and copies of their case work for consideration. The memo described the duties of the position as follows:</p>
<p>Investigator/patrol assignment</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>4 year assignment</p></li>
<li><p>Must not be on probation and at least 2 years with SPD</p></li>
<li><p>Would have use of take home squad &num;1 as outlined in policy</p></li>
<li><p>Would be assigned smart phone and other equipment as needed</p></li>
<li><p>Primary role as PO, but would take on investigations they were needed</p></li>
<li><p>Would work in uniform unless assigned otherwise</p></li>
<li><p>Rotating days off on 10 hr. shift, but work opposite the full-time investigator and have one day overlap with the F/T investigator</p></li>
<li><p>Would handle adult and juvenile cases that were reported from human services or the state as they came in</p></li>
<li><p>Assist with or be primary on cases that are not quick to resolve</p></li>
<li><p>Work cooperatively with FT investigator on cases as needed</p></li>
<li><p>Would take case assignment direction from supervisors</p></li></ol>
<p align="right">(Jt. Exh. 9)</p>
<p class="continued">Union Steward Cooper was the successful applicant for this position. Chief Hughes stated that he intended to have Broda and Cooper working opposite each other as Investigators for greater coverage, but this did not work out because it took all of 2015 to hire the 3 officers the Department had lost.</p>
<p>It is undisputed that the Chief officially changed Broda's schedule to five 8 hour work days, Monday through Friday beginning January 1, 2016. The Chief directed the Deputy Chief to meet with Broda to explain the change in Broda's schedule that would occur starting in 2016. The Deputy Chief had this conversation with Broda prior to December 15, 2015 when this grievance was filed. The Deputy Chief did not testify herein.</p>
<p>At first, Broda did not understand that this schedule change meant that he would have to use holiday or other earned time off for all contractual holidays that fell on his regular 8 hour/day, Monday through Friday work week. Sergeant Schreiner stated herein that management directed him to list Broda and the two SROs as off on vacation whenever a contractual holiday fell on their 8 hour/day, Monday through Friday work week. Schreiner explained that he had to finalize the schedules and since neither Lundquist nor Vandevrede had designated the use of other earned time (like SRO Whitson had done) for holidays, he selected holiday time off for the SROs and for Broda because he has no contractual authority to select vacation and compensatory time use for employees.<ftnote num="7"><para>Schreiner also stated that he sent in Broda's holiday time balance (16 hours) to be paid on the first paycheck in November, 2016 (as required by Article 14). Schreiner stated that this was an unintentional mistake as Schreiner had not realized that Broda wanted to use that 16 hours on Veteran's Day and Thanksgiving, 2016.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>On December 15, 2015, the Union filed the instant grievance on behalf of Investigator Broda and SRO Lundquist, which read in relevant part as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i><b>NATURE OF GRIEVANCE:</b></i></p>
<p class="continued">The City requires employees working non-patrol assignments to take holidays off. The labor agreement provides the employees receive a holiday bank on January 1 of each year to be scheduled like vacation time. The City's requirement causes the employee to subsequently lose the flexibility of scheduling their time off. In addition, the ability to cash out holiday time and earn the holiday premium pay received by other employees is lost and results in a drastic reduction in income.</p>
<p class="continued"><i><b>CONTRACT VIOLATION:</b></i></p>
<p class="continued">The City is violating the Labor Agreement to include, but not limited to Article XIV. Holidays, subsection 14.3 which provides:</p>
<p class="continued">14.3 Holiday Pay. <i>The Employer will credit the officers 120 hours per year (12 holidays &times; 10 hours) in a holiday bank. These hours can be scheduled like vacation. These hours must be used or scheduled by November 15<sup>th</sup> (sic) of each year. All unused and unscheduled hours will be paid out to employees in their fist paycheck of November</i>. Employees who work on a holiday shall receive time and one-half for the hours worked. If the employee is required to work the holiday on a scheduled day off, the employee has the choices described above and shall also receive one (1) additional day off within the following thirty (30) days. Employees required to work overtime during scheduled time off on a holiday will receive time and one-half plus time off for an equivalent compensation rate of two and one-half time.</p>
<p class="continued"><i><b>SETTLEMENT DESIRED:</b></i></p>
<p class="continued">For the City to abide by the terms outlined in the labor agreement and whatever actions required making the employee/employees whole. (emphasis in original)</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">On December 21<sup>st</sup>, the Union added the following to its remedy request herein: &ldquo;return to the current practice outlined in the labor agreement&rdquo;. (Jt. Exh. 2, p. 2)</p>
<p>The City's January 11, 2016 response from the City Administrator read in relevant part as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&hellip;During our discussion, we agreed that the School Resource Officer position should be removed from the grievance since that position has been scheduled in accordance with School District schedules for many years and no change has been made to trigger any grievance for that position. The remaining factor in the grievance involved the Investigator position and whether the schedule change for that position is cause for a grievance related to Article XIV Holidays. After due consideration, I am denying your grievance because it is without merit.</p>
<p class="continued">While not instrumental to my decision, the fact is that the 32 hours of remaining holiday bank provided under the new schedule (120 hours minus eleven scheduled 8-hour holidays) is not far out of line with recent holiday bank hours claimed by Mr. Broda of 70 hours in 2015, 70 hours in 2014 and 40 hours in 2013. In addition, the benefits of every position and every schedule vary, and Investigator Broda's position and schedule result in benefits of an automobile he takes to and from home and work at City expense.</p>
<p class="continued">The City has the authority to schedule personnel under Article 5.1 and Article 10.1, and we have scheduled the Investigator position to work 8 hour days Monday-Friday. When work is required outside of those scheduled hours, overtime is earned. When a holiday occurs during those scheduled hours, the Investigator receives paid holiday leave. The City has no obligation to allow any employee to work on a holiday, and the Investigator position is one that is not required to be on holiday duty for public safety purposes. The grievance is therefore without merit.</p></blockquote>
<p align="right">(Jt. Exh. 5)</p>
<p class="continued">On February 2, the City Personnel Committee denied the grievance as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p align="center">&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Following consideration of all relevant information presented and available to the Committee, it was determined that the grievance rationale you provided does not meet the intent of Article XIV Holidays, nor does it represent past practice.</p>
<p class="continued">The nature of your grievance is stated as &ldquo;The City is breaking a long standing past practice by requiring employees working non-patrol assignments to use banked holiday time on the specific holidays.&rdquo; There is no such long standing past practice and the School Resource Officers have never been scheduled to work holidays other than as required by the School District or the City for public safety purposes. The Investigator position was scheduled as patrol based on the City's needs for a position that combined Investigator, Patrol duties, and covering Patrol officer shortages. As the Department has grown and added officers, management scheduled the Investigator position to work a schedule reflective of the Department's needs for full-time investigation without patrol hours and without relying on the Investigator as a backup officer. There is no past practice for this schedule for the Investigator because the schedule was just implemented and Mr. Broda was informed accordingly.</p>
<p class="continued">The City has the authority to schedule personnel under Articles V and X, and we have scheduled the Investigator position to work 8 hour days Monday-Friday. We have scheduled the School Resource Officers to work a schedule consistent with School needs, and they shift to cover City needs during time periods when School is not in session for extended periods (Christmas break, Summer break, etc.). During those times, they still do not determine their own schedule nor whether they work holidays or not &ndash; they are simply put into the patrol rotation.</p>
<p class="continued">That does not in any way conflict with the holiday bank terms provided in Article XIV, and the Investigator is free to use holiday and vacation hours interchangeably. Article XIV does <i>not</i> entitle any employee to be scheduled to work on any holiday, or numerous positions could make the same demand. Patrol hours are essential to public safety, and employees essential to public safety are therefore scheduled on holidays. The Police Chief, Deputy Chief, School Resource Officers (when not on patrol), Investigator, and Clerical positions are not essential to public safety on holidays and are therefore not scheduled on holidays.</p>
<p class="continued">After hearing the LELS viewpoint and after due consideration and discussion by the Personnel Committee, the Step 3 grievance appeal is denied. We see no way to accommodate one position's demand to work hours not required by the City while not allowing other employees to make the same demands. And that means the City is no longer able to maintain our essential scheduling rights needed to efficiently and fairly provide public services.</p>
<p align="center">&hellip;</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="right">(Jt. Exh. 7)</p>
<p>Both Union witnesses (Cooper and Broda) admitted herein that the City has the right under the contract to set work schedules, including changing Broda's schedule from the 10 hours/day on a 7 week rotation, to 8 hours/day, Monday through Friday, but they urged that Article 14 makes no distinction between officers' assignments and grants all officers 120 hours of holiday time, that all officers are allowed to schedule like vacation. Investigator Broda stated that he had a practice of cashing out 65 to 80 hours of unused holiday pay yearly and that he will lose this opportunity if the grievance is denied.<ftnote num="8"><para>Broda explained that his greater use of earned time off last year will no longer be necessary as his wife will need less care from him due to her current situation.</para></ftnote> Broda stated he could fill out his investigation reports and interview witnesses on holidays.</p>
<p>On the other hand, Chief Hughes stated herein that Broda's Investigator duties are generally non-essential on holidays and can be performed on regular work days; that Broda could be assigned to work a holiday if it were deemed essential to the Department, although no employee is guaranteed work on holidays; that Broda is given an unmarked car to use and he receives 120 hours of holiday time (not 96 hours); that in future Broda could designate the use of other earned time off on holidays if he chose; and that the holiday time bank is separate from and is used differently from other earned time banks. The City Administrator and Chief Hughes stated that Articles 5 and 10 provide that the Chief alone has the reserved management right to set work schedules.</p>
<p>Finally, it is undisputed that in the 2015-17 contract negotiations, no proposals were made by either side to change Article 14 and holidays have been defined as paid non-work days for many years. In 2016, it appears that Broda and Lundquist would have worked on 5 holidays that fell on their 8 hour/day Monday through Friday schedule if they had not chosen or been scheduled off on all holidays.<ftnote num="9"><para>Sergeant Schreiner stated that he schedules the SROs on other assignments if holiday time off would prevent them from completing a full-time schedule, 160 hours work across a 7 week period.</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>Union</b></i></h4>
<p>The Union alleged that the City failed to present any evidence that patrol officers have ever been required to take holidays off and use their holiday break time to receive pay when a holiday has fallen on their regularly scheduled workday. In addition, the Union asserted that the record showed that the City has chosen not to schedule SRO Lindquist to cover patrol shifts on holidays when schools are closed (U. Br., p. 2). The Union noted that for 16 years prior to the change in his schedule in 2016, Officer Broda worked holidays that fell on his regularly scheduled work days if he chose to do so. He was allowed to use his holiday bank time on other days like vacation and he normally saved 65 hours of holiday time so he could receive payouts for this time at the end of the year.</p>
<p>All this changed on January 1, 2016, with no explanation being given to Broda. Broda would have worked at premium pay on New Year's Day, Martin Luther King, Jr. Day, and President's Day 2016, all regularly scheduled work days, but he was instead forced to use holiday time off on these days. From April to September, 2016, Broda's family responsibilities made it impossible to work on holidays that fell on his regular workdays, but from September through the end of 2016, the Union asserted Broda would have worked holidays that fell on his work days.</p>
<p>The Union argued that Section 14.3 of the labor agreement is clear and unambiguous and that the plain meaning of the language must be applied by the Arbitrator. The Union asserted that Section 14.3 allows holiday time to be scheduled and used like vacation which means that only the employee has the right to choose when to use his/her leave and under Article XV the City must make &ldquo;every practical effort&rdquo; to grant it.</p>
<p>Even if the Arbitrator finds the contract language ambiguous, the Union urged that the record evidence of past practice supports the Union's assertions &ldquo;at least with respect to Investigator Broda&rdquo; (U. Br., p. 9). Here, it is undisputed that neither party has tried to negotiate any changes in Article XIV for at least the past 12 years. Broda's working at premium pay on the holidays he chose which fell on his regular work days was the well-known norm for at least this time period. And VOTF Officer Dan Miller did the same as Broda, giving even more support to the Union's past practice argument.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the Union reiterated that Broda and Lindquist were harmed by the 2016 change requiring them to use holiday time on their regular workdays &ndash; the loss of premium pay, the loss of flexibility in use of their time off and the loss of the possibility of a holiday pay cash out at the end of the year. The Union observed that Section 14.3 makes no distinction between part-time and full-time, patrol and non-patrol or essential and non-essential employees &ndash; it refers only to &ldquo;officers&rdquo;. The City has drawn distinctions by its actions herein that are unsupported by the contract.</p>
<p>The City's management rights argument under Article V are not disputed by the Union. The Union noted:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&hellip;The Union does not challenge the City's authority to switch Investigator Broda from 10-hour to an 8-hour shift, or from a seven-week shift rotation to a weekly Monday-to-Friday schedule; nor does the Union challenge the City's right to keep SROs like Officer Lindquist on a Monday-to-Friday schedule during the school year. However, the City's right to set schedules must not be interpreted to allow the City to negate or undermine a benefit clearly set forth elsewhere in the labor agreement, <i>i.e</i>., holiday pay. See <i>How Arbitration Works</i> at 462-464 (arbitral preference to consider the contract as a whole, and to give effect to all portions of the contract). Even where officers' shift schedules are changed, they must retain the rights and privileges spelled out in Section 14.3, including the right to use holiday leave hours &ldquo;like vacation&rdquo;.</p></blockquote>
<p>In addition, the Union asserted that the City's reliance on the Section 14.1 definition of a holiday as &ldquo;a paid non-work day&rdquo; is misplaced. Patrol officers routinely work on holidays that fall on their regular workdays so those days are actually paid work days. The Union urged that when read in context, Section 14.1 &ldquo;does not change the analysis of the accrual and use of holiday leave time&rdquo; (U. Br., p. 13). And the City's argument that Broda and Lindquist could choose to use accrued vacation or comp time on holidays was belied by Sergeant Schreiner's testimony that he was directed to dock their holiday bank for the holidays that fell on their regular workdays.</p>
<p>In these circumstances, the Union requested the Arbitrator to sustain the grievance, order the City to cease and desist &ldquo;&hellip;from requiring these grievants to take days off on holidays that fall on their regularly scheduled work days. The grievants should also be made whole for loss of any holiday leave pay that they have used up since the beginning of 2016 as a result of being required to take holidays off. Finally, the grievants should be made whole for the wages that they have lost, from the beginning of 2016 to the present, as a result of being prevented from working and earning time and a half on holidays that fell on their regularly scheduled work days&rdquo; (U. Br., pp. 13-14).</p>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>City</b></i></h4>
<p>The City asserted that the clear language of the agreement, when read as a whole, requires the Arbitrator to enforce the plain meaning of Section 5.1 that authorizes Chief Hughes to set officers' work schedules and to require that a holiday be treated as a &ldquo;paid non-work day,&rdquo; as stated in Section 14.1. The City urged that &ldquo;treating a holiday that falls on an officer's regularly scheduled work day is an inherent management right which was not bargained away&rdquo; by the City (Er. Br., p. 7).</p>
<p>The City noted that Section 14.3 does not state that holiday hours can &ldquo;only&rdquo; be or must be scheduled like vacation &ndash; the employee is simply given the option to request same and if the needs of the department are otherwise met, the employee's request will be granted and the employee will be paid from his/her holiday bank. Section 14.3 does not constitute or contain a guarantee that an employee will work on a holiday so as to receive premium pay therefor. And Article V Section 5.2 reserves to management the right to &ldquo;modify, establish or eliminate&rdquo; any term and condition of employment that is no specifically established or modified by the contract.</p>
<p>The City urged that holiday pay is not equivalent to vacation leave under the contract. In this regard, the City noted that unlike vacation, 1) holiday hours are not earned, 2) they cannot be carried over to the next year and 3) they are not based on years of service. The City also pointed out that an employee cannot work on his vacation day off and earn premium pay. Here, Article V Section 5.1 and 5.2 clearly reserve to management the right to set the employee's work schedules. And the employee's rights to take vacation time off are subject to the needs of the Department under Article XV, Section 15.2.</p>
<p>The City pointed out that it has consistently exercised its management right to set the schedules of SROs since that position was created in 1995. SRO Lindquist's time sheets for 2016 also showed that she used holiday hours for 3 school district holidays when schools were closed, in accord with the historical treatment of SROs. Officer Broda was treated the same as SROs Lindquist and Vandevrede: None was denied 40 hours' work per week, all were paid properly and all received 120 hours holiday bank hours in 2015. In addition, Grievants Broda and Lindquist were eligible to work overtime and special details or switch with another officer on a holiday to earn premium pay.</p>
<p>The City urged that the Union failed to prove that management bargained away its right to set and change officers' work schedules on this record. Nor did the Union prove that the past treatment of Broda established a true past practice that the parties had mutually agreed to give employees the right to work all holidays that fall on their regularly scheduled work days. Broda's assignment to the 10-hour/28-day rotation over the years was necessary (given staffing challenges) so the Department could cover essential daily patrol duties when needed. There was no design or intention by the City to create a right for Broda to work holidays on his regularly scheduled workdays by scheduling Broda in this manner. The City contended</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&hellip;Simply because during the same time frame the SROs were being told which holidays to work and which to treat as paid non-workdays, while Officer Broda was not being told anything, does not mean the Employer gave up this contractual right of managerial discretion in establishing the work schedule as it applies to Officer Broda. &ldquo;If a right is explicitly provided for in a collective bargaining agreement, then the nonexercise of that right does not amount to a &lsquo;negative past practice&rsquo; and thus become a forfeiture of it when challenged.&rdquo; Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, How Arbitration Works, Eighth Edition (2016), Chap. 12.2. See Weyerhaeuser Co., 121 LA 1192, 1194 (Baroni, 2005) (employer's contracting out of janitorial duties for more than 30 years did not create binding past practice preventing employer's unilateral decision to make production employees responsible for cleaning their own work areas) (attached hereto as Ex. H). (Er. Br., p. 14).</p></blockquote>
<p>The City argued that the Union presented no evidence of retaliation and the record showed that the Chief's decision to change Broda's schedule was entirely reasonable. The City noted that with increased staffing to cover patrol work and with increased criminal investigations in the City, Broda was no longer needed to cover patrol shifts but his full-time attention to his investigations was required. And this investigation work is non-essential because it could be done during his new 40 hours per week schedule. The City urged that there is no need to have Broda typing his reports on holidays at premium pay. In any event, Broda remains eligible to take overtime patrol shifts or special details and to work a holiday if assigned to deal with an investigation. The City concluded that Broda and Lindquist's desire to make premium pay on holidays, without more, is not good enough reason to grant this grievance.<ftnote num="10"><para>The City submitted nine case precedents in support of its arguments. These awards have been considered fully herein .</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>DISCUSSION</b></i></h4>
<p>The place to begin in this case is with a close reading of the effective contract language. Article V, Section 5.1 reserves to the City &ldquo;the full and unrestricted right to operate and manage all staff, facilities and equipment&rdquo; and &ldquo;to establish work schedules&rdquo;. And Section is a broad zipper clause. In addition, Article X, Section 10.1 goes farther and states &ldquo;The sole authority in the work schedule is the Employer's.&rdquo; It is significant that the contract does not guarantee &ldquo;specific number of hours for the normal work day and work week&rdquo;, it only states a range of daily hours to be worked across 160 hours in a 28 day period (Section 10.1). Also, Section 10.4 is a retention of the City's right to establish &ldquo;&hellip;regular workweeks that schedule work on Saturdays, Sundays and/or holidays.&rdquo; Finally, the contract does not contain any guarantee that employees will work any of the 12 holidays listed in Article XIV.</p>
<p>The above describes a broad contractual reservation of management rights. It is in this context that the proper interpretation and application of the disputed language of Section 14.3 must be determined. Looking at Section 14.3, although disputed by the parties herein, several points are clear. First, holidays are not based on tenure time in the Department, the Section applies to all officers without distinction and the Section sets up a separate holiday leave bank (different from sick leave and vacation) of 120 hours per year for all officers, even if they are not on the 10 hours/day 7- week rotation.<ftnote num="11"><para>All officers work 2,080 hours per year, no matter their daily schedule.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Section 14.3 then provides that holiday leave hours &ldquo;<i>can</i> be scheduled like vacation&rdquo;. This language is permissive, not mandatory. In other words, holiday leave does not have to be scheduled like vacation; it <i>may</i> be scheduled as such. Also, the granting of vacation under Sections 14.4 and 15.2 (and holiday leave if requested to be used like vacation) is subject to the staffing needs of the Department.</p>
<p>The Union has argued that Section 14.3 is clear and unambiguous, that it means that only the employee has the right to request the days he/she wishes off on holiday leave time and under Article XV the City must make &ldquo;every practical effort&rdquo; to grant these requests. The Union's argument essentially equates holiday leave with vacation. I do not read Section 14.3 in this way. I find the holiday leave provision here is different from the vacation provision on its face. As stated above, the language of Section 14.3, sentence two is permissive, and Section 14.3 requires employees to schedule or use their annual holiday bank time each year or it will be paid out to them in November. This strongly implies that holiday leave requests can be denied, even after the City has made every practical effort to grant them, and that the employee will not be harmed &ndash; he/she will receive a payout. The fact that holiday leave can be scheduled and used like vacation does not make it vacation leave.</p>
<p>The Union's assertion that Section 14.3 applies to all officers is correct. But it does not follow, based on this record, that the Chief cannot decide what duties are essential and what are non-essential. this kind of judgment is part of what management must do in assessing the needs of the department. Chief Hughes' decision on this point also appears logical and reasonable on this record. Here, the record was undisputed that in 2015, Chief Hughes decided to change Broda's schedule from a part-time Investigator working the 10 hours/day 7-week rotation to a full-time Investigator position working 8 hours/day, Monday through Friday.</p>
<p>Chief Hughes reached this decision based on increased crime in Sartell and the City's agreement to increase patrol officer staff. Hughes stated that these circumstances meant that the City's criminal investigations would be more efficiently conducted Monday through Friday and that investigations could not wait while Broda was off 3 days or 4 days each week across the 7-week patrol rotation. Also, due to the City's authorization of increased patrol officer positions, Hughes stated Broda was no longer needed so often to fill in on patrol.<ftnote num="12"><para>Chief Hughes also filled Broda's part-time Investigator position when he gave Broda the full-time position, supporting evidence of the need for increased investigation hours.</para></ftnote> This evidence, supported by Articles V and X, showed that the Chief's decisions in this area were reasonable and based on business necessity and departmental efficiency, not on any intention to retaliate or discriminate against Broda or to harm him.<ftnote num="13"><para>The evidence regarding Dan Miller is not applicable here. Miller's hours of work were not set by the City &ndash; his hours and his position were dependent on the needs of the Task Force and only a portion of his pay came from the City. These facts show that the City did not control Miller's hours. And in any event, the evidence showed Miller normally worked 10-hour days for the VOTF &ndash; not 8-hour days.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>The Union urged that it proved a past practice that requires this grievance be sustained. Assuming, <i>arguendo</i>, that Article XIV is unclear, and assuming that the Union has proven a true past practice exists, in the circumstances here I do not believe that the Union's past practice evidence is applicable to determine Broda's treatment in his new full-time 8 hour/day Investigator position <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i> holidays. On this point, I note that all of the past practice evidence concerning Broda occurred when he occupied the part-time Investigator position and he was still working the 10-hour/7-week rotation. When Chief Hughes changed Broda's schedule, as he had the authority to do under the contract, he also changed Broda's position to full-time. These actions were taken based on changed circumstances and showed that made the full-time Investigator position is different and distinct from the part-time Investigator position.<ftnote num="14"><para>I need not, and have not ruled upon the Union's past practice evidence as it might apply to the part-time Investigator position in the future. I also do not find the lack of bargaining regarding Article XIV relevant to or probative of the issues in this case, one way or the other.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>The Union has argued that the definition of a holiday as a &ldquo;paid non-work day&rdquo; conflicts with the way things actually work in the Department. This is a general definition. It is true that patrol officers whose regularly scheduled work days fall on a holiday must either perform their essential duties of answering calls and protecting the citizens of Sartell or get another officer to cover for them on their paid non-work day. This is to assure patrol overage 365 days a year. The definition of a holiday, in my view, does not require different conclusions than I have reached herein.</p>
<p>In my opinion, the Union failed to prove that the City waived its management rights to set and change officers' work schedules. Articles V and X are clear reservations of such power. The fact that for approximately 12 years Broda was allowed to work overtime on holidays which fell on his regularly scheduled 10-hour shifts does not mean that Broda thereby obtained the absolute right to work on such holidays. See, e.g. <i>City of St. Cloud and LELS Inc</i>., BMS 09-PA-0887. It is crucial that here there is no contractual guarantee of holiday work. In addition, when Broda's position was changed to full-time Investigator and his shift was changed to 8 hours/day, Monday through Friday, the City also directed that Broda should take off on holidays as part of this new position. As discussed above, I have found these decisions were reasonably based on the needs if the Department. Based on this record, I conclude that no contract violation has occurred regarding full-time Investigator Broda.</p>
<p>I turn now to the grievance allegations concerning SRO Lindquist.<ftnote num="15"><para>No explanation was given why SRO Vandevrede did not join in this grievance.</para></ftnote> The record evidence clearly showed that since its inception in 1995, the SRO position has not worked in the schools when schools are closed and that on longer school breaks, SROs have normally been assigned to work 10 hour shifts on patrol. Scheduling Sergeant Schreiner stated that due to the normal work being defined as 160-hour/on a 28-day cycle when SRO's hours across 28 days would be less than 160 hours when a holiday or school closure occurs, the City has assigned SROs to work 8-hour shifts to make up the time. This has been the consistent approach for SROs for the past 22 years according to the evidence here.</p>
<p>The fact that former SRO Whitson was able to designate the use of other leave when he was off on holidays, does not mean that Lindquist or Broda were discriminated against. The record here showed that Whitson made his requests for other leave in advance of the schedule being finalized by Schreiner. Chief Hughes stated herein that Broda and Lindquist could do as Whitson had done in the future if they did so in advance of Schreiner's schedule finalization.</p>
<p>The Union asserted in its brief at page 2 that the City chose not to schedule SRO Lindquist to cover patrol shifts on holidays when schools are closed. The record does not contain sufficient evidence to support this assertion. Lindquist worked two contractual holidays in 2015 and a 10-hour shift rotation during the summer of 2015, and she worked one holiday in 2016 and regular 8-hour shifts during that summer.<ftnote num="16"><para>No explanation was given for this assignment.</para></ftnote> Lindquist worked as SRO during the 2016-17 school year before she left on maternity leave in October, 2016. Officer Cooper's testimony regarding Lindquist and the relevant documentary evidence are insufficient to show that Lindquist was retaliated or discriminated against or that she was treated any differently from the SROs that came before her.</p>
<p>In all of these circumstances, and based upon all the evidence and argument herein, I issue the following</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>AWARD</i></h4>
<p>The City did not violate Section 14.3 by requiring full-time Investigator Tim Broda to take days off on holidays that coincided with his regularly scheduled work days and to use holiday bank hours on those days.<ftnote num="17"><para>As is clear from the Chiefs testimony herein, Broda and SRO Lindquist will be able to use other accrued leave on a holiday if they designate it in advance.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>The City did not violate Section 14.3 by requiring SRO Lindquist to take days off on holidays that coincided with her regularly scheduled work days and to use holiday bank time on those days.</p>
<p>The grievance is therefore denied and dismissed in its entirety.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>