<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the matter of arbitration between: UTILITY WORKERS UNION OF AMERICA, LOCAL 600 and DUKE ENERGY OHIO, INC. and DUKE ENERGY KENTUCKY, INC.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>October 1, 2016.</p>
<p>Mitchell B. Goldberg, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>OPINION AND AWARD</b></h4>
<h4 align="left">I. <i>Introduction and Background.</i></h4>
<p>This is a labor arbitration proceeding conducted under the terms and conditions set forth in the parties' collective bargaining agreement (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo;) that expired on March 31, 2015. The Union filed a grievance on behalf of Patty Memering (&ldquo;Grievant&rdquo;) on October 2, 2014 alleging that the Company breached the CBA terms by permitting an exempt employee to perform bargaining unit work. The Company denied the grievance throughout each step and the matter proceeded to arbitration on April 26, 2016 and July 7, 2016 at the Company's offices. A reporter transcribed the proceeding and prepared the official record.</p>
<p>The parties offered testimonial evidence and submitted documentary exhibits. Witnesses were examined and cross-examined. Post-hearing briefs were filed after all of the evidence was received. The parties stipulated that all procedural and substantive requirements of the grievance/arbitration procedures and CBA were complied with that are necessary to bring this matter to a final and binding resolution.</p>
<h4 align="left">II. <i>Contract Provisions.</i></h4>
<p class="continued">Article I, Section 1(a) states:</p>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Company hereby recognizes the Union during the term of this Agreement as the sole and exclusive representative of all regular full-time and part-time employees of the occupational classifications in the units defined as &ldquo;The Office, Clerical and Technical Unit&rdquo; and &ldquo;The Residual Unit,&rdquo; &hellip;. The units so defined shall retain jurisdiction over such work as was normally performed by them prior to this Agreement but such jurisdiction shall not be expanded except by mutual agreement of the parties hereto or through due processes under the National Labor Relations Act.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Section 2 (c) provides for the Company's management rights, that include:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&hellip; the direction of the working forces, the determination of the number of men it will employ or retain in each classification, and the right to hire &hellip; transfer &lsqb;employees&rsqb;.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Section 2 (d) provides:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The above rights of Management are not all-inclusive, but indicate the type of matters or rights which belong to and are inherent to Management. Any of the rights, powers, and authority the Company had prior to entering this Agreement are retained by the Company, except as expressly and specifically abridged, delegated, granted or modified by this &lsqb;CBA&rsqb;.</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="left">III. <i>Facts.</i></h4>
<p align="center">The Grievant is employed in the bargaining unit job classification of Sr. T&amp;D Design Technician (&ldquo;STDT&rdquo;). Her job description sets for the following duties:</p>
<p>&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p>2. Serves as the primary technical contact for the Company with ODOT, KTC, City, County, and Township engineers, and their contractors and/or their consultants for relocation of Company overhead and underground transmission and distribution electric facilities for road improvements, bridge replacement, sewer, water and various other projects initiated by governmental entities or civic groups.</p>
<p>3. Works with and advises public authorities, other utilities, contractors consultants, and customers, or their agents, on Company policies and procedures associated with transmission and distribution electric facilities.</p>
<p>4. Utilizes engineering information from road prints, sewer and water, etc. furnishes in CAD format or paper drawings, to design electric facility rearrangement on large and/or complex projects.</p>
<p>5. Prepares various construction drawings in CAD format to meet the requirements of governmental entities, other utilities, and companies and other customers. These designs provide for the installation, removal and relocation of overhead and underground transmission and distribution facilities in accordance with Company standards, National Electrical Safety Code and other regulatory codes.</p>
<p>6. Prepares the necessary estimates, material lists, billing, and other forms required by law for reimbursement by federal, state, and local governments for work performed by the Company, as applicable.</p>
<p>7. Monitors and follows up on customer payments on assigned projects.</p>
<p>8. Develops the technical details and performs the engineering calculations required for the extension, rearrangement, replacement or maintenance of overhead and underground electric facilities.</p>
<p>9. Assists engineers and supervisors in the preparation of engineering reports, system designs, estimates, studies, and standards.</p>
<p>10. Acts as project liaison to governmental entities, other utilities, contractors, consultants, and customers, or their agents, and various Company personnel to coordinate the timely completion of projects.</p>
<p>11. Prepares construction drawings for large and/or complex projects involving manholes, vaults, underground cable and conduit systems, transmission pole lines, and/or distribution pole lines by using verbal and written instructions, reference drawings, CAD and other computer engineering programs, marked prints, and sketches. Works out details within established standards for clearance, location and strength requirements.</p>
<p>12. Assists engineers in the design and prepares construction drawings for transmission tower lines.</p>
<p>13. Prepares electric standard clearance drawings using approved standards and codes.</p>
<p>&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p>The Company created a new non-bargaining unit position called Senior Engineering Technologist (&ldquo;SET&rdquo;). The position was awarded to Tim Meyer, a former STDT and bargaining unit member, effective September 1, 2014. The job description for this position states that this position is a 4th level of the non-Engineer degreed technical support role job classification and is considered the Career level for the job hierarchy. SETs provide technical expertise to solve more complex problems, and leadership skills to manage work in a specific area of expertise, with minimal supervision. Incumbents are expected to develop advanced skills and to have the ability to work independently with increased latitude for unreviewed work.</p>
<p>Fifteen percent of an SET's time is to provide subject matter technical expertise and guidance in the identification, analysis and resolution of problems in area of expertise. Fifteen percent of the SET's time is to ensure accomplishment of business goals and objectives through effective planning, organizing, estimating, scheduling and monitoring of work activities. Fifteen percent of time is spent independently preparing thorough and accurate technical reports, correspondence, documentation, calculations and sketches. Fifteen percent of time is spent conducting engineering and related studies.</p>
<p>For many years, the STDTs performed their pole and line relocation work for higher voltage lines of 69kv and higher, called transmission work, and work for relocation of lines involving lower voltage, lower than 69kv, called distribution work. The Union contends that Tim Meyer, who accepted the SET non-bargaining unit position began performing and continues to perform the same work as he performed when he was a bargaining unit member in the STDT job, except that his work is for the relocation of only transmission lines, those 69kv and above. That transmission work was substantially removed from the bargaining unit, and the bargaining now performs mostly distribution relocation work.</p>
<p>The Company denies that it violated the CBA by creating the new position and by permitting him to perform some transmission relocation work, that he performed for about 15&percnt; or less of his time when he was a STDT.<ftnote num="1"><para>The percentage is sometimes referred to as 15&percnt; in the record, or 13&percnt;. Regardless of the different percentage, both percentages are determined to be more than de minimus in the below discussion and findings.</para></ftnote> He now spends 100&percnt; of his time working on transmission line projects throughout Kentucky and Ohio. He has minimal supervision while performing largely unreviewed work. He uses his expertise to solve complex problems. His work involves leadership and management skills. The Company contends that the bargaining unit has not been eroded by the creation of the SET job and the performance of transmission relocation work that he provided when he was an STDT. That work is merely incidental to his primary duty of designing and related work necessary to build electric transmission lines in Ohio and Kentucky.</p>
<h4 align="left">IV. <i>Discussion and Findings.</i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i>Contract Interpretation Standards and Proof</i></h4>
<p class="continued">The Union bears the burden to prove by a preponderance of the evidence that its interpretation of the contract language is the most probable reflection of the parties&rsquo; intent at the time the CBA was executed. The arbitrator's responsibility is to determine and carry out the parties&rsquo; mutual intent. A writing is unambiguous where the meaning can be determined without more than examining the facts and reading the language. The so called &ldquo;plain meaning&rdquo; may be drawn from the document with the assistance of plain/dictionary definitions and other accepted rules of construction. The contract language may be determined to be ambiguous when the language is reasonably susceptible to more than one meaning. In that case, the arbitrator may rely on other interpretative aids such as bargaining history, industry customs, or the parties&rsquo; past practices.</p>
<p>I find that the language of Article I is clear and straightforward in terms of reconciling the parties intent as between the Company's broad management rights in Sections 2 (c)(d) with the clear jurisdictional bargaining unit work that is described and preserved in Section 1 as &ldquo;such work as was normally performed by &lsqb;the unit employees&rsqb; prior to this Agreement.&rdquo; The language prohibits any expansion of this prior bargaining unit work except and unless the expansion is done through mutual agreement or by Labor Act processes, which may come into effect if the parties reach impasse over their negotiations. All language in a CBA should be considered and reconciled to determine the parties' intent, whether it is in the recognition clause or the management rights clause.</p>
<p>I find that the recognition clause expressly limits any &ldquo;expansion&rdquo; of the bargaining unit work that was being done when the contract was agreed upon. I find also that prohibiting any expansion without agreement after clearly fixing the work that was presently being done as unit work implies that whatever work was being done could not be reduced, decreased or removed from the unit and transferred to non-bargaining unit personnel without mutual negotiations and agreement. I agree that the language as written does not contain the exact words of a prohibition against decreasing the described unit work as all work being done at the time of the contract. However, to read the clause as permitting the Company to usurp that described work as part of its management rights after it is clearly fixed and described the work as unit work, while the Company can prohibit any expansion, could not reasonably have been within the parties' mutual intent. Accordingly, I find that the Company cannot contract or decrease the work that was being done by the unit without a mutual agreement authorizing it to do so.</p>
<p>This work preservation language, however, has certain limits. Arbitrators have permitted management to remove certain bargaining unit work in cases where there is no preservation language when it is found that:</p>
<ul type="none">
<li><p>&ast;The quantity of work is minor or de minimus;</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;The work is supervisory or managerial in nature;</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;The work assignment is temporary or for a special purpose or need;</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;The work is not covered by the contract</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;The work is experimental;</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;Under past practice the work was not exclusively performed by the bargaining unit;</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;The transfer (of the work) was caused by a reorganization or change in work methods or processes;</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;There is a change in the character of the work;</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;Automation or a technological change was involved;</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;An emergency is involved;</p></li>
<li><p>&ast;Some other special situation or need is involved.<ftnote num="2"><para><italic>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, How Arbitration Works</italic>, 6<superscript>th</superscript> Ed., Alan Miles Ruben, Editor-in-Chief, BNA, pp. 758-759 (2003).</para></ftnote></p></li></ul>
<p>Even when, as in this case, there is the recognition and intention to restrict the performance of unit work to unit employees, the restrictions sometimes are not absolute. Arbitrators have nevertheless permitted the work assignments of such work to employees outside the unit and/or to supervisory employees where (1) it is de minimus; (2) where the work is supervisory in nature; (3) when there is an emergency; (4) because of a company reorganization; or (4) some other justification. Arbitrators who have permitted the assignments decide the issue on a case-by-case basis, and sometimes interpret the prohibitory clause narrowly.<ftnote num="3"><para>Id. at 760-763.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Notwithstanding my finding that the recognition clause is a work preservation clause and a job security element inserted for the benefit of the bargaining unit and its members, I will attempt to examine the evidence related to any applicable exceptions to the prohibition based upon the particular facts and circumstances in this record.</p>
<h4 align="left">V. <i>The Applicable Factors and Findings Based Upon This Record.</i></h4>
<p>Reassigning all of the 69kv work previously performed by the STDT unit workers to a non-unit employee is more than a de minimus reassignment. It was a permanent reassignment, not a temporary one. There is no evidence that the Company acted in bad faith in removing this work. It did it based upon what it believed was a legitimate business reason in its own best interests. Whether it was &ldquo;compelling&rdquo; or not is a disputed issue.</p>
<p>I disagree with the Company's view that the reduction of the described bargaining unit work had no negative impact upon the unit, because there was no real or detrimental effect upon the size of the unit. This argument must be viewed together with the amount of work that was removed, and both the long term and short term effects of the decision upon the strength and size of the bargaining unit. Before the reassignment, 69kv work was being done by a number of STDTs who were able to perform the work. They spent 87&percnt; of their time working on distribution lines, but about 13&percnt; of time working on transmission lines (69kv and above). The transfer of all of their transmission line work to one non-bargaining unit newly created position means that the existing work of the STDTs has been decreased by some material degree, thereby lessening the need to hire more STDTs to perform that work in the future.<ftnote num="4"><para>The Union is not asking for economic relief in the nature of loss pay that otherwise would have been paid to the unit STDTs, or lost overtime opportunities. Nevertheless, it is clear that the 69kv work that Meyer performed in his new position would have been performed by STDTs, but for the Company's decision to remove 69kv transmission work from the unit.</para></ftnote> Mr. Meyer spent about 13&percnt; of his time as a STDT working on 69kv projects, the rest was on distribution lines. He now spends 65-70&percnt; of his time as a SET on 69kv work, meaning that he is doing virtually all the work of the STDTs who were performing some material amount of their time on 69kv work. From a purely economic or financial standpoint, less needed hires in the future for this removed work would produce less needed bargaining unit members, less than would otherwise be the case if the removed work stayed in the unit.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>The Relationships Between the Supervision of STDTs and SETs</i></h4>
<p>Meyer stated that when he was an STDT he worked in close proximity to his supervisor and had all of his work reviewed, but now that he is an SET, he has less supervision. He interacts with his supervisor who is located in Plainfield, Indiana only once a week, and only talks with him on a biweekly basis. My understanding of the evidence is that the amount of supervision over any particular STDT depends upon that employee's skills and experience. Both Meyer and Wright testified that supervisors and managers rarely checked their work as STDTS, or made substantive revisions. They were permitted to exercise considerable judgment depending upon the particular supervisor. The STDTs were not subject to extensive day-to-day supervision, and could set their own priorities (Tr. 301, 334-335). I agree, from examining the evidence, that Mr. Meyer has taken on more complex work and responsibilities with his SET dob description, but in terms of performing the 69kv work that he now does most of the time, that work was the same work, or substantially the same work he previously performed as an STDT, and the work that other STDTs performed relative to 69kv transmission work. Notwithstanding Mr. Meyer's other SET duties and responsibilities set forth in his job description, which are not disputed, the bargaining unit work that was removed from the STDTs and assigned to him was not &ldquo;relatively minor,&rdquo; nor merely incidental and complimentary to his new job.&rdquo;<ftnote num="5"><para>These differences distinguish the facts in this case from those decided by Arbitrator Mancini, in another arbitration between these parties. Other distinguishing facts include the finding by the arbitrator that the unit work performed by the non-unit employee was merely incidental to his primary analytical functions and only supportive to his Data Analyst non-unit job.</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="center"><i>New and Different Training and Technology</i></h4>
<p>The Company contends that the SET job is one that is completely different from the work that he performed as an STDT in the sense that his work involves more technical expertise and guidance in the identification, analysis and resolution of problems in his work involving 69kv transmission lines and relocation of those lines. He has received specialized training in the use of PLS-CADD, PLS-POLE along with Li-Dar Data that enables him to conduct conflict analysis of all submissions for road improvement projects involving transmission line facilities. PLS-CADD allows for a 3D line model which results in a greater analysis of the properties of both the poles and conductors. These upgraded technological software systems and methods were not available to him when he worked as an STDT.</p>
<p>The PLS-CADD upgraded software program was not presented as a basis for creating the new non-bargaining unit position. Mr. Meyer took his training in March 2015 well after the decisions were made to create the new position, and after he worked in his position for some 6 months. The training involved a 3 and<sup>1</sup>/<sub>2</sub> day course. Mr. Meyer did not begin using the new software until February 2016. As of the hearing date, he had not released any jobs in which he prepared his work using PLS-CADD.</p>
<p>LiDar Data is used for light detection and ranging. It is a more accurate mapping of utility poles, topographical features and other aspects of the terrain by using air surveillance over the areas in which the power lines are located. Meyer stated that it is used exclusively with PLS-CADD, but Mr. Wright has used LiDar Data on two occasions without using PLS-CADD. LiDar is used for transmission lines and not for distribution lines. This begs the question of whether training on all of this newer technology would have, or could have been provided to STDTs who performed 69kv transmission work if the work remained bargaining unit work. The technology for performing the transmission design work had constantly been upgraded, from hand drawings, to MicroStation CAD, to AutoCAD, and now to PLS-CADD. Mr. Wright testified that one of his goals addressed with his supervisor includes training on PLS-CADD (Tr. 199), which leads one to believe if the 69kv work remained with Wright and other STDTs, they would have received the upgraded training for working with the new technology.</p>
<p>Arbitrator Szuter considered somewhat similar facts regarding upgraded technology as an alleged basis for removing work from a bargaining unit. Production workers in the Roll Grinder classification were denied their opportunities to work on a new machine that performed their same grinding work using a laser, which substantially increased the production of their steel rolls. The work ceased being developmental or experimental, but the grinder operators were not given the work on the new LaserMatte machine. Instead, the employer wanted to give this work to a salaried employee, based upon the contention that the work was very complex, might never become full-time, and involved a very &ldquo;contentious&rdquo; and exacting process. The employer, however, did not deny that his existing roller-grinders could through training perform this new type of grinding work. The arbitrator found, however, that the work was nevertheless &ldquo;production work&rdquo; under the CBA. He found that a provision that required the Company to establish a new job because of a technology change, or an existing job that was radically changed due to technological improvements must be submitted to the Union for review as to classification and job description, and that disputes would be subject to the grievance procedure. He held that the work was no longer negligible or experimental, and that the employer violated the CBA by not assigning this new type of laser grinder work to the bargaining unit Roller Grinder classification.<ftnote num="6"><para><italic>Greer Steel Company and USW Local 2737-2</italic>, 136 LA 257 (Szuter, 2016).</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="center"><i>Other Job Duties</i></h4>
<p>In terms of other job duties performed by SETs, Meyer does not need to obtain approval on project designs, on project costs over &dollar;50,000, or on releasing jobs to construction. He has authority to schedule construction projects, to prioritize construction schedules, to change schedules, and he has other duties relative to his work on 69kv and above transmission lines. There is evidence, however, with respect to Mr. Wright and other STDTs, that they design projects, prepare construction drawings, and release projects for construction for both 69kv transmission lines and distribution lines. Regardless of these factual issues, the question remains whether the SET can as a practical matter retain his exclusive right to approve designs, schedule, prioritize or change schedules for lines above 69kv, but permit STDTs to do similar work as they did before for 69kv lines.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>The Company's Business Reason</i></h4>
<p>The Company decided to separate the transmission organization and the distribution organization into separate departments in 2012 after the merger between Duke Energy and Progress Energy. The Company wanted more clear lines of business for financial purposes, and somewhat for technical requirements that are needed for higher voltage work (Tr. 257-258). There is no evidence that the Company's decision was anything other than an honest exercise of its business judgment. While there is little if any dispute between the parties as to the underlying business reasons for separating out the transmission work and the distribution work, there is little that one can determine from the evidentiary record about any possible adjustments or management accommodations that reasonably could be made to accomplish the business goals and judgments, and at the same time keep and protect the work 69kv work done by the bargaining unit as their work. This is because management has focused upon its belief that its broad management rights authorize its decision, and that the language retaining the Union's jurisdiction over the 69kv work must be subservient to its management rights. While it is true that arbitrators have deferred to management decisions in the cases cited by the Company, it is also true that their awards were based upon reasons substantially different than the facts in this record.</p>
<p>For example, in <i>Matanuska Electric Assn</i>., arbitrator Landau considered the employer's acknowledgement the SET's work was bargaining unit work, but the performance of this work by a non-bargaining unit engineer was &ldquo;minimal in scope and did not become part of his normal work load.&rdquo;<ftnote num="7"><para><italic>Matanuska Electric Assn</italic>., 111 LA 596, 600 (Landau, 1998).</para></ftnote> Arbitrator Davey's award involved a foreman doing bargaining unit work for 2 days when the unit worker was absent and no available unit worker was available.<ftnote num="8"><para><italic>John Deere Waterloo Tractor Works</italic>, 22 LA 545, 546 (Davey, 1954) (Production work by supervisor was necessary due to production difficulties combined with the absence of the unit member and unavailability of another unit member).</para></ftnote> Arbitrator Abrams' award in <i>Superior Dairy, Inc</i>. involved the creation of a new non-bargaining unit position, but the CBA did not have a work jurisdiction retention clause like Article I, Section 1(a). Even without this clause, and broad management rights, however, the arbitrator justified the decision based upon the fact that only &ldquo;some&rdquo; bargaining unit work was lost, the work was only &ldquo;a very minor part of the new job&rdquo; and the work had been done on previous occasions by both unit and non-unit employees.<ftnote num="9"><para><italic>Superior Dairy, Inc</italic>., 69 LA 594, 598 (Abrams, 1977).</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Accordingly, I find, based upon the evidence in this record that the re-assignment of the subject 69kv transmission work from the bargaining unit to an employee outside the unit violated the CBA, specifically Section 1(a) that clearly retains the Union's jurisdiction over this work, because it was partof the work that was normally performed by its unit members prior to the execution of the CBA.</p>
<h4 align="left">VI. <i>Award.</i></h4>
<p>The grievance is sustained. The work performed by the STDT bargaining unit members described above in their job description and in this record as 69kv transmission work, work that was done prior to the execution of the CBA, but re-assigned to the SET, shall be returned to the bargaining unit members.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>