<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF THE ARBITRATION BETWEEN HOCKING TECHNICAL COLLEGE AND OHIO PATROLMEN'S BENEVOLENT ASSOCIATION</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS No. 16-54566-6</p>
<p>September 12, 2016.</p>
<p>Christopher E. Miles, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="left">I. <i>BACKGROUND</i></h4>
<p>The grievance considered herein was filed by the Ohio Patrolmen's Benevolent Association (hereinafter referred to as the &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) on behalf of Adam Ditmer, Trent Eskey, and Brittany Eubanks who are employed as Police Officers by Hocking Technical College (hereinafter referred to as the &ldquo;College&rdquo;). The Official Grievance Form, dated March 1, 2016 alleged violations of the parties' collective bargaining agreement,<ftnote num="1"><para>Full-Time Police Officers' and Police Sergeants' Agreement between Hocking Technical College and Ohio Patrolmen's Benevolent Association, effective July 1, 2015 through December 31, 2017 (hereinafter referred to as the <quote>Agreement</quote>).</para></ftnote> as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Violation A: In violation of Article VII.D of the Collective Bargaining Agreement, Officer Ditmer was denied eight hours of emergency pay for his shift/hours worked on 2/09/16 from 11p to 7a and was denied eight hours of emergency pay for his shift/hours worked on 1/23/16 from 3p to 7a. Payroll inquiry forms for such payment have been appropriately submitted but were denied on Feb. 22, 2016.</p>
<p class="continued">Violation B: In violation of Article VII.D of the Collective Bargaining Agreement, Officer Eskey was denied eight hours of emergency pay for his shift/hours worked on 2/09/16 from 3p to 11p and was denied eight hours of emergency pay for his shift/hours worked on 1/24/16 from 11p to 7a. Payroll inquiry forms for such payment have been appropriately submitted but were denied on Feb. 22, 2016.</p>
<p class="continued">Violation C: In violation of Article VII.D of the Collective Bargaining Agreement, Officer Eubanks was denied eight hours of emergency pay for her shift/hours worked on 2/09/16 from 7a to 3p and was denied eight hours of emergency pay for her shift/hours worked on 1/24/16 from 7a to 3p. Payroll inquiry forms for such payment have been appropriately submitted but were denied on Feb. 22, 2016.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">As the Adjustment/Remedy, the Union requested that the College pay each of the Officers eight hours of emergency pay for the shift/hours worked on 2/09/16 and also an additional eight hours of emergency pay for the shift/hours worked on January 23 or January 24, 2016, as applicable.</p>
<p>In denying the grievance, the College relied upon its position that Article VII.D &ldquo;applies when the college is closed due to an emergency and not open to the public. On the dates in question, the College was not closed and open to the public.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Having been unable to resolve the case, the Union appealed the grievance to arbitration and the undersigned was selected to hear and decide the issue. A hearing was conducted in Nelsonville, Ohio on June 28, 2016, at which time, the parties were afforded full opportunity to present testimony and evidence, to cross-examine the witnesses, all of whom were sworn, and to make arguments in support of their respective positions. Upon receipt and exchange of the parties' post-hearing briefs on July 22, 2016, the record in this case was closed.</p>
<h4 align="left">II. <i>SUMMARY OF THE TESTIMONY AND EVIDENCE</i></h4>
<p>Ms. Brittany Eubanks testified that she has been a Police Officer since 2011. She was hired by the College in 2012 as a part time officer and was made full time in 2013. She noted that the College has four campuses and the Full Time Officers work eight hour shifts five days a week which are supplemented by two part time officers. Officer Eubanks recalled that January 23 and 24, 2016 were Saturday and Sunday and an email was sent to all college employees notifying them that all classes and events were closed for January 23 and 24 due to adverse weather conditions. She noted that she was scheduled to work the 7 am to 3 pm shift on January 24 and Mr. Eskey was scheduled to work 11 pm to 7 am. She stated that Mr. Ditmer was scheduled to work from 3 pm to 11 pm on January 23.</p>
<p>According to Ms. Eubanks, Officers can request eight hours of pay or eight hours of comp time for working during an emergency closing. She identified the Payroll Inquiry Forms that she submitted regarding January 24 and on February 9, 2016. She indicated that Officer Eskey and Officer Ditmer requested eight hours of additional pay for working on January 24 and February 9. Ms. Eubanks pointed out that the Union filed a grievance on behalf of the Officers when their requests were denied and when the College denied the grievance, it was appealed to arbitration. Reference was made to a prior grievance settlement concerning emergency closing pay pursuant to Article VII.D.</p>
<p>Dr. Betty Young testified that she is the President of the College, having come there as Interim President a year earlier to address some financial difficulties of the College. There are about 3,000 students attending the main campus and 800 of them are resident students. The Perry County campus has two full time employees, while Lake Snowden and the Logan campuses are learning centers. All campuses have an agreement with the area law enforcement agencies to respond if needed. With regard to the grievance, Dr. Young asserted that there is a difference between the campus closing and cancellation of classes. She said the Police Officers receive emergency closing pay when the campus is closed. Dr. Young explained the prior grievance settlement and why the Officers were paid at that time.</p>
<p>Dr. Young stated that there are some Saturday classes but not any classes on Sunday. She acknowledged that all classes and events were cancelled on the two dates in question. She did not recall the reason but suggested that it could have been due to snow; i.e., adverse weather conditions. She indicated that cancelling classes does not mean that the employees don't have to come to work. She added that business operations are interrupted all the time and she gave a few examples. Dr. Young recalled that there was a basketball game that had to be rescheduled.</p>
<h4 align="left">III. <i>RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF THE AGREEMENT</i></h4>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE VII PAY PRACTICES</h4>
<h4 align="left">VII.D. Emergency Closing</h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">When normal business operations of the College are interrupted due to an emergency, employees shall be required to work as scheduled. Employees working any amount of time from commencement of the deviation of normal operations to the start of next day on such day shall receive additional hours of compensatory time or regular pay on an hour by hour basis, up to a maximum of eight (8) hours. Accrual of compensatory time during Emergency Closings will not be limited by the 40 hour accrual maximum (set forth in Article VII.B.4.D.) but cannot be rolled over to the next fiscal year.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="left">IV. <i>CONTENTIONS OF THE PARTIES</i></h4>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>Union</i></h4>
<p>The Union contends that the language of Article VII.D of the Agreement is plain and clear that the Police Department is a 24/7 operation and employees working any amount of time from the commencement of the &ldquo;deviation of normal operations&rdquo; to the start of the next day shall receive additional hours of compensatory time or regular pay on an hour by hour basis, up to a maximum of eight hours. According to the Union, on January 23 and 24, and February 9, 2016, all classes and events at all of the College's campuses were cancelled due to adverse weather conditions. It asserts that a Level 3 snow emergency, the most serious level in Ohio, was declared and on February 9, the College warned all faculty and staff to use their best judgment to arrive at work due to the inclement weather conditions. The Union rejects the College's claim that the additional pay only applies when it is &ldquo;closed due to an emergency and not open to the public&rdquo; and submits that no such requirement is included in the language. The Union asserts that if the College wishes to apply such a standard for payment; i.e., that the College be closed in order for the Officers to receive additional payment, then the language must be negotiated through the bargaining process and it cannot be achieved through arbitration.</p>
<p>Based upon the foregoing, the Union requests that the grievance be sustained and that Officer Ditmer be paid an additional 16 hours of pay; Officer Eskey be paid an additional 16 hours of pay, and Officer Eubanks be granted eight hours of compensatory time and be paid an additional eight hours of pay. In addition, the Union requests that the Arbitrator's fee be paid by the College as the losing party.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>College</i></h4>
<p>The College contends that the purpose of the Emergency Closing clause is to compensate the 24/7 employees who show up when nobody else does. It asserts that the Union is asking for additional pay when everyone else is working. The College points out that Article VII.D requires more than a cancellation of classes; it also requires an interruption of &ldquo;business operations&rdquo; due to an &ldquo;emergency.&rdquo; In this regard, the College maintains that a cancellation of classes due to the weather forecast does not meet this standard because the business operations continued and employees were expected to report for work. According to the College, acceptance of the Union's interpretation of Article VII.D would replace &ldquo;business operations&rdquo; with &ldquo;classroom instruction&rdquo; and shift the focus from basing emergency closure pay on what's happening with employees to what's happening with students and should not be permitted.</p>
<p>Based upon the foregoing reasons, the College maintains that the grievances should be denied.</p>
<h4 align="left">VI. <i>DISCUSSION AND FINDINGS</i></h4>
<p>The issue to be resolved herein is whether the Officers who worked on January 23 and 24, and February 9, 2016 are entitled to additional pay under the provisions of Article VII.D. Although the provision is titled &ldquo;Emergency Closing&rdquo;, the language refers to occasions when &ldquo;normal business operations of the College are interrupted due to an emergency&rdquo; and provides that employees who are scheduled to work for any portion of time during the deviation of normal operations &ldquo;shall receive additional hours of compensatory time or regular pay on an hour by hour basis, up to a maximum of eight (8) hours.&rdquo; The question which must be answered is whether on January 23 and 24 and February 9, 2016, the &ldquo;normal business operations&rdquo; of the College were &ldquo;interrupted due to an emergency.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The three Grievants are full time Police Officers who were scheduled to work a total of 16 hours during the three days in question. Officer Ditmer and Officer Eskey both requested to be paid an additional 16 hours of pay, while Officer Eubanks requested to be granted eight hours of compensatory time and be paid an additional eight hours of pay. Although the College was not &ldquo;closed&rdquo;, all classes and events were cancelled for the days in question. In my opinion, that clearly resulted in an interruption or deviation of the normal business operations at the College. The language set forth in the pertinent provision must be read as a whole and a reasonable interpretation, based upon the plain meaning of the words used, must be made. As noted, the heading of Article VII.D. is &ldquo;Emergency Closing&rdquo;, but nowhere within that provision are the words &ldquo;closing&rdquo; or &ldquo;closed&rdquo; set forth and, there is nothing about the College being closed to the public. The section refers to the interruption of normal business operations or a deviation of normal operations due to an emergency. In this regard, the generally accepted definitions of the relevant words used in Article VII.D are as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i>Emergency</i>: a serious, unexpected, and often dangerous situation requiring immediate action (Oxford Dictionary);</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Normal</i>: conforming to a type, standard, or regular pattern (Merriam-Webster);</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Operation</i>: the fact or condition of functioning or being active (Oxford Dictionary);</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Interruption</i>: to break the continuity or conformity of (Free Online Dictionary); and</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Deviation</i>: the action of departing from an established course or accepted standard (Oxford Dictionary).</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">With respect to this case, adverse weather conditions, i.e., an act of God, may create an emergency situation. Moreover, the cancellation of classes and events clearly represents an interruption in the normal business operations or a deviation from the normal operations of the College. Normally, they have classes and normally they have events. The intent of the provision, in my view, is to provide additional compensation for the Police Officers who are required to work despite the emergency condition.</p>
<p>Consequently, the grievance filed on behalf of the three Officers is sustained and the College is directed to pay an additional 16 hours of pay to Officer Ditmer and Officer Eskey. Officer Eubanks shall be paid an additional eight hours of pay and granted eight hours of compensatory time, as requested.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>AWARD</i></h4>
<p>The grievance filed on behalf of Officers Adam Ditmer, Trent Eskey, and Brittany Eubanks is sustained. Based upon the particular circumstances presented in this case, it is found that the Grievants were entitled to additional pay pursuant to the provisions of Article VII.D of the Agreement when they worked 16 addition hours during January 23 and 24 and on February 9, 2016 when classes and events were cancelled due to adverse weather conditions which resulted in an interruption or deviation of normal business operations.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>