<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>DAVE GILLICK, RICK SWANSON, BRETT LAMPKIN, VINCE PATRICO and JOHN JANSEN As Employer Trustees of the Bricklayers Local 1 of Missouri Apprenticeship and Training Trust Plaintiffs. and DON BROWN, ROBERT GUINN JOHN FINDER, JOHN HOPKIN, and BRIAN JENNEWEIN As Union Trustees of the Bricklayers Local 1 of Missouri Apprenticeship and Training Trust Defendants.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No.: 4:16-cv-00122-RLW</p>
<p>November 28, 2016.</p>
<p>Mark Berger, Arbitrator</p>
<p>The Masonry Contractors Association (MCA) of St. Louis, Missouri is a multi-employer bargaining unit composed of employers in the masonry and bricklaying industry. It has had a long-term collective bargaining relationship with the Bricklayers Union Local 1 of Missouri. The parties have entered into a series of labor agreements including the current collective bargaining contract which runs from July 5, 2015 through May 31, 2021.</p>
<p>In 1971 the parties entered into an agreement to create a Joint Apprenticeship and Training Trust pursuant to provisions of the Taft-Hartley Act and ERISA. Article II, Section 1 identifies the purposes of the Trust which include &ldquo;&lsqb;e&rsqb;stablishing apprenticeship programs in order to provide and maintain a capable workforce for the bricklaying trade and to establish apprenticeship standards&hellip;,&rdquo; as well as &ldquo;&lsqb;e&rsqb;stablishing training and teaching programs for the teaching, instruction and training of journeymen bricklayers in order to enhance and broaden the skills of such journeymen.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Trust is administered by a Board composed of five Employer Trustees and five Union Trustees. If the Trustees cannot agree on any matter, they are required by Article III, Section 4 to concur in the selection of an impartial umpire to decide the matter in dispute or, if the Trustees fail to agree upon an impartial umpire, the U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Missouri may be petitioned to select an impartial umpire whose decision shall be binding on all parties to the agreement.</p>
<p>At the Trustees' meeting on November 18, 2015, the Union and Employer Trustees deadlocked on the motion of the Employer Trustees to amend the Joint Training Program Standards to reflect new language contained in Article IX, Section 6 of the newly-adopted labor contract. Following their failure to agree on the appointment of an impartial umpire, a petition was filed with the U.S. District Court of the Eastern District of Missouri which resulted in the appointment of Mark Berger, Esq. to serve as the Umpire/Arbitrator in this matter.</p>
<p>On September 9, 2016 a hearing was held in St. Louis, Missouri on the dispute between the parties. The MCA Trustees were represented by James N. Foster, Jr., Esq. and Rex P. Fennessey, Esq. The Union Trustees were represented by Michael A. Evans, Esq. The neutral Arbitrator was Mark Berger, Esq. The parties were given a full opportunity to present evidence and to examine and cross examine all witnesses.</p>
<p>The parties disagreed as to the issue presented in this proceeding as it relates to the scope of the Arbitrator's jurisdiction. The MCA's statement of the issue is that the role of the Arbitrator is limited to deciding:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Whether the &ldquo;Bricklayer Apprenticeship Standards&rdquo; should be amended to conform to Article IX, Section 6 of the current Collective Bargaining Agreement between the Mason Contractors Association of St. Louis and the Bricklayers Union Local No. 1 of Missouri.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">In contrast, the Union Trustees took the position that the authority of the Arbitrator is to act as an independent Trustee of the Trust. As such, he would free to vote for against the proposed amendment of the Standards, or he may propose an alternative course of action.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>FACTS</i></h4>
<p>The Joint Apprenticeship Training Program Trust currently has a single employee who both administers the Program and provides instruction to the Bricklayer and Masonry Apprentices. Although the number has varied over time, there are approximately 40 Apprentices currently being trained in the Program.</p>
<p>The evidence presented at the hearing focused on three specific changes made to the provisions governing the Apprentice Training Program in the labor agreement between the MCA and the Union. During negotiations the MCA had proposed that Apprentices not be paid while attending classes and that they be subject to a 90-day probation period. The 90-day probation period was accepted, but the pay provision was changed to provide Apprentices 50&percnt; of what their wages otherwise would have been while they were participating in the Apprenticeship Program Training.</p>
<p>The third proposal, which became the area of difficulty producing the deadlock between the Union and Employer Trustees, concerns changes to the Training Program schedule. Immediately prior to the current collective bargaining agreement Apprentice Trainees were in training for a full eight hours one day every other week, an increase from four hours every other week that had been the format under the predecessor labor agreement.</p>
<p>However, the MCA was concerned that the eight hour every other week schedule was disruptive and inefficient. It pointed to the fact that pulling an Apprentice out for one day of training every other week meant that the program could not provide training continuity, and that training time was lost because of the need to spend time each day setting up before and cleaning up after the training. It was also difficult for employers to replace trainees who were away from work for such a short time.</p>
<p>The alternative proposed was to provide classroom training in full-week blocks on non-consecutive weeks. This was deemed to be a better and more efficient method of providing instruction to the Apprentices. Ultimately, the parties mutually agreed to change the existing schedule for Apprenticeship Training to two non-consecutive weeks, and this agreement was incorporated in Article IX, Section 6 of their collective bargaining agreement. However, the entire agreement, including the provision on the Apprentice Training Program, was not finalized until after the conclusion of a more than 30-day strike.</p>
<p>Along with being party to a collective bargaining contract with the MCA, the Union has also entered into separate labor contracts with Independent Contractors who are not part of the MCA. According to Union testimony, the Independent Contractors entered into identical labor agreements prior to the execution of the Union's agreement with the MCA. The Independent Contractor agreements included a provision relating to the scheduling of Apprenticeship Program training. That provision, reflected in Article VIII, Section 6 of the Independent Contractor agreements, carried forward the predecessor Apprenticeship Training schedule of one eight-hour day every other week.</p>
<p>The fact that the Independent Contractor labor agreement provision governing the scheduling of Apprenticeship Training differs from the provision on the same subject in the MCA labor agreement represents the major reason for the deadlock between the Trustees on incorporating the Union and MCA contract's Training Program provisions into the Training Program Standards. The reason for the problem is that the Union agreed to a side letter in the current labor contract with the MCA which states that</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&lsqb;e&rsqb;ffective July 5, 2015, the Union will not alter or amend any existing CBA or enter into a new CBA except to the extent that such agreement is consistent (in its entirety) with the MCA CBA,</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Association President Richard Swanson wrote a letter to Union Director Don Brown in August, 2015 which stated that &ldquo;if &lsqb;Independent Contractor&rsqb; apprentices attend school under the same schedule as agreed between the Union and MCA, then this will clearly be an alteration in the Independent Agreement.&rdquo; In effect the position reflected in the letter was that there would be a breach of contract with the MCA if the Union amended its agreements with the Independent Contractors such that their Apprentices would have a training schedule identical to the one established in the 2015 agreement between the Union and the MCA.</p>
<p>In prior years when changes in the Apprenticeship provisions were negotiated in the MCA contract, the new Standards were adopted by the Trustees in the Apprenticeship Training Standards without objection. However, that did not occur in the instant case. Although the Union Trustees knew that the MCA Trustees would be proposing to adopt the new Standards that were incorporated in the labor contract into the Apprenticeship Training Standards, they resisted adoption, stating in a letter that no adoption motion had been made. The Union was given advance notice that such a motion would be made at the Trustees' November meeting, but they abstained and produced the deadlock that has led to the current proceeding.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>DISCUSSION</i></h4>
<p>The initial question raised in this proceeding concerns the scope of this Arbitrator's jurisdiction. From the MCA's perspective, the Arbitrator is limited to voting yes or no on the MCA Trustees' proposal to amend the Bricklayer Apprenticeship Standards to conform to Article IX, Section 6 of the current labor agreement. For purposes of this proceeding, the significant consequence is that it would mean incorporating the new training schedule in the Apprenticeship Standards, even though the new schedule is inconsistent with the training schedule included in the labor agreements executed by the Union with the Independent Contractors.</p>
<p>In contrast, the Union maintains that this Arbitrator is free to act as an Independent Trustee and make a new proposal that was not placed before the Trustees at their November 18 meeting or at any other time. Specifically, the Union urges that the Arbitrator should propose that the Apprentice Training Program be offered with two separate training schedules, one consistent with the Union and MCA labor agreement covering MCA Apprentices, and the other covering Apprentices from Independent Contractors scheduled in accordance with the labor agreements between the Union and the Independent Contractors.</p>
<p>In support of its position the Union points to the fiduciary standards applicable to the Trustees. Those standards are particularly high given that the Apprentice Training Trust is a welfare benefit plan under ERISA. Decisions such as Martin v. Feilen, 965 F.2d 660, 664 (8th Cir. 1992) and Donovan v. Bierwirth, 680 F.2d 263, 272 n.8 (2nd Cir.), cert. denied, 459 U.S. 1069 (1982), cited by the Union Trustees, illustrate the demanding nature of fiduciary responsibilities under ERISA which apply to an arbitrator selected to break a deadlock among trustees of an ERISA trust.</p>
<p>In addition, the Union emphasizes that the obligation of a fiduciary under ERISA is to &ldquo;discharge his duties with respect to a plan solely in the interest of the participants and beneficiaries and&hellip;for the exclusive purpose of&hellip;providing benefits to participants and their beneficiaries.&rdquo; 29 U.S.C. &sect;1104(a)(1). Pegram v. Herdrich, 530 U.S. 211, 212 (2000); Varity Corp. v. Howe, 516 U.S. 489, 506 (1996). The Union maintains that since the Apprentices, including those working for the Independent Contractors, are the participants and beneficiaries of the Trust, a decision adversely affecting them would be a violation of the duties of the Trustees.</p>
<p>The Union Trustees pointed to cases involving the review of decisions made by arbitrators appointed to break deadlocks between employer and union trustees. In British Motor Car Distributors, Ltd. v. San Francisco Automotive Industries Welfare Fund, 882 882 F.2d 371 (9th Cir. 1989), excess funds under a trust that were refunded to the trust due to &ldquo;actuarial error,&rdquo; 882 F.2d at 375, were transferred to three successor trusts. A dispute arose between the employer and union trustees as to whether restrictions should be applied to the transfer, and an arbitrator was ultimately appointed by the federal district court to break the deadlock.</p>
<p>The court In <i>British Motor Car Distributors</i> noted that the applicable fiduciary review standard for the arbitrator in that case was whether the decision was &ldquo;&lsquo;arbitrary, capricious or made in bad faith, not supported by substantial evidence, or erroneous on a question of law.,&rsquo;&rdquo; <i>id</i>. at 378, n. 11, citing Eiser v. I.A.M Nat'l Pension Fund, 684 F.2d 648, 654 (9th Cir. 1982), cert. denied, 464 U.S. 813 (1983)(quoting Rehmar v. Smith, 555 F.2d 1362, 1371 (9th Cir.1976)). Applying that standard it upheld the arbitrator's decision which was to allow surplus funds in the trust to be transferred to successor trusts without restriction over the employers' objection that the money would be used for the benefit of individuals who were not part of the predecessor trust. Separate from the issue of the fiduciary review standard, it appears from the decision that all the arbitrator did was to vote in favor of the proposal of the union trustees to transfer the funds without restriction; there is no indication that any new or independent proposal was put forward by the arbitrator.</p>
<p>The Union Trustees argue that the motion proposed by the MCA Trustees is ultimately an effort by the MCA to force the Independent Contractors to join the MCA. This would mean imposing an obligation on the Independent Contractors to pay MCA dues which they do not owe as Independent Contractors. This could discourage them from sending their Apprentices to the training program, and since Apprentices from both the Association and the Independent Contractors are beneficiaries of the trust, enacting the proposed motion would be contrary to their interests and in violation of trustee fiduciary obligations. From the Union Trustees' perspective, this would amount to impermissibly benefiting one group of plan participants (the MCA apprentices) over another group (Independent Contractor apprentices) in violation of fiduciary requirements.<ftnote num="1"><para>Jensen v. SIPCO, Inc., 867 F. Supp. 1384, 1396 (N.D. Iowa 1993), aff'd, 38 F.3d 945 (8th Cir. 1994) (<quote>In administering a plan, a fiduciary may not favor one group of plan participants over another,</quote>)</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Even recognizing the fiduciary responsibilities of this Arbitrator in the instant case, the Company points to significant facts which argue for a more limited arbitral role in breaking the deadlock that currently exists between the MCA and Union Trustees. One such fact concerns the language in the Trust Agreement which states that the role of a selected impartial neutral only arises when the Trustees &ldquo;are unable to agree upon any matter or question.&rdquo; The specific matter or question which provoked the instant deadlock was the proposal to incorporate the Union and MCA contract standards in the separate Apprenticeship Standards.</p>
<p>That specific matter or question was placed before the Trustees in November, 2015 in the form of a motion which resulted in a deadlock. This background suggests that the specific matter or question at issue is the deadlocked proposal, not the more general question of how the Apprentice Training schedule differences between the MCA and Independent Contractor labor agreements should be resolved. Moreover, the same result is suggested by the District Court's order in the instant case which directed the appointment of an impartial umpire to &ldquo;decide the deadlock,&rdquo; as well as Section 302(c)(5)(B) of the LMRA which requires that in the event of a deadlock an &ldquo;impartial umpire &lsqb;shall be chosen&rsqb; to decide such dispute.&rdquo;<ftnote num="2"><para><italic>See also</italic>, Petition of Feldman, 165 F. Supp. 190, 193 (S.D.N,Y. 1958). There the trustees deadlocked over a proposal to discontinue certain payments for disabilities under a trust. The court concluded that whether or not to pay these benefits was a matter within the discretion of the trustees. Since the trustees deadlocked, the court stated that the responsibility of the umpire was to determine whether it was <quote>appropriate and proper for the motion to be adopted or defeated,</quote> No mention was made of the possibility of the umpire offering a new proposal. Similarly, the arbitrator in Cap v. Bowers, 218 F. Supp. 2d 505 (S.D.N.Y. 2002) appeared to have voted on existing proposals without making any independent recommendations.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>There are also practical concerns that would arise if this Arbitrator offered a proposal not previously considered by the Trustees. The fact that a new proposal was made would not mean that it would amount to a final decision on that proposal. This would be true even if it encompassed the Union proposal for the Trust to offer training on two separate schedules. Since this proposal would not be self-enacting, a motion would have to be made at a Trustees' meeting to adopt the proposal. Would this Arbitrator then become a Trustee who would not merely propose a new resolution on the training schedule, but would also be entitled to vote on it at such a meeting? Would this be permissible under the court order? If so, would it be encompassed in a reservation of jurisdiction assuming that jurisdiction could and would be reserved? These are serious questions which might entail costly litigation to resolve.</p>
<p>It is also a matter of concern to this Arbitrator that the Union proposal raises issues that relate to the administration of the Trust about which this Arbitrator has no information beyond the limited testimony that was presented at the hearing. According to the testimony of the Training Program's Coordinator and Trainer, it would not be possible to have two separate training schedules as the Union recommends without hiring an additional instructor. Integrating the distinct schedules of the MCA Apprentices and the Independent Contractor Apprentices on the basis of their separate contractual scheduling systems would create conflicts if only a single instructor was available.</p>
<p>It is true that the Apprenticeship Training Program at one time did have two instructors, but it also had over 100 Apprentices being trained. When the number got down to 50 or so, the Trustees decided that only a single instructor could be justified, and that is how the Training Program has continued to operate. It may be that an additional instructor will be needed in the future, but the complement of Apprentice Trainees now is at a level which appears to warrant only a single instructor.</p>
<p>Imposing a restructured training schedule as suggested by the Union Trustees with its inevitable additional financial cost, estimated to be well in excess of &dollar;100,000 in the salary and benefits of a new trainer, is something that should be left to the Trustees and those familiar with how the Apprenticeship Training Program operates. It would be inappropriate for this Arbitrator to take that step without much more information than was made available. For that reason the decision this Arbitrator will make will be whether or not to vote in favor of the MCA Trustees' proposal that produced the deadlock,</p>
<p>The Union Trustees argue that the Standards do not require that they conform to the labor agreement between the Union and the MCA. In support of this position the Union Trustees point to Section 26, which states that &ldquo;Nothing in these Standards shall be interpreted as being contrary to the present or subsequent bargaining agreement,&rdquo; requires reference to Article I, Section 4 of the Trust which defines collective bargaining agreement as &ldquo;the various collective bargaining agreements now existent, heretofor and hereafter made and executed between an Employer and the Union,&rdquo; The Trust, moreover, in Article I, Section I, defines an employer as &ldquo;any person, firm or corporation who employs journeymen or apprentice members of the Union and who agrees to be bound by the terms and provisions hereof.&rdquo;</p>
<p>If the connection between the Standards and the Trust is required, it would raise the possibility that the Standards would have to conform to any labor agreement made between the Union and any employer executing an agreement with the Union. If these contracts contained different training schedules, they might all have to be accommodated. This would be even more problematic than the two training schedules that the Union Trustees would have this arbitrator propose.</p>
<p>After careful consideration I cannot accept the Union Trustees' argument on this point. There is nothing in the explicit language contained within the Standards, nor in the history of the Apprenticeship Training Program, that supports the claim that Section 26 of the Standards was intended to refer to anything other than the contract between the Union and the MCA. The Trust may define the term collective bargaining agreement as encompassing &ldquo;the various collective bargaining agreements now existent,&rdquo; but the Employer Trustees persuasively demonstrated that this plural reference relates to a separate concern under the Labor Management Relations Act. Importing the Trust definition which encompasses multiple labor agreements into the Standards which refers to &ldquo;the&hellip;bargaining agreement&rdquo; in the singular is neither required nor appropriate.</p>
<p>The MCA made an effective case in support of the merits of its proposal to incorporate the new contractual apprentice training schedule provisions in the Joint Apprenticeship Standards. The new schedule provides Apprentices with a continuity of training not available in a schedule involving one full day of training every other week. There is also more training time made available because of the absence of the need to set up and clean up in connection with every single day of training, This is true in part because materials can be left out since training will continue the following day.</p>
<p>It is also true that contractors will have less difficulty finding substitutes because they can offer a full continuous week of work rather than a single day every other week. Moreover, those substitutes are likely to be more productive as a result of the fact that they will be working for a full week and can familiarize themselves with the tasks and setting of the job they are required to perform.</p>
<p>The Union Trustees, who participated in the negotiation of the new training standards with the MCA members, and agreed to incorporate the new standards in their labor agreement with the MCA, obviously also supported the merits of that proposal during contract negotiations. The reason for abstaining when the Trustees vote was taken was due to a separate matter, namely whether the effect of incorporating the standards would be to pressure the Independent Contractors into joining the MCA.</p>
<p>The &lsquo;practical&rsquo; side of the Union Trustees' argument is that Independent Contractors will have to choose between joining the MCA, which they do not want to do, or not sending their Apprentices to the training program. This would be to the detriment of the Independent Contractor Apprentices to whom the Trustees, including this Arbitrator, owe a fiduciary responsibility.</p>
<p>However, all of this is speculative since it has not been definitively established that the MCA will take the final position that the Independent Contractors will have to join the MCA in order to send their Apprentices to the training program and whether, if they do take that position, it will ultimately prevail, Additionally, no evidence was presented at the hearing by Independent Contractors as to their current position. All of this could turn into a contentious legal dispute that the parties may well choose to avoid.</p>
<p>The Union Trustees did not make the case that the new training schedule was inferior to the predecessor schedule, and indeed the testimony indicated that the Independent Contractors were not opposed to the new schedule on the merits. Nor was the Union opposed to the schedule on the merits as evidenced by their agreement to the new schedule in their current collective bargaining contract with the MCA.</p>
<p>Ultimately, however, this Arbitrator believes that his judgment must be based upon the totality of the arguments; legal, practical and speculative. Finding that the case in support of the proposal to amend the &ldquo;Bricklayer Apprenticeship Standards&rdquo; to conform to Article IX, Section 6 of the current labor agreement between the Mason Contractors Association of St. Louis and the Bricklayers Union Local No. 1 of Missouri. outweighs the case against, this Arbitrator votes yes.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>