<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between: OLIN CORPORATION, Employer, and INTERNATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF MACHINISTS AND AEROSPACE WORKERS, DISTRICT 9, Union.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Grievant: Kayla Bierman FMCS&num; 161110-00417-1</p>
<p>October 13, 2016.</p>
<p>George L. Fitzsimmons, J.D., NAA Arbitrator</p>
<table width="585" columns="1">
<caption><i>TABLE OF CONTENTS</i></caption>
<tr>
<td width="5%"><p></p></td>
<td width="85%"><p></p></td>
<td width="10%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>I. BACKGROUND <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>II. ISSUE <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>III. RELEVANT DOCUMENTS <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>IV. SUMMARY POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>4</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>A. COMPANY <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>4</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>B. UNION <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>4</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>V. SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>5</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>VI. DISCUSSION AND DECISION <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>8</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>VII. AWARD <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>11</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>I. BACKGROUND</b></i></h4>
<p>The Olin Corporation (hereinafter &ldquo;Company&rdquo;) manufactures ammunitions and explosives at their facility in East Alton, Illinois. The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers (hereinafter &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) represents bargaining unit employees including Kayla Bierman (hereinafter &ldquo;Grievant&rdquo;). The Company and Union entered into a Collective Bargaining Agreement (hereinafter &ldquo;Contract&rdquo;) which was in full force and effect at all relevant times herein. (Jt.Ex.1). The matter at issue here is the Union's challenge to Grievant's discharge for violating the Company's General Plant Rules. (Jt.Ex.2). Following her discharge Grievant filed the grievance herein. (Jt.Ex.4). The parties stipulated that there were no procedural questions and the grievance was properly before Arbitrator Fitzsimmons for decision.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>II. ISSUE</b></i></h4>
<p>Did the Company violate the Collective Bargaining Agreement, Article 4, Labor Relations, Sec. 4.1, Disciplinary Action when the Company discharged Grievant for fighting or inciting a fight? If so, what shall be the remedy?</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>III. RELEVANT DOCUMENTS</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i>ARTICLE 12 &ndash; MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</i></h4>
<p>Section 12.1: Functions of Management</p>
<ol type="lc-letter" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Subject to the provisions of this Agreement the Union recognizes that the management of the plant and the direction of the working force is vested exclusively in the Company and this shall include, but not be limited to, the right to hire, demote, promote, and suspend or discharge for just cause, to release and lay off Employees for lack of work, to assign work and to transfer Employees from one job to another and Management has the sole responsibility for the assignment of work, overtime, maintaining discipline and otherwise directing and operation the plant. (Jt.Ex.1).</p></li>
</ol>
<h4 align="center">GENERAL PLANT RULES</h4>
<p align="center">East Alton, Illinois</p>
<p class="continued">These plant rules apply to all Winchester operations and facilities in East Alton. Posted department rules also must followed. Employees arrested for, charged with or convicted of a felony may be subject to discipline up to and including discharge.</p>
<ol type="uc-roman" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>The following acts will be subject to immediate termination or discharge:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Theft or stealing.</p></li>
<li><p>Unauthorized strike or work stoppage.</p></li>
<li><p>Failure to report off 3 consecutive days, or to comply with leave of absence procedures.</p></li>
<li><p>Smoking in a hazardous area.</p></li>
<li><p>Having any unauthorized gun, explosive or fire bomb device, detonator or fuse.</p></li>
<li><p>Falsifying any record or knowingly giving false or misleading information or making false claims.</p></li>
<li><p>Having alcoholic drinks or illegal drugs in the workplace.</p></li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>The following acts will subject an employee to suspension without pay or to immediate discharge, depending on the degree of circumstance involved:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Interfering with or impeding production.</p></li>
<li><p>Refusing to follow orders or instructions; refusing to work an overtime assignment, or any other act of insubordination.</p></li>
<li><p>Fighting or inciting a fight.</p></li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
<p class="continued">(Jt.Ex.2)</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>IV. SUMMARY POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>COMPANY</i></h4>
<p>That Grievant was discharged for just cause for inciting a fight with a co-worker.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>UNION</i></h4>
<p>That Grievant was not discharged for just cause as her arguments with her co-worker did not rise to the level of &ldquo;inciting to fight.&rdquo; In the alternative, the penalty of discharge was excessive punishment.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>V. SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE</b></i></h4>
<p><i>Monika Perkinson</i> testified she is employed by an outside contractor performing janitorial services at the Company's East Alton location. She works in the Primer Department performing routine janitorial duties. (T.12,13). She knows both Grievant and Lisa Sanders who work in that Department. (T.13). On February 18, 2014 she was cleaning the ladies bathroom when Grievant entered. Grievant was upset and crying. Thereafter, Lisa Sanders enter the bathroom. A loud argument ensued so she pushed in her earplugs to avoid listening. She did hear talk from Grievant about &ldquo;leaving my family out of it,&rdquo; &ldquo;get out of my face&rdquo; and multiple obscenities, She did not want to be involved. When she left the bathroom several employees told her not to get involved as &ldquo;this has been going on a long time.&rdquo; She had observed Grievant and Sanders in &ldquo;heated discussions several times earlier that day.&rdquo; (T.14,28).</p>
<p><i>Fred Carpenter</i> testified he has been employed by the Company for four years and now is a Senior Manager of H.R. Security. (T.29). He conducts many of the investigations involving employee discipline. He identified the Company's General Plant Rules which are posted throughout the facility and explained that all employees review them annually in training sessions. (Jt.Ex.2) (T.30,31). The General Plant Rule applicable herein involves &ldquo;fighting or inciting to fight.&rdquo; (Jt.Ex.2, Rule II, 3;T.32). He began his investigation of Grievant and Sanders shortly after the bathroom incident. He spoke to Grievant, Sanders, Monika Perkinson, and reviewed a videotape showing the circumstances leading up to the bathroom incident. (Jt.Ex.9). The video had no sound but showed Grievant and Sanders opening and closing a nearby door and clearly arguing with each other loudly enough that other employees appeared to notice. (T.33-41). He explained that the work performed in the Primer Department was high risk and numerous precautions were taken to avoid an explosive accident. It was clear in observing the video that their finger pointing arguments were causing delays in their work. He obtained statements from Shannon Webb, Kyle Simmons, Joshua Hosford, Matthew Jennings, Grievant and Lisa Sanders. The statements confirmed in one way or another the facts that Grievant and Sanders had problems working together that went on for years. Some of their difficulties arose out of the fact that Grievant was required to wear a heavy primer jacket at all times to protect her from a possible fire or explosion. The jacket caused Grievant to overheat so she would open a nearby door for ventilation. Sanders did not wear a jacket so she would close the same door as the ventilation made her cold. On February 18, 2014 their argument in the work area escalated into the bathroom incident. Grievant bid out of the Primer Department for nine months to avoid Sanders but then bid back into her old job about three weeks before these events. (T.64). Company Supervisor Dedria Cooley had warned Grievant in the past that her behavior could result in her termination. (T.51-68). At the conclusion of this investigation he recommended that both Grievant and Sanders be terminated for violating the Company's General Plant Rules for &ldquo;fighting or inciting a fight.&rdquo; He admitted he could have assessed lesser discipline but he didn't think their behavior would change. (T.68-87).</p>
<p><i>Matthew Wiggenhorn</i> testified he has worked for the Company for twenty-five years and now works as a General Foreman. (T.88). His duties included supervising the Primer Department employees including Grievant and Lisa Sanders. He explained the materials being manufactured in that Department must be handled very carefully to avoid an explosion. He watched the video tape of the events of February 18, 2014 including the dispute between Grievant and Sanders. He felt that the video showed that the heated dispute prevented Grievant from paying sufficient attention to her work. (T.89-102). He agreed with the decision to terminate both Grievant and Sanders.</p>
<p><i>Dedria Cooley</i> testified she is a primer foreman in the Primer Department and is the immediate supervisor of Grievant and Sanders. She was away from work on a medical appointment at the time of the February 18, 2014 incident but she viewed the videotape. (Jt.Ex.9). Grievant and Sanders had heated issues going on for several years with many issues relating to Grievant being hot and Sanders being cold. Both came to her office on several occasions complaining about each other. At another time she moved one to a different department because of their heated disagreements. (T.103-108). Grievant bid out of the Primer Department for nine months but bid back in three weeks before the final incident. (T.108). She warned both of them that if their behavior continued they could be discharged. She agreed with the decision to terminate both Grievant and Sanders. (T.108-113).</p>
<p><i>Grievant</i> testified she has been employed by the Company for four years and never disciplined. (T.114-115). She is required to wear a heavy charge coat to protect her in the event of an explosion. She and Lisa were bickering all morning because she was hot and Lisa was cold. She opened the door for ventilation and Lisa would close it. Lisa told her: &ldquo;Fuck your mother and fuck your brothers.&rdquo; At lunch time she went into the bathroom and told Lisa: &ldquo;I don't give a fuck what you say about me but don't bring my family into it.&rdquo; Lisa told her to: &ldquo;Beat my ass.&rdquo; She was called to the office and interviewed by Fred Carpenter. After the interview she was walked out and fired. (T.115-116). She admitted that she and Lisa had always bickered. She admitted the video shows her leaving the primer table to open the door while leaving two plates of explosive primer mix in the leaf contrary to Company safety procedures. (T.116-120). Foremen Dedria Cooley had previously warned her that she and Sanders could lose their jobs due to their behavior. (T.120-121).</p>
<p><i>Shannon Webb</i> testified she has worked in the Primer Department for six years as a cap operator. (T.124). Grievant and Sanders had regular disagreements over the door being open or closed or the temperature too hot or too cold. She admitted that on February 18, 2014 she could hear them cursing, screaming and yelling obscenities at each other but she never thought that would lead to violence. (T.124-131).</p>
<p><i>Tammie Holmes</i> testified she has worked in the Primer Department for six years as a cap operator/inspector. (T.132). On February 18, 2014 Grievant and Sanders were having an ongoing argument about opening and closing the door. Grievant and Sanders argued regularly. She wanted to &ldquo;stay out of it.&rdquo; At the lunch break she went to the ladies restroom and heard them yelling at each other. They were screaming and yelling obscenities. She did not consider their behavior on that day to be much different from their past behavior. (T.131-141).</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>VI. DISCUSSION AND DECISION</b></i></h4>
<p>Since this is a discharge case the burden is upon the Company to prove it had &ldquo;just cause to terminate Grievant's employment for violating Company Rules for fighting or inciting a right.&rdquo; Discharge is the most extreme industrial penalty since the Grievant's job, seniority and other benefits under the Contract are at stake. <i>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, &ldquo;How Arbitration Works&rdquo;</i> 5<sup>th</sup> Edition, 1997. When applying the principle of just cause to justify the termination of an employee, there are two situations for the Arbitrator to examine. The first is an offense that is the final step in the progressive discipline process. The second is a single incident of very serious misconduct. <i>Midwest Coca-Cola Bottling Co., 94-1 ARB (1993)</i>. Grievant had no prior discipline in her years working for the Company. Therefore, I must decide whether Grievant's actions on February 18, 2014 were of such serious misconduct as to justify the Company's termination of her employment.</p>
<p>Employers have become very concerned about workplace violence. Many employers have implemented specific rules and policies to protect their workforce from physical harm and threats of physical harm. Threats of violence are often an early warning sign of a person's propensity to commit a physical assault in the future. For these reasons employers often include a zero tolerance policy for workplace violence.</p>
<p>The great majority of the facts in this case are undisputed. The Company is a contractor for the U.S. military and manufactures ammunition and high explosives at its plant in East Alton, Illinois. Grievant was employed by the Company for four years and worked in the Primer Department where she mixed ingredients to make high explosives. Grievant was required to wear a primer jacket to protect her from a flash fire or explosion when mixing these materials. The primer jacket caused Grievant to be overheated so she opened a nearby door for ventilation. Co-worker Lisa Sanders worked in close proximity to Grievant but was not required to wear a primer jacket. Sanders apparently objected to Grievant opening the door because it made her &ldquo;cold.&rdquo; Grievant and Sanders had been engaged in arguments and bickering for several years. Both had been warned by Supervisor Dedria Cooley that their continued bad behavior could result in the termination of their employment. Because of the problems Grievant had working with Sanders, Grievant bid out of the Primer Department for nine months but then chose to bid back into the Department a short time before this incident.</p>
<p>On February 18, 2014 Grievant and Sanders began ongoing heated exchanges apparently related to opening and closing of the ventilation door. An eleven minute videotape without audio was shown at the Hearing. The videotape showed Grievant opening the door and Sanders closing the door several times shortly thereafter. Grievant and Sanders are shown shouting and pointing fingers at each other on several occasions. Even though the plant is a very noisy environment where employees wear hearing protection the videotape shows other Primer Department employees reacting to the dispute by looking in Grievant and Sanders direction. Grievant appears to be distracted from her work due to the ongoing dispute with Sanders.</p>
<p>The Company subpoenaed outside contractor Monica Perkinson to the Hearing. Perkinson performed janitorial services at the plant including the Primer Department. She observed Grievant and Sanders engaged in a heated argument on the work floor when they were engaged in opening/closing the nearby door. Later that day she was cleaning the women's restroom when Grievant entered. Grievant was visibly upset and crying. Sanders entered shortly thereafter and a loud argument ensued. Although she pushed in her earplugs to avoid listening she heard Grievant say such things as &ldquo;leave my family out of it,&rdquo; &ldquo;get out of my face,&rdquo; and multiple obscenities. She left the restroom ASAP.</p>
<p>Company witness Fred Carpenter, Senior Manager of Security conducted the Company's investigation. He obtained statements from other Primer Department employees. These statements confirmed that Grievant and Sanders had ongoing and frequent disputes related to Grievant's overheating while wearing the Primer jacket and the frequent opening/closing of the door. Company witnesses further testified to the safety issues involved with the explosive materials Grievant handled and the necessity to pay careful attention to her work to avoid a flash fire or explosion that could injure her and others.</p>
<p>Foreman Cooley testified that she supervised Grievant and Sanders. Grievant and Sanders had heated arguments for several years. Both came to her office on numerous occasions complaining about the other person. Because of their arguments Grievant bid out of the Primer Department for nine months to avoid Sanders. Grievant bid back in to the Primer Department three weeks before this incident. Cooley warned both of them that their threats and arguments could lead to their discharge.</p>
<p>Grievant admitted her long, ongoing disputes with Sanders which related primarily to her becoming overheated while wearing the Primer jacket. She wore the jacket for protection in the event the materials she worked with caused a flash fire or explosion. She also admitted the distraction caused by her arguments with Sanders and leaving her work area to open/close the door that caused inattention to her work in violation of Company safety procedures. The dispute with Sanders escalated from the Primer Department to the restroom where she and Sanders engaged in a loud, obscenity filled dispute. She admitted she had been warned by Foreman Cooley that these ongoing arguments with Sanders could result in her termination.</p>
<p>Primer Department employees Shannon Webb and Tammie Holmes testified to the ongoing obscenity filled arguments between Grievant and Sanders which had continued for several years. They wore hearing protection but could still hear them arguing and shouting obscenities at each other. At the conclusion of the investigation the Company discharged Grievant and Sanders for violating General Plant Rules for &ldquo;fighting or inciting to fight.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In reviewing all the evidence herein I find that the Company had just cause to discharge Grievant. The Company manufactures ammunitions and high explosives for the U.S. military. Grievant's job was particularly dangerous requiring her to wear a heavy duty Primer jacket to protect her in the event of a flash fire or explosion. The Company and Union jointly agreed to install videotaping in several departments so safety procedures could be observed to avoid unsafe work practices. Several years ago there was a previous explosion at the very job Grievant performed which injured several employees. The Company posted its &ldquo;General Plant Rules&rdquo; throughout the plant which included possible termination for &ldquo;fighting or inciting to fight.&rdquo; The videotape and Company witness testimony proved that Grievant's fighting or inciting to fight with Sanders prevented her from concentrating on her work and violated Company safety procedures when she left the charging table unattended while priming mix was present. I find that Grievant's conduct in the Primer Department and later in the restroom rose to the level of inciting to fight and justified her termination. Grievant's conduct was particularly inexcusable when considering her dangerous work on high explosives that caused Grievant to be inattentive to her work which could have seriously injured Grievant and her co-workers.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>VII. AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>The grievance filed herein is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>