<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION BETWEEN MINNESOTA LAW ENFORCEMENT ASSOCIATION, Union, and STATE OF MINNESOTA, DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE Employer.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>BMS Case No. 16-PA-0386</p>
<p>February 3, 2017.</p>
<p>Stephen F. Befort, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>INTRODUCTION</b></h4>
<p>Minnesota Law Enforcement Association (Union or MLEA), as exclusive representative, brings this grievance claiming that the State of Minnesota, Department of Commerce (Employer) violated the parties' collective bargaining agreement through its implementation in 2015 of a salary range reassignment for employees in the Insurance Fraud Specialist job classification. The Employer asserts that its manner of implementation was consistent with both the parties' contract and with past practice. The grievance proceeded to an arbitration hearing at which the parties were afforded the opportunity to present evidence through the testimony of witnesses and the introduction of exhibits.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>ISSUE</b></h4>
<p>Whether the implementation of the salary range reassignment for the classification of Commerce Insurance Fraud Specialist from Salary Range 20H to Salary Range 21H, effective January 28, 2015, violated the terms of the labor agreement?</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>RELEVANT CONTRACT LANGUAGE</b></h4>
<h4 align="left">ARTICLE 5 - MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i><b>Section 1. Right to Operate and Direct.</b></i> It is recognized that except as expressly stated herein, the Employer shall retain all rights and authority necessary for it to operate and direct the affairs of the employer in all of its various aspects, including but not limited to: the right to direct the working forces; to plan, direct, and control all the operations and services of the Employer; to determine the methods, means, organization, and number of personnel by which such operations and services are to be conducted; to assign and transfer employees; to evaluate employees' performance; to schedule working hours and to assign overtime; to determine whether goods or services should be made or purchased; to hire, promote, demote, suspend, discipline, discharge, or relieve employees for legitimate reasons; to make and enforce reasonable rules and regulations; and to change or eliminate existing methods, equipment, or facilities.</p>
<p class="continued"><i><b>Section 2. Terms and conditions of the Agreement.</b></i> Any term and condition of employment not specifically established by the Agreement shall remain solely within the discretion of the Employer to modify, establish, or eliminate.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="left">ARTICLE 28 &ndash; WAGES</h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i><b>Section 1. Salaries of Conservation Officers, Fugitive Specialists, Commerce Insurance Fraud Specialists, Special Agents and Special Agent Seniors</b></i></p>
<p class="continued"><b><i>A. Salary Ranges</i></b></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The salary ranges for Conservation Officers shall be those contained in Appendices E-1 and E-2.</p>
<p class="continued">The salary ranges for Fugitive Specialists, Commerce Insurance Fraud Specialists, Special Agents and Special Agent Seniors shall be those contained in Appendices D-1 and D-2.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b><i>B. Conversion.</i></b> Effective July 1, 2015, all employees shall be assigned to the same relative step within the salary range for their respective class as specified in Appendices E-1 or D-1, except as set forth below.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Employees who are paid at a rate which exceeds the maximum rate established for their class prior to the implementation of this Agreement, but whose rate falls within the new range for their class, shall be assigned to the maximum of the new range.</p>
<p class="continued">In the event the July 1, 2015 maximum rate set forth in Appendices E-1 or -1 is equal to or less than the employee's salary as of June 30, 2015, no adjustment shall be made, but employees assigned to these classes shall suffer no reduction in pay.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b><i>C. First Year Wage Adjustment.</i></b> Effective July 1, 2015, all salary ranges and rates shall be increased by two and one-half percent (2.5&percnt;), rounded to the nearest cent. The compensation grids for these classes are contained in Appendices E-1 and D-1. Employees shall convert to the new compensation grids as provided in B above.</p>
<p class="continued"><b><i>D. Second Year Wage Adjustment.</i></b> Effective July 1, 2016, all salary ranges and rates shall be increased by two and one-half percent (2.5&percnt;), rounded to the nearest cent. Salary increases provided by this section shall be given to all employees including those employees whose rates of pay exceed the maximum for their class.</p>
<p class="continued"><b><i>E. Progression</i></b></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>1. <i>Conservation Officers.</i></b></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Employees shall be eligible to receive a one (1) step progression increase after completing one (1) year of service at each step of their salary range until the maximum rate is attained.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>2. <i>Fugitive Specialists, Commerce Insurance Fraud Specialists, Special Agents and Special Agent Seniors.</i></b></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Employees in the classifications Fugitive Specialist, Commerce Insurance Fraud Specialist, Special Agent and Special Agent Senior shall be eligible to receive a one (1) step progression increase after completing one (1) year of service at each step of their salary ranges until the maximum is attained.</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">All increases authorized by this Section shall become effective at the start of the pay period nearest to the employee's anniversary date.</p>
<p class="continued">Time spent on suspension, leaves of absence or layoff of more than one full payroll period in duration shall extend the employee's anniversary date.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>FACTUAL BACKGROUND</b></h4>
<p>The Union serves as exclusive representative of a unit of approximately 700 non-supervisory law enforcement officers employed by the State of Minnesota. The grievance at issue involves a dispute over the implementation of a salary range reassignment applicable to eight unit employees working in the Commerce Department as Insurance Fraud Specialists. Under Minnesota law, job classifications are analyzed for compensation and pay equity purposes based upon an evaluation of the classification's required skill, effort, responsibility, and working conditions. The Insurance Fraud Specialist initially was rated at 324 points on the Hay Associates scale. A new study conducted in 2013 revised the classification rating to 417 points.</p>
<p>As a result of the revised job classification assessment, the Employer determined that the applicable salary range for these employees should be increased from salary range 20H to salary range 21H. The Employer notified the Union of this salary range reassignment effective January 28, 2015 in a letter dated January 16, 2015. That letter also outlined the process for implementing the reassignment. The letter stated that incumbents will move to the new salary range with no salary increase, except as follows:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Incumbents whose January 27, 2015 rate of pay is below the minimum rate for the new salary range shall move to the new minimum rate on January 28, 2015;</p></li>
<li><p>Incumbents who have been at the maximum step of range 20H for one year or longer as of January 27, 2015, are eligible to receive a one-step increase to place their salary at the maximum step of salary range 21H effective January 28, 2015,provided their performance is satisfactory; and</p></li>
<li><p>Incumbents who have been at the maximum step of range 20H for less than a year as of January 27, 2014, will be eligible to move to the 21H maximum step on their next anniversary date, provided their performance is satisfactory.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">The letter also provided the Union with a ten-day period to discuss the range reassignment plan. Although one unit member did raise questions during this period, the Union did not formally respond to the discussion invitation.</p>
<p>The Employer subsequently implemented the salary range reassignment as outlined in the January 16 letter. One unit employee received an immediate pay increase based on the new range reassignment because she had been at the maximum of the 20H range for more than 12 months. Five other unit employees remained at their 20H range step and received a pay boost based on the new salary range only upon reaching their respective anniversary dates. Two other unit members were new hires in 2015 and were automatically placed on the new salary range.</p>
<p>The Union filed a grievance challenging the Employer's implementation of the salary range reclassification on February 18, 2015. The Union's principal contention is that the Employer was obligated to move all Insurance Fraud Specialist employees to the appropriate step on the salary range 21H effective on January 28, 2015.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></h4>
<p class="continued"><b>Union:</b></p>
<p>The Union contends that the Employer violated the parties' collective bargaining agreement by not immediately placing all Insurance Fraud Specialists at their respective steps on the 21H salary range. The Union claims that the Employer's method of implementation conflicts with its contractual obligations to pay employees based on their &ldquo;same relative step&rdquo; of the appropriate salary range. The Union argues that the Employer improperly merged implementation of the salary range reclassification with the step progression that occurs within a non-reclassified salary range upon each employee's anniversary date of hire. Finally, the Union maintains that neither management rights nor past practice support a contrary interpretation.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Employer:</b></p>
<p>The Employer asserts that its method of implementing the salary range reclassification for the Insurance Fraud Specialist clasification did not conflict with any of the terms of the parties' collective bargaining agreement. More specifically, the Employer contends that the parties' contract is wholly silent with respect to the appropriate manner of implementing a salary range reclassification. In addition, the Employer maintains that its implementation was consistent with language in Article 28, Section 1. E. stating that salary increases &ldquo;shall become effective at the start of the pay period nearest to the employee's anniversary date.&rdquo; The Employer finally argues that its method of implementation was consistent with both its managerial rights and past practice.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>DISCUSSION AND OPINION</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>The Contract Language</b></h4>
<p>As with any contract interpretation dispute, the appropriate starting point for analysis is the language of the parties' agreement. The Union relies on the following provisions of Article 28:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">The salary ranges for Fugitive Specialists, Commerce Insurance Fraud Specialists, Special Agents, and Special Agent Seniors shall be those contained in Appendices D-1 and D-2.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Section 1. A.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Effective July 1, 2013, all employees shall be assigned to the same relative step within the salary range for their respective class as specified in Appendices E-1 or D-1 &hellip;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Section 1. B.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Employees in the classifications &hellip;, Commerce Insurance Fraud Specialist &hellip; shall be eligible to receive a one (1) step progression increase after completing one (1) year of service at each step of their salary range until the maximum rate is attained.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Section 1. E. 2.</p>
<p>The Union argues that the Employer's method of implementing the salary range reclassification is inconsistent with these provisions because 1) five Fraud Specialist employees were not placed on the appropriate salary range (21H) and step as of January 28, 2015; and 2) by implementing subsequent step progression based on time served on the employee's range 20H step rather than on their range 21H step.</p>
<p>The Employer responds that none of the provisions cited by the Union specifically apply to the salary range reclassification context. Indeed, the Employer argues that the parties' agreement is wholly silent about the proper methodology for implementing a salary range reclassification. In addition, the following provision in Article 28 lends support to the Employer's reliance on anniversary dates in its method of implementation:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">All increases authorized by this Section shall become effective at the start of the pay period nearest to the employee's anniversary date.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Section 1. E.</p>
<p>I believe that the Article 28 language relied upon by the Union does not establish a clear contract violation. Article 28 provides that employees generally should be compensated based on their assigned salary range. Article 28 also provides that employees generally should progress through the steps of their salary range based upon years of service measured at their individual anniversary date of hire. But, Article 28 does not specify how these general rules should apply in the event of a salary range reclassification. On the face of the contract, accordingly, the Union has not carried its burden to establish that the Employer's method of implementing the salary range reassignment constitutes a violation of the parties' agreement.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>Past Practice and Management Rights</b></h4>
<p>The Employer asserts that its method of implementing the salary range reassignment for the Insurance Fraud Specialist job classification is consistent with past practice. In this regard, it is well-recognized that a clear and well-established course of past practice may provide significant guidance in interpreting the terms of a collective bargaining agreement. A &ldquo;past practice&rdquo; arises from a pattern of conduct that is clear, consistent, long-lived, and mutually accepted by the parties. Richard Mittenthal, <i>Past Practice and the Administration of the Agreement</i>, 59 MICH. L. REV. 1017 (1961). A practice that comports with these factors generally is binding on the parties and enforceable under contract grievance procedures. <i>See</i> <small-cap>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, How Arbitration Works</small-cap> Ch. 12 (7th ed. 2012).</p>
<p>The Employer has submitted evidence of a longstanding and consistently applied practice of implementing salary range reassignments in a manner similar to that utilized in this case, namely, by providing pay raises based on the new salary range only upon individual employees reaching their anniversary date of hire. The shortcoming of the Employer's position, however, is that none of these incidents have involved the MLEA. Accordingly, the Union convincingly argues that the practice is not binding since one of the parties, <i>i.e.</i> the Union, has never acquiesced in such a practice.</p>
<p>While the Employer's practice is not formally binding, its consistent application provides at least some evidence as to the appropriate methodology for implementing salary range reassignments. Coupled with the fact that the parties' collective bargaining agreement contains no language prohibiting the Employer's practice, the Employer's actions in this regard appear to be within the managerial rights preserved by Article 5 of the agreement.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>AWARD</b></h4>
<p>The grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>