<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of a Controversy Between SEIU UNITED HEALTHCARE WORKERS WEST, Union, -and- CORIZON HEALTH, Employer.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>July 25, 2013.</p>
<p>Claude Dawson Ames, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>DECISION AND AWARD</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>I.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>INTRODUCTION</b></i></h4>
<p>This arbitration proceeding arises pursuant to the Agreement between the <b>SEIU UNITED HEALTHCARE WORKERS WEST,</b> (hereinafter &ldquo;SEIU&rdquo;or &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) and <b>CORIZON HEALTH</b> ( hereinafter &ldquo;Corizon,&rdquo; or &ldquo;Employer&rdquo;) under which Claude Dawson Ames, Esq., was selected to serve as Arbitrator. Pursuant to the Agreement, the Arbitrator's Findings, Opinion and Award shall be final and binding on the parties. The arbitration hearing was conducted at Alameda, California on March 18, 2013 and April 17, 2013. Jordan Mazur, Esq. of Weinberg, Roger and Rosenfeld, represented the Union and Grievant, Jennifer Broughton. David Durham, Esq., and Christopher Foster, Esq. of Arnold and Porter, represented the Employer, Corizon Health. At issue is the removal of grievant Jennifer Broughton from her job as a Health Information Clerk at the Santa Rita Jail by her employer, Corizon Health. All witness testimony was under oath and a stenographic transcript was taken at the hearing. The parties were afforded a full opportunity to present documentary and testimonial evidence, to examine and cross-examine witnesses and for rebuttal. The parties stipulated that all procedural requirements have been complied with or waived, and the matter is properly before the Arbitrator. Per the parties' request, the Arbitrator shall retain jurisdiction over the enforcement of any remedy. The hearing was officially closed by the Arbitrator after receipt of the parties' post-hearing briefs on June 20, 2013.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>II.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>STATEMENT OF CASE</b></i></h4>
<p>The Employer, Corizon Health (formerly Prison Health Systems), is a healthcare provider who contracts with Alameda County to provide medical services to inmates at the Santa Rita jail. Included in its service is the maintenance of inmate health records. The Employer's Health Information Services Department (&ldquo;HISD&rdquo;) maintains the inmate health records at the jail in individual charts and in a standardized format. The charts are accessed by the facility's healthcare providers, including physicians, nurses and dentists, as well as by staff of the HISD, including employees in the classification of Health Information Clerk (HIC). At all times relevant herein, the HISD employed approximately 13 to 14 HIC's at the jail. The HIC position requires an employee to diligently create, organize and file charts and to maintain the accuracy and accessibility of inmate medical records. (Er. Ex. 17) The HISD utilizes detailed policy and procedure statements which outline and explain the procedures to be followed by the HIC. (Er. Ex. 2-14) Examples of these procedures are: Criteria for Making Chart Folder and Assigning Medical Record Number; Chart Assembly, Analysis, and Coding; Opening and Closing a Chart; Flow of Charts and Loose Filing; and Processing Loose Filing/Work. In addition to these policies and procedures, the HISD utilizes HISD Clerk Standards. (Er. Ex. 15) The Standards include such criteria as how much loose paper the clerk may have unfiled, and the maximum number of charts awaiting creation and number of charts awaiting to be opened. The Standards indicate that each clerk is responsible for any back-log occurring during the clerk's absence from work and that each clerk is ultimately responsible for backup and duty assignments, including maintenance of the standards; such that any assistance received from the other clerks will not relieve the clerk of her own responsibilities.</p>
<p>The Alameda County Sheriff's Department, which oversees the Santa Rita jail facility, is accredited by the American Correctional Association and the National Commission on Correctional Healthcare. Accrediting audits are periodically performed at the jail to evaluate various aspects of the County's operations, including the Employer's provision and documentation of safe, efficient and effective inmate healthcare. As a contractor with the Sheriff's Department, the Employer must comply with applicable accreditation standards or risk loss of its contract with Alameda County.</p>
<p>The Santa Rita jail houses approximately 4000 prisoners daily and detains approximately 50,000 inmates a year. Each inmate booked into the jail is evaluated by a nurse at a nursing station; this nurse completes a standard Receiver Screening Form (RSF) which serves as the inmate's first medical record. When an inmate is first booked into the jail, an individual medical records chart is created for that inmate; for any subsequent detention of that inmate, his or her medical chart is retrieved for inclusion of further information. Each chart is assigned an individual medical record number containing a terminal digit. A HIC is then assigned a range of terminal digit numbers for which that clerk is responsible and creates the inmates' medical chart. When creating the charts, the clerks are required to adhere to highly detailed written instructions regarding how to assemble and order the chart. Medical records are bradded into the charts on the left and right sides in specific order, with additional information added in reverse chronological order, under particular tabs.</p>
<p>Within its Medical Services Department the Employer utilizes physicians, who are primarily engaged as independent contractors. During their detention, inmates may receive routine medical care by attending sick call where they are seen by a nurse. In the case of an emergency, the inmate may be seen immediately by a nurse or a physician. When an inmate is to be seen at sick call, his or her chart is pulled by the HIC and placed in a basket in a holding area, where a nurse retrieves the chart before an inmate is seen in the housing unit sick call room.</p>
<p>If an inmate needs particular treatment or a prescription, the nurse may contact a facility physician by telephone to obtain an order for the treatment or prescription. Upon receipt of an oral order from the doctor, the nurse prepares a written form, called a Telephone Order, in duplicate copy. A yellow copy of the order is routed to the facility's pharmacy and the white original order is routed back to HISD. The white order form is considered at this point to be &ldquo;loose filing.&rdquo; Loose filing is any type of medical record which has not yet been processed and properly added to the chart, in the appropriate order. Loose filing is processed by a HIC, who determines the inmate's medical record number and files the medical document in a corresponding health information sorter, according to the terminal digits of the medical record number. The loose documents are gathered for further processing by the clerk to which the terminal digits have been assigned. The HISD policies and procedures require that clerks promptly file all loose filing into the inmate's chart. Consistent with the above-noted HISD Clerk Standards, if it is determined that a clerk has more than 2 inches of loose filing in her assigned sorter area, she is considered to be behind on her filing.</p>
<p>If the loose medical record is a telephone order, HISD policy and procedure provides that it is to be signed by a physician within 72 hours of the oral order. After the order is placed in the clerk's sorter, the clerk takes the order and flags it for a physician's signature with a green &ldquo;sticky note,&rdquo; crosses out any portion that has been left blank by the nurse and places the chart with the flagged order in a designated area where physicians sign such orders. This physician may not be the same physician who orally provided the telephone order to the nurse; but the physician assigned to sign telephone orders collects the charts from the designated area, reviews the flagged orders as appropriate, signs them and returns the charts to the HISD for filing by the clerk assigned to the applicable terminal digits. Upon receipt of the chart, the clerk reviews it for completeness, including checking to see if the telephone order was signed by the physician and then files the chart in the appropriate open or closed chart storage area.</p>
<p>Along with the above, HICs are responsible for maintaining the charts in proper order. Although the healthcare providers, including nurses and physicians, have access to the files, they are discouraged from removing documents from, or changing the order of the documents within a file, this being within the job description and responsibility of the clerks. HISD provides written instruction to the clerks regarding the order in which the medical records are to be maintained within the charts. (Er. Ex. 26-27) Document order is accomplished by the clerk's insertion of colored and labeled tabs and accurate filing of the records. Each chart contains a Master Problem List (&ldquo;MPL&rdquo;) which is a chronological listing of known health conditions of the inmate. The MPL is also utilized by the healthcare providers to quickly identify critical health conditions for informed treatment or prescriptions. The MPL is to be kept by the clerk on top of the right side of each chart for easy access.</p>
<p>Clerks are responsible for checking a box on the outside of the chart showing the current year, to indicate if the chart is active. A chart lacking a check mark for the current year is routed off site, or purged. Clerks are responsible to make sure the charts are complete, especially when an inmate is released or transferred (known as &ldquo;NIC,&rdquo; or No Longer In Custody). This process is known as closing a file. The clerk initials a blue NIC sheet, kept at the front of the right side of the chart, to signify the clerk has thoroughly inspected the file and determined everything is in order, including ensuring all telephone orders have been signed. When closing a file, the clerk must ensure the chart is complete since the chart may be moved off-site or transferred to a new detention facility.</p>
<p>Grievant Jennifer Broughton was employed by Corizon between October 14, 2008 and November 10, 2011 as a Health Information Clerk. She had four years of prior experience as a records clerk in another correctional facility, performing similar duties. Grievant was assigned to terminal digit numbers 77-84 upon her hire by the Employer. At the time of her termination, Ms. Broughton was assigned numbers 77-83. The record indicates she was provided hands-on training and coaching upon her hire, along with access to the Employers' &ldquo;How to Book&rdquo; Manual on Applicable Policies and Procedures. (Er. Ex. 28) Grievant signed a detailed New Employee Orientation Checklist acknowledging her completion of various training and indicating her understanding of HISD's Policies and Procedures. (Er. Ex. 22)</p>
<p>On March 24, 2009 Ms. Broughton's supervisor, HISD's Assistant Health Services Administrator, Lenore Gilbert, conducted an informal audit of the staff shelving, finding that all the clerks were up to date except for Grievant and another clerk. Gilbert spoke to all the staff to ensure the clerks understood the importance of keeping the filing up to date. (Er. Ex. 31)</p>
<p>Grievant's written performance review of December 16, 2009, indicates that her performance was &ldquo;very good&rdquo; as to quality of work, productivity, knowledge of job, reliability and dependability, and in her adherence to policies. The review further indicates that she could do a better job and she could increase her productivity without sacrificing the quality and accuracy of her work, by having no loose filings at the end of each day. (Er. Ex. 29)</p>
<p>On December 16, 2010, Grievant was given a documented verbal warning by her supervisor after an audit found that several charts for which she was responsible contained problems including dropped filing, misfiling over the MPL and closed charts not moved to the filing room, among other things. (Er. Ex. 36) Grievant was told that she must improve the quality and accuracy of her chart assembly and that she would be monitored for a year.</p>
<p>On March 29, 2011 Grievant requested and went on a leave of absence. During her time off, fellow clerks were responsible for maintaining her charts, and ensuring that existing records within the charts were properly organized and that any telephone orders were properly signed by a physician. On April 5, 2011, staff physician Magat complained to Ms. Gilbert that there were a large number of charts with unsigned telephone orders requiring Magat's signature. Gilbert then performed an initial audit of a random sampling of five charts from each clerk's assigned terminal digit range to confirm the complaint. During the audit, Gilbert checked for compliance with HISD's policies and procedures and began looking for missing physician signatures on telephone orders. She discovered that only the Grievant's charts had a large number of errors, including telephone orders missing physician signatures, loose filings, charts out of order, records filed upside down, charts that needed to be separated into new volumes, missing purge dates, and improper placement of the MPL. (Er. Ex. 37, 38)</p>
<p>On April 7, 2011, Ms. Gilbert conducted a more thorough and detailed audit of all of Grievant's active charts to determine both the scope of the errors and what would need to be done to correct the errors. (Er. Ex. 37) This audit revealed the same type and extent of errors including loose filing, missing telephone order physician signatures, missing purge dates and failure to maintain chart order. (Er. Ex. 37, 38) Gilbert concluded that Grievant's work was very substandard and that she would need to pull and correct all of Grievant's active and inactive charts. (Er. Ex. 37; TR 138-139) Gilbert then instructed the other HIC's to review Grievant's open and closed files and to pull all those with missing physician signatures. Gilbert testified that there was no leeway regarding ensuring that all physician orders were signed, because the physicians needed to confirm that their orders written by the nurse on the telephone order form were appropriate. (TR 187)</p>
<p>Approximately 789 of the Grievant's charts were determined to have missing physician signatures on telephone orders. In mid-April 2011, Gilbert arranged for all staff physicians to review and sign the telephone orders; this process took an entire day during which inmate care had to be cancelled. After correcting the errors within Grievant's charts, Gilbert performed a follow-up audit on May 9, 2011 to assess the quality of the health records for the entire HISD, based upon a random sample from each clerk's charts. This audit revealed that the records, including those assigned to Grievant, were now in reasonable shape, with no further loose filing or missing physician signatures.</p>
<p>Gilbert testified that she did not know the exact number of files Grievant came into contact with each year that needed physician signatures on orders</p>
<p>Upon Grievant's return to duty on August 29, 2011 from her requested leave, Gilbert met with her and a Union representative to discuss Grievant's charts. Gilbert advised Grievant that she had discovered a large number of problems with the charts and that she wanted to understand Grievant's side of the story and to determine if Grievant understood the HISD policies and procedures for maintenance of the charts. Gilbert provided Grievant with a representative sample of her 17 uncorrected charts, which she personally closed and signed before her leave of absence. Grievant was then asked to analyze the charts and identify any errors. Grievant was able to correctly identify the various errors in the charts. (TR 148-149) When Gilbert asked Grievant for an explanation for the errors within Grievant's charts, Grievant stated she had not received sufficient training or oversight from Gilbert, and that her fellow clerks, physicians and nurse, had mishandled her charts. (TR 150-151) Gilbert advised Grievant that she had been trained on HISD policies and procedures, that she could have sought help from her fellow clerks or supervisors at any time and that her fellow clerks could not have been responsible for the errors, since many of the charts had been closed by Grievant.</p>
<p>Gilbert imposed an unpaid, two-day suspension on Grievant based upon the number of errors in her charts, her demonstrated knowledge of proper procedures, and refusal to accept responsibility for her errors. (Jt. Ex. 2) The suspension notice indicates that Ms. Broughton violated Corizon policies/procedures, had an unsatisfactory performance and failure to document properly in that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Jennifer has exhibited extremely poor performance in executing her assigned responsibilities as a Health Information Clerk. Over 780 charts were found to lack physician signatures. Jennifer has failed to maintain the assigned charts by failing to obtain physician signatures, failing to file loose paper in charts, failing to file in the proper chart order, failing to place year dates on the outside cover of charts, failing to place loose filing in chart right-side-up, failing to make second volumes when charts are too large, failing to document clerk initials on closing document page, failure to ensure pages belonging to correct chart, failure to maintain chart sections in reverse date order, and failure to properly place documents from other providers under the Master Problem List.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">The corrective action and time frame noted that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Jennifer is to immediately improve her performance by discontinuing the behaviors stated above. The behaviors listed represent extremely poor performance and a standard that is not acceptable. The employee will be monitored for one year. Continued poor performance and behavior may result in discipline and possible termination.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Gilbert testified that she had considered a lesser level of discipline, but felt that a suspension was appropriate due to the volume of chart errors and Grievant's failure to take responsibility for the errors. Gilbert considered terminating Grievant at this time but felt Grievant was redeemable and that she wanted to give her a chance to improve. Grievant served the suspension on August 30 and September 1, 2011.</p>
<p>On September 8, 2011, the Union filed a grievance objecting to imposition of a suspension without a Step 1 &amp; 2 verbal and written warning. (Jt. 3)</p>
<p>Approximately 35 days after Grievant's August 30- September 1, 2011 2 day suspension, Gilbert conducted a further audit of clerk files. Gilbert testified that she felt a month was a sufficient time period for Grievant to show improvement in her file handling. On October 6 and 7, 2011, Gilbert performed an audit of the HISD records in randomly-selected charts from all the clerks in order to see how well the clerks were performing as far as the frequency and type of errors they might be making. (Er. Ex. 43) Five charts from each clerk were chosen for the clerks other than Broughton, for whom Gilbert chose a higher number of charts; these numbers were chosen based upon Gilbert's professional knowledge and previous history with her staff.</p>
<p>The audit revealed that Grievant's charts contained a high number of errors of the same type which had been discovered and corrected previously, including charts out of order, improper placement of the MPL, failure to separate large charts into volumes and one chart which was missing its physician's orders. (Er. Ex. 43; TR 154-160) Gilbert's notes from the audit indicate she reviewed seven of Grievant's files and found 14 errors. Gilbert then conducted a focused audit on charts for which Grievant was responsible and which she had closed since returning from her leave. Gilbert discovered eight errors in these four charts, including failure to maintain chart order, upside down records, missing purge dates, and improper and/or non-placement of the MPL. Gilbert concluded then that Grievant's performance was not improving. (TR 164-165)</p>
<p>Under cross-examination, Gilbert indicated she may have miss-counted some of the errors that she noted in the staff charts; however given the passage of time and not having the files in front of her, it was difficult for her to now recall the details in the files. It had been her intention to consistently and equally assess the performance of all the clerks, including Grievant.</p>
<p>Gilbert then drafted an internal memorandum detailing Grievant's performance problems and recommended termination. (Er. Ex. 45) She considered imposing lesser discipline but determined that Grievant's continued employment would pose an unacceptable hazard to Alameda County's medical record system and inmates. The Employer accepted Gilbert's recommendation and on November 10, 2011, Grievant's employment was terminated due to her poor performance. (Jt. Ex. 3) Thereafter, the Union filed a timely grievance complaining of an alleged unfair termination of the Grievant Jennifer Broughton and that she had a good and satisfactory work performance, per evaluations, and her termination for &ldquo;poor performance&rdquo; was unjust. (Jt. Ex. 3)</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>III.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ISSUES PRESENTED</b></i></h4>
<p>The Employer proposes that the issue before the Arbitrator is: Whether the Employer violated the collective bargaining agreement in the suspension of Grievant in August 2011 and/or the discharge of Grievant in November 2011. If so, what is the appropriate remedy? The Union proposes that the issue before the Arbitrator is: Whether there is just cause in the imposition of the discipline of the Grievant in August 2011 and/or November 2011. If not, what is the remedy? The parties stipulated that the Arbitrator frame the issues and the Arbitrator hereby adopts and incorporates by reference the Employer's statement of the issues.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>IV.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>RELEVANT CONTRACT LANGUAGE</b></i></h4>
<blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>ARTICLE 4 MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</b></i></h4>
<p class="continued"><b>4.2</b> Among the rights retained by the Employer, but not totally inclusive of those rights, are the sole right to hire, discipline, discharge, lay off and promote&hellip;to promulgate rules and regulations; to assign duties to the workforce&hellip;to introduce new or improved methods, equipment or facilities; and in all respects to carry out the ordinary and customary functions of management whether or not exercised by the Employer prior to the execution of this Agreement&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>4.4.</b> The Union, on behalf of the employees, recognizes that the primary obligation of the Company is to ensure the safety, health and comfort of the inmates. Consequently, the Union agrees to cooperate with the Employer to attain and maintain full efficiency and maximum inmate care. The Union recognizes that inmate care is the primary concern of the Employer, and in emergency situations, inmate care may be placed ahead of the terms of this Agreement, without the Union permanently forfeiting any of its rights.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>ARTICLE 17 DISCIPLINE AND DISCHARGE</b></i></h4>
<p class="continued"><b>17.1</b> Non-probationary employees shall only be disciplined or discharged for just cause&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>17.2</b> The Employer shall determine the appropriate discipline to administer. In so doing, the Employer will consider the seriousness of the offense, the intent, attitude and record of the employee and the conditions under which the offense took place. Unless circumstances warrant severe actions the Employer will use a system of progressive discipline.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>17.2.1</b> Progressive disciplinary action may take several forms, for example, verbal counseling (documented), demotion and/or probation, written counseling and/or warnings, disciplinary suspensions with or without pay, and/or termination of employment. All disciplinary actions may become a permanent part of the employee's personnel file.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>17.3</b> Where the cause of discipline is poor performance and/or poor attendance, the disciplinary notice may but is not required to advise the employee of the general time period in writing during which the employee must evidence sustained improvement and, if warranted in the judgment of the Employer, the date on which termination will occur if sustained improvement is not made. The Employer may accelerate the termination date if performance declines during this period or if other intervening events occur that warrant discipline in the Employer's judgment.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>V.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>A. Employer's Position</b>:</i></h4>
<p>The uniquely strong Management Rights provision in the contract affords the Employer broad discretion to determine the appropriate level of discipline for poor job performance, especially for chronic poor performance that jeopardizes the welfare of inmates and the Employer's contract with Alameda County. The Arbitrator's review of the penalty is limited by the principle that an arbitrator should not substitute his judgment for that of management as to penalty unless the arbitrator finds the discipline was arbitrary, capricious, discriminatory or contrary to the terms of the labor contract.</p>
<p>The imposition of progressive discipline (which was not required here given the egregiousness of the errors) at both the point of suspension and termination was only done after advance notice, provision of reasonable opportunity for improvement, consideration of alternative discipline and detailed investigations. For all of the above and following reasons, especially the Grievant's candid admissions that she was aware of the Employer's policies and procedures, understood their importance, and that she failed to request any help or guidance, and the fact that the Employer conducted detailed investigations revealing that her mistakes compromised over 780 charts which could have caused harm to inmates and the Employer's contract with Alameda County, the grievances should be denied.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>B. Union's Position:</b></i></h4>
<p>The Employer did not have just cause to terminate the Grievant and the Grievant should be restored to her previous position with full back pay and benefits. The Employer has failed to meet the standard of fairness required in imposing the discipline against the Grievant. The Employer presented Gilbert's testimony to suggest that Grievant was not improving and was beyond hope after imposition of discipline; this assessment is not supported by the evidence. This conclusion and the subsequent file examination was extremely hasty, violating even the appearance of fairness. Gilbert's testimony makes clear her conclusion was at least partially based on an assessment that Grievant fell far below the standard of others and the evidence does not show this. At no time was Grievant or the Union informed that this was the standard by which Grievant would be assessed.</p>
<p>The Employer's failure to apply even basic fairness to the Grievant does not satisfy just cause and the grievance must be sustained. The Employer failed to show that the degree of discipline administered was reasonably related to the seriousness of the Grievant's proven offenses, if any. At most, the evidence shows that Grievant was not perfect but improved immediately upon notice of her deficiencies. The Employer used a flawed methodology and a pre-existing bias against Grievant's work, concluding without evidence that Grievant would never improve. Grievant showed exactly the improvement she was asked to show and there was no terminable offense. For these reasons the Union respectfully requests that the Arbitrator sustain the Union's grievance and order that Grievant be immediately reinstated to her position without loss of seniority, that she be made whole for all back wages and lost benefits, with interest, at the legal rate in California.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>VI.</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>DECISION</b></i></h4>
<p>The Employer's disciplinary action against HIC Jennifer Broughton concerns charges that Ms. Broughton's job performance was unsatisfactory. The issue is whether Corizon had just cause to suspend and then terminate Grievant based on her alleged unsatisfactory job performance, if not, what is the appropriate remedy. Corizon maintains that just cause exists for its disciplinary action of a two (2) day suspension and subsequent termination based on Grievant's repeated failure to meet its job performance standards. The Union disagrees and argues that the Employer failed to meet the standard of fairness required to terminate Grievant and failed to show that her termination was reasonably related to the seriousness of any proven offenses. According to the Union, Grievant showed exactly the improvement that she was asked to show in job improvement, and there was no terminal offense.</p>
<p>After careful analysis and review of the evidence presented, transcript of record and the parties' post-hearing arguments, the Arbitrator finds for the Employer. Just cause does exist for the Employer's implementation of a two (2) day Suspension and subsequent Notice of Termination based on the Grievant's unsatisfactory job performance. The evidence record before the Arbitrator does not find or support the Union's argument that the Employer's disciplinary action was arbitrary based on several findings of fact.</p>
<p>First, as to the suspension, it is found that prior to Grievant's suspension in August 2011 by all accounts, she clearly failed to satisfactorily perform her job duties and properly maintain her charts as required by the Employer, particularly with regard to her personal responsibility as the HIC to obtain physician signatures on all telephone medical orders and medications prescribed and place them in the inmate charts under her care. Supervisor Gilbert did not single out Ms. Broughton for any special scrutiny or hold her to a higher standard of job performance review when randomly selecting charts for audit. The evidence indicates that Grievant's charts were riddled with consistent errors in filing and improperly organized medical reports. This is not to say that other HIC charts were found not without problems, some were; but not to the extent or consistency in numbers and errors that were found in Ms. Broughton's charts.</p>
<p>There is no dispute that one of the HIC's essential duties in maintaining an inmates' medical chart is to ensure that the Master Problem List (MPL) is updated regularly and remains unobstructed for easy accessibility by either a nurse or treating physician and filed as the first document on the right side of the chart. Charts randomly pulled and audited by Supervisor Gilbert indicated that a disproportionate number of Ms. Broughton's charts failed to adhere to applicable HISD policy and procedures required of all HIC's in order to properly ensure inmate safety and maintain compliance with accreditation standards for reliable inmate health care services and treatment.</p>
<p>The Union has argued that Grievant was on a medical leave from late March to early August 2011 and that other clerks were responsible for her files during her absence, but the record reflects that the signature problem which led to the April 7, 2011 audit of Grievant's charts was discovered within days of the commencement of her leave, such that it cannot reasonably be concluded that responsibility for the chart errors lies with anyone other than Ms. Broughton. The Union further argues that perhaps the lack of physician signatures was the fault of the physicians, that they were not signing their orders and that as a clerk the Grievant had no power to force the physicians to sign their orders. This argument, however, is neither well grounded or supported by the Employer's HISD policy and procedures which places (rightly or wrongly) responsibility on the HIC for a specific range of terminal digit numbers corresponding to inmate charts, analyzing and processing loose filings, maintaining the chart order, including having the MLP on top and unobstructed. But an essential duty of the HIC necessary to maintain the Employers' continued contract with Alameda County and provide proper inmate health care accreditation standards, is to ensure that all telephone orders (TO's) are signed by physicians within 72 hours of creation. HISD policy requires the HIC to flag a TO for the physician signature (with a green &ldquo;sticky note) after being transcribed by a nurse and returned to the inmates' chart as a loose filing for processing by the HIC. HISD policy then requires the HIC to place the chart with flagged TO in a designated area where the physician will pick up the chart for signing. The Arbitrator finds that this was a critical function of Ms. Broughton's job duty which she failed to perform and placed at risk not only the integrity of inmate medical care and treatment, but also called into question the ordering physician's professional ethics by failing to adhere to HISD's required 72 hour signing policy for TO's prescribed to inmates at the Santa Rita Jail.</p>
<p>The record contains no evidence that the physicians were neglecting their duties and in fact it was a physician (Dr. Magat) who brought the problem to the attention of Ms. Broughton's supervisor. Further, the evidence indicates that there was a common denominator among the approximate 780 unsigned orders; which was Ms. Broughton and not a fellow clerk or any particular physician. Additionally, with regards to the two-day suspension, it is noted that Supervisor Gilbert's audits of Grievant's charts found multiple types of chart organization and maintenance errors other than just the lack of physician signatures. These errors indicate that Ms. Broughton was either in attentive to her duties or improperly trained to maintain medical records and inmate charts by the Employer.</p>
<p>However, the evidence record supports a conclusion that Grievant was highly trained and had notice and understanding of HISD policies and procedures, as shown by her ability to find errors in charts when asked to do so by Gilbert in August 2011. Given the fact that Grievant had experience as clerk prior to being hired by Corizon and was able to demonstrate her knowledge and understanding of her job duties, and given the lack of any evidence that Grievant requested further training, it was not unreasonable for Supervisor Gilbert not to offer remedial training to Grievant when she return to work from her leave of absence in 2011. Instead, Gilbert offered her personal assistance to Grievant when needed.</p>
<p>Second, as to Grievant's termination, it is found that after being advised in August 2011 that there were performance deficiencies in her work, Grievant failed to improve her job performance going forward. In October 2011, further audits of Ms. Broughton's work done after August, revealed continuing errors including charts out of order, improper placement of the MPL, failure to separate charts into volumes, upside-down records, missing purge dates and a chart missing any physician orders at all. Although Grievant may have not had any drop filings in the charts audited in October 2011, the October 2011 audits continued to show critical errors that could negatively impact patient care, such that Gilbert's conclusion that Broughton's work was not improving is supported by the evidence.</p>
<p>The Union has challenged Gilbert's methodology and accuracy in conducting the audits, but this argument is not found to be persuasive. While the audits may have only involved a limited number of Grievant's files and may have shown some improvement by Grievant as to a few types of errors, the evidence record supports Gilbert's conclusion that Broughton continued to make a significant number and variety of critical errors; and her determinations that (1) Grievant fell below an acceptable standard of performance, and (2) her improvement in the future was not anticipated, are found not unreasonable given Ms. Broughton's knowledge of what was expected of her as indicated by her prior demonstration of how to properly organize and maintain an inmate's health records and chart.</p>
<p>Third, as to the level of penalties imposed, the evidence record supports the conclusion that Grievant's job performance was sufficiently poor to warrant first a two-day suspension upon her return to work in August 2011 and then her subsequent termination in November 2011. Progressive discipline was followed here; previously Broughton had been reminded in a December 2009 performance review that she should increase her accuracy and eliminate loose filing in her charts and in December 2010, she was given a written verbal warning that she needed to eliminate loose filing. Broughton's lack of acceptance of responsibility here, blaming Gilbert, her fellow clerks and the healthcare providers for the errors in her charts, is a factor mitigating against a finding that a lesser discipline is warranted.</p>
<p>It is found that Ms. Gilbert's testimony, as the charging supervisor responsible for ensuring that the HIC's maintain the highest level of accuracy in filing inmate health record and proper handling of their medical charts, was credible . Grievant was given adequate time and opportunity to correct her performance deficiencies and to properly collate, sort and file the medical charts. This was an essential duty of a health information clerk, which Grievant failed to perform, placing inmates at risk of not being properly treated or not receiving prescribed medications. Grievant also placed the Employer and physicians at risk of claims of negligence and dereliction of their medical duties and responsibilities as professional care givers by failing to properly place doctor's orders and prescriptions in both the order and as required so that the orders could be properly signed and charts closed.</p>
<p>There is no dispute that Grievant was aware of what was required of her, but either could not or would not perform to the expectations or standards required by the employer. The Arbitrator is at a loss to explain, just as the Employer, exactly what transpired which caused Ms. Broughton to go from an efficient employee with a demonstrated knowledge of her job duties, to an employee who just stopped performing at the level of proficiency expected of her as a HIC at the Santa Rita Jail.</p>
<p>Accordingly, for the reasons as stated above, the Employer had just cause for the imposition of a two (2) day suspension and subsequent Notice of Termination. The Union's grievance is hereby denied.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>The Employer had just cause for discipline in this matter.</p></li>
<li><p>The Employer's disciplinary actions of suspension and subsequent termination of Grievant Jennifer Broughton are upheld. The Union's grievance is denied in its entirety.</p></li>
</ol>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>