<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between: CITY OF CHAMPAIGN Employer -AND- ILLINOIS FOP LABOR COUNCIL Union</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS Case No. 16-56091-6</p>
<p>December 30, 2016.</p>
<p>Micheal J. Falvo, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>ARBITRATION OPINION AND AWARD</i></b></h4>
<p>This arbitration took place under the July 1, 2012 &ndash; June 30, 2015 (as extended) Agreement between the Illinois FOP Labor Council, referred to herein as &ldquo;Employer&rdquo; or &ldquo;City,&rdquo; and the Illinois FOP Labor Council, referred to herein as &ldquo;Union.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The hearing took place at the Champaign Police Department, 82 E. University, Champaign IL. on September 19, 2016. The parties were afforded the opportunity to examine and cross-examine witnesses, to introduce relevant exhibits, and for argument. A transcript of the proceedings consisting of 350 pages was received on October 4, 2016. Post-hearing briefs were received on November 21, 2016 and upon receipt the record was closed. The record consists of the arbitrator's notes and exhibits admitted into evidence at the hearing.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i><small-cap>Issue</small-cap></i></b><ftnote num="1"><para>My customary practice is to not include the names of complainants or witnesses where to do so would serve no purpose. In this case the names of several individuals have been publicly disclosed in a press release. Excluding the names of those individuals would be pointless and create confusion. When necessary I have identified such individuals whose names have not been publicly disclosed by initials.</para></ftnote></h4>
<p class="continued">Was the Grievant discharged for just cause? If not, what is the remedy?</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i><small-cap>Relevant Contractual Provisions</small-cap></i></b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>Agreement</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>ARTICLE 32 &mdash; DISCIPLINARY ACTIONS (Excerpt)</b></h4>
<h4 align="left">32.1 IN GENERAL</h4>
<p class="continued">Discipline shall be based on just cause, administered progressively and correctly based on the individual circumstances of each case. Disciplinary action shall be limited to written reprimands, suspensions without pay (maximum thirty (30) calendar days) and suspensions with a recommendation for discharge. Demotion may be a disciplinary option for serious conduct unbecoming a sergeant which conduct impacts the sergeant's ability to supervise officers.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>ARTICLE 33 &mdash; GRIEVANCE AND APPEAL PROCEDURES (Excerpt)</b></h4>
<h4 align="left">33.5 &mdash; ARBITRATION/BOARD HEARING</h4>
<p class="continued">The Board of Fire and Police Commissioners or the arbitrator shall conduct a fair and impartial hearing, having the power to administer oaths, secure the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of books, papers and records by subpoena. If the Board of Fire and Police Commissioners or the arbitrator orders the City to produce information about the disciplinary records of other officers, such information shall be produced in such a manner that no individual officer's name is on a record and access will be limited to the Union. The Board of Fire and Police Commissioners or the arbitrator shall make a decision only on the issue(s) presented in the grievance and shall have no right to amend, modify, nullify, ignore, add to or subtract from the provisions of this Agreement. The Board of Fire and Police Commissioners or arbitrator shall be without authority to make a decision which is contrary to or inconsistent with law or rules and regulations having the force of law. The Board of Fire and Police Commissioners' or arbitrator's decision shall be rendered in writing to the parties within thirty (30) days of the close of hearing or the submission of post-hearing briefs, whichever is later.</p>
<p class="continued">The Board of Fire and Police Commissioners or the arbitrators shall either confirm, amend or reverse the decision of the CITY. In reaching its decision in fashioning a remedy, if any, the Board or the arbitrator shall take into account interim compensation and efforts to mitigate damages. No liability shall accrue against the CITY for events prior to the event grieved or in the case of discipline, the date of discipline.</p>
<p class="continued">The decision of the Board of Fire and Police Commissioners or the arbitrator shall be final and binding on all parties. This shall not prevent the filing of an Administrative Review action in Circuit Court by either the CITY or the UNION.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i><small-cap>Background</small-cap></i></b></h4>
<p>The City of Champaign has a population around 86,000 and is the home of the University of Illinois at Champaign-Urbana. The Champaign Police Department has an authorized strength of 125 sworn members. For the most part patrol officers work alone but two person patrol units are deployed for special details and in connection with training for new officers. Chief Anthony D. Cobb became Chief of Police in September 2010 after a 20-year career with the Urbana Police Department where he achieved the rank of Deputy Chief. Among his innumerable duties is the obligation to enforce the department's rules, regulations, and policies and to make determinations concerning discipline when an investigation determines that a member of the department has committed an act of misconduct.</p>
<p>The Grievant joined the Champaign Police Department on February 8, 2010. He successfully completed a three-month police academy program followed by a 22-week field-training program. By any measure his tenure with the Department has not been trouble free as demonstrated by a significant history of disciplinary actions. The record also contains substantial evidence demonstrating diligence and competence as a police officer.<ftnote num="2"><para>I concur with the assessment by Arbitrator Fredric R. Dichter: <quote>Thus, in addition to his deficiencies there are many positive aspects to Grievant's performance as a police officer.</quote> &lsqb;CITY EXH. 5, p. 13&rsqb;.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Department policy requires supervisors to complete &ldquo;Performance Reviews&rdquo; for patrol personnel.<ftnote num="3"><para>Performance reviews require supervisory personnel to rate officers in one of three categories: <quote>exceed standards,</quote> <quote>met standards,</quote> or <quote>below standards.</quote> The Grievant was deemed to have met standards in each performance review. It should be pointed out that the evaluations also contained suggestions for improvement such as focusing on traffic enforcement, using the training simulator for <quote>controlling your emotions,</quote> attending a training class to enhance investigative abilities, to conduct additional directed patrols in the vicinity of an apartment complex, and to keep up-to-date in reading policy and procedures.</para></ftnote> The first review was for the period February 11, 2011 to January 31, 2012. His shift supervisors wrote: &ldquo;Matt is an energetic officer. He likes to get out and make things happen. He has been involved in several foot chases due to the amount of citizen contacts and traffic stops he makes. Matt is the first in the District for midnight shift for the amount of stops he has made.&rdquo; &lsqb;UNION EXH. 8, p. 3&rsqb;. The next evaluation states, &ldquo;His verbal skills have helped to de-escalate many tense calls on the shift.&rdquo; That evaluation continued:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Officer Rush sets the example for other officers when it comes to listening to the radio, recognizing when there is a need for another officer for backup, assistance, a need for paperwork, and to take a report for another officer from another beat that is buried in paper. Officer Rush truly believes what his patch says &ldquo;Champaign Police.&rdquo; There are no district boundaries in his mind, but he does respect the limit and takes care of his district at the same time.</p>
<p class="continued">Officer Rush is an energetic officer who wants to be involved in everything and experience new things. Officer Rush is well prepared for his duties, exceptionally dressed, and willing to take on responsibilities when generally asked of officers. Officer Rush prepares his reports, generally, in a timely manner, with very few errors or corrections. Officer Rush is social with all his coworkers and recognized as a team player. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 8, p. 10&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">In the next evaluation his supervisor observed that his level of proactive enforcement was significant and that in the second quarter of the rating period he responded to the most calls for service on his shift (370 calls compared to the shift average of 240 calls). The evaluation continued:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Officer Rush is always courteous and treats people in an equal and fair manner. During this rating period Officer Rush received seven thank you letters: One for politeness, respect and efficiency, one for proper handling of a volatile situation (use of force/pepper spray arrest), one for a job well done, one for court preparedness and professional testimony, one for professionalism, respect, and courtesy, and one letter of general appreciation. Based on the level of unsolicited feedback, it is obvious that Officer Rush is treating people fairly and making good judgments on the street. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 8, pp. 14-15&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">In his next evaluation his supervisor wrote that he continues to have some of the highest number of proactive contacts for the North District, leads his shift in criminal arrests, and works well with other officers on the shift. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 8, p. 22&rsqb;. In the final evaluation for the period February 1, 2015 to January 31, 2016 &ndash; for not the first time &ndash; his adeptness at deescalating situations was noted.<ftnote num="4"><para><quote>His verbal skills have helped de-escalate many tense calls on the shift.</quote> &lsqb;UNION EXH. 8, p. 35&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> The evaluating supervisor also described a &ldquo;family trouble&rdquo; incident he observed when reviewing in-car video recordings.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The family was intoxicated and not happy with &lsqb;another officer&rsqb; on a family problem on &lsqb;redacted&rsqb; Road. As soon as Officer Rush arrived one female immediately said, &ldquo;I want to talk to him.&rdquo; Officer Rush had a calming presence and helped to mitigate the scene. Both officers cleared without making an arrest. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 8, p. 24&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">That evaluation commended him for attempting to fix a homeless man's motorized wheelchair and securing assistance when he could not repair it. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 8, p. 25&rsqb;. The evaluation noted that on two occasions he received congratulatory emails from Deputy Chief Gallo. In the first email, dated October 2, 2015, the Deputy Chief was present when a female arrestee thanked Officer Rush for his nice treatment.<ftnote num="5"><para>5The e-mail from Deputy Chief Gallo stated:</para>
<block-quote>
<para>Just shared an elevator ride with Officer Rush and a female that he transported to investigations. The young lady, who was in handcuffs, thanked him for the way he was treating her. I have already spoken to Officer Rush and expressed my appreciation. I wanted to make sure you were aware of this positive interaction he had today with this young lady. Great example of Unconditional Respect!! &lsqb;UNION EXH. 7(p)&rsqb;.</para></block-quote></ftnote> In the second email, dated October 2, 2015, Deputy Chief Gallo complimented Officer Rush for professionalism while assisting University police officers handling a disturbance at Presence Hospital during which an officer was attacked. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 7(m) &amp; TR. p. 279&rsqb;. The supervisor who prepared the evaluation wrote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">On 11/13/2015, Officer Rush was first to arrive on the scene of a Domestic Battery in progress. He was going to wait for other officers but heard screaming and saw someone run inside. He ultimately had to wrestle a suspect and later spray him with OC. When I arrived the brother of the suspect told me several times how much he appreciated our efforts, particularly Officer Rush. The witness even pulled me in to hug me in thanks before the Officers left the scene. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 8, p. 25&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p>By stipulation, the record includes a synopsis of the testimony of 11 character witnesses who testified before Arbitrator Fredric Dichter on February 6 and March 13, 2015 with the understanding that they would offer the same testimony if called as witnesses in this proceeding.<ftnote num="6"><para>The parties also stipulated that except for officers who served as Field Training Officers the witnesses did not have supervisory authority over the Grievant, were not privy to his personnel or discipline files, were not involved in or familiar with the three disciplinary incidents at issue in the prior arbitration, and were not involved in or familiar with the facts of the matter before this arbitrator. The City entered the stipulation without waiving its objection that character is not relevant or at issue in the pending case.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued"><i>Sergeant Tom Petrilli</i>: The Grievant is a team player and the sergeant never had to correct him. He is proactive and very eager. He works well with other officers and always strives to produce a quality work product.<ftnote num="7"><para>Chief Cobb explained at the hearing that officers are expected to be proactive: they should be <quote>out there looking for potential problems.</quote> &lsqb;TR. p. 180&rsqb;. He shared Sergeant Petrilli's assessment that the Grievant is a proactive officer who chose to work in the City's <quote>busy</quote> districts. &lsqb;TR. p. 216&rsqb;.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued"><i>Officer Tim Atteberry</i>: The witness was the Grievant's Field Training Officer as well as his instructor in the police academy. He is very respectful, well liked, professional, and courageous.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Detective Andre Davis</i>: The witness was the Grievant's Field Training Officer for eight weeks. The Grievant is the best recruit he ever trained. He has an uncanny ability to retain information. He strives to learn more and grow. He admits when he makes mistakes and accepts criticism well. He is responsible and goes above and beyond the call of duty.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Detective Ed Sebestik</i>: The Grievant epitomizes what one wants in a police officer. He is always available to answer questions and if he does not have an answer he finds one. The witness observed him handle very dangerous calls professionally and he was able to get chaotic situations under control. He holds the Grievant in the highest regard. The Grievant has integrity and no one cares more about the job than he does.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Officer Nick Krippel</i>: The Grievant is the most reliable officer he ever worked with. He regularly volunteers for calls. He is direct and to the point and professional. He has strong and dependable character. The witness would trust the Grievant with his children and he has helped officers on and off duty.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Detective Brad Kraul</i>: The Grievant is a productive officer and always helpful on calls. He makes sure to back up other officers.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Officer Art Miller:</i> The Grievant is a hard worker and very passionate about the job. As a new officer he was a quick learner who takes pride in his work. He is proactive, always responsible, and helps out other officers. For the Grievant police work is not just a job: it is his calling.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Officer Greg Campbell</i>: The Grievant is always the first officer to respond no matter where he is working. As a new officer he was respectful and receptive to training tips. He exhibits very impressive tactical thinking on hot call. He always stays in control of situations and acts professionally.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Officer Dave Butler</i>: The witness worked as the Grievant's partner and in 2011 and 2013 and they responded to hundreds of calls together. He is a great officer who is knowledgeable, energetic, and professional.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Officer Steve Vogel</i>: The Grievant is always willing to help out. The Grievant would be the first officer he would call if he needed assistance.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Officer Brian Rogers</i>: The witness selected to work in the same districts as the Grievant. He is dependable, conscientious, and &ldquo;watches your back.&rdquo; He is the first to respond when officers request assistance. He is a standup person who is &ldquo;an open book&rdquo; with the highest integrity. The department needs more officers like the Grievant.</p>
<p>The Grievant's personnel records contain three &ldquo;Letters of Commendation&rdquo; (one in 2012<ftnote num="8"><para>On September 1, 2012, the Grievant and three other officers received a Letter of Commendation. It states: <quote>&lsqb;W&rsqb;ith little regard for their personal safety</quote> they entered an apartment building, portions of which were fully engulfed in fire and evacuated the entire building prior to the arrival of the fire department. It concluded that the officers' <quote>heroic efforts in evacuating this building</quote> undoubtedly prevented serious injuries or deaths.&rdquo; &lsqb;UNION EXH. 7(j)&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> and two in 2013) and four &ldquo;Letters of Appreciation&rdquo; from citizens (three in 2012 and one in 2015).<ftnote num="9"><para>Somewhat astonishingly, at least in my experience, on February 28, 2012 a citizen to whom the Grievant issued a traffic citation sent a compliment using the City's website. He wrote that the officer explained that residents in the area were concerned about speeding <quote>which I found helpful to know.</quote> He said: <quote>Officer Matt Rush was very polite, respectful, and efficient &lsqb;and&rsqb; I appreciated Officer Rush's polite demeanor and efficiency and I will definitely pay more attention to how fast I am driving.</quote> &lsqb;UNION EX. 7(e)&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> A letter dated January 31, 2012 &lsqb;UNION EXH. 7(b)&rsqb; from a particularly articulate citizen to the City Manager is noteworthy. The individual was working at a caf&eacute; during a student run party when a fight broke out between two patrons that quickly escalated when others joined the melee and one of the combatants produced a handgun and threatened people. She wrote that the first officers on scene (one of whom the Department identified as the Grievant) &ldquo;without fear or hesitation&rdquo; instructed people to break up the fight and dispersed people using pepper spray being careful not to affect anyone who was positioned away from the brawl. The officers then located and handcuffed the man who had produced the handgun.<ftnote num="10"><para>The officers recovered the firearm at the scene. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 8, p. 4&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> She continued: &ldquo;Within minutes, the officers of the Champaign Police Department had deescalated the situation and made all the necessary steps in preserving the peace and ensuring the safety of all the patrons who were not involved in the incident.&rdquo; The citizen concluded:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">I have always been very outspoken against police misconduct in general and the use of excessive force &ndash; both of which are legitimate issues in the American Justice system that should be discussed and addressed &ndash; but in my opinion, the police officers who responded to this call in the early hours of January 20<sup>th</sup> did <i>everything right</i> in regards to force.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;I send you this letter in hopes that these officers will receive my heartfelt thanks. These officers should be commended for their actions and their ability to keep their cool in a heated situation: they are a great asset to this town and our community. (Emphasis in original).</p></blockquote>
<p>The Grievant's personnel records reflect that he has received six complaints filed by citizens (one in 2011, three in 2012, one in 2013, and one in 2014).<ftnote num="11"><para>Although listed as <quote>Complaints</quote> in a document titled <quote>Officer's Combined Administrative Records</quote> for purposes of this summary I have excluded complaints where the complainant is listed as <quote>Department</quote> or <quote>Chief Cobb.</quote> State's Attorney Rietz is also listed as a complainant in connection with her February 23, 2016 letter and is also not included in the above summary.</para></ftnote> The finding in one complaint was &ldquo;sustained&rdquo; and the findings in the other five complaints were designated either &ldquo;unfounded&rdquo; or &ldquo;not sustained.&rdquo;<ftnote num="12"><para>The complaint was made by <quote><fill character="space" width="5"/></quote> on July 31, 2013 &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 33&rsqb; and was deemed <quote>Sustained</quote> after an investigation on September 9, 2013. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 96&rsqb;. This disciplinary action will be discussed in further detail. My understanding that the designation <quote>unfounded</quote> is used when the investigation established that the officer acted properly and the designation <quote>not sustained</quote> is used when the investigation disclosed insufficient evidence to substantiate the allegations.</para></ftnote> The personnel file indicates that the Grievant has been counseled on four occasions.<ftnote num="13"><para>Three counseling entries were made <fill character="space" width="5"/> <quote>Officer was counseled in/re his use of force with non-compliant subject.</quote> &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 14&rsqb;. Article 32.1 of the collective bargaining agreement limits the definition of <quote>disciplinary actions</quote> to written reprimands, suspensions without pay for a maximum of 30 days, and suspensions with a recommendation for discharge. The City asserts in its post-hearing brief that counseling is not considered discipline but that it can be taken into account for purposes of progressive discipline.</para></ftnote> <fill character="space" width="5"/> As will be discussed in substantially greater detail, his personnel record reflects disciplinary suspensions on three dates:<ftnote num="14"><para><fill character="space" width="5"/></para></ftnote>; 9/10/2013 &ndash; 2 days<ftnote num="15"><para>This suspension involved the sustained citizen complaint made by <quote><fill character="space" width="5"/></quote> and will be discussed in further detail. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 98&rsqb;.</para></ftnote>; and 8/8/2014 &ndash; 1 day,<ftnote num="16"><para>This disciplinary offense concerned the circumstances surrounding the completion and submission of an accident report and citation from a traffic crash investigation on March 3, 2014. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 106&rsqb;. It will be discussed in further detail.</para></ftnote> 3 days,<ftnote num="17"><para>This suspension arose from an investigation concerning the Grievant's actions during the arrest of Kissica Seets on April 11, 2014. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 122&rsqb;. It will be discussed in further detail.</para></ftnote> and 30 days. The 30-day suspension resulted from an arbitration award that overturned a termination decision by the Chief of Police.<ftnote num="18"><para>The disciplinary offense that resulted in the Grievant's first termination involved the arrest of Precious Jackson on May 26, 2014. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 194&rsqb;. Arbitrator Fredric R. Dichter rescinded the termination and imposed a 30-day suspension. The award was issued on April 3, 2015. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 429&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> Under the terms of Arbitrator Dichter's award the Grievant was reinstated with partial back pay on April 8, 2015. The disciplinary action under review here, which terminated his employment a second time, took effect on April 13, 2016.</p>
<p>Because the disciplinary action arising from the arrest of Precious Jackson included a charge of untruthfulness, Chief Cobb sent the following letter dated October 9, 2014 to State's Attorney Rietz. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 1&rsqb;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Ms. Rietz,</p>
<p class="continued">As required by law, I write to inform you of a recent disciplinary matter involving an officer of the Champaign Police Department. On August 8, 2014, Officer Matt Rush was charged with a violation of department policy wherein the offending behavior involved untruthful or deceptive representations. As you are aware, under <i>Brady v. Maryland</i>, 373 U.S. 83 (1963) and <i>Giglio v. United States</i>, 405 U.S. 150 (1972) and its progeny, the Champaign Police Department is required to disclose such information regarding the untruthfulness of law enforcement officers to prosecutors.</p>
<p class="continued">Please feel free to contact my office in the event that you have any questions regarding this matter.</p></blockquote>
<p>When Chief Cobb received Arbitrator Dichter's Opinion &amp; Award he sent a second letter and a copy of the decision to State's Attorney Reitz and United States Attorney Ronda Holliman-Coleman. &lsqb;TR. pp. 230-231&rsqb;. The Grievant's personnel record as it stands today does not reflect any disciplinary action for untruthfulness because the single prior disciplinary action involving that offense was deleted in accordance with the arbitration decision. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 6 &amp; TR. pp. 231-232&rsqb;.</p>
<p>The Grievant was reinstated on April 8, 2015. Chief Cobb told him that he was being given a &ldquo;fresh start&rdquo; and the Chief disposed of a pending matter to give him a &ldquo;clean slate.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 203&rsqb;. The Grievant asked to be assigned to the day shift in Southwest District because it was not as fast paced as the districts he previously worked. &lsqb;TR. p. 257&rsqb;. Chief Cobb arranged for the Grievant to receive additional training and procedures were implemented for additional supervision. &lsqb;TR. p. 203&rsqb;. Chief Cobb testified that after being reinstated the Grievant did not receive any citizen complaints. He did not receive any discipline. &lsqb;TR. p. 219&rsqb;. &ldquo;The few use of force incidents he has been involved in &lsqb;after his reinstatement&rsqb; have all been reviewed and approved.&rdquo; UNION EXH. 8, p. 32&rsqb;. Chief Cobb acknowledged: &ldquo;I think we were moving forward. He was moving forward in a positive manner.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 220&rsqb;.<ftnote num="19"><para>The record amply supports the Chief's characterization of the Grievant's work performance after his reinstatement on April 8, 2015. The two laudatory emails from Deputy Chief Gallo have been discussed. The record also contains the following.</para>
<block-quote><para>&bull; On September 17, 2015 Sergeant Maloney wrote in an email: &ldquo;Nice job by Rush. He also went out of his way to take a report from the guy at &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb;. He didn't want one but Rush asked him if he could process the car. He agreed, and got a print and then also got that info about &lsqb;store name redacted&rsqb; for &lsqb;Detective Christian&rsqb;. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 7(n)&rsqb;. The information concerned the possibility of obtaining video that could identify perpetrators of a recent crime.</para>
<para>&bull; On September 30, 2015 Detective Christian wrote in an email:</para>
<block-quote><para>Matt: Thanks for your hard work and tenacity processing the numerous BMV &lsqb;Burglary Motor Vehicle&rsqb; that you have been assigned. I notice that you processed all the scenes for prints and went as far as to track down other victims from evidence you found during your investigation. The information you gathered made my job that much easier and resulted in the arrest of &lsqb;name redacted&rsqb;. He confessed to 5 BMV in the same area but I was only able to put the 2 cases you processed on him. &lsqb;He&rsqb; lives at &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb; which is in general area for most of the BMV reports that I have been assigned. Fine work, thanks! Jere. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 7(o).</para></block-quote>
<para>&bull; On November 3, 2015 Day Shift Commander Lieutenant Tod Myers sent an email to the Grievant and Officer Talbot.</para>
<block-quote><para>I spoke to &lsqb;name redacted&rsqb; this morning. You both responded to a garage alarm at her house on 10/30 at &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb;. She just wanted to call and thank you for remaining at the location until her daughter arrived. In this particular case she was transporting her husband to the ER and thought she had shut it. Her husband is a retired LT from ISP and she was very grateful for what you both did. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 7(q).</para></block-quote>
<para>&bull; On November 13, 2015 Sergeant Bruce Ramseyer sent an email to the Day Shift Commander. (I have revised punctuation in the original email).</para>
<block-quote><para>Domestic at &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb;. Rush arrived and was waiting outside for his backup when he heard screaming and saw someone run back inside, more screaming. The female came running out screaming that she had been thrown to the ground. The male balled up his fists and asked Rush if he wanted to fight. Rush ultimately sprayed him with &lsqb;Officer&rsqb; McLearin. Family members on scene were cooperative and supportive of police. Rush had scrapes on his knees. Ambulance responded and decontaminated him, he then complained about seizures, etc. He was taken to ER for medical release. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 7(r)&rsqb;.</para></block-quote></block-quote>
<para>As already noted, the use of force investigation into the November 13<superscript>th</superscript> incident (and all others after his reinstatement) concluded that the Grievant's actions were within policy.</para></ftnote> The Chief said that after being reinstated &ldquo;he has done what we have asked him to do; he has handled the calls that came before him and I am not aware of any call that has come up that he did not handle in the manner we expected him to handle it.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 226-227&rsqb;.</p>
<p>The situation changed in December 2015. The News Gazette published a series of articles about several lawsuits filed against the Champaign Police Department that had recently been settled. The articles and documents pertaining to the settlement are not in the record but have been characterized as disparaging. Although he was not the only officer named as a defendant in the lawsuits, the Grievant testified &ldquo;&lsqb;m&rsqb;y face and name was across every newspaper in Central Illinois&rdquo; with the caption &ldquo;Breaking News in boldface across the front page.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. pp. 257-258&rsqb;. In order to &ldquo;let the smoke settle down some&rdquo; he decided, with the Department's concurrence, to take an extended leave that continued for several months until he was cleared for full duty on March 1, 2016. &lsqb;TR. pp. 266-269&rsqb;. When he returned to duty he was placed on paid investigative leave until April 13, 2016 at which time he was fired. &lsqb;UNION EXH. 3 &amp; 4&rsqb;.</p>
<p>The media coverage did not go unnoticed. State's Attorney Rietz testified that members of the clergy and other citizens contacted her and she convened a meeting that was attended by about a dozen persons including pastors, a state representative, the president of the local NAACP, graduate students, and other citizens. &lsqb;TR. p. 49 &amp; pp. 129-131&rsqb;. The individuals in attendance &ldquo;were demanding that I charge him&rdquo; and she told them, without making anybody any promises, that she would review the matter. &lsqb;TR. p. 49&rsqb;. On December 11, 2015, the Clerk of Court of the Circuit Court of Champaign County, &ldquo;pursuant to a criminal investigation being conducted by the Champaign County State's Attorney's Office&rdquo; issued a Subpoena Duces Tecum &lsqb;CITY EXH. 2&rsqb; requiring the production of:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Any and all records in whatever form including but not limited to: case reports; internal investigative reports; crime scene processing reports; inventory slips; photographs; audio recordings; video recordings; investigative notes; litigation and case summaries; arbitrator's decision; citizen complaints relating to: any citizen complaints or lawsuits regarding Champaign Police Officer Matthew Rush; and unredacted copies of any documents previously released to the media on December 10, 2015 regarding the settlement of a lawsuit.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">On February 23, 2016 she sent a letter to Chief Cobb concerning her findings. &lsqb;JOINT EXH. 1&rsqb;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Dear Chief Cobb,</p>
<p class="continued">As you are aware, I was asked by community members to review Officer Matt Rush's conduct with regards to the use of force. The Champaign Police Department provided my office with internal documents detailing Officer Rush's disciplinary history, and I and my staff have thoroughly reviewed those materials as well as additional materials related to those events. We have now completed that review process, and I am sending this letter as confirmation of the conclusions of the State's Attorney's Office.</p>
<p class="continued">I am declining to file criminal charges against Officer Rush with regard to his use of force in making arrests that have been the subject of public concern and civil legal action as I and my staff do not find sufficient legal basis to proceed in criminal court. However, my review of Officer Rush's disciplinary history has led me to conclude that the State's Attorney's Office is unable to call Officer Rush as a witness on behalf of the state in criminal proceedings in light of his repeated failure to adequately document use of force in multiple discipline actions for untruthfulness. These incidents create a substantial issue with regards to his credibility as a witness, subject him to cross-examination on these issues, and require the State's Attorney's Office to work around him in order to bring criminal cases to trial. Moreover, our review of these incidents causes us great concern about his judgement and decision-making in crisis situations, particularly with regard to his response to the mentally ill. In light of these concerns, having given this matter serious consideration and taking into account his full disciplinary history, we have concluded that if Officer Rush were to return to active duty, we will not call Officer Rush as a witness for the prosecution in criminal proceedings.</p>
<p>I appreciate and support your efforts to resolve these matters internally and will continue to be available to work with you as we move forward.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Sincerely,</p>
<p class="continued">/s/</p>
<p class="continued">Julia Rietz</p>
<p class="continued">Champaign County State's Attorney</p></blockquote></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Simultaneously she issued a press release. &lsqb;JOINT EXH. 2&rsqb;.</p>
<blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>Office of State's Attorney</b></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>Champaign County, Illinois</b></h4>
<p align="right">February 23, 2016</p>
<p class="continued">Officer Matt Rush Review</p>
<p class="continued">At the request of community members, following the City of Champaign's entry into settlement agreements in civil lawsuits filed on behalf of William Brown, Benjamin Mann and Kissica Seets and an arbitrator's decision to overturn the Champaign Police Department's termination of Officer Matt Rush, the State's Attorney's Office has conducted a review of the reports and investigations surrounding these settlements to determine the appropriateness of criminal charges. In response to a subpoena, Champaign Police Department provided my office with documentation of Officer Rush's personnel file, including all complaints filed with the department involving him, all disciplinary actions, and accompanying police reports and videos, and we have carefully reviewed all those materials.</p>
<p class="continued">We have also reviewed relevant Illinois statutes and case law. 720ILCS 5/7-5, provides that a peace officer is justified in the use of any force which he reasonably believes to be necessary to effect an arrest and of any force which he reasonably believes to be necessary to defend himself or another from bodily harm while making the arrest. The courts have reviewed allegations of excessive use of force in criminal and civil proceedings. Generally, excessive force complaints have been sustained when an officer uses force on an individual who is in custody and not resisting, when an officer uses unreasonable force with a tool or weapon such as a bludgeon or a firearm, or when the injuries to the individual are severe. Excessive force complaints have not been sustained in cases involving individuals who were actively resisting the officer's efforts during the course of an arrest, and when the officer did not use a weapon and the individual did not sustain serious bodily injury.</p>
<p class="continued">Based on our review, we are declining to file criminal charges against Matt Rush with regard to his use of force and the arrest of William Brown, Benjamin Mann, Kissica Seets, and Precious Jackson. These matters were or are appropriately handled in internal discipline and in civil court proceedings. The evidence as outlined below does not provide a reasonable likelihood that we would be able to meet the standard of proof beyond a reasonable doubt as is required for the filing of criminal charges. Furthermore, particularly with regards the Seets and Jackson incidents, although Officer Rush failed to deescalate the situation through his aggressive and unprofessional behavior, his actions in using force to subdue resistive subjects are defensible under Illinois law.</p>
<p class="continued">While we are declining to file criminal charges, the State's Attorney's Office affirmatively states that we will not rely on Officer Rush as a witness for the prosecution in criminal cases. Officer Rush's substantial history of internal discipline for untruthfulness and failure to document use of force call his credibility as a witness into question and will subject him to cross examination by defense counsel in every case. Moreover, our concerns about his judgement and decision-making with regards to his approach and contact with citizens in crisis, particularly those with mental health concerns, makes us unable to vouch for his credibility and reliability as a witness in our cases, regardless of his role.</p>
<p class="continued">The following is an outline of the four relevant incidents:</p>
<p class="continued"><b>William Brown</b>: On June 2, 2013, Officer Rush was involved in the arrest of William Brown following a hit-and-run traffic crash. Brown fled from Officer Rush and Officer Coleman. Brown was resistive and Officer Rush punched Brown in the face in the course of taking him into custody. Brown admitted that he was intoxicated and that he ran from officers because he was driving under the influence of alcohol. There is no squad car video of the arrest. Brown did not make a formal complaint however he obtained a settlement from the City of Champaign after filing a civil suit. The settlement is not evidence of admission of liability and cannot be considered for criminal review purposes. No information other than the original police reports is available with regard to this incident. Officer Rush was not subject to internal discipline with regard to this case. There is no evidence to support criminal charges alleging excessive use of force under Illinois law.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Benjamin Mann</b>: On March 16, 2014, Officer Rush and other officers were involved in the arrest of Benjamin Mann. Rush and Officer Marshall Henry responded to <fill character="space" width="5"/> at the request of Mann's former girlfriend, <fill character="space" width="5"/>, who had called 911 requesting officer assistance because Mann was outside her residence, he had been drinking and was wanting his property. During the course of the incident Mann refused to remove his hand from his pocket and refused to comply with the officers' directives. The officers attempted to take Mann into custody, and he resisted their efforts. Officer Rush requested additional assistance, and 3 other officers arrived. The event lasted 4 minutes, the first three which involved Rush and Henry alone, the final minute involving all 5 officers attempting to get Mann in custody. Mann sustained injuries. Rush sustained injuries as well. Due to the lack of lighting and the distance, squad car video provided no visual documentation of the incident. Mann and <fill character="space" width="5"/> filed formal complaints against the officers. A formal review by the CPD command staff resulted in a finding that Mann's arrest was lawful. Additionally, certain allegations of excessive force were determined to be unfounded. Other allegations could &lsqb;sic&rsqb; &lsqb;not&rsqb; be sustained based upon the available evidence. No officers, including Rush, were subject to internal discipline. Mann later initiated civil proceedings and the City entered into a settlement of his claims. The settlement cannot be considered for criminal review purposes. Criminal charges are not appropriate against Officer Rush or the other officers involved in this incident because the use of force in subduing a resistive subject was appropriate under Illinois law. We agree with the internal review findings and conclusions. Those findings create a legal defense for Officer Rush with regard to potential criminal liability.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Kissica Seets</b>: On April 11, 2014, Officer Rush and other officers were involved in the arrest of Kissica Seets. Officers were dispatched to <fill character="space" width="5"/> regarding a fight in progress. Thirteen officers responded to the call. <fill character="space" width="5"/> Kissica and <fill character="space" width="5"/>, reported that the two were fighting. Officers Schweska and Henry were the first to arrive. The scene was chaotic. In the presence of officers, Kissica struck<fill character="space" width="5"/> in the face with her fist and the two engaged in an active fist fight, resulting in the two of them being sprayed by Officer Schweska with OC spray. <fill character="space" width="5"/> also picked up a chair and threw it at Kissica, hitting her in the side. Other officers, including Officer Rush, arrived and detained the two. Officer Rush and Officer Haugen attempted to escort Kissica to a nearby squad car. Audio recording captured exchanges between Rush and Kissica which were later determined by command personnel to be inappropriate and unprofessional and demonstrated a failure by Officer Rush to deescalate the situation. In response to the exchanges Kissica spat directly in Officer Rush's face. Rush maintained control of her and took her to the squad car. In his report, Rush wrote &ldquo;I escorted Kissica to Officer Canales squad car without further incident.&rdquo; However, review of squad car video and audio shows that Officer Rush uses his right leg to push Kissica into the vehicle, and then delivers a knee strike to Kissica. Officer Haugen then steps in and takes over. Officer Haugen reported during internal review of the matter that Kissica was kicking at the officers while they attempted to put her in the squad car. Kissica did not suffer injuries as result of the knee strikes.</p>
<p class="continued">Kissica was charged with Aggravated Battery to a Peace Officer for spitting in Rush's face. She pleaded guilty to that offense and was sentenced to 12 months of probation. The issue of excessive use of force was not raised by defense counsel in resolving her case.</p>
<p class="continued">Following internal review of the event, Officer Rush was suspended for 3 days due to his failure to document the use of force, his violation of rules with regards to unprofessional behavior, and his use of force with regards the second knee strike. The suspension was reviewed in arbitration pursuant to the FOP contract. The Arbitrator sustained the 3 day suspension, agreeing with the Department's findings with regard to Officer's Rush's use of profanity and lack of professionalism and his failure to document the use of force. However, the Arbitrator disagreed with the department's conclusion that the second kick was inappropriate. The arbitrator wrote, &ldquo;looking at the video of the incident it is hard to determine where the woman's legs were when the second kick occurred. The testimony was that she still was not completely in the car. The video is not clear enough to contradict that testimony.&rdquo; The Arbitrator recommended that Officer Rush receive additional training to show him how he might better handle confrontational situations, as &ldquo;skills in deescalating a situation are critical to prevent force from having to be used.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">Kissica Seets filed a civil suit and entered into a settlement agreement with the City. The settlement of this claim cannot be considered as evidence with regard to potential criminal charges. Criminal charges cannot be filed against Officer Rush with regards to the two knee strikes in that, although Officer Rush failed to deescalate the situation and failed to document the use of force, Kissica was actively resistant, spit in his face, and physically resisted being placed in the squad car, thus providing a legal defense that his use of force with regards to the knee strikes was reasonable and appropriate to effectuate the rest of a resistive subject.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Precious Jackson</b>: On May 26, 2014, Officer Rush arrested Precious Jackson for Aggravated Battery to a Peace Officer. Earlier in the day Champaign Fire Department and Champaign police responded to a fire at Jackson's residence. Jackson was not present, but concern arose as to her condition in light of her history of mental health issues and reports that she had been drinking alcohol. As that was going on, officers were dispatched to Thornton's, 101 S. Mattis, regarding a criminal damage to property and disorderly subject. The clerk advised that a woman matching Jackson's description damaged merchandise and was screaming at customers. In response to that call Officer Rush located Jackson on University Avenue.</p>
<p class="continued">As documented by Officer Rush's squad car video, Officer Rush pulled up next to Jackson and yelled at her &ldquo;come here!&rdquo; In his written report he said he &ldquo;instructed her to stop and come to me.&rdquo; Jackson yelled back at him and continued walking, then began running. Officer Rush ran after her and she stopped and turned back towards him. Officer Rush reported that Jackson raised her left hand and grabbed him by the throat. He had scratch marks consistent with his account of the situation. In response to her grabbing him by the throat, Officer Rush took Jackson to the ground. In his report Rush described the struggle with Jackson, saying that he used a knee strike and OC spray to get her under control. Review of the video shows he also made a motion consistent with punching or striking Jackson. Rush was able to get Jackson under control and placed her under arrest. She was transported to the Champaign County Correctional Center.</p>
<p class="continued">Jackson was charged formally with Aggravated Battery to a Police Officer. The Public Defender's Office was appointed and a preliminary hearing was held on June 13, 2014. Judge Kennedy found probable cause for the arrest. The Public Defender's Office filed a motion &lsqb;sic&rsqb; requested that Jackson be evaluated by a psychiatrist for fitness to stand trial. Dr. Larry Jeckel conducted the evaluation and concluded that she was unfit to stand trial based on her mental health status and alcohol use. <fill character="space" width="5"/> She remained in the Champaign County Correctional Center until July 27, 2014, following a review of fitness by the Department of Human Services. <fill character="space" width="5"/>, her condition was stabilized and she had regained fitness. The charges were dismissed in light of Officer Rush's termination on July 23, 2014. Although not part of the CPD review, it's important to note that Jackson was arrested again in April, 2015, which led to a second finding of unfitness and hospitalization. As a result of that situation, Jackson is currently on probation.</p>
<p class="continued">Jackson did not file a formal complaint against Officer Rush. CPD conducted a standard internal use of force review of the event, which raised concerns about Rush's confrontational and discourteous initial approach with Jackson and his failure to document the action that could have been a strike or a punch in his formal report. During further investigation, CPD located a witness who was in a nearby parked car. That individual, who lives in Colorado, reported by phone that he had just gotten in his car when he heard yelling. He saw Jackson walking eastbound. He heard the officer tell her to stop. He heard Jackson yell back using profanity. He saw her turn and run and saw Rush chase her. He said Jackson &ldquo;turned on him and became aggressive towards him.&rdquo; He said she was &ldquo;not being compliant.&rdquo; He described the knee strike and said he left after she went down to the ground. He said he did not see the officer strike Jackson with his hand or fist. As a result of the review, Champaign command staff recommended termination of Officer Rush's employment. Lt. Swenson noted numerous attempts at training opportunities to guide and counsel Rush in his continuous failure to conduct himself in a professional matter, control his temper, display sound judgement and bring his job performance in line with city values. He recommended termination. Lt. Shaffer agreed. Deputy Chief Gallo reviewed the reviews, and noted that the camera angle does not show if the strike impacted Jackson, that she did not confirm or deny that she was struck, and that her booking photo does not show any visible signs of injury. He concluded that Rush did make &ldquo;a striking motion&rdquo; and did not adequately document it. He agreed with termination based on this pattern of failure to document use of force and disciplinary issues.</p>
<p class="continued">Lt. Paulus also reviewed the investigation and reviews. Lt. Paulus said the video is not clear as to the strike, it may have hit her or it may have missed her. Lt. Paulus said the conclusion that the strike was not necessary or reasonable does not take into account what Jackson was doing in her confrontation with Rush. He said &ldquo;in the tense and uncertain time of an active struggle with a suspect who is allegedly attacked and scratched an officer, I find it concerning that such conclusions are made without the totality of the situation being articulated.&rdquo; Lt. Paulus concurred with termination, noting that the strike was not documented in his report, a violation of policy. But, he said that fact &ldquo;does not negate the fact that the strike may have been in response to what Jackson was doing at the time.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">Officer Rush's termination was reviewed in arbitration pursuant to the FOP contract. The Arbitrator disagreed with the Department's decision to terminate Rush's employment, granted Rush's grievance and set aside the termination in favor of a 30 day suspension. Specifically with regard to the punch or strike, the Arbitrator wrote &ldquo;there is no evidence anything was done, even if it was a punch, out of malice or loss of temper, but was instead done to subdue an uncooperative person. It must be viewed in that context.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">A lawsuit has been filed on Jackson's behalf on February 20, 2016, in federal court. The suit contains allegations that Jackson suffered a miscarriage as result of Rush's actions. These allegations are inconsistent with information provided in Jackson's booking records at the time of her arrest.</p>
<p class="continued">The State's Attorney's Office is declining to file criminal charges against Officer Rush with regard to his use of force in this incident. While we agree with the conclusions of the internal review, and while we believe that Officer Rush escalated the situation by his aggressive approach, his actions with regard to that initial approach are not a violation of criminal law. Officer Rush appropriately followed Jackson when she ran from him, and was not in violation of law or policy in taking Jackson to the ground after she grabbed him by the throat. Finally, with regards to the punch or strike, we decline to file criminal charges due to issues of proof. It is unclear in the video if Rush actually struck Jackson, and neither Jackson nor the independent witness report a punch or strike. Moreover, the action, if it was a punch or a strike, was determined by the Arbitrator to be reasonable under the circumstances in order to subdue a resistive subject.</p>
<p class="continued">Although the State's Attorney's Office is declining to file criminal charges against Officer Matt Rush, in light of our review of Officer Rush's actions and behavior during these incidents and in the light of the entirety of Officer Rush's history of internal discipline for failure to adequately document use of force and untruthfulness, we are unable to use Officer Matt Rush as a witness for the prosecution in criminal cases. Officer Rush's repeated discipline for failure to adequately document use of force and untruthfulness as outlined here and in other disciplinary actions reviewed in the course of this examination create a substantial issue with regards to his credibility as a state witness, subject him to cross-examination on these issues, and require the State's Attorney's Office to work around him in order to bring criminal cases to trial. Moreover, a review of these incidents cause us great concern about his judgement and decision making in crisis situations, particularly with regard to his response the mentally ill. In light of these concerns, having given this matter serious consideration and taking into account his full disciplinary history, we have concluded that if Officer Rush were to return to active duty, we will not call Officer Rush as a witness for the prosecution in criminal proceedings.</p>
<p class="continued">Julia Rietz</p>
<p class="continued">Champaign County State's Attorney</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Upon receiving State's Attorney Rietz's letter Chief Cobb contacted the City Attorney and Human Resources Director for guidance. He also initiated an internal investigation to determine the effect of her position on the Grievant's employment. Fact-finding hearings occurred on March 16, 2016 &lsqb;JOINT EXH. 5&rsqb; and April 6, 2016 &lsqb;JOINT EXH. 6&rsqb; at which the Grievant and his counsel were provided the opportunity to comment upon each of the contentions made by the State's Attorney. The Union discussed the cases relied upon in its brief and made essentially the same arguments. The City was not persuaded and terminated the Grievant's employment on April 13, 2016. The letter of termination letter &lsqb;JOINT EXH. 3&rsqb; stated:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">This letter is in reference to internal investigation 16-II-02.</p>
<p class="continued">Internal investigation 16-II-02 was initiated after Champaign County State's Attorney Julia Rietz issued a letter and press release on February 23, 2016 stating that her office would be unable and unwilling to utilize you as a witness for the State in criminal proceedings, regardless of your role, due to your repeated failure to adequately document your use of force, your disciplinary history, and her concerns regarding your judgment and decision-making in crisis situations, particularly with respect to the mentally ill. Internal investigation 16-II-02 concludes that you are no longer able to meet the essential functions of your position as a Champaign Police Officer. Namely, the investigation concluded that you are unable to cooperate in the prosecution of criminal offenses, and you are unable to &ldquo;develop and maintain positive working relationships with other employees, government officials, and the public.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">The City does not have any positions available in which you would not be required to exercise your powers as a sworn police officer and would not be called upon to testify in criminal matters. As the conclusion of this investigation is that you are unable to perform the essential functions of your position, I have recommended to the City Manager termination from your position as a police officer. The City Manager has accepted and approved my recommendation and your termination shall take effect immediately.</p>
<p class="continued">If you have any questions about your employee benefits, please contact Steve Harms in the Human Resources Office at 217-403-8770.</p>
<p class="continued">You have the right to appeal this decision under Article 33 of the terms of the Illinois FOP Labor Council contract with the City of Champaign.</p>
<p class="continued">Sincerely,</p>
<p class="continued">/s/</p>
<p class="continued">Anthony D. Cobb</p>
<p class="continued">Chief of Police</p></blockquote>
<p>The parties were unable to resolve the matter at the earlier steps of the grievance procedure. On July 14, 2016 the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service notified me of my appointment as the arbitrator in this matter.</p>
<p>State's Attorney Julia Rietz testified. Her testimony covers 142 pages of the transcript of proceedings and in large part is cumulative of the information in her letter to Chief Cobb and the press release. The post-hearing briefs extensively discuss aspects of her testimony that the parties consider relevant to their arguments. I have not attempted to recount her testimony in its entirety but testimony relied upon in my assessment of the record evidence requires discussion.<ftnote num="20"><para>State's Attorney Rietz did not find any issue with the arrests of William Brown and Benjamin Mann. Consequently, those cases do not require discussion.</para></ftnote> During her testimony she referred to five incidents that constituted the factual basis for her decision that the Grievant would not be called as a witness by the State's Attorney's Office in any criminal case.<ftnote num="21"><para>In addition, State's Attorney Rietz spoke to a member of the City's legal staff, Fred Stavins, about one of the civil lawsuits <quote>and I was told that Officer Rush was not a great witness for himself, which caused me concern if I was to put him on the stand in a criminal case because obviously how an officer testifies is significant for their credibility in front of a jury, but I didn't see anything in the Mann case that I had received that would lead me to file criminal charges in that case.</quote> &lsqb;TR. p. 69 &amp; p. 147&rsqb;.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>An appropriate starting point is Arbitrator Dichter's award issued on April 3, 2015. He considered three separate disciplinary matters involving: (1) a one-day suspension for violating Rule 1(A)(3);<ftnote num="22"><para>Rule 1(A)(3) provides: <quote>Employees shall perform their duties in a productive, effective, and efficient manner.</quote></para></ftnote> (2) a 3-day suspension arising from the arrest of Kissica Seets; and (3) termination arising out of the arrest of Precious Jackson.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>1. Accident Investigation.</b><ftnote num="23"><para>The record evidence concerning this investigation is contained in CITY EXHIBIT 3, pp. 99 &ndash; 120.</para></ftnote> On March 3, 2014 the Grievant was dispatched to a hit and run accident. In such circumstances department policy requires the completion of an Illinois Traffic Crash Report. In addition, it is undisputed that the Grievant issued the at-fault driver a citation for &ldquo;Failure to Reduce Speed in Order to Avoid an Accident.&rdquo; Nine days later the not-at-fault driver contacted the police department and spoke with Lieutenant Tod Myers to request a copy of the Traffic Crash Report. Lieutenant Myers located a dispatch ticket indicating that the Grievant and Officer Butler were dispatched and that a file number (C14-1781) had been assigned but he was unable to locate the report. He sent an email to both officers advising them that the citizen had not yet received the accident report and said that the officer responsible for completing the report needed to do so as soon as possible. Later that morning the Grievant, who was off duty, stopped by his office and informed Lieutenant Myers that he would complete the report and contact the citizen. A short time later the Grievant told the lieutenant that he had completed the accident report. However, when the citizen made another inquiry on March 31<sup>st</sup> the computerized accident report was not listed in the records management database. Another query was made on April 11<sup>th</sup> and the report was still not listed. At that time Lieutenant Shaffer also attempted to locate the report and spoke with Sergeant Ramseyer who said that he had spoken with the Grievant who told him that he had completed the accident report and that a citation had been issued to the at-fault driver. Lieutenant Shaffer located the citation in Grievant's ticket tin in the men's locker room. The investigation by Lieutenant Jon Swenson, dated May 19, 2014, submitted to the Chief of Police disclosed:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">There are two plausible explanations as to why the report(s) that Officer Rush claims to have previously competed are not reflected in the IyeTek history or properly submitted.</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>On or about March 27, 2014, Lt. Myers learned that the &ldquo;rollback&rdquo; software that had been installed on the report writing computers was deleting crash reports from the Iye Tek system. This leaves open the possibility that the report(s) that Officer Rush claims to have completed prior to that date were in fact completed but deleted from the system through no fault of his own.</p></li>
<li><p>In early 2014, Lt. Myers discovered an issue with IyeTek after finding that other crash reports submitted by other officers had not properly made their way into the IyeTek system. Upon inquiry, Lt. Myers discovered that in order to properly &ldquo;validate and submit&rdquo; a report the submitting officer must wait until all data is transmitted before closing the IyeTek program. Lt. Myers was not aware of that requirement, and nor were the officers who had been trained to use the system. This could likewise account for the absence of Officer Rush's report(s) from the IyeTek system and/or its history.</p></li></ol></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Based on these facts, in a report dated May 19, 2014, Lieutenant Swenson concluded that an allegation that the Grievant failed to promptly complete the accident report could not be sustained.<ftnote num="24"><para>During a <italic>Garrity</italic> interview on May 15, 2014 the Grievant explained to Lieutenant Myers that he <quote>hit validate and submit</quote> and <quote>I just X out of the program.</quote> &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 175&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> However, the report concluded that the failure to process the ticket and the failure to give the citizen driver information exchange forms merited a suspension for failing to &ldquo;perform duties in a productive, effective, and efficient manner. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 101-102&rsqb;.<ftnote num="25"><para>It should be noted that several weeks earlier Lieutenant Dave Shaffer completed another investigative report addressed to Chief Cobb and Deputy Chief Gallo. In addition to recommending that the Grievant be disciplined for a violation of Rule 1(A)(3), he recommended that he be disciplined for violating Rule 2(C)(1) (Failure to make a prompt official report). &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 114&rsqb;. Chief Gallo approved Lieutenant Swenson's findings and recommendations &ndash; not Lieutenant Shaffer's findings and recommendations &ndash; on May 28, 2014. <bold>Importantly, in my view, neither Lieutenant Shaffer nor Lieutenant Swenson (or anyone else) ever made (and Chief Cobb did not approve) any finding or recommendation that the Grievant had at any time been untruthful.</bold></para></ftnote> The Department imposed a one-day suspension for a violation of Rule 1(A)(3). Arbitrator Dichter's opinion contains two paragraphs concerning this matter.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The first incident occurred on March 13 2014. Grievant had made a traffic stop. He issued a citation. A ticket is supposed to be turned in immediately so that it can be processed. The Officer must also record the information on the computer. Grievant was charged with not turning in the ticket and for failing to file the report. It was later determined there was a problem with the software and reports were sometimes deleted by the computer. <i>The allegation was then dropped</i>. Grievant acknowledged that he forgot to turn in the ticket into the Department. He put it in a folder and forgot about it. He was interviewed regarding this incident on May 14 and again on June 18. He acknowledged on both occasions he was wrong. He also admitted that during the hearing. It was recommended that the Grievant receive a one-day suspension for this failure. Grievant does not challenge the conclusion and agrees that this level of discipline was appropriate for this offense.</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator does not disagree. He did forget to turn in the citation. There are consequences to that failure for the parties concerned. It can effect insurance claims and have other ramifications. Grievant acknowledged this. Thus, the Arbitrator can find no fault with the Department's conclusions regarding this incident. Grievant did what he was charged with doing and was appropriately disciplined. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 416-417&rsqb;. &lsqb;Emphasis added&rsqb;.<ftnote num="26"><para>Although I am unaware of the testimony at the hearing, on the basis of a careful reading of the record, I believe that Arbitrator Dichter's statement that the allegation <quote>was dropped</quote> is mistaken because there never was such an <quote>allegation</quote> so it could be <quote>dropped.</quote></para></ftnote></p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>2. Arrest of Kissica Seets.</b></h4>
<p>The general picture of what occurred on April 11, 2014 is described in State's Attorney Rietz's press release. From what can be pieced together from police reports filed by seven officers,<ftnote num="27"><para>Incident reports were filed by the following officers: Sergeant Jaceson Yandell &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 127-130&rsqb;; Officer Kristine Haugen &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 122-126&rsqb;; Officer Cully Schweska &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 131-133&rsqb;; Officer Jeffrey Creel &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 136-139&rsqb;; Officer Jeremy Canales &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 138-139&rsqb;; Officer Mason Voges &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 140-142&rsqb;; and Officer Matt Rush &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 143-144&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> the melee occurred during a birthday party for <fill character="space" width="5"/> when her sister Kissica Seets &ldquo;got in the face&rdquo; of an individual named <fill character="space" width="5"/> &ldquo;about him sleeping with someone&rdquo; other than <fill character="space" width="5"/> . <fill character="space" width="5"/> reportedly punched Kissica Seets and this prompted <fill character="space" width="5"/> to begin fighting with Kissica Seets in defense of <fill character="space" width="5"/>, who told Officer Voges that he is the <fill character="space" width="5"/> asked Kissica Seets why she called <fill character="space" width="5"/> &ldquo;a bitch&rdquo; and Kissica Seets reportedly answered, &ldquo;because he is a bitch.&rdquo; An individual named <fill character="space" width="5"/>, who is Kissica Seets' boyfriend, along with <fill character="space" width="5"/>, reportedly &ldquo;jumped&rdquo; <fill character="space" width="5"/> knocking his glasses off and causing him to drop his phone. <fill character="space" width="5"/> of Kissica and <fill character="space" width="5"/> called the police. Officers were informed that prior to their arrival on scene <fill character="space" width="5"/> threatened Kissica with a knife prior to the police arriving. When the first officers (Officers Henry and Schweska) arrived the sisters were yelling and fighting. <fill character="space" width="5"/> emerged from the house, said, &ldquo;fuck the police&rdquo; and &ldquo;I hate the police,&rdquo; and began walking in the direction of the officers who were standing in the street. As Officer Schweska was directing <fill character="space" width="5"/> to go back into the house Kissica Seets struck <fill character="space" width="5"/> in the face with a closed fist. The sisters reportedly continued to &ldquo;engage in physical combat&rdquo; and ignore orders to &ldquo;stop&rdquo; and &ldquo;break it up,&rdquo; Officer Schweska administered one burst of OC spray at both sisters and, for a short time, they stopped fighting. A large number of people emerged from the house and Officer Schweska requested that additional units respond. Moments later <fill character="space" width="5"/> threw a folding chair striking Kissica Seets. <fill character="space" width="5"/> later told officers that Arthur retreated into the house when he saw the lights of squad cars approaching and that she tried to hold him when he came out because she wanted him arrested on an outstanding warrant but he ran away on foot. Joseph stated that he suspected either <fill character="space" width="5"/> had taken his missing phone. Both Kissica Seets and <fill character="space" width="5"/> were arrested. Kissica Seets later pleaded guilty to Aggravated Battery of a Police Officer.</p>
<p>The Grievant was one of 11 police units at the scene. He filed this incident report. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 143-144&rsqb;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">On 4/11/2014, at approximately 2225 hrs, I was wearing a Champaign Police Department Class &ldquo;B&rdquo; uniform and operating a fully marked squad car. Officers were dispatched to &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb; in regards to a fight call. Officer Schweska requested additional units upon his arrival.</p>
<p class="continued">When I arrived at scene, I observed two black females, later identified as <fill character="space" width="5"/> and Kissica, fighting in the front yard. I observed <fill character="space" width="5"/> strike Kissica with a folding chair. Officers separated the parties and during the course of the investigation it was determined that Kissica and <fill character="space" width="5"/> would be arrested for domestic battery.</p>
<p class="continued">Officer Haugen and myself then secured Kissica into handcuffs which I double locked and checked for proper fit. It should be noted that Kissica was resistive in my initial efforts to secure her. Officer Haugen and myself attempted to escort her to a squad car, however, Kissica was pulling away in an attempt to speak to her family members.</p>
<p class="continued">As I pulled her left arm, Kissica turned her face turned me and took a deep breath. Kissica then spit directly into my face. The spit hit me directly on my right temple and cheek. At this time I wrapped my right arm around Kissica's head. Her jaw was cradled in my elbow with the intent of controlling her head so that she could not spit at Officers. It should be noted that there was never pressure against Kissica's throat or neck. The arm around her head cradled her jaw in the &ldquo;V&rdquo; of my arm simply to keep her from turning her head. I escorted Kissica to Officer Canales squad car without further incident. It was at this time other Officers secured Kissica into the squad car so that I could clean the spit of &lsqb;sic&rsqb; my face.</p>
<p class="continued">I have no further information regarding this investigation.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">As noted in the Grievant's report, Officer Kristina Haugen was the other officer who escorted Kissica Seets to Officer Canales's squad car. Her report &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 124-125&rsqb; is consistent with the Grievant's report except in one respect. In pertinent part Officer Haugen's report states:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">After speaking with Sgt. Yandell it was determined to arrest Kissica for domestic violence. Ofc. Rush took Kissica into custody and told her to walk towards the squad car. Kissica was refusing to walk. As Ofc. Rush was escorting Kissica to a marked squad car she spit in his face. <i>Kissica was told to sit in a marked squad car and she resisted by pushing her legs out of the vehicle. Ofc. Rush was trying to get her inside the vehicle and she refused. I took over for Ofc. Rush and told Kissica to get into the back seat</i>. Kissica would not put her legs inside the squad and kept telling me she was trying. I told the officers on the other side to pull her inside and they did. Kissica was able to sit in the back seat but she was still yelling and screaming. Kissica turned her head and spit on my vest cover. If I hadn't moved my head she would have gotten me in the face. I was handed a spit hood and placed it over Kissica's head. When I pulled the spit hood down Kissica was still trying to fight to get it off. I went to pull down her spit hood and she was moving her head a lot. Kissica pushed forward as I put the hood on and I thought she was going to bite me so I pushed her face back with my palm. I again adjusted her spit hood to ensure it was on properly. Kissica wanted me to take the spit hood off because she had asthma. Kissica was talking and breathing normal at this time.</p>
<p class="continued">Kissica was turned over to Ofc. Canales #715 for transport to CSCO. Kissica was complaining of asthma so she was transported to Presence Hospital for treatment. Javon was released without charges because it could not be confirmed if he actually did have a knife and threaten Kissica during the altercation. &lsqb;Emphasis added&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The record includes two photographs showing what appears to be a large glob of saliva on the upper right quadrant of Officer Haugen's vest cover. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 134-135&rsqb;. According to Officer Canales's report, during conveyance to the hospital &ldquo;Kissica said she never battered anyone, but she did mean to spit on Officer Rush. Kissica said she did not mean to spit on Officer Haugen and wanted to apologize to her, she only intended to spit on the &lsquo;bald&rsquo; officer.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 139&rsqb;.</p>
<p>During the use of force investigation Lieutenant Myers reviewed audio recordings that picked up the Grievant's conversation with Kissica Seets. He noted that at first the Grievant &ldquo;handled himself very professionally&rdquo; but during a four minute period he acted unprofessionally and used profanity. Among the &ldquo;banter&rdquo; recorded shortly before Kissica Seets was arrested are the following:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>In response to the statement &ldquo;You better stop looking at me (unintelligible),&rdquo; the Grievant said, &ldquo;If you're going to tell me what to do, take the booze out of the front seat and put it somewhere. How about that?&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant said, &ldquo;I'm going to tell you right now you are not going to throw shit at me. You understand that? You are not going to throw shit at me. You understand that?</p></li>
<li><p>In response to the statement, &ldquo;My leg is really hurting&rdquo; the Grievant said, &ldquo;I don't care about your leg, you're not going to throw anything at me, do you understand?&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p>In response to the statement, &ldquo;Would you please get off my arm?&rdquo; the Grievant said, &ldquo;Don't pull away. You will go to jail tonight. I'll tell you right now, you put your ass in that car seat and you will go to jail for DUI. Keep that in mind.&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p>In response to the statements &ldquo;Bitch ass newbie&rdquo; and &ldquo;fuck you&rdquo; the Grievant said, &ldquo;Keep talking. Why don't you just walk away?&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p>In response to the question &ldquo;What are you waiting for?&rdquo; the Grievant said, &ldquo;Waiting for a reason to take you to jail&rdquo; and in response to the next question &ldquo;What's your reason?&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;I'll find one.&rdquo;</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">Lieutenant Myers concluded that although &ldquo;there is no question that Kissica was not overly cooperative during this incident&rdquo; the Grievant's comments were inappropriate and violated Rule 3(B) requiring officers, among other things, to be tactful and not use profane language. Based on his review of the video, Lieutenant Myers also concluded that the Grievant delivered a knee strike while the arrestee was in the backseat of the police vehicle. Because the video did not show what Kissica Seets was doing in the backseat, Lieutenant Myers asked Officer Haugen for clarification. She explained that the arrestee was in a seated position with her legs partially outside the car and was kicking at the officers and not attempting to get inside the car. She said that although she did not see the Grievant deliver a knee strike, she is positive that Kissica Seets was kicking because she herself got kicked and had a small bruise on her leg. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 151-156&rsqb;.</p>
<p>During an investigative interview on May 14, 2014, that was preceded by <i>Garrity</i> warnings,<ftnote num="28"><para><italic>Garrity v. New Jersey</italic>, 385 U.S. 493 (1967). <italic>Garrity</italic> prohibits the use in a criminal trial any statement an officer is compelled to make under threat of discharge for refusal. An officer can be required to answer questions related to the performance of official duties and the answers can be used for internal discipline purposes. Prior to being questioned in each of the internal investigations Champaign police officers are given the following admonition.</para>
<block-quote><para><underline>Refusal to Answer.</underline> You have an obligation to truthfully answer all questions. Your answers or responses constitute an official report. If you persist in a refusal to answer questions after an order of a superior officer to answer, you are advised that such refusal constitutes a violation of Department Rules and may serve as a basis for suspension, removal or discharge or other disciplinary actions. You are further advised that by law, any admission made by you during the course of this interrogation cannot be used against you in any subsequent criminal proceeding.</para></block-quote></ftnote> the Grievant explained that after watching the video he did not consider what he saw a knee strike because &ldquo;in my mind a knee strike is when you take a step and drag your knee through someone.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXHIBIT 3, p. 168&rsqb;. The Grievant said he considered it a jab &ldquo;right at the thigh&rdquo; and said that he did not remember doing it. Lieutenant Myers and Lieutenant Swenson told him they observed two movements: first, when he &ldquo;nudged&rdquo; or &ldquo;wedged&rdquo; her into the car with his knee and second, when he took a step back and delivered what they considered a knee strike. &lsqb;CITY EXHIBIT 3, pp. 167-169&rsqb;. The Grievant stated that he believed he acted appropriately in using force: &ldquo;I told her to get in the car, she wouldn't, and she got rigid and stiff at the door. She started to kick back at me a little bit. And it looked like she was, you know, actively fighting me, but she would not get in the car. &lsqb;CITY EXHIBIT 3, p. 167&rsqb;. When asked whether the knee strike was reasonable and necessary under the circumstances, he responded: &ldquo;I would say yes and no. Yes in the fact that she was resisting my efforts to place her inside the car. I have a lawful reason to do so. I would &lsqb;say&rsqb; no because there was so many officers there I could have just removed myself from the scene and had somebody else do it. She's, but she's already so pissed off at me.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXHIBIT 3, p. 171&rsqb;. The Grievant agreed that he &ldquo;didn't necessarily do a great job of articulating her resistance at the door of the squad car.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 169&rsqb;. After taking a recess during which he looked at the video he acknowledged that there was a knee strike. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 176&rsqb;.</p>
<p>The Grievant received a three day suspension for violating four rules: Rule 3(B)(1) &ndash;Courtesy; Rule 5(A)(2) &ndash; General Operations (&ldquo;Each employee shall provide aid or furnish information consistent with police duty and in accordance with law and departmental directive); Rule 5(C)(1) &ndash; Mistreatment of persons in custody; and Rule 5(D)(1) &ndash; Use of physical force.</p>
<p>Arbitrator Dichter agreed that the three day suspension was proper and noted: &ldquo;Grievant does not challenge this conclusion. He admitted he used profanity and did not act professionally during the encounter. He also acknowledged he did not include in his report the kicks or that he had grabbed her arm when escorting her to the car.&rdquo; However, Arbitrator Dichter disagreed with the Department's conclusion that &ldquo;the second kick&rdquo; was inappropriate. He wrote: &ldquo;Looking at the video of the incident it is hard to determine where the woman's legs were when the second kick occurred. Testimony was that she still was not in the car. The video is not clear enough to contradict that testimony.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXH. 5, p. 535&rsqb;.</p>
<h4 align="left">3. Arrest of Precious Jackson</h4>
<p>State's Attorney Rietz's press release provides a thorough description and it is unnecessary to restate that information. The Grievant prepared this incident report after the arrest. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 272-279&rsqb;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">On 5/26/2014, at approximately 0652 hrs, I was wearing a Champaign Police Department Class &ldquo;B&rdquo; uniform and operating a fully marked squad car. Officers were dispatched to &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb; for an assist fire call. Witnesses reported hearing an explosion, followed by yelling at which time a black female exited as smoke was coming from the house. It should be noted, Officers had been sent to this residence on four other occasions throughout the Memorial Day weekend. The resident identified as Precious continued to drink and become disorderly with guest and Officers were dispatched to the scene.</p>
<p class="continued">Sgt. Crane and myself responded to the residence in an attempt to locate Precious. We searched the area for approximately 15 minutes however we were unable to locate Precious anywhere in the area. Sgt. Crane allowed me to clear the call and return to Post in order to complete previous reports. As I was driving towards Post C, a criminal damage in progress was dispatched by METCAD. The clerk at Thornton's advised a black female wearing a purple dress had entered the store, damaged merchandise and was screaming at customers. The clerk advised the female, later identified as Precious, then left eastbound on University Avenue. It should be noted when the call was dispatched I was driving past Thornton's in the 100 block of South Mattis.</p>
<p class="continued">I turned east onto University and observed a black female matching the aforementioned description near the intersection of University and Victor. I exited my squad car and instructed Precious to stop and come to me. Precious yelled &ldquo;Fuck you!&rdquo; and continued walking east bound on University. I gave Precious several more commands to stop walking and come to me. Precious ignored my commands and began screaming at me pounding her fist into her hand.</p>
<p class="continued">As I approached Precious, she turned and began running east down the sidewalk. I was able to close the distance and catch up to her. As I came to within approximately 4 feet of Precious, she came to a complete stop and turned towards me. As she did this, I began to reach for her arm in an attempt to secure her into handcuffs. Precious raised her left hand and grabbed me by the throat. I felt her finger nails sink into my neck as she was squeezing my wind pipe.</p>
<p class="continued">In order to stop this attack, I delivered a knee strike to Precious's right thigh. This use of force was effective in that it knocked her off balance and she released her grip. I threw Precious onto the ground in order to have an advantage in securing her into handcuffs. Precious continued to pull away from me and was attempting to roll away from me. At this time, Precious began taking deep breaths and pursed her lips together. I believed Precious was about to spit on me. I used my department issued OC spray and delivered a short burst that hit Precious directly in the eyes.</p>
<p class="continued">This force was also effective in that Precious stopped pulling away and lay on the ground. She still had her body tense and rigid, however I was able to pin both of her arms on the ground. I knew at this point Precious would not be able to pull away as I had both of her arms pinned to the ground using all of my body weight.</p>
<p class="continued">I asked Precious if she was done fighting and was ready to roll onto her stomach. Precious said &ldquo;yes&rdquo; and I was able to roll her over on her stomach. Precious was still tense and rigid however I was able to secure her in handcuffs without further incident. The handcuffs were double locked and checked for proper fit. After she was secured into handcuffs, I kept her on the ground until additional officers arrived at scene and could take custody of Precious.</p>
<p class="continued">Officer Petkunas then arrived on scene and secured Precious into the rear of the squad car. She then transported Precious to the Champaign County Jail where she was booked for Aggravated Battery, Resisting a Peace Officer, and Criminal Damage to Property. It should be noted, after Officers arrived on scene, I was informed that my neck was bleeding. The injury to my neck was later photographed and the digital memory card was entered into evidence at the Champaign Police Department.</p>
<p class="continued">Use of Force Reporting &ndash; 1) Officers dispatched for numerous calls regarding the same offender. Offender damaged property, ran from Officers and battered arresting Officer. 2) A knee strike and OC Spray were in order to effect the arrest. 3) The knee strike and OC Spray were effective in that the offender was knocked off balance and taken to the ground. The OC Spray was effective in that it stopped the offender's efforts to pull away. 4) The offender had a small scratch to her right arm. 5) It is not know if the offender had any pre-existing injuries. 6) The offender has obvious mental deficiencies and the statements made did not make sense and were impossible to understand. 7) Offender had small scratch of her right arm. Officer had a cut on his neck from offender's attack. 8) The offender was intoxicated at the time of the incident. The offender had an odor of alcoholic beverage on her person and her eyes were glossy. 9) A witness observed the initial altercation however, drove away prior to speaking with Officers. Incident captured by in car camera and the footage was entered into evidence.</p>
<p class="continued">I have no further information on this investigation. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 272 &ndash; 279&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p>As indicated in State's Attorney Rietz's press release all of the supervisory personnel who reviewed the matter agreed that after Precious Jackson was taken to the ground (at the 7:22:09 mark) the video depicts what Lieutenant Shaffer described as the Grievant's &ldquo;hand being drawn back and upwards with an accelerating downward strike which is consistent with a punch.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 195&rsqb;.<ftnote num="29"><para>The press release does not mention the conclusion reached by Sergeant Crane, who serves as the department's certified defensive tactics instructor, that the Grievant's actions <quote>were consistent with how a punch is thrown</quote> but he was <quote>unwilling to definitively classify Officer Rush's actions as a &lsquo;punch&rsquo;</quote> because it was not entirely clear whether or not he made contact. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 242&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> The press release did not include the Grievant's explanations in two interviews that were preceded by <i>Garrity</i> warnings. During the first interview on June 5, 2014 he was asked whether he denied punching her.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Yes, I am. What I was trying to do was separate myself from her lower body. She had a sundress on that was all the way up to her breasts, she had no underwear on. Her legs were spread wide open. I was trying to get as far away from that end of her body as I could. I stayed right by her right shoulder, pinned her arms to the ground, and radioed for assistance. Said that she wasn't actively fighting me but I didn't have her in handcuffs and she was on the ground. So at that time I just held her there and waited for other units or her to calm down, whichever came first. And then she did eventually calm down. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 210&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">He claimed that when the video depicted his arm reaching up and then going down he was attempting to pin both of her arms to the ground. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 213&rsqb;. In the second interview on June 18, 2014 the Grievant insisted &ldquo;the thing that looks like a punch is when I was pinning her on the ground.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 219&rsqb;. According to the transcript of the interview he physically demonstrated what he did and while doing so explained:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">She's laying. Her right arm is pinned down with me on the side. She's got her left hand up towards my face so I reach back, grab her hand and slam it in the ground and then just me sitting, holding her on the ground. But I waited and waited and tried to do everything I could not to use force on her because I realized uh, that I pinned her on the, pinned her arm on the ground. I realized it wasn't a criminal act and it was more mental deficiencies causing her behavior so I didn't want to use force, that's why I just held her as long as I did before I put handcuffs on. Because I knew I had her pinned to the ground like that. She wasn't gonna get away and she didn't pose a threat to me anymore. So, if I would have punched her, I always put it in my report. I've punched people. There's no reason for me not to do so in this case. I can understand the way your video, the video looks but that's just not what happened and this, the thing that bothers me about this most is my integrity is coming into play and without integrity I might as well not be a police officer.</p>
<p class="continued">And I've never lied to you guys about anything I've done. I've always owned up to my mistakes and I'm stating emphatically that I did not punch Precious at all. That was just me turning, pinning her to the ground, holding her there so she couldn't continue to scratch my face and she couldn't get away. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 219&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">At the conclusion of the investigation the Grievant was charged with seven rule violations:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Rule 1(A)(3) &ndash; Employees shall perform duties in a productive, effective, and efficient manner.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 1(B)(1) &ndash; Employees shall be familiar with and obey written orders and directives issued or authorized by the Chief of Police.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 2(A)(1) &ndash; Employees shall, in departmental work product or departmental communication, transmit truthful, complete, and accurate information.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 3(B)(1) &ndash; Employees shall be courteous in their conduct and communication to citizens and other employees. Employees shall be tactful in the performance of their duties, control their tempers, and exercise reasonable patience and discretion. In the performance of their duties, employees shall not use harsh, rude, overbearing, abusive, violent, profane, or indecent language or conduct and shall not express any prejudice or insulting language concerning race, sex, religion, politics, national origin, lifestyle, or similar personal characteristics.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 5(A)(2) &ndash; Each employee shall provide aid or furnish information consistent with police duty and in accordance with law and Department directive.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 5(C)(1) &ndash; Officers shall not mistreat persons who are in their custody by violating a provision of law or Departmental directive.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 5(D)(1) &ndash; The use of physical force to accomplish a police task is restricted by law and Departmental directive to that force which is reasonable and necessary under the circumstances.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">&lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 215&rsqb;. Chief Cobb determined that dismissal was the appropriate penalty for these violations. As noted in State's Attorney Rietz's press release Arbitrator Dichter reduced the penalty to a 30-day suspension. He agreed that by ordering her to &ldquo;come here&rdquo; when he first made contact the Grievant &ldquo;heightened the tension&rdquo; and stated that if he had been &ldquo;less directive and tried to quietly meet with him the whole confrontation might not have taken place.&rdquo; He agreed that his failure to take steps to prevent the situation from escalating &ldquo;is a symptom of a continuing problem.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXH. 5, p. 539&rsqb;. Consequently, his Award required the Department to provide additional training in light his need &ldquo;to work on his ability to find those alternative ways and to deescalate an encounter so that force might be necessary.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXH. 5, p. 544&rsqb;.</p>
<p>Arbitrator Dichter agreed with the conclusion approved by Chief Cobb concerning what the video of the incident showed:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Grievant said during his interview the woman &ldquo;got her left hand up and reached up towards my face so I reach back, grab her hand and slam it to the ground. He testified when asked by the Arbitrator if this interview statement was accurate. He said it was. The Arbitrator has reviewed the tape countless times and even stopped it as the arm was coming up and going down. The picture is anything but clear. However, there are two troubling aspects as to what is seen. Grievant said he was simply trying to pin her arms down. His arm comes up to his shoulder before it comes down. That seems to be more than simply trying to pin her down. It need not go that high to accomplish that purpose. Grievant said her left arm was at his face while he had the right pinned. The video does not show the woman's arm moving. It seems to be moving twice. The alleged punch occurs between 1 minute and one minute and one second into the tape. It does look like but one cannot be certain from the tape that her arm was moving at the 56-second mark. It does come right down again. The second movement is after his arm movement. There is no arm movement from her observed at the instant of his arm movement. If her arm could be seen moving right after the alleged punch and possible before it, it should have been seen moving right when it was occurring.</p>
<p class="continued">On the other hand, the fact that her arm moved only seconds before the punch and then right after would indicate that her arm was not contained at this juncture and that would add some credibility to Grievant's contention he did what he did because he was concerned what she might do next. The woman had scratched Grievant and his face was bleeding. She was not under control even after the pepper spray and after she was taken to the ground. She was even still moving her arms after the alleged strike, and not lying quietly. Her actions up to that point, especially since she was not in handcuffs and was unstable would legitimately be cause for concern for any officer in that situation, especially one there by himself.</p>
<p class="continued">Grievant tried to get control of the situation. He cannot be faulted for that. His intent might honestly have been to control her and her arms, but it nevertheless does appear that towards that end he wound up throwing a punch. His arm, as noted, came up too high for it to have simply been an attempt to pin her arm. This Arbitrator and the supervisors who viewed the tape have the advantage of seeing it over and over and breaking it down segment by segment. In reality, it all happened fast. It must be judged in that context. If she was fighting him as she appears to be doing, then taking action to subdue her cannot be faulted, especially given his prior injury. He said his goal was, and there is no reason to discount that given her arm movements, to gain control and toward that end he engaged in a physical act. There is no evidence anything was done, even if it was a punch, out of malice or loss of temper, but was instead done to subdue an uncooperative person. It must be viewed in that context. That is a significant factor. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 5, pp. 540-541&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p>Arbitrator Dichter disagreed with the department's conclusion that the Grievant had violated Rule 2(A)(1) by being untruthful and exonerated him on that charge. He explained the reasoning leading to that conclusion.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">This brings the Arbitrator to the other serious charge, dishonesty. The Department argues Grievant's testimony should not be credited. It argues he only admitted to his wrongdoings regarding the first two incidents because he knew he was being investigated for the last serious incident. The problem with that argument is that it does not conform to the evidence. This last incident took place on May 26, 2014. Grievant was interviewed regarding the first two incidents on May 15. He admitted during that interview that he failed to turn in the citation and was wrong. During the same interview, he also admitted he was wrong in several respects during the second incident. All of these admissions occurred 11 days before the last incident. These admissions could not have been made to save him from discharge for this last incident.</p>
<p class="continued">The Department then argues Grievant denied throwing a punch because of these two ongoing investigations knowing he was in trouble. While there is merit to that argument, it does seem out of character for him to now change course from his truthfulness in the past. The Union has pointed out that Grievant has always admitted when he has made errors in the past, and there is no reason to believe he is lying now given that fact. His admissions regarding the first two incidents it argues proves that point. <i>The Arbitrator after observing Grievant and listening to the testimony of others finds the Grievant to be an honest person</i>. Would he lie about this last incident fearing his job was on the line as the Department argues? The Arbitrator finds that argument just does not ring true. It would be too large a deviation from his character. Furthermore he might not have known this incident could mean discharge. He would not automatically know this incident could be a last straw, if he told the truth. A major reason discharge is on the table is because of the allegation he lied. He, as is true with all those in the police profession knows how serious lying is and he knew there was a camera capturing the event. Why then would he compound his dilemma by lying?</p>
<p class="continued">How then does his story comport to what the video shows? The Arbitrator finds the most plausible explanation is that in Grievant's mind the video does comport to his recollection and his recounting of events. Others observing it, including this Arbitrator see it one way and he may very honestly be seeing it another. Lying requires intent. <i>Grievant is apparently wrong in his perception of what he did, but the Arbitrator finds it is based on his errant perception of events and not an intent to deceive</i>. That is not an uncommon occurrence. No doubt the action was taken for the purpose he has stated, he just did not do it the way he thinks he did. There is a difference between being simply mistaken and knowing what one says is wrong and saying it anyway. One requires intent and the other does not. Finding such intent to deceive for this Grievant is a bridge too far for this Arbitrator given all that preceded the event. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 5, pp. 541-543&rsqb; &lsqb;Emphasis added&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Arbitrator Dichter concluded: &ldquo;The Arbitrator also finds it difficult to sustain a discharge when the only evidence is a blurry video taken from some distance away that shows an act that took all of second&rdquo; and specifically addressed the effect of his decision on the Grievant's ability to testify:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">More importantly, the Arbitrator has disagreed with the Department that Grievant exhibited dishonesty during this event. The Arbitrator fully agrees with the Department that the honesty of an officer is paramount. How can one testify in a criminal case if that officer has no credibility? A finding of dishonesty is fatal to the employment of one holding a position like that of Grievant. The absence of such a finding here, however, is fatal to the case of the Department. This fact and the other facts noted have been weighed by the Arbitrator in deciding to overturn the discharge, but Grievant does deserve to receive another suspension for this last event. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 5, pp. 543-544&rsqb;.<ftnote num="30"><para>Arbitrator Dichter did not indicate how he allocated the 30-day suspension to the individual offenses. What matters is his interpretation of Rule 2(A)(1) &ndash; not mine &ndash; but as I interpret the rule a disciplinary penalty could be assessed even if the arbitrator exonerates the employee from the accusation he was untruthful because the phrase <quote>truthful, complete, and accurate information</quote> does not require the employee to violate all three terms.</para></ftnote></p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left">4. Complaint concerning response to domestic violence incident.</h4>
<p>Although not addressed in the press release, State's Attorney Rietz discussed this incident in an internal memorandum that summarized her office's review. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 4, pp. 519-520&rsqb;. Because the memorandum is not a public document I have replaced names with initials.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">On July 28, 2013, at 10:00 p.m., Officer Rush was on duty assigned as a Northwest District Patrol Officer. At 10:15 p.m., Rush received a call on his personal cell phone from &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>,&rdquo; a personal friend. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; told Rush that he was at his residence at &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb;, that he was arguing with his girlfriend, and that his girlfriend was tearing up the house. He asked Rush to come over to the house to assist him. Rush reported to METCAD that he was going &lsqb;to that address&rsqb; for &ldquo;Code 27&rdquo; meaning a follow up investigation. Rush met &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; outside the house. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; told him that his girlfriend, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; and he were arguing, that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; had grabbed him by the arm and put her hands on his face, and that she had fallen backwards onto the floor. Rush went inside and found &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; She was crying, her speech was slurred, and in Rush's opinion she was highly intoxicated. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; told Rush she wanted to go home. Rush drove her to her residence at &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb;. He did not report to METCAD that he was transporting &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; He did not create a file or report of the event. The next morning &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; called METCAD and reported that she wanted to file a domestic violence report. She reported that Rush had responded to &lsqb;&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo;s&rsqb; address the previous night, and said she believed she had a broken wrist. Further investigation revealed that she did have a broken wrist. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; reported that she had told Officer Rush that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; had pushed her down and twisted her wrist. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; reported that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; was in the room with her when she was talking to Rush. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; reported that Rush offered to give her a ride home, and that during the drive she complained to him about her wrist hurting. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; reported that Rush gave her a bag of ice when they arrived at her home and told her to go to sleep, and that he would return in the morning to bring her back to &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>'s&rdquo; to get her vehicle. Investigation revealed that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>'s&rdquo; residence is in County jurisdiction. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; was arrested and charged with felony Domestic Violence. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; had three prior convictions for Aggravated Battery and one prior conviction for Aggravated DUI. He ultimately pleaded guilty to the charge arising out of this incident and was sentenced to one year in the Illinois Department of Corrections.</p>
<p class="continued">Lt. Jon Swenson conducted an investigation into &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; complaint. Lt. Swenson interviewed &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>,&rdquo; and officers involved in the subsequent investigation, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; medical records, squad car videos and METCAD recordings, and interviewed Officer Rush. Rush was interviewed as a requirement of his employment, so his statement cannot be used against him for criminal investigation purposes and will not be considered for purposes of this review.</p>
<p class="continued">With regard to Allegation 1, that Officer Rush failed to assist &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; in receiving medical care after learning of the injury to her arm/wrist, Lt. Swenson sustained that allegation, writing that Officer Rush's role at the scene was that of a caretaker, but he made no attempt to determine the extent of her injury nor did he request medical personnel to respond to the scene. Lt. Swenson went on to state that Officer Rush had violated other CPD Rules and Policies. Specifically, Officer Rush was obligated to conduct a thorough on scene investigation, write an offense report, and provide assistance to the involved parties because he had reason to believe that a violation of the Domestic Violence laws had been committed. Lt. Swenson outlined 6 CPD Rules Officer Rush violated, including failure to make a prompt official written police report of offenses investigated, observed or known, failure to provide aid, failure to take action on the occasion of a criminal offense requiring police attention while on duty, and engaging in personal activities which might conflict, compromise, or interfere with his performance of police duties.</p>
<p class="continued">Lt. Swenson's investigation was reviewed by Lt. Shaffer, Deputy Chief Gallo, and Chief Cobb, who all concurred with his findings. Officer Rush was suspended for 2 days due to multiple rule violations. On September 9, 2013, Chief Cobb wrote a letter to &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; advising her that her complaint was sustained.</p>
<p class="continued">Concern here is untruthfulness.</p></blockquote>
<p>In the interest of completeness, and to place the &ldquo;untruthfulness&rdquo; concern in a proper context, discussion of the chronology of events is necessary. The Citizen's Complaint, signed by &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>,&rdquo; was made three days after the incident on July 31, 2013. The portion of the complaint that describes, &ldquo;What you believe the officer/employee did properly or improperly,&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 34&rsqb; states:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>got back to &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>'s&rdquo; house at 9:30</p></li>
<li><p>went to bed</p></li>
<li><p>got into verbal argument</p></li>
<li><p>head back to bedroom to get away from situation</p></li>
<li><p>on the way down the hallway he tackled me to the ground, while pinning me down he twisted by wrists; heard snap</p></li>
<li><p>he immediately called Officer Rush outside</p></li>
<li><p>Officer Rush arrived had a conversation with &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; outside</p></li>
<li><p>Rush came inside. I told him of the incident</p></li>
<li><p>told him I was in a lot of pain in my wrist</p></li>
<li><p>he said okay &amp; he would take me home, on the way home I expressed my severe pain</p></li>
<li><p>got home; he got me ice &amp; said he would be back in 4 hours to take me to my car and to leave the door unlocked.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">Not included in the summary prepared by the State's Attorney's Office is a memorandum prepared by Sergeant Aaron Lack detailing &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; account given several hours after the event. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 32&rsqb;.</p>
<h4 align="left">MEMORANDUM</h4>
<p>TO: DC Gallo &amp; Lt. Myers</p>
<p>DATE: July 30, 2013</p>
<p>SUBJECT: Interview with &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/> .&rdquo; regarding file #C13-6904</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The intent of this memorandum is to document part of a conversation I had with &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; on July 29, 2013 at approximately 0700 hours at her residence located at &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb;. I responded to the address when I was notified that she was reporting that her arm was injured during an incident on July 28, 2013 at approximately 2200 hours. During the incident she had been in an argument, with her boyfriend, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>,&rdquo; while they were at his address &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb;. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; called Officer Rush, who was on duty at the time, to come to the residence to help them prevent the situation from getting worse. Officer Rush arrived on scene and eventually transported &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; from &lsqb;&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; address&rsqb; to her address at &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb; in order &lsqb;sic&rsqb; prevent any further problems at the residence.</p>
<p class="continued">When I spoke with &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; she explained that she believed her arm was broken due to swelling that had occurred overnight. I asked her if she believed her arm was broken when Officer Rush drove her home from &lsqb;&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/> address&rsqb;<i>. She said although it was sore, she did not think it was broken at that time. She said she told Officer Rush at the time her arm was sore</i>. I asked her if she reported to Officer Rush at that time that a physical fight occurred between her and &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; at &lsqb;his address&rsqb;. <i>She said she did not report it to Officer Rush at that time because she believed that nothing would be done and so she &ldquo;did not want to get into it.&rdquo; She said she did not want the situation investigated so she did not tell Officer Rush about the domestic dispute becoming physical</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">At the conclusion of my conversation, Officer Rush finished his interview with &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; and transported her back to &lsqb;&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; address&rsqb; where she wanted to pick up her vehicle. Also, Champaign County Deputies were going to meet us there and conduct an investigation regarding the allegations of domestic battery since it was discovered that &lsqb;&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; address&rsqb; is not within the city limits of Champaign. &lsqb;Emphasis added&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Grievant did not complete a report after he went to &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; home and drove &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; to her home on July 28<sup>th</sup> around 10:00 p.m. He did complete a report on July 29<sup>th</sup> after he was dispatched to her address at 6:44 a.m. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 38-42&rsqb;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">On 7/28/2013, at approximately 2215 hrs, I was wearing a Champaign Police Department Class &ldquo;B&rdquo; uniform and operating a fully marked squad car. I received a phone call from &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; &lsqb;word obliterated by punch hole&rsqb; he was arguing with his girlfriend and wanted to make sure the argument did not get any worse. I proceeded to &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; address located at &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb;. At this time, I believe the aforementioned address was the jurisdiction of the Champaign Police Department.</p>
<p class="continued">Upon arrival, I observed &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; standing in the front yard talking on a cell phone. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; walked up to me and stated that his girlfriend, identified as &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; has &lsqb;sic&rsqb; extremely intoxicated and out of control. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; explained that he had been with &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; throughout the day in Peoria. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated he took &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; on a date and it was actually a very good day for the two of them. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; advised that upon returning home they began arguing.</p>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that he was in the front yard of his residence talking on the phone with his landlord. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that she believed he was talking to another woman at this time. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; had consumed numerous mixed drinks with vodka. While &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; was outside, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; entered a spare bedroom and began tearing up property, gifts for &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; children. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated she was throwing the neatly stack &lsqb;sic&rsqb; pile of gifts around the room. I did not actually observe the bedroom as I only entered the living room of the house. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; advised that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; was more intoxicated than he has seen her in a very long time. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that they began yelling at each other in the hallway of the residence. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; advised that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; continued throwing items around the residence. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; informed me he was stepping outside to call when &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; grabbed onto his arm. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated he continued arguing while his arm was in her grasp.</p>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that as they were yelling, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; put her hand on his face, in a manner described as getting his attention. I did observe two small red marks on &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; face that had the appearance of pimples. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that he turned to walk away at which time &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; fell back wards onto the floor. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated he then walked outside at which time he called me. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; advised he waited outside until I arrived. It should be noted, that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; did not appear to be intoxicated. His speech was not slurred and he did not have any issues walking or holding a conversation.</p>
<p class="continued">I instructed &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; to wait outside while I talked with &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; inside the residence. I entered the residence and observed &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; sitting on the couch. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; was crying and swaying side to side. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; was highly intoxicated as her speech was heavily slurred, her eyes were blood shot and she could not maintain her balance.</p>
<p class="continued">I asked &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; if she was okay to which she stated, &ldquo;I just want to go home. I just want to go home.&rdquo; <fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; continued to cry and was not able to maintain a conversation. In &lsqb;sic&rsqb; conitued &lsqb;sic&rsqb; attempting to speak with &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; however, her intoxication was too high for a successful interview. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; would say that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; is mean to her and that she was scared of him. I informed <fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; that I could not allow her to drive in her condition. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; said she was fine and just wanted to drive home. I told &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; approximately 3 times I could not allow her to drive, however, I would provide her with a ride home. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; reluctantly agreed and I began assisting her with locating her belongings. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; was not able to find her phone, keys, purse or coat due to the intoxication. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; was eventually able to locate her keys and provided them too &lsqb;sic&rsqb; me. I then transported <fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; home &lsqb;to her residence&rsqb;. While en route, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; continued saying how she was tired of &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; being mean to her and brought up &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; possibly being with other women. I then dropped off &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; at her residence where she stated she just wanted to pass out for the evening.</p>
<p class="continued">It should be noted, that there were no independent witnesses to the event and conflicting stories. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; appeared to be very believable while &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; struggled to maintain the conversation. At approximately 0630 hrs on 7/29/2013, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; called METCAD and stated she believed her arm was broken and wanted to know why no report was taken.</p>
<p class="continued">At this time, Sgt. Lack and myself proceeded to her residence in order to photograph any possible injuries and interview &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>.&rdquo; As I approached the residence I observed &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; standing in the living room. She was crying and holding her arm. I asked &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; if she needed an ambulance to which she replied, &ldquo;No, I will be fine.&rdquo; I asked &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; if she could relay what had occurred prior to my arrival on 7/28/2013.</p>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that she been with &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; throughout the day in Peoria on a date. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; said everything was great throughout the day and they enjoyed themselves. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; advised that upon arrival at the residence an argument immediately began to escalate. &ldquo;&rdquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; started yelling at her after she questioned what he was doing in the front yard.</p>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; advised they continued to yell at each other and as she was walking in the hallway, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; approached and placed her in a &ldquo;bear hug.&rdquo; At this time, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated she attempted to pull away and they fell onto the ground. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stood up and grabbed her arms and twisted them. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that her arm began to hurt. It should be noted, that while at &lsqb;&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo;&rsqb; address, I did not observe any redness or scratches on the arm she stated was injured. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; then left the residence and used his cell phone. It was shortly after this, that I arrived on scene.</p>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; did have a small amount of swelling on her right forearm at the time of the second interview. I used a digital shift camera and photographed the injury. The digital memory card was later entered into evidence. Sgt. Lack informed me that the Champaign County Sheriff's Department would also investigate the incident so an impartial decision could be made regarding any possible enforcement action. In addition, I later learned that &lsqb;&ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; address&rsqb; is actually the jurisdiction of the Sheriff's Department.</p>
<p class="continued">I then transported &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; back to &lsqb;<fill character="space" width="5"/>.'s address&rsqb; in order for the to speak with the Sheriff's Department. While en route, &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; stated &ldquo;I didn't want to make a big deal about this and did not want a report. Upon arrival, I released &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; to Deputy Maxey for the interview.</p>
<p class="continued">I have no further information regarding this information &lsqb;sic&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">A fact-finding hearing preceded by <i>Garrity</i> warnings was conducted on August 14, 2013. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, pp. 63-80&rsqb;. In addition to the information in the incident report, the Grievant stated that he did not follow the protocol for handling domestic violence incidents because at that time he considered it a &ldquo;remove intoxicated subject&rdquo; situation involving a drunken woman who needed to go home. He agreed that advising the dispatcher that he was responding to the address where &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/> resided on a &ldquo;Code 27&rdquo; (follow-up investigation) was inaccurate. He stated that at that time both &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; and &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; said that she fell. He said that he provided <fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; a bag of ice when they arrived at her house because she had complained about her arm hurting but said that she did not want medical attention and he thought it would help. He said that when he and Sergeant Lack went to her home the following morning she again refused medical attention. He stated that he did not record the transport because it is not required by policy. The Grievant agreed that he exercised poor judgment and that his handling of the situation gives the appearance that he was trying to conceal a criminal act committed by an acquaintance.</p>
<p>The Grievant was disciplined for violating six rules and received a 2-day suspension. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 98&rsqb;.</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Rule 1(A)(2) &ndash; Employees shall perform police duties and make discretionary decisions in a manner consistent with the law.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 1(B)(1) &ndash; Employees shall be familiar with and obey written orders and directives issued or authorized by the Chief of Police.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 2(C)(1) &ndash; Employees shall make a prompt official written police report of offenses investigate, observed, or known.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 5(A)(2) &ndash; Each employee shall provide aid or furnish information consistent with police duty and in accordance with departmental directive.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 5(A)(3) &ndash; Each officer shall take appropriate action on the occasion of a criminal offense, disorder, or other act or condition requiring police attention on or off duty.</p></li>
<li><p>Rule 7(B)(1) &ndash; Employees shall not engage in personal activities which might conflict, compromise, or interfere with his or her performance of police duties.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued"><b>5. &ldquo;Unfounded&rdquo; complaint filed by</b> &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo;</p>
<p>State's Attorney Rietz testified that in reaching her decision that the Grievant would not be called as a witness by her office &ldquo;I really didn't consider the ones that were unfounded because they were unfounded.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 79&rsqb;. However, she also testified that this complaint, although determined to be unfounded, &ldquo;caused me concern&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 55&rsqb; about how the Grievant handled situations involving individuals with mental health problems. &lsqb;TR. p. 66&rsqb;. The discussion in her internal memorandum outlines the necessary information. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 4, pp. 518-519&rsqb;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>10/28/12 &ndash;</b> &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/><b>&rdquo; complaint</b>. On October 28, 2012, CPD officers were dispatched to &lsqb;address redacted&rsqb; for a juvenile problem. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; called 911 requesting assistance with her 17 year old son, who was tearing up the house. Officers Rush, McAllister and Rogers responded. The call was concluded with no report, parenting advice given. &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; filed a complaint on the city's website alleging that Officer Rush used inappropriate language and threats towards her son. Sgt. Nate Rath conducted the investigation. Sgt. Rath interviewed Officer Rush, who reported that his goal was to be forceful with &lsqb;her son &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo;&rsqb;, to take a firm stance with him, and to be &lsqb;sic&rsqb; authoritative male figure for &lsqb;him&rsqb;. Officer Rush believed &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; desired a firm, intimidating effort to persuade her son to stop and this conduct was what &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; had originally requested. He denied threatening &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; but said &ldquo;it will be your ass,&rdquo; if he could not control himself and the officers had to return, believing that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; was of an age that the word &ldquo;ass&rdquo; would not be considered offensive. Lt. &lsqb;sic&rsqb; Rath interviewed &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; reported that Officer Rush said, &ldquo;if I have to come back I'll beat your ass.&rdquo; During the interview &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; asked &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; if he might have been mistaken, and if Officer Rush might have said &ldquo;it will be your ass&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;I'll beat your ass.&rdquo; <fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; said it was possible. Officer McAllister and Officer Rogers were interviewed and denied hearing Officer Rush make threats. Sgt. Rath concluded that the complaint regarding the use of profane language was unfounded as the word &ldquo;ass&rdquo; can be heard on the radio, television, and PG-13 movies, and is rarely considered a profane word. Sgt. Rath concluded that the complaint that Officer Rush made threats was unfounded because it is possible that &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; misheard Officer Rush, and the statement made by Rush conveys a general requirement of responsibility on &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; part. Sgt. Rath's review was reviewed by Lt. Mike Paulus, who, on November 29, 2012, wrote a memorandum confirming Sgt. Rath's review, but expressing concern that Officer Rush &ldquo;allowed himself to be asked to give &lsquo;the talk&rsquo; to a developmentally slow person.&rdquo; Lt. Paulus went on to say &ldquo;this can be a problem if the message is not given or received in the right manner.&rdquo; On January 4, 2013, Chief Cobb sent a letter to &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; advising her that the complaint was not sustained because &ldquo;while the officer spoke very firmly and directly&rdquo; to &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; he did not use any harsh, rude or overbearing language in doing so.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>TESTIMONY OF STATE'S ATTORNEY JULIA RIETZ</i></b></h4>
<p>A prominent issue in the State's Attorney's testimony concerned the basis for the assertion in the letter to Chief Cobb that the Grievant has &ldquo;multiple discipline actions for untruthfulness.&rdquo; &lsqb;JOINT EXH. 1, p.1&rsqb;. In its opening statement and during questioning the Union insisted that the disciplinary record showed that he had been charged with violating Rule 2(A)(1) &ldquo;(Employees shall, in departmental work product or departmental communication, transmit truthful, complete, and accurate information&rdquo;) only once and that Arbitrator Dichter exonerated him on that charge. The confusion was to some degree cleared up by the State's Attorney's explanation that when she used the word &ldquo;discipline&rdquo; she was using that term &ldquo;loosely&rdquo; and referring to the entire file and not only to instances where the Department accused or charged him with being untruthful. &lsqb;TR. p. 152&rsqb;. During her testimony she pointed to a number of instances that she thought constituted untruthfulness, notwithstanding that the Department did not make a finding, or prefer a disciplinary charge, of untruthfulness.</p>
<p>The witness pointed out that in his report concerning the arrest of Kissica Seets arrest the Grievant inaccurately stated that he took her to the squad car without further incident. In addition to the verbal exchanges with Ms. Seets, she said that the Grievant did not document the two leg strikes used to get her into the squad car. &lsqb;TR. p. 70&rsqb;.</p>
<p>With regard to the arrest of Precious Jackson, the witness found that the report<ftnote num="31"><para>The referenced verbiage from the report states:</para>
<block-quote><para>I exited my squad car and instructed Precious to stop and come to me. Precious yelled, <quote>Fuck you!</quote> and continued walking east bound on University. I gave Precious several more commands to stop walking and come to me. Precious ignored my commands and began screaming at me pounding her fist into her hand. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 273&rsqb;.</para></block-quote></ftnote> was &ldquo;very inconsistent&rdquo; with what occurred at the beginning of the interaction because &ldquo;when he pulls up next to her and starts screaming at her, that's crystal clear.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 121&rsqb;. A follow-up question was asked:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Q: So, I am just &ndash; I am confused. What do you &ndash; so, is it your position that how he approached Ms. Jackson was inconsistent with what was in his report?</p>
<p class="continued">A: Yes, that's one of my positions on that situation. &lsqb;TR. p. 121-122&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">She stated that she did not know whether the Grievant was aware of her history of mental health issues but believed that based on his experience and training he should have realized that he was approaching an individual who might have mental health issues. &lsqb;TR. pp. 123-124&rsqb;. She stated that she disagreed with Arbitrator Dichter's finding that the Grievant had been truthful in his account of the force used in that incident. &lsqb;TR. p. 124&rsqb;. She explained the reason why his finding did not affect her decision that the Grievant could not testify on behalf of the state:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Because the arbitrator is one individual making a decision about credibility and an officer's credibility is on the line in every single case in which he or she testifies and a jury has an independent ability to make a decision about credibility. &lsqb;TR. p. 85&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p>State's Attorney Rietz discussed the circumstances surrounding the Grievant's 2-day suspension for his handling of the domestic violence situation involving &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>.&rdquo; When asked on cross-examination whether the discipline was for being untruthful she stated, &ldquo;I frankly don't know&rdquo; but said that one of the multiple rule violations was &ldquo;not reporting where he was &ndash; where he was when he was supposed to be somewhere else. My concern when I reviewed it was truthfulness.&rdquo;<ftnote num="32"><para>As the previous discussion indicates the record evidence is that he did notify METCAD that he was enroute to the address where &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/> resided on a <quote>Code 27.</quote></para></ftnote> She declined to agree that the six disciplinary charges in that matter did not involve untruthfulness. &ldquo;I don't know if there's a particular rule that's called lying, but I would consider any one of these things a variety of different ways to say lying.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 168&rsqb;.</p>
<p>The witness testified that the Grievant was not truthful about the circumstances surrounding the filing of a motor vehicle crash report.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Q: Are you claiming that's untruthfulness?</p>
<p class="continued">A: It's untruthfulness when your supervisor asks you whether you have done it and you say no. That's untruthfulness.</p>
<p class="continued">Q: Why &ndash;</p>
<p class="continued">A: Or, I'm sorry, when your supervisor asks you if you have done something and you say yes, you have done it when, in fact, you haven't done it, that's untruthfulness. &lsqb;TR. pp. 113-114&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">When asked if she was claiming that the Grievant &ldquo;deliberately lied&rdquo; about the accident report she answered, &ldquo;yes.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 114&rsqb;. She stated that it &ldquo;was not relevant to me&rdquo; that the Department did not claim the Grievant had been untruthful because &ldquo;I am making my decision as the person who has to put this officer on the stand and vouch for his credibility and it was my opinion, based on what I read that he was untruthful.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. pp. 114-116&rsqb;.</p>
<p>State's Attorney Rietz testified that her office is comprised of 21 assistant state's attorneys and 43 full-time staff. Her office handles all state crimes that occur in the county and that the office annually files approximately 1,800 felony cases, the same number of misdemeanor cases, the same number of traffic tickets, and juvenile delinquency and juvenile abuse and neglect cases. &lsqb;TR. pp. 29-30&rsqb;. She testified that because of the heavy workload her office must make decisions based entirely on the information contained in officers' reports and that they do not have the technology to review video to make sure it is consistent with what the officer's report says occurred prior to making charging decisions. &lsqb;TR. pp. 32-34&rsqb;.</p>
<p>State's Attorney Rietz explained a prosecutor's responsibility under <i>Brady v. Maryland</i> and said that her office takes it very seriously. &lsqb;TR. p. 33&rsqb;. She said that her officer does not keep any &ldquo;Brady list&rdquo; of officers with credibility problems because &ldquo;quite frankly, we don't have that problem in Champaign County&rdquo; and she has never received information about truthfulness issues from another department with the exception of the Grievant and another officer who was charged with three sexual assaults and terminated after pleading guilty. &lsqb;TR. pp. 34-35&rsqb;.</p>
<p>In her view her office must vouch for the credibility of officers. She emphasized that view throughout her testimony.<ftnote num="33"><para><italic>See, e.g</italic>. &lsqb;TR. p. 80&rsqb; (<quote>Every time an officer gets on the stand, their credibility is at issue and my office is responsible for vouching for that credibility every time.</quote>); &lsqb;TR. p. 114&rsqb; (<quote>I am making my decision as the person who has to put this officer on the stand and vouch for his credibility &hellip;.</quote>); &lsqb;TR. p. 131&rsqb; (&ldquo;it's my responsibility to put cases in front of juries and vouch for the credibility of the witnesses that I am putting on &hellip;.); &lsqb;TR. p. 86&rsqb; (<quote>Every time an officer gets on the stand, their credibility is at issue and my office is responsible for vouching for that credibility every time.</quote>).</para></ftnote></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">As a prosecutor, we are putting these officers on the stand and vouching for their credibility and we have to be able to do that and they have to be able to trust us and know that were are trying to do the very best we can for them and that we understand the difficulty of the work they are doing. &lsqb;TR. p. 31&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p>State's Attorney Rietz testified that her office's ability to prosecute cases had already been affected by the Grievant's actions. The criminal case of Benjamin Mann, a plaintiff in one of the civil cases filed against the Grievant and other officers, was dismissed after the Grievant was terminated in August 2014 and prior to his reinstatement in April 2015.<ftnote num="34"><para>State's Attorney Rietz did not explain the reason for the dismissal of this case. The Grievant was not employed by the Champaign Police Department at the time of the dismissal.</para></ftnote> She testified that in another criminal case her office allowed the defendant to plead to a lesser charge and receive probation rather than prison for a number of reasons, including difficulty in getting witnesses. The prosecution went through great lengths to prepare its case without using the Grievant as a witness. However, she testified that defense counsel subpoenaed the Grievant as a witness and indicated that the defense would attempt to make the Grievant an issue in the case. &lsqb;TR. pp. 36-39 &amp; 147-150&rsqb;.</p>
<p>As previously mentioned, State's Attorney Rietz testified about a conversation with a member of the City of Champaign legal staff during which she learned that the &ldquo;Grievant was not a great witness for himself&rdquo; in connection with the civil case. This caused her concern because &ldquo;obviously how an officer testifies is significant to their credibility in front of a jury.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 69&rsqb;.</p>
<p>She also explained a statement in her press release concerning individuals having mental health issues:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Moreover, our concerns about his judgement and decision-making with regards to his approach and contact with citizens in crisis, particularly those with mental health concerns, makes us unable to vouch for his credibility and reliability as a witness in our cases, regardless of role. &lsqb;JOINT EXH. 2, p. 2&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">She testified that by &ldquo;screaming&rdquo; at Precious Jackson &ldquo;come here, come her&rdquo; he unnecessarily escalated the situation. &lsqb;TR. p. 74&rsqb;. When considered together with the unfounded complaint by &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; who &ldquo;was not happy&rdquo; with how the Grievant talked to her son &lsqb;TR. p. 55&rsqb;, the Grievant's ability to interact with people with mental health issues is, in her opinion, a major concern. &lsqb;TR. p. 105&rsqb;.</p>
<p>The witness testified that she has not asked a judge whether the information concerning the Grievant's disciplinary history would be admissible. &lsqb;TR. p. 135-136&rsqb;. She testified that having a judge make a determination on the admissibility of potentially impeaching evidence would not solve the problem because &ldquo;there are significant issues of truthfulness that the judge would likely say should be put in front of a jury, first of all, and second of all, every defense attorney out there would want their opportunity at this. It would &ndash; it would be a ridiculous waste and distraction in criminal cases.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 91&rsqb;. Even if her office attempted to work around the Grievant testifying by using other officers as witnesses, the defense could call him and derail the case. &ldquo;All of this is out there in the public.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 90&rsqb;.</p>
<p>The witness was asked about the legal significance of Arbitrator Dichter's exoneration of the Grievant on the allegation that he had been untruthful concerning his use of force in the arrest of Precious Jackson. She said that the arbitration decision could not be presented to a jury and that there is &ldquo;absolutely no legal basis&rdquo; to admit an arbitrator's decision into evidence to rehabilitate an officer's credibility. &lsqb;TR. p. 142&rsqb;. This prompted a follow-up question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Q: If you &ndash; if Officer Rush were called to the stand and a judge ruled that the Chief's finding that he was untruthful was relevant, it came into evidence, wouldn't a finding by an arbitrator or anybody that he is truthful be appropriate rehabilitation evidence?</p>
<p class="continued">A: Fist of all, no. And, second of all, I wouldn't try to discredit the Chief's opinion.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">&lsqb;TR. p. 143&rsqb;. To clarify the answer I restated the question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Q: If the Chief of Police made a finding of dishonesty that made its way into court, the question was would the arbitration decision that overturned that decision be proper rehabilitation. And, frankly, I don't know the answer to that question.</p>
<p class="continued">A: I don't either. &lsqb;TR. p. 145&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>TESTIMONY OF CHIEF OF POLICE ANTHONY COBB</i></b></h4>
<p>Chief Cobb explained in detail the reasons that State's Attorney Rietz's refusal to allow the Grievant to testify would adversely affect police department operations. An officer who is unable to testify could not perform many of the essential functions required of patrol officers. &lsqb;TR. pp. 171-185&rsqb;. Consequently, the department would need to deploy an extra officer to meet minimum manning requirements. &lsqb;TR. p. 176&rsqb;. Other officers could feel that accommodating an officer who cannot testify is giving him special treatment. &lsqb;TR. p. 177&rsqb;. The work of patrol officers consists of everyday responsibilities that frequently require testimony. This includes traffic enforcement. &lsqb;TR. p. 189&rsqb;. He said that if an officer's investigation cannot be described in court citizens are victimized a second time. &lsqb;TR. p. 178&rsqb;. An officer who cannot testify in court cannot fulfill the job requirement of &ldquo;cooperating in the prosecution of criminal offenders&rdquo; by giving testimony in grand jury, coroner's inquests, or trial proceedings. &lsqb;TR. pp. 180-183&rsqb;. Although an officer could &ldquo;respond&rdquo; and handle some calls for service &ndash; for example a neighbor dispute about a non-criminal matter &ndash; he could not appropriately do what needs to be done when dealing with a shoplifting case or a homicide or sexual assault crime scene. &lsqb;TR. pp. 180-185&rsqb;. The Chief does not think it is an effective use of taxpayer funds for officers to aimlessly drive around the city. &lsqb;TR. p. 223&rsqb;.</p>
<p>Chief Cobb testified that the department does not have any positions that the Grievant could fill if reinstated. &lsqb;TR. p. 177 &amp; p. 185&rsqb;. For example, an officer whose integrity has been called into question could not be placed in an evidence technician position because access to the evidence vault could jeopardize every case involving evidence rather than just the officer's own cases. &lsqb;TR. pp. 190-191&rsqb;. Desk jobs are the bargaining unit work of another union. &lsqb;TR. p. 190&rsqb;. Assigning him as the second officer would be &ldquo;giving him a free pass&rdquo; because &ldquo;I am not getting the work out of him&rdquo; and &ldquo;that's not how we operate.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 191&rsqb;. Light duty positions are available for officers with on-duty or off-duty injuries on a short term, temporary basis &ldquo;if we can find something that the employee can do.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. pp. 191-192&rsqb;. There have been no assignments to permanent light duty and if someone is permanently assigned it would deprive other officers of the opportunity to work when injured. &lsqb;TR. p. 191&rsqb;.</p>
<p>Chief Cobb testified that the department does not currently use body cameras for officers but will be converting squad car dash cameras to body cameras. &lsqb;TR. p. 196&rsqb;. He stated that although body cameras are good they would not solve the problem because they do not catch everything. Unlike the human head that swivels, body cameras are fixed on the front of the body and incapable of capturing something that occurs off to one side. They may not function in a low light environment. &lsqb;TR. pp. 195-197&rsqb;.</p>
<p>Chief Cobb testified that he sent the State's Attorney Office and the United States Attorney's Office a &ldquo;Brady letter&rdquo; concerning another officer.<ftnote num="35"><para>The name of the officer is in the record but I deem it unnecessary to include it in this Opinion. I am cognizant of the provision in Article 33.5 concerning the disclosure of officers' names in disciplinary matters.</para></ftnote> He explained:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">It was a letter that was sent in regards to an incident in which we did an internal investigation where &lsqb;the officer&rsqb; was dispatched to a call; he was at a location; his supervisor had known him to not &ndash; to frequent this location more active as a friend/acquaintance's home. The supervisor happened to be a couple blocks away when the call came out. The officer acknowledged the call over the radio and never cleared that friend's house. He stayed there the entire time and several minutes later cleared the call saying whatever he was supposed to investigate wasn't there, at which point in time the supervisor addressed it and dealt with it and that was the initial untruthfulness over the radio, but when we confronted him about it, he became 100 percent clear on what he did and we moved forward from there but we notified the state's attorney's office. &lsqb;TR. pp. 210-211&rsqb;.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The officer was disciplined. The Chief did not recall the discipline that was imposed but the officer was not terminated. He said that he has not been notified by the State's Attorney's Office that the officer would not be called to testify and that he &ldquo;never heard back once I sent the letter.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. pp. 213-214&rsqb;. He testified that he could not say whether the officer has testified without speculating but he would guess that he has testified after he sent the letter. &lsqb;TR. p. 216&rsqb;.<ftnote num="36"><para>Chief Cobb estimated that the frequency with which officers testify varies depending on their assignment and how proactive they are but estimated that the majority of officers testify around five or six times a year. &lsqb;TR. p. 182&rsqb;.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>On cross-examination Chief Cobb agreed that all the discipline matters discussed in the hearing have already been addressed and said he was not asking the arbitrator to &ldquo;revisit those issues &ndash; we are here for the letter.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 217-218&rsqb;. He also agreed that none of the discipline prior to the first arbitration involved an allegation of untruthfulness. &lsqb;TR. p. 232&rsqb;. He agreed that physically the Grievant can testify but explained that an officer cannot barge into a courtroom and say, &ldquo;Judge, I want to tell you what's going on.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 221&rsqb;. He agreed that the Grievant has never indicated an unwillingness to testify. &lsqb;TR. p. 222&rsqb;. He stated that in his experience the letter from the State's Attorney Rietz is unprecedented and that none of the chiefs from across the state that he talked to were aware of any State's Attorney preventing an officer from testifying. &lsqb;TR. p. 226&rsqb;.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>TESTIMONY OF MATT RUSH</i></b></h4>
<p>In large measure the Grievant's testimony has already been discussed. With regard to the accident report he testified that &ldquo;through word of mouth&rdquo; he learned that officers were also having reports &ldquo;disappear&rdquo; and that he did not know that the accident report he prepared was not showing up in the system. He confirmed that he was not disciplined for not completing the report or misrepresenting the facts and that he deserved the one-day suspension for forgetting to turn in the citation. &lsqb;TR. pp. 252-253&rsqb;. He also agreed that the three day suspension arising out of the arrest of Kissica Seets for being discourteous and unprofessional and for not documenting the knee strike in his report was justified and &ldquo;more than fair.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. pp. 250-251&rsqb;.</p>
<p>He testified that after the attorney who handled the lawsuit filed by Benjamin Mann obtained the defendant officers' personnel files he contacted other persons who had complaints against him and then more lawsuits came. &lsqb;TR. p. 259&rsqb;. He testified that the City settled the lawsuits without his involvement. &lsqb;TR. p. 261&rsqb;. He testified that he learned about the State's Attorney's press release and the letter to Chief Cobb through the media. &lsqb;TR. p. 272&rsqb;.</p>
<p>The Grievant testified that he is fully capable of performing everything listed in the job description of a patrol officer. He said the he is able to cooperate with the State's Attorney's Office and that he has always had good working relationships with Assistant State's Attorneys. &lsqb;TR. p. 274&rsqb;. He said that he has testified approximately 40 to 50 times and his credibility has never been an issue. &lsqb;TR. p. 275&rsqb;.</p>
<p>On cross-examination the Grievant agreed that it is up to the State's Attorney to decide to call witnesses on behalf of the state. &lsqb;TR. p. 286&rsqb;. He stated that there is no factual basis for the State's Attorney's decision not to use him as a witness. &lsqb;TR. p. 293&rsqb;. With regard to the domestic violence incident involving &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/> he stated that &ldquo;code 27&rdquo; is used for a follow-up investigation and conceded that what he was not doing would not be considered a follow-up investigation. He agreed that he did not give either <fill character="space" width="5"/> or &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; a domestic violence package. &lsqb;TR. p. 302&rsqb;. He said his mistake was not investigating something that he should have but he did not lie. &lsqb;TR. p. 307&rsqb;. He admitted that the citation related to the accident investigation was not turned in after it was initially returned for corrections. &lsqb;TR. p. 317&rsqb;. He admitted that he had been stopped in 2011 by a University of Illinois police officer and that the officer exercised his discretion not to make an arrest. &lsqb;TR. p. 322&rsqb;. He said that he did not report any suspension to the State's Attorney's Office because he was unaware of any obligation to do so and assumed that any mandatory reporting obligation would be taken care of by administration. &lsqb;TR. p. 322&rsqb;.<ftnote num="37"><para>There is nothing in the record that members of the Champaign Police Department have been made aware of any <quote>self-reporting</quote> requirement when discipline is imposed.</para></ftnote> With regard to the use of force involving Kissica Seets, the Grievant stated that he did not consider his action to be a knee strike as he interprets that term. &lsqb;TR. p. 325&rsqb;.</p>
<p>On redirect examination he explained that with regard to his actions concerning &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; and &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>&rdquo; that he thought they were just intoxicated and trying to get each other in trouble. &lsqb;TR. p. 335&rsqb;. He restated his explanation about the computer issue with the motor vehicle crash report and explained that he simply forgot to resubmit the citation after it had been turn back by a supervisor for a correction. &lsqb;TR. pp. 337-340&rsqb;. He insisted that he told the truth when asked about the accident report and citation and asserted that the one-day suspension was not based on an allegation that he had been untruthful. &lsqb;TR. p. 337&rsqb;.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><small-cap>Positions of the Parties</small-cap></b><ftnote num="38"><para>Where deemed helpful to an understanding of the cases cited by the parties, or my assessment of their relevance, I have included additional factual background or information about the cases. I have included the parties' positions as outlined in opening statements as well as post-hearing briefs.</para></ftnote></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b><i>EMPLOYER</i></b></h4>
<p>The City relies on the description of just cause in <i>The Common Law of the Workplace</i>. The essence of the just cause principle is that the employer must have some demonstrable reason for imposing discipline that concerns the employee's ability, work performance, or conduct, or the employer's legitimate business needs. Just cause is not synonymous with &ldquo;fault&rdquo; and does not require proof that the employee intended to commit the violation. The standard of proof applicable to this case is the preponderance of evidence but, in the City's view, under any quantum of proof the record establishes that the Grievant is unable to perform the essential functions of his job because his own misconduct has caused the State's Attorney's Office to determine that he cannot be called as a witness in any criminal proceeding.</p>
<p>The Union's argument that the Grievant should remain employed even though he cannot perform any meaningful employment for the City because he is physically and mentally able to testify despite the State's Attorney's conclusive decision is unsupportable and should not be credited. The well-established <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine is intended to address situations where, as here, an outside party renders a decision that makes a Grievant unemployable, even when the person would otherwise be covered by a &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; discipline provision. The City maintains that the application of the <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine requires denial of the grievance.</p>
<p>In <i>Harris Trucking Co</i>.<ftnote num="39"><para><italic>Harris Trucking Co</italic>., 80 LA 496 (Gentile, 1983). The trucking company that employed the Grievant provided loading and unloading and delivery services using its eight tractor trailers. Far West operated a wholesale lumber yard and contracted with Harris Trucking to deliver product to its customers. Approximately 95&percnt; of the company's business came from Far West. The Grievant made deliveries of Far West's products for 19 years and prior to his termination raised concerns that other drivers were receiving preferential delivery routes and filed a grievance with Harris Trucking about his complaint. The same month Far West received two complaints from its customers about the Grievant's <quote>disruptive performance.</quote> Far West told the company that the Grievant was <quote>a troublemaker</quote> and that he could not enter onto Far West's facilities. <quote>The Grievant was laid off or terminated for lack of work.</quote> Subsequently, in the arbitrator's words, the Grievant <quote>placed gasoline on the flames</quote> when he solicited Far West customers to provide character references on his behalf. Arbitrator Gentile concluded: <quote>There is no work for which the Grievant was employed by the Company. The Company is not required to make work where none exists.</quote> The grievance was denied.</para></ftnote> Arbitrator Joseph Gentile considered how a &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; discipline standard is applied in a <i>persona non grata</i> situation. He established a seven factor analysis to determine when an arbitrator should uphold the termination of an employee in such circumstances.</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Is the dispute between the employer and the employee or between the employee and a third party?</p></li>
<li><p>Did the employer act in good faith when it complied with the third party's demands?</p></li>
<li><p>Was there collusion between the employer and the third party to circumvent the &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; provision?</p></li>
<li><p>Did the third party act in good faith when it made its demands on the employer?</p></li>
<li><p>Was there available work from the employee if the employer complied with the third party's demands?</p></li>
<li><p>Was there a clear showing that the third party would no longer allow the employee to work on its equipment or the property?</p></li>
<li><p>Is there a real possibility of adverse economic impact on the employer if it does not comply with the third party's demands?</p></li></ol>
<p class="continued">The City's position is that in this case these factors can be distilled to the following three questions:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Did the State's Attorney make a good faith determination that her office could not use the Grievant as a witness?</p></li>
<li><p>Did the State's Attorney reach her decision independently without any influence from the City?</p></li>
<li><p>Does the Grievant's inability to testify in court render him unfit for duty?</p></li></ul>
<p>The record evidence establishes that State's Attorney Rietz did not make her decision lightly. She testified that in the twelve years in her current position and seven years as an Assistant State's Attorney she had never had to publicly address an officer with the level of discipline, &ldquo;particularly an officer who has only been on the force for five years.&rdquo; Along with her first assistant and lead prosecutor she carefully reviewed the voluminous materials because she wanted to make sure she was being very fair to the Grievant as well as being very aware of the citizens who were bringing the issue to her attention.</p>
<p>According to the City, the Grievant's claim that he has never been disciplined for untruthfulness is not persuasive. A police officer can be untruthful in more than one way: being intentionally untruthful or being untruthful by omission. In fact three of the disciplinary actions (the 2013 discipline for mishandling the domestic violence complaint, the arrest of Kissica Seets, and the arrest of Precious Jackson involved discipline for failing to submit complete or accurate police reports. The Union's heavy reliance on Arbitrator Dichter's opinion that the Grievant did not intentionally lie about punching Precious Jackson ignores at least four points<i>. First</i>, State's Attorney Rietz is entitled to come to her own conclusion. <i>Second</i>, Arbitrator Dichter was considering only three incidents. State's Attorney Rietz made her credibility determination after reviewing thousands of pages spanning his entire disciplinary and complaint record. <i>Third</i>, his opinion is not binding on the State's Attorney's Office nor would it be admissible in a criminal case as evidence of his truthfulness. <i>Fourth</i>, and perhaps most importantly, Arbitrator Dichter identified four acts of misconduct, including omissions from the reports he completed.</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>He failed to turn in a traffic ticket and failed to file a report, justifying a one-day suspension.</p></li>
<li><p>He omitted from official reports that the arrestee had kicked at him or that he grabbed her arm while escorting her to the police vehicle, justifying a three-day suspension.</p></li>
<li><p>He failed to take immediate steps from preventing a situation from escalating which the arbitrator concurred is a continuing problem.</p></li>
<li><p>He &ldquo;wound up throwing a punch&rdquo; which was contrary to his testimony and written reports, justifying a 30 day suspension.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">Thus, a single arbitration decision disclosed: 1) one incident of failing to submit any ticket or report at all; 2) two incidents of inaccurate reports; 3) a continuing pattern of preventing situations from escalating; and 4) testimony from the Grievant that contradicted events that actually took place. As the California Court of Appeals explained, the submission of reports that contain omissions and numerous inaccuracies constitute <i>Brady</i> material that must disclosed to defense counsel and would be admissible impeachment evidence.<ftnote num="40"><para><italic>Adolf v. Civil Service Commission of Ventura County</italic>, 2003 Cal. App. Unpub. LEXIS 1809 (2d Dist. February 26, 2003). The involved Deputy was assigned to the sexual assault unit and had been the primary investigator in 99 cases. After being informed of discrepancies by the Ventura County District Attorney's Office that resulted in the dismissal of several cases, the Sheriff's Department conducted an investigation that <quote>revealed a pattern of misrepresenting or mischaracterizing witness statements.</quote> In one case he attributed statements to the suspect and victim they did not make. In another case he failed to disclose that a suspect requested an attorney shortly before and during an interview. In another case he omitted a victim's statements that could have been used to attack the victim's credibility. In another case he stated that a victim said that she remained standing during an attack when the interview transcript showed that her statement was that she had fallen to the ground. The departmental investigation concluded that he misinterpreted and misstated facts, failed to investigate and document inculpatory and exculpatory evidence, and incorrectly quoted suspects, victims, and witnesses.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>The Grievant's handling of the domestic violence incident that started with a call from his friend on July 28, 2013 similarly caused the Grievant great concern. He did not report to dispatch where he was going or what he was doing; instead he falsely reported that he was &ldquo;code 27&rdquo; meaning he was conducting a follow-up investigation. He took an intoxicated victim home and gave her a bag of ice with no further medical treatment to address what turned out to be a significant broken wrist and ignored the requirement to give the victim a state-mandated domestic violence package.</p>
<p>The arbitrator urged the parties to address in their briefs the question of &ldquo;what, if any significance would it have on the issue before me if the state's attorney based the decision on non-Brady material?&rdquo; As an initial matter it must be emphasized that much of the material the State's Attorney relied on is Brady material. All of the following constitute material omissions and errors that could constitute potential impeachment evidence that would have to be disclosed to criminal defense counsel:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Grievant's failure to turn in a traffic ticket and his failure to write a report.</p></li>
<li><p>Grievant's omission from his official reports that an arrestee had kicked at him or that he had grabbed her arm while escorting her to the car.</p></li>
<li><p>Grievant's failure to report use of pepper spray and a hip toss during an arrest.</p></li>
<li><p>Grievant's dishonesty telling dispatch that he was conducting a &ldquo;follow-up investigation&rdquo; when he was actually leaving the jurisdiction to help a friend.</p></li>
<li><p>Grievant's failure to submit a report or case file when his friend was involved in a felony domestic battery.</p></li>
<li><p>Grievant's failure to give a domestic violence packet to the victim of his friend's abuse.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">The City's position is that it is immaterial whether a court would construe these incidents as Brady material because the correct inquiry in applying the <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine is whether the third party (here, the State's Attorney) acted in good faith, not whether they were right or wrong in every detail of their analysis. <i>Corley Distribution</i><ftnote num="41"><para><italic>Corley Distribution</italic>, 68 L.A. 513 (Ipavec, 1977). The Grievant's job was to drive to and from the Stroh Brewery in Detroit to the Stroh warehouse in West Virginia. The Grievant had a disagreement with the dock supervisor who stopped a particular pallet from being loaded onto his truck. His conduct was described as <quote>very loud and almost obnoxious.</quote> As a result Stroh management instructed the employer that the Grievant was no longer to be used to transport its product. The Grievant's version that he was did not act in an abusive manner as alleged and that the disagreement concerned the truck being improperly loaded that could cause the load to shift and cause breakage.</para></ftnote> is on point. The Grievant was discharged because he was denied access to the premises of a major customer. Arbitrator Ipavec sustained the discharge even though the third-party customer's decision left &ldquo;much to be desired and tend&lsqb;ed&rsqb; to have an abusive effect on the arbitrator's sense of justice.&rdquo; However, faced with the &ldquo;unalterable fact&rdquo; that the customer had banned the employee from the premises he could not perform the requirements of his job. Finding just cause the arbitrator denied the grievance.</p>
<p>According to the City the same &ldquo;unalterable fact&rdquo; analysis controls here as well. State's Attorney Rietz made it clear that under no circumstances would she call the Grievant as a witness even if the Arbitrator orders him reinstated. To succinctly answer the arbitrator's question: whether the State's Attorney relied in part on information that is not &ldquo;Brady material&rdquo; within the strict confines of that term is not dispositive because her decision involved a large amount of Brady information and the determination that her office would not rely on his reports or testimony was made fairly and in good faith.</p>
<p>The City also maintains the second applicable <i>Harris Trucking</i> factor is clearly satisfied. Chief Cobb and State's Attorney Rietz both testified that neither he nor anyone under his command had anything to do with the decision that he would not be called as a witness. Indeed, when she requested the Grievant's personnel file the Chief refused and required her to obtain a subpoena. No one from the police department or the city was present when the State's Attorney met with citizens who wanted the Grievant to be criminally charged.</p>
<p>The City asserts that the record supports Chief Cobb's conclusion that an indispensible requirement for every position in the police department is the ability to testify in criminal cases. The Union's suggestion that all would be well if he were assigned with another officer does not withstand scrutiny because police work sometimes requires partners to split up. What would happen, the City asks, if the Grievant alone saw a homicide suspect dispose of the gun used to kill the victim in a trash can during a foot chase and the weapon is the only evidence linking the suspect to the crime? The City also believes that having the Grievant testify would contaminate the credibility of other officers because defense attorneys could call him as a witness and create a sideshow where the focus of the trial would be his extensive disciplinary history instead of the behavior of the defendant. State's Attorney Rietz testified that a judge &ldquo;would likely&rdquo; require the jury to consider the evidence. She also testified that her office cannot review video to make sure it shows what the officer has written in its reports.</p>
<p>The City contends that reinstating the Grievant would violate public policy. Under the current contract his annual salary is &dollar;73,289.63. The Illinois Constitution, Article VII, Section 1(a) states: &ldquo;Public funds, property or credit shall be used only for public purposes.&rdquo; Chief Cobb's testimony explained in great detail the reasons why the citizens of this community would not be receiving the full value of their taxpayer money if he is reinstated but incapable of performing the essential job requirement of being called as a witness on behalf of the State.</p>
<p>The Union relies on two types of mitigating evidence: character testimony and letters of commendation and awards. The City argues that none of that evidence is convincing and most certainly does not overcome the fundamental problem that has resulted from his own conduct. Of approximately 120 sworn police officers only 11 came forward to testify on his behalf. With the exception of a few Field Training Officers who worked with him as a trainee, none of the witnesses had supervisory authority. Only one of the officers was familiar with the three disciplinary offenses that led to his first termination. None of the officers put forth any evidence that the State's Attorney's decision was made in bad faith and only two officers specifically testified as to the Grievant's credibility or trustworthiness. The Union's argument that his seven letters of commendation and awards constitute grounds for mitigating the disciplinary sanction imposed by the Chief of Police is unpersuasive. The Chief testified that his disciplinary record is &ldquo;near the top&rdquo; in the department despite his relatively short tenure. &ldquo;The Grievant's seven commendations are far outweighed by his total of <u>39 unpaid suspension days</u> from eleven separate counseling and disciplinary incidents!&rdquo; The Department lists the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">1. <fill character="space" width="5"/></p>
<p class="continued">7. April 29, 2013. Counseling for missing court.</p>
<p class="continued">8. September 10, 2013. 2-day suspension for mishandling of a domestic violence call.</p>
<p class="continued">9. August 8, 2014. 1-day suspension for failure to complete reports in a timely fashion.</p>
<p class="continued">10. August 8, 2014. 3-day suspension for failure to document use of force and discourteous behavior.</p>
<p class="continued">11. August 8, 2014. 30-day suspension for excessive use of force, failure to document use of force, and discourteous behavior.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The City claims that the Union introduced the Grievant's performance reviews as a last-ditch effort to obtain reinstatement. Each of the reviews summaries show that he consistently &ldquo;met standards,&rdquo; no more and no less. Simply meeting, not exceeding standards is hardly justification to retain an officer who cannot conduct criminal law enforcement activities.</p>
<p>The City argues that the cases relied upon the Union do not support the requested relief of reinstatement because they are factually and legally distinguishable. For example, in <i>Wetherington</i> the North Carolina Supreme Court in significant part reversed parts of the lower courts' decisions and remanded the case to the Personnel Commission for further proceedings. Unlike here the issue in that case concerned the statutory, not contractual, definition of just cause. In that case the lie involved the trooper saying a truck came by and blew his hat off his head, when in fact he simply lost his hat. The critical distinction is that no prosecutorial authority had made a decision that he could not testify in court. That is not the case here where the State's Attorney decided she cannot rely on the Grievant's reports and that calling him as a witness would be detrimental to the prosecution of criminal defendants. Unlike Trooper Wetherington, the Grievant here is &ldquo;barred from testifying in court.&rdquo;</p>
<p>While factually similar, the City argues that the legal holdings in <i>Brown v. Nero</i> lend no support to either party's position in this case. The only question in that case was whether the &ldquo;indefinite suspension&rdquo; based on the county and state's attorneys' letter was properly considered a non-disciplinary termination disentitling her to a civil service hearing. The Court of Appeals simply held that she was entitled to a hearing but decided that it did not have jurisdiction to rule on the merits of the officer's claims. The case is factually distinguishable in another respect as well. In a separate lawsuit in federal court the former officer claimed that the county and district attorneys had agreed to retract the letter of no-confidence.<ftnote num="42"><para><italic>Brown v. Nero</italic>, 2016 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 67808 (W.D. Tex., May 24, 2016). The District Court denied defendants' motion to dismiss plaintiff's claims brought under <xref pub="epg" root="federal-law-42usc" normval="1983">42 U.S.C. &sect;1983</xref>.</para></ftnote></p>
<p><i>Hubacz v. Village of Waterbury</i> is not a persuasive authority for the Union's argument because the employer produced absolutely no evidence as to why the State's Attorney determined that the officer would not be called as a witness and that the letter, standing alone, was insufficient to establish &ldquo;officer misconduct&rdquo; as that term is used in the applicable Vermont statute. Tellingly, according to the City, the District Court did not order the officer's reinstatement but instead remanded to allow the Board of Trustees to reconsider its decision in light of the guidelines in the court's decision. The decision suggested that the officer's inability to testify could be considered &ldquo;a legal disability insofar as he is unable to effectively perform his job.&rdquo;</p>
<p><i>Duchesne v. Hillsborough County Attorney</i> involved a case where three officers were disciplined and the arbitrator completely overturned the discipline and ordered that the incident be expunged from their personnel files. In that case &ldquo;a <i>court</i> decided as a matter of law that there was nothing in the officers' files that was &lsquo;potentially exculpatory.&rsquo;&rdquo; &lsqb;Emphasis in original&rsqb;. Unlike in that case, the Grievant has not brought any litigation against the State's Attorney. Furthermore, according to the City, a more recent case of the New Hampshire Supreme Court<ftnote num="43"><para><italic>Gantert v. City of Rochester</italic>, 168 N.H. 640 (2016). The officer mistakenly thought a required Lethality Assessment Protocol form (LAP) had not been completed by the arresting officer and after unsuccessfully attempting to contact the arresting officer watched the victim's videotaped interview and completed a second LAP form. The original form answered almost all the questions <quote>yes</quote> which triggered the protocol; the second form answered almost all the questions <quote>no</quote> and did not trigger the protocol. An arbitrator found that under the circumstances the department had just cause for discipline but that termination was an excessive penalty because the Grievant had a good record and this was an isolated event. The officer subsequently sued the City of Rochester for tortious interference with advantageous business relations, violations of procedural due process, and damage to his reputation. The Supreme Court agreed with the trial court that the Grievant was afforded an adequate opportunity to explain his side of the story and that, unlike the circumstances in <italic>Duchesne</italic>, the arbitrator's just cause finding was based on the same information that led to the Grievant's placement on the list. <quote>Had his findings been different, they could have had the same ramifications as in <italic>Duchesne, i.e</italic>., providing a basis for removing the plaintiff from the &lsquo;Laurie List.&rsquo;</quote></para></ftnote> distinguished <i>Duchesne</i> and declined to order an officer's removal from the <i>Laurie</i> list because the original arbitration decision, which upheld discipline for the officer while finding there was no intentional deceit, was &ldquo;certainly enough of a reflection of the plaintiff's <i>general credibility</i> to trigger at least a prosecutor's obligation to disclose such information to a court for <i>in camera</i> review.&rdquo; &lsqb;Emphasis in original&rsqb;.</p>
<p>The City asserts that the Union's reliance on <i>Polk County</i> is &ldquo;strange&rdquo; because in that case the arbitrator upheld the termination. While declining to consider the <i>Brady</i> letter as evidence of the Grievant's guilt, the arbitrator did say that a <i>Brady</i> letter &ldquo;would be relevant&rdquo; to reinstatement in the event that the employer fails to establish just cause for its disciplinary action.</p>
<p>Although actually not cited in its post-hearing brief, the City anticipated that the Union would rely on <i>Franklin County Sheriff's Office</i>.<ftnote num="44"><para><italic>Franklin County Sheriff's Office</italic>, 127 LA 283 (Felice, 2010). The case involved a note that was taped on another deputy's locker that contained a racial slur. During an interview on March 12<superscript>th</superscript> the Grievant was asked if he <quote>ever wiped the locker down</quote> and he answered, <quote>no.</quote> Several days later he approached his supervisor that he wanted to speak with internal affairs again and in a second interview on March 17<superscript>th</superscript> he stated that he had wiped the locker with cleaning solvent. The Grievant in that case testified that he met with his pastor two days after the first interview and was told that he needed to tell the truth. The arbitrator acknowledged that under <italic>Giglio v. United States</italic> the failure to disclose evidence affecting credibility could result in the reversal of a conviction. Nevertheless, based on evidence that the Sheriff's Office had issued discipline less that termination for untruthfulness <quote>on numerous occasions</quote> after <italic>Giglio</italic> was decided, the arbitrator overturned the dismissal and imposed a 90-day suspension.</para></ftnote> In that case there had been no finding by the State's Attorney's Office that the deputy would not be called as a witness. The arbitrator also relied on the fact that other officers had been disciplined but not discharged for being untruthful and that during his 18 year career the deputy never testified in court. There is no such evidence of disparate treatment in this case. The Grievant estimated that he has testified, &ldquo;40, 50 times probably.&rdquo; This case is, therefore, readily distinguishable from <i>Franklin County</i>.</p>
<p>According to the City, the Grievant in this case is not an innocent victim of circumstances beyond his control. His poor judgment and own disciplinary problems have created the situation he now finds himself in. It was his own actions that caused the understandable loss of confidence from the State's Attorney's Office and its inability to rely on his reports or vouch for his credibility. Because he cannot testify in court he cannot serve as a law enforcement officers. The citizens of Champaign must not be saddled with the burden of paying the substantial salary and benefits of a police officer unable to perform the essential functions of his job. The grievance must be denied.<ftnote num="45"><para>Subsequent to the submission of briefs the City, with the concurrence of the Union, submitted an Opinion &amp; Award authored by Arbitrator Marvin Hill captioned <italic>City of Crystal Lake &amp; MAP</italic>, dated December 6, 2016. Both parties have shared their comments concerning the case. The case involved an officer who had been involved in an on-duty motor vehicle accident and was subsequently dismissed because he repeatedly lied about the extent of his injuries and his physical capacity to do police work. Arbitrator Hill denied the grievance. He discussed the <italic>Brady</italic> implications when disciplinary charges that an officer has been untruthful are sustained. The City asks that I adopt Arbitrator Hill's viewpoint that when an officer's documented untruthfulness is at issue an arbitrator should not lightly substitute his judgment and discretion for the judgment and discretion honestly exercised by a Chief of Police who met the contractual requirements of due process, fairness and just cause. The Union argues that the case decided by Arbitrator Hill is entirely different than this case because, contrary to Arbitrator Dichter, Arbitrator Hill agreed that the Grievant repeatedly lied. The Union says that to be comparable the facts in that case would have to be that an arbitrator found the employee not guilty of lying, ordered reinstatement, and fired him a second time because the State's Attorney disagreed with the arbitrator and banned him from testifying. I find Arbitrator Hill's reasoning persuasive and I have taken it into account.</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="left"><b><i>UNION</i></b></h4>
<p>The purported basis for State's Attorney Rietz's pronouncement that the Grievant would not in the future be allowed by her office to testify as a witness in any criminal case is the decision of the United States Supreme Court in <i>Brady v. Maryland</i>.<ftnote num="46"><para><italic>Brady v</italic>. Maryland, 373 U.S. 83 (1962). The disclosure requirements at issue are known in some agencies as <quote><italic>Brady/Giglio</italic></quote> or <quote><italic>Giglio</italic></quote> policies. The reference is to a decision of the United States Supreme Court that reinforced the disclosure obligations of prosecutors established in <italic>Brady v. Maryland</italic>. <italic>Giglio v. United States</italic>, 405 U.S. 150 (1972).</para></ftnote> Although she testified that she did not put the Grievant on an actual &ldquo;Brady list&rdquo; per se, the net effect was the same as if she had: she absolutely and unequivocally barred him from testifying ever, regardless of the case or the circumstances. The Union maintains that she misapplied the <i>Brady</i> doctrine and by doing so abused her discretion as a public official. In deciding that her office would not vouch for his credibility she impermissibly acted as prosecutor, judge, and jury. Consequently, Chief Cobb's decision to terminate his employment &ndash; which was based solely on a unilateral decision by a third party &ndash; flies in the face of due process and violates the contractual requirement that discipline be consistent with principles of just cause.</p>
<p>The <i>Brady</i> line of cases requires the prosecution to disclose to the defense evidence favorable to the accused that is material either to guilt or punishment. This duty to disclose encompasses exculpatory information as well as information that may be used to impeach the State's witnesses, and applies whether or not the defendant requests the information. The individual prosecutor has an obligation to learn of favorable evidence known to others acting on the government's behalf, including the police. The prosecutor's disclosure obligation applies even when the police do not disclose all that they know to the prosecutor. In practice, if <i>Brady</i> material is disclosed, it is up to the presiding judge to determine if it is relevant and admissible. If it is used at trial to impeach the witness, the State's Attorney is free to rehabilitate the witness using other relevant information or evidence.</p>
<p>The Union's post-hearing brief references case law that it contends amply supports the conclusion that the State's Attorney's interpretation and application of <i>Brady</i> is unsupportable. Moreover, the Union maintains that case law it relies upon likewise establishes that Chief Cobb acted inconsistently with just cause by terminating the Grievant in reliance on the wrongful decision of a third party.</p>
<p>The Union asserts that the misapplication of <i>Brady</i> by the State's Attorney is illustrated by the North Carolina Court of Appeals' decision in <i>Wetherington v. Dept. of Crime Control &amp; Public Safety</i>.<ftnote num="47"><para><italic>Wetherington v. North Carolina Dept. of Crime Control &amp; Public Safety</italic>, 752 S.E.2d 511 (N.C. App. 2013). The case concerned the circumstances under which the Grievant lost his hat during a traffic stop on a highway. Regulations of the North Carolina Highway Patrol require troopers to wear hats when leaving the patrol vehicle. He had previously been reprimanded for not wearing his hat during a traffic stop. The trooper confided to another officer that after he left the location of the traffic stop he realized that he did not have his hat. He was unable to locate it when he returned to the scene and falsely told his supervisor that he was wearing the hat during the investigation and it blew off his head when an eighteen-wheel truck drove by and that he had been unable to find it. In fact he had placed it on either the trunk lid of the stopped vehicle or on the light bar of the patrol vehicle. A citizen eventually returned the undamaged hat and the trooper subsequently acknowledged that the statement to the supervisor that he had been wearing the hat was untruthful. The cost of the hat was &dollar;50.</para></ftnote> A state trooper was terminated for violating the Agency's &ldquo;truthfulness policy.&rdquo;<ftnote num="48"><para>The policy provided: <quote>Members shall be truthful and complete in all written and oral communications, reports, and testimony. No member shall willfully report any inaccurate, false, improper, or misleading information.</quote></para></ftnote> The agency contended that <i>Brady</i> would require his untruthfulness to be disclosed to defense counsel in any case in which he was involved and consequently he could not perform the essential job duty of providing sworn testimony in criminal cases. The appellate court rejected that argument and affirmed the lower court's findings that terminating his employment was arbitrary and capricious and that the agency lacked just cause for ending the officer's career. It concluded:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Respondent's argument depends on at least two assumptions that Respondent does not address: (1) that defense counsel will elect to impeach Petitioner using this finding; and (2) that defense counsel's impeachment will necessarily influence a jury to the point that a jury will disregard the entirety of Petitioner's testimony. The possibility of impeachment and the possibility of impeachment's success must both occur in order to diminish Petitioner's performance of the duty to testify successfully. Respondent presents no argument that the likelihood of the two possibilities justifies dismissal.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Union's position is that <i>Wetherington</i> demonstrates that just cause for discipline must be based on the employee's own misconduct rather than what an individual who is not a party to the collective bargaining agreement assumes might occur in future cases.<ftnote num="49"><para>As noted in the Union's post-hearing brief, the North Carolina Supreme Court affirmed and modified the Court of Appeals decision. <italic>Wetherington v. North Carolina Dept. of Public</italic> Safety, 780 S.E.2d 543 (N.C. 2015). The Supreme Court remanded the case for further review by the agency because the agency head, Colonel Randy Glover, mistakenly believed that when there is <quote>a substantiated or adjudicated finding of untruthfulness</quote> he has <quote>no choice</quote> but to terminate a trooper's employment. The Supreme Court stated that the Colonel's erroneous understanding that he lacked discretion in cases involving untruthfulness was an error of law. It ordered that the matter be returned to the agency for reconsideration with the understanding that termination is not mandatory and that factors such as the severity of the violation, the subject matter involved, the resulting harm, the trooper's work history, and discipline imposed in other cases involving similar violations are appropriate considerations in deciding issues of just cause. The Supreme Court left untouched the Court of Appeals <italic>Brady</italic> analysis.</para></ftnote> The Union emphasizes that in this case, unlike in <i>Wetherington</i>, there is no comparable finding of untruthfulness on the part of Officer Rush. State's Attorney Rietz misstated the facts in her February 23, 2016 letter to Chief Cobb and the press release. She said, &ldquo;the State's Attorney's Office is unable to call PO Rush as a witness on behalf of the State in criminal proceedings in light of his repeated failure to adequately document use of force and multiple discipline actions for untruthfulness.&rdquo; The record evidence substantiates that during his career there has been only one disciplinary action for untruthfulness and that finding was in connection with the description of his use of force in effecting the arrest of Precious Jackson. However, the Department's discipline for being untruthful had been overturned almost a year earlier by Arbitrator Fredric Dichter. He stated: &ldquo;The Arbitrator after observing Grievant and listening to the testimony of others finds Grievant to be a credible person. Even his supervisors have said they found him to be a honest person.&rdquo; Arbitrator Dichter continued:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator finds the most plausible explanation is that in Grievant's mind the video does comport to his recollection and his recounting of events. Others observing it, including this Arbitrator see it one way and he may very honestly be seeing it another. Lying requires intent. Grievant is apparently wrong in his perception of what he did, but the Arbitrator finds it is based on his errant perception of events and not an intent to deceive. That is not an uncommon occurrence. No doubt the action he took was taken for the purpose he has stated, he just did not do it the way he thinks he did. There is a difference between being simply mistaken and knowing what one says is wrong and saying it anyway. One requires intent and the other does not. Finding such intent to deceive for this Grievant is a bridge too far for this Arbitrator given all that preceded this event.</p></blockquote>
<p>The State's Attorney's misapprehension that a <i>Brady</i> disclosure to defense counsel is required when an officer who has been charged with being untruthful is subsequently exonerated, the Union argues, is at odds with case law. It relies on a recent decision by a Texas appellate court in <i>Brown v. Nero</i><ftnote num="50"><para><italic>Brown v. Nero</italic>, 477 S.W.3d 448 (Texas App. 2015).</para></ftnote> that it contends is instructive because the facts of that case closely parallel the facts here. In Nero, an individual with whom Georgetown Police Officer Stephanie Hoskins Brown had been in a previous relationship alleged that she had been taking his prescription medication and that she had ingested mescaline, a controlled substance. As the result of the investigation Chief Nero terminated her employment on June 11, 2013. She appealed and a civil service hearing before an independent third-party hearing examiner was conducted on August 26-27, 2013. Three days later, and before the hearing officer issued a decision, Chief Nero met with the County Attorney and County District Attorney and told them about her alleged misconduct. Following the meeting the prosecutors issued a joint letter to Chief Nero dated October 31, 2013 informing him that their offices would no longer &ldquo;accept cases&rdquo; in which Officer Brown &ldquo;has played a role.&rdquo; The following day the hearing officer issued a decision that concluded that the Grievant had used prescription medication prescribed for her acquaintance but also found that she had her own prescription for the same medication and that she had not used if for recreational purposes. He also found that the department had not met its burden of proof on the charge that she used mescaline that she had been untruthful during the investigation. He overturned the dismissal, imposed a 15-day suspension, and ordered her reinstated with back pay and benefits. She was reinstated on November 7<sup>th</sup>. On November 8<sup>th</sup> Chief Nero fired her a second time solely based on the joint letter. The termination letter explained that since the County Attorney and County District Attorney would no longer &ldquo;sponsor her as a witness&rdquo; she could no longer fulfill one of the essential job functions for her position. Furthermore, because Chief Nero's letter characterized his action as a &ldquo;non-disciplinary termination&rdquo; the civil service director refused to allow her to appeal on the ground that only disciplinary actions are appealable under the civil service statute. The Court of Appeals of Texas rejected the City's &ldquo;essential job function&rdquo; argument.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The defendants presented no evidence that she was incapable of testifying or performing any other required function. Brown was not fired because she failed to maintain a license, pass an exam, or perform satisfactorily in the field. Rather, the evidence showed that the prosecutors' decision not to accept Brown's cases was based on Chief Nero's accusations of untruthfulness, which the hearing examiner found to be groundless. And instead of abiding by the hearing examiner's award, which was &ldquo;final and binding on all parties,&rdquo; Chief Nero allowed the unilateral decision of elected officials to circumvent the protections of the Civil Service Act.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Court reasoned that acceptance of the City's argument would give prosecutors &ldquo;unbridled discretion to declare that they will not accept cases from an officer, and the police chief may &ndash; and, in fact, has a duty to &ndash; terminate that officer.&rdquo; It continued: &ldquo;The Civil Service Act was intended to prevent the sort of factual scenario we have before us. The purpose of this chapter is to secure efficient fire and police departments composed of capable personnel who are <i>free from political influence</i> and who have permanent employment as public servants.&rdquo; (Citation omitted, italics in original).</p>
<p>The rationale and result in <i>Brown</i> should be applied in this case, the Union argues, because the relevant facts are indistinguishable. Like Officer Brown, Officer Rush was ordered reinstated with partial back pay and benefits. Like the independent hearing examiner in that case, Arbitrator Dichter determined that the allegation of untruthfulness was groundless. As did the prosecutors in <i>Brown</i>, State's Attorney Rietz chose to disregard that the Grievant was exonerated in a final and binding decision. And like Chief Nero, Chief Cobb terminated the Grievant's employment in the absence of any new allegation of misconduct but solely based on the letter declaring that the Grievant would not be called as a prosecution witness. As in <i>Brown</i>, the City's argument that the Grievant could not perform an essential job function had nothing to do with failing to maintain a license or not passing an exam or unsatisfactory performance. As in <i>Brown</i>, where the Court found that her termination was unrelated to her qualifications and the employer presented no evidence that she was incapable of testifying, the City of Champaign is similarly off the mark when it says that the Grievant &ndash; who has testified 40 to 50 times without his credibility ever being impeached &mdash; is incapable of testifying. According to the Union these facts are more compelling because in <i>Brown</i> the officer's second termination occurred one day after her reinstatement. In contrast, the Grievant's work record after being reinstated in April 2015 and prior to the second termination in April 2016 was exemplary. And for the same reasons that persuaded the <i>Brown</i> court, the arbitrator must not uphold the decision to terminate his career when it is based solely on the unilateral decision of a third party politician and without any evidence of misconduct on his part that the Department had not already addressed.</p>
<p>The Union similarly relies on <i>Hubacz v. Village in Westbury</i><ftnote num="51"><para><italic>Hubacz v. Village of Waterbury, Vermont</italic>, 2014 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 52131 (D. Vt. April 15, 2014).</para></ftnote> in which the United States District Court of Vermont granted summary judgment to the plaintiff officer when the sole basis for firing him was an announcement by the county prosecutor that the officer would no longer be called as a prosecution witness in criminal cases.<ftnote num="52"><para>Officer Hubacz worked as a patrol officer in the Village of Waterbury Police Department from 2009 until his termination on January 27, 2012. The termination resulted from a decision by Washington County State's Attorney Thomas Kelly that his cases would no longer be prosecuted. After the Chief of Police confirmed that information he advised the officer that he was recommending his dismissal because in light of the prosecutor's decision he could no longer function effectively as a police officer. At the hearing before the Village Trustees the parties stipulated that the sole basis for the termination was Kelly's decision to stop prosecuting his cases. The Trustees acknowledged that Officer Hubacz <quote>was a good and diligent officer in that he fulfilled his duties, was community-minded, showed an aptitude for police work, and an interest in learning more.</quote> Nevertheless, the Trustees upheld the Chief's decision because they thought that Officer Hubacz's involvement would jeopardize the investigation of cases and <quote>&lsqb;i&rsqb;n such instances crimes would go unprosecuted and the law would be left unenforced.</quote> The Trustees reasoned that the department had only four full-time officers and concluded that allowing him to retain his position would constitute a misuse of taxpayers' funds.</para></ftnote> The Court considered whether the Village Trustees' decision comported with a state statute that specified that the removal of full-time police officers must be based on negligence or dereliction in performance of official duties or engaging in acts constituting conduct unbecoming an officer.<ftnote num="53"><para>The Trustees <quote>concluded that Hubacz's inability to contribute to the prosecution of cases rendered him negligent and derelict in his duties.</quote> They also concluded that <quote>his inability to participate in police work</quote> is encompassed in the meaning of conduct unbecoming an officer because it would <quote>destroy public respect for police officers and confidence in the operations of the police department.</quote> The Trustees rejected the officer's argument that termination on the basis of State's Attorney Kelly's decision <quote>would essentially permit prosecutors to determine who may serve as police officers.</quote></para></ftnote> Since the Board of Trustees made no findings of specific misconduct and based their ruling entirely on the prosecutor's decision, according the Union, the dispositive question was whether that decision &mdash; &ldquo;effectively barring Hubacz from performing his job&rdquo; &mdash; provided sufficient grounds for termination as negligence or dereliction or conduct unbecoming. It did not.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Rather than finding specific misconduct, the Trustees concluded that Hubacz was unable to perform his job. This inability, they reasoned, constituted dereliction and conduct unbecoming an officer. Section 1932, however, entitled &ldquo;Negligence of officer: suspension; hearing&rdquo; clearly contemplates officer misconduct. Instead of reviewing the officer's actions, the Trustees considered actions of a third party that <i>impacted</i> the officer. Nothing in Section 1932 suggests that such third-party conduct is a valid basis for termination under its terms. (Emphasis in original).<ftnote num="54"><para>The District Judge concluded that the Village's argument sought to carry the removal statute <quote>beyond its plain language in an effort to encompass the facts of this case, urging the Court to read the statute broadly, but also to assume misconduct. A fair reading of the statute, as well as Vermont Supreme Court precedent, counsels otherwise.</quote> The District Court remanded the matter to the Trustees for reconsideration of the question whether recourse for termination of a police officer is limited under Vermont law to the removal statute.</para></ftnote></p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Union urges the arbitrator to adopt the Court's reasoning: conduct by a third party that impacts the officer cannot be considered to be the same thing as the officer's own misconduct.</p>
<p>A critical issue in this case, the Union argues, is the significance of State's Attorney Rietz's decision to rely on an allegation of untruthfulness that was overturned by an arbitrator who, contrary to the conclusion reached by Chief Cobb, found the Grievant truthful and credible. The New Hampshire Supreme Court addressed that question in <i>Duchesne v. Hillsborough County Attorney</i><ftnote num="55"><para><italic>Duchesne v. Hillsborough County District Attorney</italic>, 119 A.3d 188 (N.H. 2015).</para></ftnote> and the answer sheds light on the appropriate disposition of this matter. Three officers of the Manchester Police Department were involved in an off-duty altercation at a bar that was widely reported in the media. A criminal investigation by the New Hampshire Attorney General's Office concluded that the officers' conduct was justified under state law and that no criminal charges were warranted. An internal affairs investigation resulted in disciplinary charges alleging that the officers had used excessive force and the Chief sent letters advising of that finding to the County Attorney. The County Attorney placed the officers on a &ldquo;Laurie list.&rdquo;<ftnote num="56"><para>The <italic>Laurie</italic> case is a New Hampshire case that imposes an obligation on prosecutors to disclose potentially exculpatory material in personnel files of police officers for an <italic>in camera</italic> review by the presiding judge for a judicial determination if it must be turned over to defense counsel and potentially admitted as evidence at trial. <italic>State v. Laurie</italic>, 653 A.2d 549 (N.H. 1995).</para></ftnote> The officers appealed the discipline to arbitration and the arbitrator ruled in their favor finding no just cause. References to the discipline were removed from their personnel files and the Chief sent a second letter requesting that, pursuant to the arbitrator's award, their names be removed from the Laurie list. The County Attorney declined to do so because the Chief initially sustained the allegation. The officers brought an action to have their names removed from the list and the trial court ruled in the County's favor reasoning that granting the requested relief would substitute the court's judgment for that of the prosecutor.</p>
<p>The New Hampshire Supreme Court reversed the lower court and held that the officers were entitled to have their names removed from the Laurie list.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&lsqb;A&rsqb;lthough petitioners were initially disciplined by the police chief for their alleged excessive use of force, the chief's decision was overturned by an arbitrator, a neutral fact finder, following a full hearing conducted pursuant to procedures agreed to in a CBA&hellip;. Given that the original allegation of excessive force has been determined to be unfounded, there is no sustained basis for the petitioners' placement on the &ldquo;Laurie list.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>
<p>As did the Hillsborough County Attorney, State's Attorney Rietz chose to ignore the finding that the Grievant was in point of fact adjudged truthful in the only instance where the Department charged him with being untruthful. She thinks Arbitrator Dichter got it wrong. That opinion cannot abolish the principle that when an arbitrator overturns a disciplinary charge of untruthfulness based on the factual finding that the officer had been truthful there is no <i>Brady</i> problem.</p>
<p>The Union points out that the issue being decided in this proceeding is not one of first impression. A deputy sheriff in Oregon who was receiving workers compensation benefits was fired because he allegedly lied about the extent of his physical disability from an on-duty injury.<ftnote num="57"><para><italic>Polk County</italic>, <xref pub="arb" root="cch-internal-ref" normval="15-2ARBP6507">15-2 ARB &para;6507</xref> (Landau, 2015). The Grievant testified under oath at a workers compensation hearing that at the time he was receiving disability benefits for an on-duty slip and fall he was unable to use his right hand. Surveillance video showed him performing activities (including washing his car) that the City maintained contradicted that claim.</para></ftnote> <fill character="space" width="5"/> The arbitration hearing appealing his dismissal was scheduled for June 9, 2015. On June 8<sup>th</sup> the Polk County District Attorney notified the Grievant by letter that pursuant to <i>Brady v. Maryland</i> in the future he would be disqualified as a witness for the prosecution in criminal proceedings based on his &ldquo;deceptive conduct,&rdquo; &ldquo;deceptive statements,&rdquo; and &ldquo;dishonesty.&rdquo; The Deputy Sheriff's Association contended that the &ldquo;District Attorney's issuance of a <i>Brady</i> letter to Grievant is highly suspect and appears to be an effort by the Sheriff's Office to justify Grievant's termination.&rdquo; The arbitrator concluded that the District Attorney's letter was entitled to &ldquo;no weight.&rdquo;</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The County relies on the <i>Brady</i> letter issued to Grievant by the District Attorney to argue that he is no longer fit to testify on behalf of the prosecution in criminal cases and therefore he is &ldquo;functionally unemployable&rdquo; as a law enforcement officer. On this point, I agree with the Association's contention that a <i>Brady</i> letter does not provide an independent basis for discipline under the collective bargaining agreement and the employer must still prove that it had just cause for discipline or discharge. Therefore, I give the <i>Brady</i> letter no weight in the just cause analysis. At most, a <i>Brady</i> letter would be relevant to the issue of reinstatement in the event an employer fails to establish just cause for its disciplinary action.</p></blockquote>
<p>Although he concluded that the District Attorney's <i>Brady</i> letter was entitled to no weight, the arbitrator upheld the discharge because he determined that the surveillance video clearly and convincingly showed that on multiple occasions he intentionally misrepresented his physical ability to use his right arm. &ldquo;As a result the County had just cause to terminate his employment.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Union argues that <i>Polk County</i> is similar and dissimilar to this case. Neither the letter from the Polk County District Attorney nor the Champaign County State's Attorney's letter can provide an independent basis for fulfilling the requirement that the Grievant not lose his job except for just cause. The Polk County Sheriff accused a deputy of being untruthful and the Chief of Police accused the Grievant of being untruthful. However, unlike Arbitrator Landau, who found the evidence in that case substantiated the untruthfulness allegation, Arbitrator Dichter concluded the opposite. The City's attempt to reopen and relitigate closed matters is improper. The reason that Arbitrator Landau ruled that just cause existed in that case &ndash; proof of misconduct was alleged and proven at the hearing &mdash; is the reason that just cause cannot support this Grievant's dismissal. Misconduct (except old charges that had already been adjudicated) was neither alleged nor proven.</p>
<p>As has made clear, the Union strongly disagrees that <i>Brady</i> requires, or justifies, disqualifying the Grievant as a witness in future criminal cases. Her misinterpretation and misapplication of that doctrine should be determinative of the outcome here. However, even if the arbitrator overlooked those problems the Union asserts that the Grievant's termination cannot pass muster. Essentially, the Union contends that this case involves overreaching by a politician in an election year<ftnote num="58"><para>The Union contends that the State's Attorney Rietz's decision to issue a press release after her review determined that there were no grounds to file criminal charges was <quote>really all about</quote> politics. According to the Union's opening statement, <quote>she has a right to campaign the way she wants but not on the back of this officer.</quote> &lsqb;TR. p. 22&rsqb;. The City's post-hearing brief indicates that State's Attorney Rietz was reelected to her position on November 8, 2016.</para></ftnote> encouraged by a small percentage of citizens who have an issue with Officer Rush from media coverage over which he had no control about lawsuit settlements in which he had no say. The contention in her letter to Chief Cobb that the Grievant had &ldquo;multiple discipline actions for untruthfulness&rdquo; is a blatant falsehood because, as has been repeatedly explained, the Department issued only one accusation of untruthfulness and Arbitrator Dichter exonerated him of that charge. The State's Attorney chose to ignore and reweighed findings made by the Department and considered events as discipline when no discipline was involved. Not only did she not afford the Grievant an opportunity to respond but also &ndash; astonishingly &ndash; she did not consider his version of events contained in the investigative reports because <i>Garrity</i><ftnote num="59"><para><italic>Garrity v. New Jersey</italic>, 385 U.S. 493 (1967).</para></ftnote> statements should not be considered in deciding whether a prosecutor will bring criminal charges. However, she conceded that there was nothing preventing her from considering those statements in deciding whether she would or would not call him as a witness. The Department already scrutinized everything that gave rise to her &ldquo;concerns&rdquo; and where discipline was deemed appropriate the discipline had been administered. In other words, nothing presented in this arbitration concerned any allegation of misconduct that had not already been finalized and adjudicated. After his reinstatement on April 7, 2015 he received no discipline and not a single complaint. On the contrary he received several emails from superior officers commenting on his good work. All of this should lead the arbitrator to conclude that the State's Attorney interjected herself into the disciplinary process without authority or justification. The City's invitation to the arbitrator to overlook the failure to afford due process and the resultant abuse of just cause principles should not be accepted.</p>
<p>Finally, the Union contends that the City's reliance on the <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine is spurious. As noted in the Elkouri &amp; Elkouri treatise, the doctrine is invoked in circumstances when the bargaining unit employee performs his duties on the premises of a customer and the employee is barred from the customer's premises. Often these cases arise when the complaining party is the company's most significant client and not acceding to the client's demands would have an adverse financial impact.<ftnote num="60"><para><italic>See Rebar Engineering Inc</italic>., 105 L.A. 662 (Riker, 1995). <italic>See also Corley Distributing Co</italic>., 68 L.A. 513, 515 (Ipavec, 1995) (Arbitrator concluded that the company's business was dependent upon the major supplier and termination of the employee was the only course of action so as to not jeopardize its beer franchise).</para></ftnote></p>
<p><i>UGL UNICCO</i><ftnote num="61"><para><italic>UGL UNNICO</italic>, 126 L.A. 474 (Yancy, 2008).</para></ftnote> is a typical case. It involved a company that provided facilities maintenance services at a tire manufacturing facility. The Grievant was a lead mechanic who had worked at the customer's facility for 34 years and had &ldquo;a flawless record.&rdquo; The customer became dissatisfied with how the Grievant responded to a report of a fire and informed the company that he was banned from the premises. The employer investigation concluded that the response was not mishandled but its efforts to reverse the decision to ban him were unsuccessful because the customer thought he had &ldquo;a bad attitude.&rdquo;<ftnote num="62"><para>The company did not attempt to defend the customer's decision to ban the employee from the plant. On the contrary, it conceded at arbitration that it was <quote>wrongful, irrational and downright reprehensible.</quote> The arbitrator saw it the same way. <quote>The arbitrator finds the third party's actions obnoxious, troublesome, repugnant, and totally devoid of fairness.</quote></para></ftnote> The arbitrator analyzed the company's <i>persona non grata</i> argument and decided that the Grievant's termination was not supported by just cause.<ftnote num="63"><para>Arbitrator Yancy wrote: <quote>The arbitrator notes that the ability of a third party to ban an employee from a facility based on the mere unsupported assertion that he has a bad attitude, and thus effectively terminating him from his job, seems to render the labor agreement between the parties a sham and the grievance process a mockery.</quote></para></ftnote> At the same time he acknowledged that an order returning the Grievant to work at the customer's facility would be &ldquo;futile, unenforceable, and not worth a &lsquo;tinker's damn.&rsquo;&rdquo; His award required to the company to again ask the customer to reconsider its decision and to revisit the feasibility of assignment to a different work location. The award provided that if both courses of action failed the matter was remanded to the parties to determine damages. He retained jurisdiction. Eventually the arbitrator awarded the Grievant damages equivalent to 68 weeks salary (two weeks for each year of service).</p>
<p>The employer brought an action to vacate the award. The federal district judge granted the Union's motion to enforce the award.<ftnote num="64"><para><italic>UGL UNICCO v. District Lodge 110 International Assoc. of Machinists &amp; Aerospace Workers</italic>, 723 F. Supp.2d 844 (E.D.N.C. 2010).</para></ftnote> The Court decided: (1) the collective bargaining agreement did not specifically provide for the <i>non persona grata</i> situation; (2) an arbitrator commissioned to interpret and apply a collective bargaining agreement is expected to bring his informed judgment to bear to each a fair solution of a problem; and (3) the company's good-faith did not cure the breach of the just cause provision.</p>
<p>The City's <i>persona non grata</i> argument is unpersuasive because, among other reasons, there is no similarity between a publicly employed police officer and a subcontracted private sector employee. As was true in <i>UGL UNNICO</i>, the absence of a specific clause giving a third party removal authority<ftnote num="65"><para>The Union's post-hearing brief cited an arbitration case involving a collective bargaining agreement that allowed a <quote>house account customer</quote> to prohibit an employee from driving one of the customer's trucks for a justifiable reason. The provision allowed the driver to be laid off until a vacancy with another customer became available. <italic>Transports Drivers Inc</italic>., 1997 L.A. Supp. 101989 (Hockenberry, 1997).</para></ftnote> requires that the just cause provision be enforced. So even if this arbitrator takes a quantum leap and finds that the <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine applies to the case at hand, that does not eviscerate the contractual obligation that an employee be discharged only for just cause. The Union has convincingly shown that just cause does not exist and the parties' agreement does not delegate a police officer's removal from service to a third party. A politician's ill-motivated, unilateral, unsubstantiated opinion to decide the fate of bargaining unit members is not what the parties' incorporation of the just cause provision intended.</p>
<p>In conclusion, for the above-stated reasons the Union, on behalf of the Grievant, respectfully requests that the arbitrator find there was no just cause for termination, reinstate the Grievant, award back pay and all lost benefits, make the Grievant whole, and take any further action deemed equitable and just.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i><small-cap>Discussion</small-cap></i></b></h4>
<p>It is axiomatic that an arbitrator derives his or her authority exclusively from the express terms of the collective bargaining agreement. The parties are at liberty to make that authority as broad or as narrow as they deem appropriate. This contract forbids modifying any term of the Agreement in any respect and divests an arbitrator of the authority to award any remedy that is contrary to any provision. This means that my responsibility is to enforce the contractual undertakings by which the parties have agreed to be bound. &ldquo;It is not within the authority of the arbitrator to substitute his own concepts of fairness or justice for those that the parties have established.&rdquo; <i>See University of Michigan</i>, 103 L.A. 401, 403 (Daniel, 1994).</p>
<p><i>Brady v. Maryland</i> was decided more than a half-century ago. However, a familiarity with reported judicial and arbitration decisions leads to the observation that judges and arbitrators have not had occasion to deal with the thorny issues at the heart of cases like this one until much more recently. <i>Brady</i> and its progeny erect valuable protections for defendants in criminal cases and impose important duties on prosecutors. On the other hand, public safety officers have a weighty interest in decisions that affect their livelihood and in enforcing hard-fought for job protections (i.e., just cause for discipline and discharge) established in collective bargaining agreements. The potential for miscarriages of justice from faulty thinking in cases like this one exist. For example, it is too common that some individuals unjustifiably attach the &ldquo;kiss of death&rdquo; label of &ldquo;untruthfulness&rdquo; to circumstances when an officer honestly misperceives or misremembers or through oversight files a report that is shown to be inaccurate in some detail.</p>
<p>Even more unsettling, the potential for behind-the-scenes collusion to end the career of a disfavored officer by circumventing pledges to abide by &ldquo;final and binding&rdquo; decisions by arbitrators is, unfortunately, not illusory. A telling example is the <i>Brown v. Nero</i> case cited by the Union.<ftnote num="66"><para>I am aware that in Texas police discipline cases arbitrators act as mutually selected <quote>hearing officers</quote> and apply a just cause standard that is established by statute rather than contract. The term <quote>indefinite suspension</quote> is synonymous with termination. These distinctions are not relevant to the discussion.</para></ftnote> An ex-boyfriend says a police officer used mescaline, the Chief believes him, and fires the officer for lying by maintaining her innocence during the investigation. The appeal hearing does not go well (from the police department's perspective) and sensing how the wind is blowing the Chief meets with the District Attorney and County Attorney and gives them a one-sided assessment of her deficient credibility. He receives what he seeks: a jointly signed &ldquo;no-confidence&rdquo; letter. As anticipated the arbitrator concludes that the ex-boyfriend's accusation is not credible and in a decision issued on Friday orders the officer reinstated. She is reinstated on the following Thursday. The next day she is terminated a second time for the &ldquo;non-disciplinary&rdquo; reason that the letter precludes her from being able to perform the essential job function of testifying in court. In my view the Texas Court of Appeals Third District got it right: this cannot be how it is supposed to work. If a prosecutor is empowered with the unbridled and unreviewable discretion to deem an officer &ldquo;disqualified&rdquo; to testify &mdash; with the consequence that she loses her job because obviously there is no place in a police department for a law enforcement officer with that incapacity &ndash; contractual or statutory just cause protections are a nullity. An arbitrator would need to be more na&iuml;ve than parties should expect not to realize that one must be alert to the danger that a losing party in a disciplinary arbitration will try to undo a disappointing result by finding an alternative path to reinstate what the arbitrator reversed. By no means is this to imply that a decision by a prosecutor that an officer will not be called testify that results in her dismissal cannot in the appropriate case meet the just cause standard. Rather, it means that an arbitrator's non-delegable responsibility to determine whether just cause does or does not exist requires that he bring informed judgment to the case with the recognition that deference to the judgments of public officials cannot be blindly and uncritically ratified.</p>
<p>To avoid any inference from being drawn that is not intended, I want to say as emphatically as I am able that there has been no collusion or underhandedness by Chief Cobb or the City. I found Chief Cobb's testimony entirely credible in every aspect. He answered questions directly and did not attempt to deflect the question asked to a question more to his liking. He did not avoid giving frank answers even when the answer was not particularly helpful to the City's position. The opposite was the case. As one example, counsel for the City asked him whether the Grievant activated the in-car video equipment during the transport of &ldquo;<fill character="space" width="5"/>.&rdquo; He answered &ldquo;no&rdquo; but &ldquo;in fairness&rdquo; added that he acted consistently with then-existing policy. His candor was also demonstrated by not withholding the information that he had sent a &ldquo;Brady&rdquo; letter to the State's Attorney's Office concerning another officer. Moreover, the record makes it clear that he has treated this officer fairly throughout his career. The suspensions imposed were consistent with principles of progressive discipline and likely less severe than sanctions that would survive arbitral scrutiny if grieved. When reinstated by Arbitrator Dichter<ftnote num="67"><para>When asked about Arbitrator Dichter's decision Chief Cobb insightfully put his finger on an important nuance. He explained that the arbitrator agreed that the City's interpretation of the video was <quote>correct</quote> (i.e., <quote>truthful</quote>), but that, in the arbitrator's view, the Grievant's <quote>inaccurate</quote> description of what occurred was from his perspective a <quote>truthful</quote> (i.e., honest) accounting. &lsqb;TR. pp. 228-229&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> he gave the Grievant a fresh start with a clean slate, arranged for increased supervisory monitoring, and afforded him opportunities to attend training.<ftnote num="68"><para>This included a <quote>Verbal Judo</quote> class for law enforcement officers. &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 229&rsqb;. This training teaches officers to use one's choice of words, tone of voice, and body language to deflect invective and hostile threats and to deescalate situations without resorting to the use of force.</para></ftnote> Chief Cobb unhesitatingly confirmed that after being reinstated in April 2015 the Grievant had no citizen complaints, no disciplinary infractions, no out-of-policy uses of force, was moving forward in a positive manner, handled his calls as the department expected, and did everything he was asked to do. I credit his testimony and make the factual finding that the police department had nothing to do with the State's Attorney's decision. As previously mentioned &ndash; but worth restating &ndash; he said that the Union is correct that except for the charge that was overturned by Arbitrator Dichter, the Grievant has not been accused of or disciplined for being untruthful.<ftnote num="69"><para>Q: (by Ms. Cummings) Right. So before that, was there ever a finding of a rule violation, the rule being untruth &ndash; lack of truthfulness. I don't see any.</para>
<para>A: I am not aware of an untruthfulness violation against Mr. Rush prior to the first termination. &lsqb;TR. p. 232&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> He acknowledged that he is &ldquo;certainly not here today to say that we need to fire Officer Rush for all these disciplinary issues that have already been addressed&rdquo; and confirmed that &ldquo;I am not asking &lsqb;the arbitrator&rsqb; to revisit those issues. We are here for the letter.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. pp. 217-218&rsqb;.<ftnote num="70"><para>Q: (by Ms. Cummings) Today, the issue we are here for today, we are here for one reason and one reason only &ndash;</para>
<para>A: Yes.</para>
<para>Q: &mdash; and that's because Julia Rietz has said she will not call him to testify, correct?</para>
<para>A; Yes, that is the reason why we are here. &lsqb;TR. p. 219&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> He summed up the situation facing the Champaign Police Department in two sentences: it was not his choice but a Chief of Police must deal with reality. The reality is that if the Grievant's work as a police officer cannot be produced in court an offender he apprehends cannot be prosecuted. &ldquo;That's a problem.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. pp. 224-225&rsqb;.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>1. Double Jeopardy</b></h4>
<p>As is unmistakably obvious, the City and the Union do not agree about much concerning each other's theory of the case. The City disputes that by using past discipline as the foundation for the State's Attorney's decision &mdash; which in turn precipitated its own decision to terminate his employment &mdash; it has acted inconsistently with the double jeopardy principle inherent in the just cause standard. The Union says that is precisely what the City is doing.</p>
<p>The constitutional commandment that no &ldquo;person shall be subject for the same offence to be twice put in jeopardy of life or limb&rdquo; has long been recognized not only to be &ldquo;deeply rooted in the American tradition of justice&rdquo; but also a fundamental requirement of just cause.<ftnote num="71"><para><italic>Durham Hoisery Mills</italic>, 24 LA 356, 358 (Livengood,1958).</para></ftnote> In industrial relations the significance of double jeopardy is &ldquo;that if an employee is punished for a specific act, he is entitled to regard such punishment as final for that particular misconduct.&rdquo;<ftnote num="72"><para><italic>City of Kenosha</italic>, 76 LA 758, 759 (McCrary, 1981).</para></ftnote> More recently, an arbitrator explained:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Any prudent employee, who has violated a rule, is charged with the violation, admitted to committing the misconduct, and serves a 5-day suspension: would reasonably assume that the issue is closed. They should have the full expectation that no further discipline is to be administered on that misconduct. This should be true if the discipline is called something else or it is rescinded&hellip;. When an employee violates a rule the agency is limited to one charge and discipline for that offense, they are not free to make any number of charges limited only by a thesaurus.<ftnote num="73"><para><italic>Department of Homeland Security</italic>, 132 LA 745 at p. 8 (Hoose, 2013). The second page reference is to the online version of the opinion that does not cross-reference the pagination in the bound volume of <small-cap>Labor Arbitration Reports</small-cap> (BNA).</para></ftnote></p></blockquote>
<p>I believe there is substantial merit in the Union's position. On the other hand, the City is correct that the State's Attorney is not bound by the department's disciplinary decisions. That being said I think the City has somewhat exaggerated the extent of his disciplinary history to justify its contention that his &ldquo;own disciplinary problems have created the situation he now finds himself in.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The City's reference to counseling as support for that conclusion is problematic. Article 32.1 excludes counseling from the definition of disciplinary actions and crediting this expansive definition of &ldquo;disciplinary problems&rdquo; would run afoul of the prohibition in Article 33.5 that I not amend or add to what the parties themselves have defined as discipline. That the Grievant once missed court or once was late for work several years ago is a historical fact that should have no bearing on whether his career is ended in 2016. Similarly, it is a stretch to bolster the reasonableness of the State's Attorney's decision by reference to four year old reprimands for having an avoidable accident and not activating lights and sirens. When counseling and reprimands are excluded the Grievant's 39 unpaid suspension days are based on 4 &ndash; not 11 &ndash; disciplinary actions.</p>
<p>I do not want to be misunderstood as minimizing the seriousness of this discipline or having overlooked Chief Cobb's testimony that some officers finish careers with a spotless disciplinary record. The best measure of the seriousness of misconduct is the penalty the employer adjudged to be merited. Suspensions of one, two, or three-days should be kept in perspective. Those three disciplinary actions are neither inconsequential nor of immense magnitude in a neutral assessment of an employee's overall disciplinary history. Article 32.1 requires discipline to be &ldquo;administered progressively and correctly based on the individual circumstances of each case&rdquo; and the purpose of progressive discipline is to correct unacceptable behavior by the imposition of penalties less than discharge to impress upon employees the seriousness of the misconduct and to afford an opportunity to improve.<ftnote num="74"><para><small-cap>Brand &amp; Biren, discipline &amp; Discharge in Arbitration</small-cap> (2d ed. 2008).</para></ftnote> That the Grievant was not disciplined again for those infractions suggest that the suspensions served that purpose. An arbitrator cannot be expected to measure the seriousness of past misconduct more severely than the employer did. Obviously the Grievant's termination, converted to a 30-day suspension, is by any measure a very serious disciplinary penalty and a heavy blot on his career.</p>
<p>Notwithstanding the cogency of the Union's double jeopardy argument, I cannot conclude that the requested remedy of reinstatement can rest on double jeopardy alone.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>2. <i>Persona non grata</i></b></h4>
<p>The City has not, wisely in my view, taken the position that its obligation not to discharge the Grievant, except for just cause, can be satisfied by embracing as its own position whatever the State's Attorney dictates, reasonable or otherwise. Instead, the City argues that the relief the Union seeks should be denied based on the well-established arbitral doctrine of <i>persona non grata</i>. The City's comprehensive brief makes the best possible case for using that doctrine to resolve this dispute. The Union's response is that the <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine is not applicable to the employment of public sector public safety employees. The parties have not pointed me to a public sector arbitration case that applies the doctrine and my own research (which I do not claim to be exhaustive) has not found any case. By no means does the absence of precedent establish that the Union is correct and the City is wrong but it does counsel caution.</p>
<p>There are readily apparent reasons to be skeptical that the private sector cases should be carried over to the public sector in general and to the employment of law enforcement officers in particular. The typical <i>persona non grata</i> case involves a dissatisfied customer who becomes displeased with the company's employee who performs all or part of his work on the customer's premises. First, it is a stretch to analogize the relationship that exists between a police employee and a public prosecutor to the relationship that exists between a private sector company and a third party customer. Second, a courtroom is clearly not the &ldquo;premises&rdquo; of the prosecutor. Third, unlike the situation where a business's economic viability can depend on not losing the customer's business, that does not describe the relationship between the Champaign County State's Attorney's Office and the Champaign Police Department. But these differences do not compel the conclusion that the City's <i>persona non grata</i> argument should be rejected.</p>
<p>A close reading of several arbitration cases involving the <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine discloses distinctions that are arguably important. In the cited arbitration cases (1) all of the conduct resulting in the <i>persona non grata</i> status occurred on the third party's premises and affected the third party's business interests; (2) in none of the cases did the third party justify the <i>persona non grata</i> status on past conduct; and (3) in none of the cases was the conduct on which the third party justified the <i>persona non grata</i> status based on acts for which the employee had been previously disciplined.<ftnote num="75"><para><italic>See, e.g., American Building Maintenance</italic>, 117 LA 17 (Herzog, 2002) (company employee used third party's copy machine without authorization); <italic>Burns International Security Services</italic>, 98 LA 226 (Cox, 1991) (security guard sleeping at nuclear plant); <italic>Corley Distributing Co</italic>., 68 LA 513 (Ipavec, 1977) (verbal altercation with third party's employees on its premises); <italic>First Student, Inc</italic>., 121 LA 575 (McCurdy, 2005) (involvement in <quote>unavoidable</quote> accident in third party's school bus); <italic>Harris Trucking Co</italic>., 80 LA 496 (Gentile, 1983) (threat to complain to Labor Board if third party did not accede to demand for more desirable route); <italic>Granny Goose Foods</italic>, 42 LA 497 (Koven, 1964) (shortchanging third party grocery store on delivery of merchandise); <italic>Rebar Engineering, Inc</italic>., 105 LA 662 (Riker, 1995) (saying <quote>I'm going to kick your fucking ass</quote> to an employee of third party); <italic>Wackenhut Corporation</italic>, 122 LA 1623 (Landau, 2006) (viewing pornography on duty at federal office building).</para></ftnote> In contrast, the State's Attorney's <i>persona non grata</i> designation involved conduct unrelated to the State's Attorney's Office that in some instances occurred several years earlier for which discipline had already been issued and finalized. Furthermore, a good case can be made that the dismissal of a janitor, security guard, school bus driver, truck driver, salesman, or ironworker does not impose comparable lifelong consequences as it does for a fired police officer.<ftnote num="76"><para><italic>See Bishop v. Wood</italic>, 426 U.S. 341, 350 (1976) (Brennan, J., dissenting) (<quote>Petitioner was discharged as a policeman on the grounds of insubordination, &lsquo;causing low morale,&rsquo; and &lsquo;conduct unsuited to an officer. It is difficult to imagine a greater &lsquo;badge of infamy&rsquo; that could be imposed on one following petitioner's calling; in a profession in which prospective employees are invariably investigated, petitioner's job prospects will be severely constricted by the governmental action in this case.</quote>).</para></ftnote></p>
<p>These distinctions notwithstanding, the City's brief makes a compelling case that a police officer is in a different category than other employees. Because they are entrusted with the authority to make arrests and use force, as well as their duty to ensure the safety of the community, law enforcement officers are not ordinary employees who are held to a lesser standard of accountability. Consequently, I agree with the City that there can be circumstances when the <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine &ndash; scrupulously applied &ndash; is appropriately considered in the police employment context. The question is whether the City's asserted justification &ndash; in the words of Article 32.1 &ndash; has been &ldquo;correctly applied based on the individual circumstances in &lsqb;this&rsqb; case.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The City suggests that the seven <i>Harris Trucking</i> factors can be distilled to three questions. The second of the City's proposed questions (did the State's Attorney reach her decision independently without any influence from the City) has already been discussed. The answer is &ldquo;yes.&rdquo; The answer to the City's third question (did the Grievant's inability to testify in Court render him unfit for duty) depends on the resolution of the City's second question (did the State's Attorney make a good faith determination that her office could not use the Grievant as a witness).</p>
<p>Arbitrator Gentile did not define the term &ldquo;good faith&rdquo; in the <i>Harris Trucking</i> decision. One definition is the opposite of &ldquo;bad faith,&rdquo; a term that connotes &ldquo;actual or constructive fraud&rdquo; or the &ldquo;conscious doing of a wrong because of a dishonest purpose.&rdquo;<ftnote num="77"><para><small-cap>Black's Law Dictionary</small-cap> 139 (6<superscript>th</superscript> Ed. 1991).</para></ftnote> The term &ldquo;good faith&rdquo; describes an individual's <i>subjective</i> belief: &ldquo;an honest belief; a concept of an individual's of his own mind; the absence of a design to defraud.&rdquo;<ftnote num="78"><para><italic>Id</italic>. at 693.</para></ftnote> There is no doubt that Arbitrator Gentile was not using the term &ldquo;good faith&rdquo; as an entirely subjective criterion because a patently spurious, irrational, or even delusional belief can be honestly (even if foolishly) held. The <i>Harris Trucking</i> standard is more than that: it is a subjective good faith belief that is objectively reasonable.<ftnote num="79"><para><italic>See United States v. Leon</italic>, 468 U.S. 897, 920 n. 20 (1984) (describing the <quote>Good Faith Exception</quote> to the exclusionary rule as an objective standard of reasonableness that does not turn on the subjective good faith of individual officers.).</para></ftnote> In explaining why the third party customer in that case met the &ldquo;good faith&rdquo; criteria he said, &ldquo;from their perspective&rdquo; it barred the Grievant from its premises based on a decision that had a &ldquo;rational and reasonable foundation.&rdquo; Arbitrator Gentile approvingly cited <i>Granny Goose Foods</i> in which Arbitrator Koven articulated an <i>objectively</i> grounded definition of good faith.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">But the doctrine of <i>persona non grata</i> as a basis for discharge obviously must have some limits. In the Arbitrator's opinion, those limits depend on a showing that the customer's assertion that the employee is unacceptable to it must be made in good faith. <i>Not only must there be good faith but there must be the strongest showing of good faith</i>. Otherwise the situation could well lend itself to a dubious understanding between the Company and the customer where the Company improperly wishes to rid itself of one of its employees.<ftnote num="80"><para><italic>Granny Goose Foods</italic>, 42 LA 497, 502 (Koven, 1964) (emphasis added). Arbitrator Yancy evaluated the fourth <italic>Harris Trucking</italic> <quote>good faith</quote> question to be whether <quote>the third party's action was rational.</quote> <italic>UGL UNICCO</italic>, 126 LA 474, at page 8 (Yancy, 2008).</para></ftnote></p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">It is with this understanding of the term &ldquo;good faith&rdquo; that the City's <i>persona non grata</i> argument must be evaluated.<ftnote num="81"><para>The collective bargaining agreement includes, in my experience, a somewhat uncommon provision. <quote>The Board of Fire and Police Commissioners or arbitrator shall be without authority to make a decision which is contrary to or inconsistent with law or rules and regulations having the force of law.</quote> Article 33.5. The parties have directed that I am not to <quote>ignore</quote> that instruction. <italic>Id</italic>.</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>JUSTIFICATIONS NOT BASED ON BRADY v. MARYLAND</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. To the extent that the State's Attorney's decision to bar the Grievant from testifying is based on her stated concerns &ldquo;about his judgment and decision-making with regards to his approach and contact with citizens in crisis, particularly those with mental health concerns,&rdquo; the City's reliance on that decision as a ground for terminating the Grievant's employment violated the just cause requirement in Article 32.1.</b></h4>
<p>In the American system of justice a prosecutor yields enormous power: the authority to determine who is and is not prosecuted with the potential consequence of losing one's freedom. While the law invests prosecutors with enormous powers, it does not license prosecutors to usurp the authority and prerogatives of other government officials. The State's Attorney's letter to Chief Cobb, her press release, and her testimony substantiate that one of the reasons the Grievant ended up being fired by the City of Champaign is that on one occasion he &ldquo;instructed&rdquo; a woman with a history of mental health issues, in a purportedly unnecessarily &ldquo;loud&rdquo; or &ldquo;screaming&rdquo; voice, to &ldquo;stop&rdquo; and &ldquo;come to me&rdquo; and &ldquo;come here, come here&rdquo; which, in the State's Attorney's opinion, was &ldquo;very unnecessary.&rdquo; &lsqb;TR. p. 74&rsqb;. And on another occasion he told a &ldquo;developmentally slow&rdquo; 17-year-old that &ldquo;it will be your ass&rdquo; if he did not stop &ldquo;tearing up&rdquo; his mother's house.<ftnote num="82"><para>The State's Attorney testified: <quote>This complaint was not sustained; however, I think the issues in that caused me concern as I later reviewed the Precious Jackson situation.</quote> &lsqb;TR. p. 66&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> I feel confident that no one having familiarity with police labor relations &ndash; and totally confident that no American labor arbitrator &ndash; would consider these incidents (undoubtedly a minuscule percentage of the police matters handled annually by a Champaign police officer) adequate grounds to end an officer's career. To be clear my finding that Article 32.1 has been violated is not based on the State's Attorney's decision to bar the Grievant's access to the witness stand in criminal cases because of perceived poor decision-making skills. She is not a party to the contract and is free to think what she thinks.<ftnote num="83"><para>The press release stated:</para>
<block-quote>
<para>Moreover, our concerns about his judgement and decision-making with regards to his approach and contact with citizens in crisis, particularly those with mental health issues, <italic>makes us unable to vouch for his <underline>credibility</underline> and <underline>reliability</underline> as a witness</italic>, regardless of role. &lsqb;JOINT EXH. 2, p. 2&rsqb; (emphasis added).</para>
</block-quote>
<para>I concede difficulty in understanding the logic behind the idea that having poor judgment or decision-making skills rationally supports an insinuation that &mdash; for those reasons &ndash; a witness's courtroom testimony is either fabricated or unreliable.</para></ftnote> The problem is the City's adoption of an <i>ultra vires</i> assessment as its own justification for meeting the requirements of the <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine. I do not in any way minimize the importance of interacting with all citizens in a professional manner. However, giving that laudatory concern full weight, neither Chief Cobb, nor the Mayor of Champaign, nor the Governor of Illinois, nor the President of the United States could provide the City a sustainable basis to justify the Grievant's termination because of his interaction with these two individuals. Acceptance of the City's theory that the analysis is different when the opinion comes from the State's Attorney is not supportable.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. To the extent that the State's Attorney's decision to bar the Grievant from testifying is based on the opinion that not being a good witness for himself would hurt his credibility with juries, the City's reliance on that decision as a ground for terminating the Grievant's employment violated the just cause requirement in Article 32.1.</b></h4>
<p>Not any reason at all will suffice to fulfill the objectively reasonable/good faith <i>persona non grata</i> standard. State's Attorney Rietz testified that a city attorney told her about his assessment that the Grievant &ldquo;was not a great witness for himself&rdquo; and that concerned her because &ldquo;obviously how an officer testifies is significant to his credibility in front of a jury.&rdquo; It is undoubtedly true that among the estimated 900,000 sworn law enforcement officers in the United States there are many who fall short of being &ldquo;great&rdquo; witnesses. But to ask the question whether for that reason a tenured police officer protected by a just cause provision can be terminated is to answer it.<ftnote num="84"><para>The conclusion that one attorney's opinion is not enough would seem particularly apt when the decision is made without consulting attorneys in her office who had used the Grievant as a witness to ascertain if they shared that negative assessment.</para></ftnote> For the reasons stated in the preceding paragraph the City's contention that it reasonably relied on this aspect of the State's Attorney's decision to disqualify the Grievant from being called as a witness is not well-founded.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i>JUSTIFICATIONS BASED ON BRADY v. MARYLAND</i></b></h4>
<p>In <i>City of Hutchinson</i><ftnote num="85"><para><italic>City of Hutchinson</italic>, 134 LA 1683, at p. 14 (Kossoff, 2014). Arbitrator Kossoff concluded that the District Attorney's letter did not give the police department just cause to terminate the Grievant's employment because under Kansas's law the officer's conduct would be inadmissible to impeach his credibility. He reinstated the employee with back pay.</para></ftnote> Arbitrator Kossoff considered a District Attorney's letter that said he would not allow a police officer (who he concluded lacked credibility) to testify as a witness for the state in any criminal prosecution &ldquo;unless absolutely necessary to avoid a gross miscarriage of justice or to protect the community's safety from a real threat.&rdquo; He reasoned that in order to determine if the letter could provide just cause for the Grievant's dismissal it was necessary to scrutinize the District Attorney's understanding of the <i>Brady</i> and <i>Giglio</i> decisions and the Kansas Rules of Evidence concerning the admissibility of the circumstances for which he was disciplined if he testified at a criminal trial. For reasons urged by the Union, I agree that State's Attorney Rietz's reasoning can properly be scrutinized because the City's <i>persona non grata</i> doctrine requires that the third party's stated justifications be objectively reasonable. In doing so my view is that her judgment is entitled to appropriate deference.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>C. To the extent that the State's Attorney's decision to bar the Grievant from testifying is based on the legally erroneous opinion that she must personally &ldquo;vouch&rdquo; for any police officer the State's Attorney's Office puts on the witness stand, the City's reliance on that decision as a ground for terminating the Grievant's employment violated the just cause requirement in Article 32.1.</b></h4>
<p>As already noted State's Attorney Rietz repeatedly contended that she &ldquo;is the person&rdquo; who must &ldquo;vouch&rdquo; for the credibility of any police officer who the State's Attorney's Office puts on the witness stand. There is nothing in <i>Brady</i> or its progeny that even remotely supports that conclusion. The <i>Brady</i> obligation is a disclosure obligation. It is certainly true that a prosecutor (or for that matter any attorney) cannot knowingly offer perjured testimony &mdash; to borrow a phrase from Arbitrator Dichter &mdash; but it is a &ldquo;bridge too far&rdquo; to deduce that proscription entails vouching. Indeed, the law is exactly the opposite. As Illinois law (and the law in every other state) makes clear: &ldquo;It is prejudicial error for the prosecutor to express personal beliefs or opinions, <i>or invoke the integrity of the state's attorney's office, to vouch for the credibility of a prosecution witness.</i>&rdquo;<ftnote num="86"><para><italic>People v. Lee</italic>, 593 N.E.2d 800, 804 (Ill. App. 1992) (emphasis added).</para></ftnote> Clearly, &ldquo;it is the duty solely of the jury to determine the credibility of the witnesses; it is not the privilege of the prosecutor.&rdquo;<ftnote num="87"><para><italic>People v. Wilson</italic>, 557 N.E.2d 571, 573 (Ill. App. 1990).</para></ftnote> This expansive interpretation of a State's Attorney's power &ndash; if correct &ndash; would mean that by declining to vouch for an officer (and for that reason saying he cannot testify on behalf of the state) sets in motion the police department process that ends in the officer's termination.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>D. To the extent that the State's Attorney's decision to bar the Grievant from testifying is based on the conclusion that the Grievant's exoneration of the charge he had been untruthful is not relevant under Brady/Giglio, the City's reliance on that decision as a ground for terminating the Grievant's employment violated the just cause requirement in Article 32.1.</b></h4>
<p>Among other reasons, State's Attorney Rietz testified that Arbitrator Dichter's decision exonerating the Grievant on the charge of untruthfulness was in her estimation not relevant to <i>Brady/Giglio</i> and that she would never discredit the Chief of Police. If I correctly understand the point it is that being accused of misconduct by Chief Cobb conclusively establishes guilt. Besides being irreconcilable with elementary precepts of fairness and due process, the City's reliance on that interpretation is in my judgment unsupportable. It is true, as the City points out, that the State's Attorney is not bound by Arbitrator Dichter's decision. But I find unpersuasive the argument that the City is not obliged to abide by a decision that the collective bargaining agreement makes &ldquo;final and binding on all parties.&rdquo; I have been unable to find any arbitration decision or court case that supports the notion that &ldquo;exoneration&rdquo; on the untruthfulness charge is not fatal to the employer's reliance on <i>Brady/Giglio</i> as justification for upholding a discharge. Indeed, arbitral authority<ftnote num="88"><para><italic>See, e.g., City of Springboro</italic>, <xref pub="arb" root="cch-internal-ref" normval="04-1ARBP3809">04-1 ARB &para;3809</xref> (Richard, 2003) (<quote>There has been absolutely no showing of dishonesty on the part of the grievant in this matter. The employer's alleged concerns regarding grievant's credibility under <italic>Brady</italic> ignores one simple fact: no charge of dishonesty against the grievant has ever been sustained, and therefore no disclosure is required.</quote>) (<quote>Clearly, the perceived dishonesty and the accompanying <italic>Brady</italic> implications weighed heavily in the decision to terminate and, as already noted above, there is insufficient evidence to sustain any finding of dishonesty.</quote>). <italic>See also FOP Lodge</italic>, 2015 LA Supp. 199114 (Colflesh, Sept. 28, 2015) (<quote>He did not, therefore lie under oath, as the Borough contends. Therefore, he should not be the subject of any disclosures to defense counsel that he has previously perjured himself, and if returned to duty, he would not be a valueless member of the Borough's Police Department.</quote>).</para></ftnote> and judicial authority<ftnote num="89"><para><italic>See, e.g., Duchesne v. Hillsborough County District Attorney</italic>, 119 A.3d 188, 197-98 (N.H. 2015).</para>
<block-quote><para>&lsqb;A&rsqb;lthough petitioners were initially disciplined by the police chief for their alleged excessive use of force, the chief's decision was overturned by an arbitrator, a neutral fact finder, following a full hearing conducted pursuant to procedures agreed to in a CBA&hellip;. Given that the original allegation of excessive force has been determined to be unfounded, there is no sustained basis for the petitioners' placement on the <quote>Laurie list.</quote></para></block-quote>
<para><italic>See also, People v. Cacini</italic>, 45 N.E.3d 738, 757 (Ill. App. 2015) (holding that claims against officers that were unfounded or not sustained by sufficient evidence are not discoverable or admissible).</para></ftnote> is to the contrary.</p>
<p>Besides being at odds with arbitral and case law, State's Attorney Rietz's understanding of the effect of an employee's exoneration on <i>Brady/Giglio</i> disclosure obligations is at odds with the understanding of other prosecutorial officials. The United States Department of Justice &ldquo;<i>Giglio</i>&rdquo; policy is contained in Section 9-5.000 of the U.S. Attorney's Manual. With regard to law enforcement witnesses it states &ldquo;allegations that cannot be substantiated, are not credible, <i>or have resulted in the exoneration of an employee</i> generally are not considered to be potential impeachment information.&rdquo;<ftnote num="90"><para>The U.S. Attorney's Manual is available at the Department of Justice website.</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="left">E. To the extent that the State's Attorney's decision to bar the Grievant from testifying is based on unsupportable inferences of untruthfulness completely at odds with all record evidence, the City's reliance on that decision as a ground for terminating the Grievant's employment violated the just cause requirement in Article 32.1.</h4>
<p>I have already laid out the evidence and testimony in great detail about the accident report and I submit, respectfully, that the State's Attorney's supposition that the Grievant lied falls outside the parameters of reasoned analysis. Frankly, I am at a loss to explain how one could arrive at the conclusion that the Grievant came into the station on his day off to complete the report, told Lieutenant Meyers that he did it before leaving, and lie about it. I have quoted the Department's own investigation confirming that the reports of other officers were &ldquo;disappearing&rdquo; because of a software issue and operator error due to inadequate training on the new system. No one from the police department ever said he lied. Arbitrator Dichter clearly said the one-day suspension was because &ldquo;&lsqb;h&rsqb;e did forget to turn in the citation.&rdquo; &lsqb;CITY EXH. 3, p. 416&rsqb;. The statement on page 19 of the City's post-hearing brief that Arbitrator Dichter &ldquo;specifically identified &lsqb;as an act&rsqb; of misconduct &lsqb;that&rsqb; Grievant failed to turn in a traffic ticket <i>and failed to file a report</i>, justifying a one-day suspension&rdquo; is not supported by the record.</p>
<p>I believe three additional observations are in order.</p>
<p>First, I believe the City's contention that fulfillment of the obligations imposed by <i>Brady/Giglio</i> would automatically mean that if the Grievant were to testify every trial would entail a mini-trial within a trial overstates the situation. As the North Carolina Court of Appeals observed in <i>Wetherington</i>, that conclusion depends on several assumptions. Illinois case law does not necessarily support the State's Attorney's conclusion: it is a judge, not the defense attorney, who determines whether the jury will hear evidence about an officer's disciplinary record. For example, in <i>People v. Collins</i>,<ftnote num="91"><para><italic>People v. Collins</italic>, 985 N.E.2d 613 (Ill. App. 2013).</para></ftnote> the trial judge granted the prosecution's motion <i>in limine</i> to bar the impeachment of the arresting officer with information disclosed from his personnel file that included a one-day suspension for knowingly providing inaccurate information to a superior officer. Ruling that impeachment evidence cannot be remote or uncertain and must give rise to an inference that the witness has something to gain or lose by his testimony, the appellate court agreed with the trial court that the officer could not be impeached by his disciplinary history.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Here, the evidence contained in the personnel file indicated that Officer Tucker received a one-day suspension for knowingly providing inaccurate information to a deputy chief conducting an investigation in another department. The matter was not in any way related to Officer Tucker's ability to conduct undercover drug transactions and did not raise an inference that he had anything to gain or lose by his testimony in the present case. The defendant's argument that Officer Tucker would testify falsely to avoid any further discipline is unsupported speculation that is remote and uncertain.<ftnote num="92"><para><italic>Id</italic>. at 618. <italic>See also People v. Davis</italic>, 550 N.E.2d 677, 680 (1990) (affirming circuit court's refusal to allow defendant to question officer where police department had not suspended or reprimanded the officer regarding allegations of misconduct made in two civil suits).</para></ftnote></p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Indeed, as the Union has argued, when confidential files such as police personnel records are sought in discovery the proper procedure is for the trial court to review the records <i>in camera</i><ftnote num="93"><para><italic>See, e.g., People v. Jones</italic>, 2012 Ill. App. Unpub. LEXIS 1120 at p. 8 (Ill. App., May 14, 2012).</para>
<block-quote><para>Moreover, the very practice employed here &ndash; where the trial court reviews potentially sensitive material &lsqb;police personnel files&rsqb; <italic>in camera</italic> and, thereafter, allows discovery of only the relevant portion of that material is appropriate for addressing a situation where one party contends that the information is sensitive and not discoverable.</para></block-quote></ftnote> and use its discretion to disclose only material information.<ftnote num="94"><para><italic>People v. Cacini</italic>, 45 N.E.3d 738, 756 (Ill. App. 2015).</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Second, understanding that the police department had nothing to do with it, I am nevertheless concerned with the fairness of the procedures that ultimately culminated in the Grievant's dismissal. He had no input into the decision to settle the civil cases that led to the newspaper articles that led to citizens vociferously demanding<ftnote num="95"><para>The State's Attorney testified that people <quote>stormed the courthouse</quote> and said there were <quote>all kinds of protest.</quote> &lsqb;TR. p. 161&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> that the State's Attorney prosecute him. Lawsuits are settled for many reasons, including reasons that have nothing to do with whether an officer's actions were justified such as the cost of litigation and jury unpredictability. As described the inquiry was initiated to decide if criminal charges were warranted, the subpoena said it involved a &ldquo;criminal investigation being investigated by the Champaign County State's Attorney's Office&rdquo; yet it commanded the production of the entire personnel file.<ftnote num="96"><para>State's Attorney Rietz testified that in all her years working as an Assistant State's Attorney or State's Attorney she had never seen a personnel file <quote>of this volume.</quote> &lsqb;TR. p. 89&rsqb;. However, if I understood the testimony correctly, her office does not routinely obtain personnel files &lsqb;TR. p. 133&rsqb; and Chief Cobb refuses to release personnel files except under order of subpoena. &lsqb;TR. p. 204&rsqb;. I acknowledge that the record is unclear on this point because the question State's Attorney Rietz answered was, <quote>Have you ever &ndash; have you ever, based on a community request, subpoenaed an officer's entire personnel file before?</quote> &lsqb;TR. pp. 132-133&rsqb;.</para></ftnote> Although the apparently unprecedented scrutiny prompted by community demands revealed some problems (such as the Grievant improperly involving himself in matters involving acquaintances and neglecting to follow proper investigative protocols), the State's Attorney (nor I) have any idea how many other Champaign police officers have been disciplined or reprimanded for similar offenses. I have no idea how many use of force reports would reveal inconsistencies with the video recording if similarly studied. If critical newspaper articles had instead been about an officer with 15 or 25 years of service, could decades old misconduct drawing a minor suspension be resurrected to disqualify an officer from testifying? Although the Department afforded the Grievant ample opportunity to be heard after the State's Attorney made her decision, the fact that he had no opportunity to tell his side of the story (and apparently did not have his side contained in police reports even considered) is concerning. Finally, the <i>Brady</i> issue involving another officer who lied about responding to a dispatched police run but has not been disqualified from testifying raises the specter that the purported justification for dismissing this officer might not be the entire story.<ftnote num="97"><para>Regrettably State's Attorney Rietz had already been excused when this information was disclosed and did not have the opportunity to provide an explanation.</para></ftnote></p>
<p>Third, I recognize that reinstatement places the police department in an unenviable quandary. As the City's post-hearing brief noted concerning Officer Brown's situation, prosecutors sometimes do reconsider their decisions and allow an officer to testify. It may be the case that the State's Attorney anticipated that the Grievant's second dismissal would withstand arbitral scrutiny and rethink her position. It could be that upon reflection the State's Attorney's Office will reconsider the legal soundness of the &ldquo;vouching&rdquo; theory. Perhaps that office will consider adopting the Department of Justice's <i>Giglio</i> policy that exempts from disclosure exonerated disciplinary matters. Conceivably the State's Attorney's Office will revisit the practice not to use the <i>in camera</i> inspection procedure approved by Illinois appellate courts. Although the State's Attorney made clear that she would not allow the Grievant to testify, she was not asked (and perhaps has not fully considered) if she would move away from that position if the consequence is turning loose a criminal who poses a threat to the safety of the citizens of Champaign County. I do not know the answers to any of those questions, but the answer to whether the Grievant's discipline was administered correctly based on the individual circumstances of this case is &ldquo;no.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Based upon the entire record I find that that the Grievant's dismissal was without just cause.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b><i><small-cap>Award</small-cap></i></b></h4>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>The grievance is granted.</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant's discharge was not for just cause as required by Article 32.1 of the Collective Bargaining Agreement.</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant shall be offered reinstatement to his former position without the loss of seniority.</p></li>
<li><p>Upon request by the Grievant, the date of reinstatement may be deferred for not more than 21 days from the date of this Award for the purpose of providing appropriate notice to his current employer (if any).</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant shall be made whole for the loss of wages and benefits. Back pay shall be calculated in accordance with Article 33.5 of the Collective Bargaining Agreement.</p></li>
<li><p>The Grievant's personnel records shall be expunged of all references to this disciplinary action.</p></li>
<li><p>The arbitrator shall retain jurisdiction for the sole purpose of resolving issues that may arise concerning the implementation of this Award for a period of 90 days.</p></li></ol>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>