<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<h4 align="center"><b>FEDERAL MEDIATION AND CONCILIATION SERVICE ARBITRATION DECISION AND AWARD</b></h4>
<p class="continued"><b>IN THE MATTER BETWEEN</b>: Dart Container Corporation, Solo Cup Operating Facility, Augusta, Georgia &ldquo;Company/Employer&rdquo; <b>AND</b> The International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT), Local 528 and Ms. Tamela Welts &ldquo;Grievants&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>FMCS Case Number 15-51124-3</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Issue</b>: Did the Company violate provisions of the parties' collective bargaining agreement and/or any provisions of Federal law when it separated the Grievant from employment If so, what is the remedy?</p>
<p class="continued">Date Decision issued: August 24,2015</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>APPEARANCES:</b></h4>
<p class="continued"><i>For the Company/Employer</i></p>
<p class="continued">Mr. Edward J. Starmer</p>
<p class="continued">Assistant General Counsel</p>
<p class="continued">Dart Container Corporation</p>
<p class="continued">500 Hogsback Road</p>
<p class="continued">Mason, Michigan 48854</p>
<p class="continued">Technical Representative: Ms. Maribeth McCue</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i>For the Union/Grievant</i></p>
<p class="continued">Mr. James D. Fagan, Jr.</p>
<p class="continued">Stanford Fagan, LLC</p>
<p class="continued">191 Peachtree Street, NE</p>
<p class="continued">Suite 4200</p>
<p class="continued">Atlanta, Georgia 30303</p>
<p class="continued">Technical Representative: Mr. Johnny Gabriel</p>
</blockquote>
<p><b>BEFORE: William A. Dealy, Jr., Arbitrator</b></p>
<h4 align="left"><b>WITNESSES TESTIFYING:</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><i>Called by the Company/Employer</i></h4>
<p class="continued">Mr. Benjamin Benedict<ftnote num="1"><para>Plant Manager, Dart Container Corporation, Solo Cup Operating Facility, Augusta, Georgia.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">Ms. Jennifer Davis<ftnote num="2"><para>Human Resources Manager, Dart Container Corporation, Solo Cup Operating Facility, Augusta, Georgia.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">Ms. Shah Sweeney<ftnote num="3"><para>Leave of Absence and Disability Management Program Manager, Dart Container Corporation.</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Called by the Union/Grievant</i></h4>
<p class="continued">Mr. Johnny Gabriel<ftnote num="4"><para>Assistant Business Agent, IBT, Local 528.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">Ms. Cherrylle Williams<ftnote num="5"><para>Forklift Operator, Dart Container Corporation, Solo Cup Operating Facility, Augusta, Georgia.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">Ms. Tamela Wells<ftnote num="6"><para>Forklift Operator and Grievant, Dart Container Corporation, Solo Cup Operating Facility, Augusta, Georgia.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">Mr. John Cross<ftnote num="7"><para>Instructor, Southern Crescent Technical College, Griffin, Georgia.</para></ftnote></p>
<table width="585" columns="1">
<tr>
<td width="8%"><p></p></td>
<td width="76%"><p></p></td>
<td width="16%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" valign="top"><p></p></th>
<th align="center" valign="top"><p><b>Arbitration Decision and Award Sections</b></p></th>
<th align="left" valign="top"><p><b>Page:</b></p></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>1.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Procedural Matters</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>2</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>II.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Background</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>III.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Positions of the Parties<br/>&emsp;The Company/Employer<br/>&emsp;The Union/Grievant</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>6<br/>13</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>IV.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Statement of the issue(s)</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>22</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>V.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Summary of the Evidence, Discussion, Analysis, and Findings</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>23</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>VI.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Decision and Award</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>31</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>VII.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>End Notes</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>33</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
<h4 align="left"><b>I. PROCEDURAL MATTERS</b></h4>
<p class="continued">By letter dated October 10, 2014, Ms. Tamela Wells, the Grievant was notified that she was being terminated from her employment with Dart Container Corporation's Solo Cup Operating Facility in Augusta, Georgia.<ftnote num="8"><para>According to the record, on October 10, 2014, the Grievant, Ms. Wells was called by Ms. Jennifer Davis, Human Resources Manager, Dart Container Corporation, Solo Cup Operation Facility, and participated in a three-way conversation with Ms. Davis and her Regional Business Manager, Mr. Howard Quales, during which Ms. Davis and Ms. Quales informed Ms. Wells that she was being terminated. The letter dated October 10, 2014, was actually received by the Grievant on or about October 15, 2014, and simply transmitted a completed/signed/dated <quote>State of Georgia Department of Labor Separation Notice,</quote> providing that the reason for separation was &ldquo;unable to return from leave. Under Georgia's Employment Security Law, OCGA &sect;34-8-199 and rules pursuant thereto, a Separation Notice, form DOL-800, must be completed for each worker who leaves a company's/firm's employment, regardless of the reason for the separation.</para></ftnote> In accordance with the provisions of Article 10 of the parties' CBA, on October 16, 2014, Ms. Wells filed a formal grievance contending that the separation was improper, unfair, unjust; and the Company did not have just cause to terminate her under the CBA With the grievance unresolved, in accordance with the provision of Article 11 of the CBA, the Union appealed the action to arbitration.</p>
<p class="continued">By letter dated January 27, 2015, the U. S. Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service (FMCS) informed the undersigned Arbitrator that the parties had jointly selected him and FMCS was appointing him to hear and decide the above cited matter. Following telephonic and email communications with the parties, by letter dated February 5, 2015, the Arbitrator informed the parties that he accepted their appointment, outlined the basic procedures to be followed, confirmed and explained his per diem rates and charge policies, and offered three periods of time that he was available to hear the matter - April 22-23, June 2-3, and June 9-10,2015.</p>
<p class="continued">Following additional communications with the parties, by letter dated February 18, 2015, the Arbitrator scheduled a hearing in the above cited matter to be held Wednesday and Thursday, April 22 and 23,2015, in a conference room of the Hilton Garden Inn, 1085 Stevens Creek Road Augusta, Georgia, 30907; with an administrative conference with the parties to convene at 8:30AM, April 22<sup>nd</sup> and the hearing to commence immediately at the conclusion of the administrative conference. The hearing scheduling letter also requested that the parties provide the Arbitrator with a copy of the parties' collective bargaining agreement together with any amendments and/or memorandums of understanding, as well as, the grievance file. The parties were also provided an opportunity to file pre-hearing briefs, and informed when they should exchange witness lists.<ftnote num="9"><para>The hearing scheduling letter was amended by letter dated March 13, 2015, providing the address were the hearing was to be held.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">At 8:30AM, Wednesday, April 22, 2015, the Arbitrator held an administrative conference with the parties to discuss, among other things, the purpose of the hearing; hearing procedures, including attendance and the handling of witnesses; the recording of the hearing<ftnote num="10"><para>While Article 11, Section 2 of the parties' CBA provides how costs associated with recorders/transcription services will be handled, neither of the parties requested and/or provided for official recording/transcription services. As explained and discussed during the administrative conference, the Arbitrator recorded the hearing; and, per the discussion and parties' request provided the parties' a copy of his audio files. Per Arbitrator notes and audio file:</para>
<para>Per Arbitrator notes and audio file:</para>
<table-group columns="1" content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title/></head>
<body>
<table width="585">
<tr>
<td width="30%"><p></p></td>
<td width="70%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>As I previously mentioned, I will be recording the hearing for my own use&hellip;Would the parties like me to provide them a copy of the audio files?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Yes.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Yes.</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</html>
</table-group></ftnote>; and any stipulations reached. As to the parties' CBA, at the beginning of the administrative conference the Arbitrator noted that the copy of the CBA provided in pre-hearing submissions is between the Solo Cup Operating Corporation, Augusta, Georgia and the International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT), Local 528 which became effective April 1,2012, did not identify Dart Container Corporation which obtained Solo Cup Company, including the Augusta facility a month later, on May 4,2012. On this point the parties stipulated that the CBA provided is the current and applicable CBA and that the CBA presented was properly extended and continues in effect Accordingly, the parties further stipulated that there were no arbitrability issues or questions that needed to be addressed.<ftnote num="11"><para>Article 10 &mdash; Complaints, provides as follows:</para>
<block-quote>
<para>Section 1 - Both parties to this agreement shall have the right to present grievances as provided In this Article. It is mutually agreed that all grievances, defined as a dispute or complaint arising during the term of this Agreement over the interpretation or application of its contents, shall be settled in accordance with the provisions herein provided.</para>
<para>Every effort shall be made to adjust grievances in an amicable manner between the Company and the Union. In the event that any grievance cannot be settled in this manner, the question may be submitted by either for arbitration as provided in Article 11.</para>
<para>Section 2 - Should any grievance arise over the interpretation or application of the contents of this Agreement there shall be an earnest effort on the part of the parties to settle such promptly and no grievance will be considered or discussed which is presented later than five (5) working days after the occurrrence.</para>
<para>Step 1. If an employee has a grievance, he or his steward will reduce the grievance to writting and present it to the aggrieved employee's immediate supervisor within five (5) working days after the occurrence. The supervisor will give his answer within four working days after receiving the written grievance.</para>
<para>Step 2. If no settlement is reached at Step 1, the matter may be referred to the chief steward and presented to the department manager within five (5) days from the Step 1 answer. The department manager will give an answer within five (5) days.</para>
<para>Step 3. If no settlement is reached at Step 2, the matter may be referred to the representative of the union, the Human Resources Manager or the Plant Manager within fourteen (14) days from the Step 2 answer. The Human Resources Manager will provide the Company's answer within seven (7) days.</para>
<para>Section 3 - Grievances involving discharges, if not settled within five (5) days, shall at the request of either party be referred directly to Step 3 of the grievance procedure.</para>
<para>Section 4 - If a party fails to abide by the above time limits, the matter will be settled in favor of the other party. Grievances being settled by monetary adjustments shall be settled within ten (10) working days and shall be paid within 21 calendar days of the settlement. Time limits may be extended by mutual agreement in writing and the Union will not unreasonably withhold agreement. The grievant may be present at each step of the grievance procedure.</para>
</block-quote>
<para>Article 11 &mdash; Arbitration, provides as follows:</para>
<block-quote>
<para>Section 1 - If a grievance is not settled pursuant to the procedure set forth in Article 10, it will be at the request of either the Union or the Company submitted to arbitration and the decision of the arbitrator shall be final and binding on both parties. In such event, the party desiring arbitration shall notify the other party in writing within ten (10) days after the termination of the proceedings set forth in Article 10, which writing shall set forth the matter to be arbitrated. The parties may mutually agree upon an arbitrator, but if they are unable to do so within five (5) days, either party shall request the Federal Mediation and Concidiation Service to provide a panel of arbitrators, all of whom shall be members of the National Academy of Arbitrators, and invoke its procedure for the selection of an arbitrator to conduct the arbitration in accordance With its Rules on Voluntary Labor Arbitration.</para>
<para>The arbitrator shall have no power to add to, subtract from or modify the terms of this Agreement and premiums for jobs or to set or change standards of production.</para>
<para>Section 2 - Each party shall bear the costs of preparation, representation, witnesses, etc., for their respective case; however, all fees and expenses of the arbitrator will be borne by the loser of said arbitration. Charges for stenographer's fees and expenses shall be borne by the party ordering such services.</para>
</block-quote>
<para>Accordingly, at the administrative conference the Arbitrator noted that&hellip; Per the Arbitrator's notes and audio file:</para>
<table-group columns="1" content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title/></head>
<body>
<table width="585">
<tr>
<td width="30%"><p></p></td>
<td width="70%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Do the parties acknowledge that the copy of the CBA provided in pre-haring fillings by the Company is the applicable full and complete CBA; and, is it the parties' position that Dart Container Corporation is the successor of Solo Cup Operating Corporation, Augusta, GA.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Additionally, when asked to be provided a copy of the grievance file, the Union provided only a copy of a one-page document identified as the IBT, Local 528 Grievance Report Form, which was apparently completed by or for Ms. Tamela Wells and submitted to and received by management on October 16, 2014.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>However, Article 10 of the parties' CBA provides a three-step grievance process which may be shortened if Involving a discharge. Accordingly, are there any arbitrability issues or questions that need to be addressed?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>I don't know of any&hellip;</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>No sir.</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</html>
</table-group></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">With regard to the Arbitrator's powers, it was noted that, with the exception of provisions relating to notification, selection of an Arbitrator, payment of costs/fees/stenography services; and the standard phrase &ldquo;The arbitrator shall have no power to add to, subtract from or modify the terms of this Agreement.;&rdquo; Article 11 of the parties' agreement is silent regarding hearing procedures and the Arbitrator's powers. Accordingly, when asked if the parties were, in any way, restricting the Arbitrator's powers to determine and define the issue or issues presented in the hearing and through the evidence presented at hearing, to decide the matter, the Counsels for both parties said they were not restricting the Arbitrator in any way.<ftnote num="12"><para>Per Arbitrator notes and audio file:</para><table-group columns="1" content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title/></head>
<body>
<table width="585">
<tr>
<td width="30%"><p></p></td>
<td width="70%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Other than the provisions of Article 11 of the CBA. are the parties placing any specific restrictions on my powers to hear and decide the subject case?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>No.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>No.</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</html>
</table-group></ftnote> With regard to attendance at the hearing, the parties agreed that witnesses would not be allowed to be in the hearing, except when testifying; and, that each side would be permitted to have one technical assistant attend the hearing.<ftnote num="13"><para>Per Arbitrator notes and audio file:</para>
<table-group columns="1" content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title/></head>
<body>
<table width="585">
<tr>
<td width="30%"><p></p></td>
<td width="70%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>With regard to attendance at the hearing&hellip; Having read the parties' CBA, it is my understanding that Article 11&hellip;makes no mention of the parties entitled to attend the hearing&hellip;Normally, only the parties and their representatives are entitled to attend the hearing without Arbitrator approval&hellip; Is this the understanding of the parties?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Yes.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Yes.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Accordingly, besides Counsels, who will be attending the hearing?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Mr. Johnny Gabriel, for the Union and as technical representative.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Ms. Maribeth McCue, for the Company and as technical representative/co-counsel.</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</html>
</table-group></ftnote> After discussing streamlining measures, rules of evidence, post-hearing briefs, and when the parties could expect the written decision and award; and determining that no other matters needed to be covered, the administrative conference was adjourned at 8:50AM, and the hearing on the matter convened at 9:10AM, Wednesday, April 22,2015.</p>
<p class="continued">At the beginning of the hearing, the Arbitrator asked both parties to introduce themselves and their technical representatives; explained the various exhibit lists being maintained<ftnote num="14"><para>As explained at the administrative conference, three exhibit lists were being maintained - (1) the Arbitrator/Joint Exhibit list which would record all documentary evidence Identified as joint exhibits and all documentary evidence requested by the Arbitrator; (2) the Company/Employer List recording all documentary evidence offered by and accepted from the Company; and (3) the Union/Grievant List recording all documentary evidence offered by and accepted from the Grievant.</para></ftnote>, and entered into the record the initial three (3) exhibits identified as Arbitrator/Joint exhibits; explained ail previous communications with the parties, including any dealings with the parties during his thirty-plus years Federal service; and, asked the parties if they had any concerns or issues regarding his ability to conduct a fair and impartial hearing on the matter before him - To which both parties answered they had no objection.<ftnote num="15"><para>Per Arbitrator notes and audio file:</para><table-group columns="1" content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title/></head>
<body>
<table width="585">
<tr>
<td width="30%"><p></p></td>
<td width="70%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>With the exception of the contacts and correspondence just identified&hellip; 1 have had no previous contacts or relationships with any of the specific parties in this proceeding&hellip;Accordingly, do the parties have any concerns or issues regarding my ability to conduct a fair and impartial hearing in the matter before us?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>No.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>No.</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</html>
</table-group></ftnote> Following opening statements the hearing then proceeded in an orderly manner. All witnesses testified under oath as administered by the Arbitrator.</p>
<p class="continued">The Company's advocate and Counsel, as well as, the Grievant's advocate and Counsel, fully and fairly represented their respective party. While the hearing record was open, and/or subsequently as requested by the Arbitrator, a total of twelve (12) Arbitrator/Joint exhibits were offered and accepted into the record; eight (8) Company/Employer exhibits offered and accepted; and eighteen (18) Union/Grievant exhibits offered and accepted. As discussed during the administrative conference, at the close of testimony the Arbitrator requested post-hearing briefs from both sides. Following receipt of the post-hearing briefs and rebuttal briefs, the hearing record was closed at 8:00AM EDT, Tuesday, July 7,2015.<ftnote num="16"><para>As discussed at the administrative conference and confirmed at the close of the hearing, Article 11, of the parties' CBA provides no guidance as to when the parties should expect the Arbitrator to render his decision/award. On this point, both parties agreed to allow the Arbitrator to render his decision within sixty (60) calendar-days from the close of the hearing as allowed by FMCS regulations.</para>
<para>Per Arbitrator notes and audio file:</para>
<table-group columns="1" content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title/></head>
<body>
<table width="585">
<tr>
<td width="30%"><p></p></td>
<td width="70%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>With regard to the Issuance on my decision/award, again I note that the parties' CBA is silent on this matter - In such cases I normally ask the parties if they would agree to allow me to have my decision/award to them within the 60-day limit provided by FMCS rules/regulations. Is this agreeable to the parties?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Yes.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Yes.</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</html>
</table-group></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">Accordingly, the undersigned Arbitrator acknowledges the position of the parties; that the matter is properly before him in accordance with the appropriate provisions of law, regulations, and the parties CBA<ftnote num="17"><para>While the parties' collective bargaining agreement has been noted and several provisions already cited, the Arbitrator further notes that while all provisions of the parties' agreement may be considered for applicability to. and guidance on, the current matter, the following specific provisions are deemed paramount &mdash; Article 2-Recognition; Article 5-Management Rights; Article 8-Seniority; Article 9-Job Posting; Article 10-Complaints; Article 11-Arbitration; Article 12-Hours of Work; Article 21-Family and Medical Leave; Article 27-Fair Employment Practices and Equal Opportunities; Article 36-Duration of Agreement; and Appendix showing Job classifications by department/operation.</para></ftnote>; that he is solely responsible to hear and determine the issues; and to render a written decision and award, in accordance with FMCS policies, and State and Federal law.</p>
<p class="continued">To this end, the undersigned has thoroughly reviewed the evidence presented in pre-hearing submissions, through testimony<ftnote num="18"><para>With regard to the documentary evidence presented, and particularly the witness testimony presented at hearing, the Arbitrator has sought to impress upon the parties that a primary goal of his management of the hearing is to provide the parties the maximum opportunity to provide the evidence it feels necessary to adequately present its case. As to witnesses the Arbitrator is particularly cognizant of the need to assess the veracity of witnesses by paying particular attention to the demeanor of the witness, the character of the testimony, and any self-interest of the witness.</para></ftnote> and exhibits offered/accepted at hearing; and, through post-hearing briefs, rebuttals, and clarifying information submitted by the parties. The Arbitrator does not feel compelled to address all of the numerous arguments and issues raised by the advocates. However, please do not interpret this to mean that the Arbitrator has not read and reread the parties' briefs, rebuttals, citations includes in the some 1,158 pages of documents submitted as evidence; as well as, thoroughly listened/reviewed the several hours of audio files of the hearing; and carefully considered all arguments by the advocates. Rather, the Arbitrator elects to address only those elements that have a significant impact on his decision-making process. The Arbitrator, as a general rule, will not comment on matters that he believes are irrelevant superfluous, redundant, or rendered moot by his decision. The following decision and award will serve as the Arbitrator's final and binding decision regarding this matter.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>II. BACKGROUND</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The grievant, Ms. Tamela Wells, began her employment with the Solo Cup Company's<ftnote num="19"><para>According to information on the Dart Container Corporation's website, Solo Cup Company, which manufactures disposable consumer products including beverage cups, disposable plates and bowls, was founded in 1936, with headquarters in Lake Forest Illinois, and by 2011 was a &dollar;1.6 billion global company with facilities in Europe and the Americas. On May 4, 2012, Dart Container Corporation acquired Solo Cup Company, including its Augusta, Georgia facility, and now employees an estimated 15,000 employees with more than forty-five production, distribution center, and office locations in eight countries.</para></ftnote> Augusta, Georgia facility on March 29, 1982, as a packer, then worked as a machine operator and production worker before becoming a forklift operator in 1990.<ftnote num="20"><para>The parties' applicable/current CBA provides for and covers two groups of employees (Bargaining unit employees)&hellip;Group one includes the job classifications/categories sweeper-operator, utility, production worker, material handler and product handler working primarily in the Buildings and Grounds Department and General Production Department; Group two includes all other Job classifications/categories &lsqb;Machine operator I, II, III, and IV; Plate Maker; Bagger Technician; Electro-Mechanical Technician; Maintenance Mechanic; Electrician; Senior Spare-Parts Attendant; Senior QC Technician; QC Technician; and Forklift Operator&rsqb; working primarily in the Printing and Press, Foam Dinnerware, Trophy, Extrusion, Maintenance, Quality-Control, Warehouse and Material Handling Departments. Accordingly, the Grievant worked both group one and group two jobs. Her current position is a group two job.</para></ftnote> She remained in this job/classification until her separation on October 10, 2014. At the time of her separation, Ms. Wells had had approximately thirty-two years of service, had been a Union Steward for twenty-five years, and was one of the more senior employees.</p>
<p class="continued">After the acquisition of Solo Cup Company in May of 2012, by Dart Container Corporation, in 2013, management at the Augusta facility made the decision to transition from use of sit-down forklifts to stand-up forklifts. Management announced the transition to the Augusta workforce through a series of plant-wide meetings, and the new forklifts were delivered in February 2014. With the delivery of the new stand-up forklifts, the facility began a training and certification program<ftnote num="21"><para>The record indicates that the Augusta facility contracted with an outside provider to train and certify each employee identified as required by their Job functions to operate a forklift. The training consisted of classroom (addressing theory, understanding of the machines components, inspections, etc.) and operational training (actual skills assessment (driving, making turns, clearances, etc.). Each individual was required to pass a written test as well as a driving/operational test. The Grievant, Ms. Wells participated in the training, passing the written test and operational skills component for certification on March 5, 2014.</para></ftnote> for all operators, and beginning in April 2014, the sit-down lifts were phased out and operators began using the new stand-up lifts full time.</p>
<p class="continued">In mid-March 2014, after completion of the training/certification program, the Grievant, Ms. Wells, began driving the new stand-up lift on a regular full time basis. Almost immediately after beginning full time operation of the new stand-up forklift, the Grievant began having issues of swollen ankles, back strain, tingling and numb feet; sufficient enough to cause Ms. Wells to discuss her problems with Company officials<ftnote num="22"><para>The record is not clear as to whom in the Augusta facility the Grievant initially talked to regarding her medical problems. However, the evidence does show that Ms. Wells received a letter dated March 11, 2014 (Note: The copy of the correspondence offered/accepted by the Company as Employer exhibit E-5 was a single page letter dated/stamped mailed March 11, 2014, to Ms. Wells in response to her request for changes to her current position due to a medical condition. The letter noted that the request was accepted as a request for accommodation under the Americans with Disability Act; went on to explain what was needed to be covered and eligible for a reasonable accommodation under the Act; provided a <quote>Fact Sheet regarding the Disabitty Accommodation Process,</quote> as well as, a blank Request for Disability Accommodation (Dart form HR302a dated 6/13) which needed to be completed; requested the following documentation/information: (1) medical documentation of the impairment and how it affects a major life activity, (2) whether the condition is permanent or long term, and (3) which of the essential functions outlined in the attached job description are affected by the impairment, as well as any suggestions Ms. Well's health care provider may have for accommodations that would allow her to perform the essential duties; and informed her if she had any questions to contact the Human Resources Department. This communication presented as the initial official communication from the Company and reported as transmitting the identified documents to Ms. Wells, was unsigned. Nevertheless, Union exhibit U-10 (a copy of a letter from Dart LOA/ADA Specialist Michelle Jones to Ms. Wells dated April 30, 2014, (which was formally dated March 11.2014 but was corrected at hearing to have been produced/sent on/or about April 30, 2014) included a completed Request for Disability Accommodation (Dart HR302a) signed by Ms. Wells and dated March 21, 2014; showing that the Company had provided the blank forms to the Grievant prior to March 21.2014.</para></ftnote> and seek medical attention.<ftnote num="23"><para>This initial doctor's visit was with Dr. Darrell Boutwell, a chiropractor Ms. Wells had been a patient of Dr. Boutweil for about ten years. Dr. Boutwell found the Grievant had chronic tower back and left saroillac paid due to a degenerative arthritic condition; and recommended that Ms. Wells refrain from long periods of standing or walking in her job. See Union exhibit U-9.</para></ftnote> As a result of this initial visit to seek medical attention, the Grievant's doctor provided her a written note explaining that she had chronic tower back and left sacroiliac pain due to a degenerative arthritic condition and recommending that she refrain from long periods of standing or walking in her job. When the Grievant provided this note to the Company<ftnote num="24"><para>The record is not clear as to who in the Augusta facility the Grievant provided Dr. Boutwell's note. Nevertheless, she was Informed that the Company would not accept Dr. Boutwell's finding and recommendation since he was a chiropractor.</para></ftnote> she was informed that it was not acceptable because it was from a chiropractor and not a medical doctor; and received a letter dated March 11, 2014, accepting her request as a request for accommodation, explaining the provision of the ADA providing copies of a &ldquo;Fact Sheet regarding the Disability Accommodation Process&rdquo; and &ldquo;Request of Disability Accommodation&rdquo; form; and requesting specific documentation and information.<ftnote num="25"><para>The March 11, 2014, unsigned letter from the Company specifically requested: (1) Medical documentation of the impairmeht and how it affects a major life activity&hellip;; (2) Specification as to whether or not the condition is permanent or long termed, and if long termed, the approximate duration; and (3) Which of the essential functions outlined in the attached job description are affected by the impairment, and any suggestions your health care provider may have for accommodations that would allow you to perform these duties, if any&hellip;. See Employer exhibit E-5.</para></ftnote> Accordingly, on April 11, 2014, the Grievant went to see an orthopedist who, after examining her, provided a written explanation of her medical condition and recommended that Ms. Wells be returned to her old type forklift where she was able to sit down.<ftnote num="26"><para>The second doctor Ms. Wells went to see was Dr. Robert C. Gambrell, an orthopedist, who provided a written explanation of her condition and recommendation for accommodation&hellip;Specifically providing, <quote>Tamela is under my care for lower back pain. She has significant pain in her back and In her left ankle causing her difficulties performing her Job. She also has a history of a left ankle injury that has left her with arthritis in her ankle. Her back and ankle feel better with rest My recommendation would be that she return to her old type of forklift to be able to sit down. She should avoid prolonged standing at work. She could sit for 10-12 hours but should have relative limited standing&hellip;.</quote> See Union exhibit U-11.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">On April 14,2014, the Company again wrote to Ms. Wells outlining the provisions of the Americans with Disability Act (ADA), defining a disability, explaining what is required to be covered and eligible for accommodation; and, acknowledging that on March 21, 2014, she filed a Request for Disability Accommodation providing &ldquo;That &ldquo;standing on my legs, feet go numb &amp; pressure on my back, thighs and calves&hellip;Would like to use standard sit down truck.&rsquo;&rdquo; The letter further explained that in order to make a determination in the case specific medical information was needed,<ftnote num="27"><para>The letter provided in part&hellip;Please provide a physician's statement that includes: (1) Medical documentation stating the duration of time you can continuously stand before you lose feeling in your feet&hellip;How long do you need to sit before you can stand again; (2) Medical documentation of the impairment and how it affects your ability to walk/stand when using a stand-up forklift vehicle; (3) Which of the essential functions outlined in the attached job description you cannot perform because <quote>standing causes flare-ups of your condition</quote> as you stated in your Request for Disability Accommodation, and any suggestions your health care provider may have for accommodation that would allow you to perform the essential functions of your job, if any; and (4) Please specify if the condition is permanent or long term&hellip; if long term, please state the approximate duration. See Employer exhibit E-6. The record also shows that during this same time frame the Grievant was also provided a Dart Fitness for Duty form for her doctor to fill out. It is unclear if this from was transmitted as part of the Company's April 14<superscript>th</superscript> letter or provided by the local Human Resource Manager, nevertheless the record does show the form was completed by Dr. Gambell. See Union exhibit U-1 and Employer exhibit E-6.</para></ftnote> and asking that the Grievant provide the listed information as soon as possible.</p>
<p class="continued">Accordingly, on April 24, 2014, the Grievant went back to both her chiropractor and orthopedist to obtain the medical documentation/information requested. Both doctors again provided Ms. Wells written statements explaining her medical condition and recommending that the &ldquo;most obvious simple solution to her problems would be to allow her to return to using a sit down forklift&hellip; lf that solution &lsqb;could not be taken&rsqb; then while she is operating a standup forklift she should be allowed to get off the forklift for 15-20 minutes every hour to perf&lsqb;orm&rsqb; duties or take one of her scheduled rest breaks.&rdquo;<ftnote num="28"><para>The Grievant's chiropractor, Dr. Boutwell's April 24, 2014, written statement provided that <quote>&lsqb;Ms.&rsqb; Wells is under our care for lower back and SI pain. It is our recommendation that she refrain from working longer than one hour without sitting down for a 15 minute period. She is however able to sit for long periods in a work situation, i.e., a 12 hour shift&hellip;.</quote> See Union exhibit U-12. The Grievants orthopedist, Dr. Gambrell's April 24, 2014, written statement provided in part that &lsqb;Ms.&rsqb; Wells is a patient under my care for low back pain and left ankle arthritis. She recently presented for evaluation of exacerbation of her back and ankle pain from driving a stand-up forklift at work. &lsqb;S&rsqb;he states that she has been working for the company for 20&plus; years using a sit down forklift and has had no significant problems performing the duties of her job. &lsqb;S&rsqb;he has recently made a change to a stand-up forklift which requires her to keep both feet in the same position for hours at a tim&lsqb;e&rsqb; &lsqb;and&rsqb; keep both her feet firmly pressed against pedals on the floor of the forklift to keep it operating. Operation of the forklift is primarily with the upper extremities. Due to the unique configuration of the stand-up forklift, as compared to the sit-down forklift &lsqb;she&rsqb; experiences significant pain in her back, legs, and ankles which she has never experienced in the past&hellip;The most obvious simple solution to her problems would be to allow her to return to using a sit-down forklift If that solution &lsqb;cannot be provided&rsqb; then while she is operating a stand-up forklift she should be allowed to get off of the forklift for 15-20 minutes every hour to perf&lsqb;orm&rsqb; duties or to take one of her scheduled rest breaks&hellip;if she &lsqb;is&rsqb; allowed to return to the sit-down forklift she would have no restrictions whatsoever&hellip;.&rdquo; See Union exhibit U-13.</para></ftnote> In addition, Dr. Gambrell completed a fitness-for-duty form, signing off on the following declaration:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;The above named individual &lsqb;Ms. Tamela Wells&rsqb; is currently under my care. I hereby confirm that &lsqb;she&rsqb; has no physical limitations that would prevent &lsqb;her&rsqb; from performing the essential functions listed in the attached job description in a safe manner without endangering &lsqb;herself&rsqb; or &lsqb;her&rsqb; coworkers. I understand that the work is being performed in a manufacturing facility wherein the individual will work in direct contact with product production and heavy machinery. I further understand the nature of the required safety-sensitive duties to be performed in an environment with the aforementioned machinery, constant forklift movements and individually assigned tasks.&rdquo; &lsqb;Edited to include the proper employee identifiers.&rsqb;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">And further providing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;&lsqb;Ms: Wells&rsqb; is able to return to work effective 4-08-2O14 with the following restrictions&hellip;While on stand-up forklift employee must have 15-20 minutes off of the forklift every hour of work. Recommend change to sit down forklift&hellip; Restrictions effective through 12/31/2014.&rdquo; &lsqb;Edited to include the proper employee identifiers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">On April 30, 2014, the Company acknowledged Ms. Wells medical problems as meeting the requirements of the ADA and approved the following accommodation&hellip;&rdquo;While operating the stand-up forklift, &lsqb;you&rsqb; will be allowed to get off of the forklift and work on arranging materials, filling out necessary paperwork, and other job duties for 15 minutes after every one hour of standard forklift use.&rdquo;<ftnote num="29"><para>The record provides that the Grievant was off work, mostly on medical and/or FMLA leave from March 22 &mdash; April 29, 2014&hellip;Then on April 30, 2014, received a letter from Ms. Michelle Jones, Dart LOA/ADA Specialist providing&hellip; <quote>We hope that this accommodation will enable you to perform the essential functions of your job, but we understand that modification is sometimes necessary. Please feel free to contact your supervisor, local HR representative in the Corporate Benefits Department if this accommodation does not prove effective or if over time modifications needed. As always we will review this accommodation on a regular basis to ensure that (1) the accommodation continues to allow you to perform the essential functions of your job and (2) to make any adjustments to the accommodation that are reasonable. Thank you for your cooperation in this process.</quote> See Union exhibit U-10.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">From approximately March 22 through April 29, 2014, the Grievant was off work on medical and/or Family Medical Leave Act (FMLA) leave. When she returned to her regular work schedule on/or about April 30, 2014, Ms. Wells, performed her assigned forklift operator duties using a stand-up forklift and working in accordance with the approved accommodation, one-hour on the lift and fifteen minutes off performing other assigned work.<ftnote num="30"><para>Testimony from the facility Human Resources director provided that the Grievant's department manager provided Ms. Wells a list of duties to perform within the fifteen minute periods she was off the forklift, including paper work, sweeping, etc.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">About a month after returning to working her regular twelve-hour schedule, on May 23, 2014, the Grievant went to her primary care physician, Dr. Newman, for her annual physical. During this examination Dr. Newman inquired about the swelling in the Grievant's legs and ankles, and Ms. Wells explained her work situation. As a result of his examination, Dr. Newman provided Ms. Wells a written statement explaining the results of his examination and recommending that the Grievant not be required to stand all day long and allowed to return to operating a sit-down forklift<ftnote num="31"><para>The May 23, 2014, written statement from Dr. Newman provided&hellip; <quote>This letter is in regard to Tamela Wells, a patient I have been following for a number of years. Tamela recently came in with the complaint of bilateral lower-extremity edema which appears to be worse at the end of the day. It is better by the next meaning but not completely eradicated. It is sot accompanied by shortness of breath or chest discomfort. It began after her work changed to where she is now having to stand all day on an upright forklift instead of being able to sit throughout the day. After evaluation, she has been diagnosed with venous insufficiency. As a consequence of this, I have advised her to ear compression stockings daily. It would be better if the patient did not need to stand all day long. This is clearly contributing to her underlying problem, and would be markedly better for her to be able to go back to a sit-down forklift&hellip;.</quote> See Union exhibit U-15.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">On June 24, 2014, the Grievant provided the Company Dr. Newman's May 23<sup>rd</sup> written statement providing that &ldquo;&hellip;would be better if the patient did not have to stand all day long&rdquo; and again suggesting a return to a sit-down forklift. Since this amounted to a new accommodation request the LOA/ADA Specialist sent a letter to the Grievant that day requesting further information.<ftnote num="32"><para>The June 24, 2014, letter again explained the ADA provisions and eligibility requirements then provided&hellip; <quote>On June 24, 2014, you submitted a doctor's note from Danny Newman MD stating that <quote>&hellip;has advised to wear leg compression stockings daily&hellip;it would be better if the patient did not need to stand all day long&hellip;.</quote> &lsqb;And providing further&rsqb; in order to make a determination in this case we will need some additional inforiflatiun. Please provide the following documentation/information to me as soon as possible so that we may provide you with a prompt and appropriate decision on your request for accommodation. Please provide a physician's statement that includes: Medical documentation stating the duration of time you can continuously stand&hellip;How long do you need to sit before you can stand again; Medical documentation of the Impairment end how it affects your ability to walk/stand when using a standup fork lift vehicle; Which of the essential functions outlined in the attached job description you cannot perform because <quote>standing causes flare-ups of your condition</quote> as you stated in your original Request for Disability Accommodation dated March 11, 2014, and any suggestions your health care provider may have for accommodations that would allow you to perform the essential functions of your job, if any; Please specify if the condition is permanent or long-term. if long term, please state the approximate duration&hellip;</quote> See Employer exhibit E-7.</para></ftnote> According to the Company, the Grievant failed to acknowledge or respond to the June 24<sup>th</sup> request So after thirty-days passed with no communication from the Grievant, on July 25, 2014, the LOA/ADA Specialist sent a letter informing the Grievant that the request was being closed based on the Grievant stalling the interactive process, but that she could restart the process at any time by submitting the requested information.<ftnote num="33"><para>The July 25, 2014, letter concluded&hellip;Without your collaboration the interactive process is halted and we are unable to make a determination or move forward with the ADA process. We will gladly resume this process once the necessary Information has been submitted. While this process is halted we are unable to continue any temporary accommodations that may have been provided&hellip;.&rdquo; See Employer exhibit E-8.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant did go back to see Dr. Newman on August 7,2014, because he had scheduled her for a follow-up appointment. On this visit Dr. Newman gave Ms. Well a second letter providing that she could not stand for more than one hour without being able to be seated for thirty minutes, and recommending that she be able to return to a sit-down forklift<ftnote num="34"><para>This August 7, 2014, letter from Dr. Newman provided: <quote>This letter is in regard to Tamela Wells, a patient I have been following in my office for the last several years. Tamela presented to my office on May 23 with complaints of increasing bilateral lower extremity edema. This is a new problem. It seemed to occur since she began standing at her forklift all day long as compared to previously when she was able to sit. Since that time she has developed 1&plus; bilateral lower extremity edema which persists throughout the night and is sometimes better in the meaning but is certainly worse by the end of the day. At the time she was advised to wear TED hose daily and to be able to sit and keep her legs elevated as often as possible. In my opinion she cannot continuously stand for more than one hour without being able to be seated for at least 30 minutes in order to keep this from being a consistent problem. If indeed this continues she will have worsening swelling in her legs bilaterally that can lead to venous insufficiency and chronic swelling and edema as well as pain. If the patient would be allowed to sit while working on her forklift I think it would essentially eradicate this problem &lsqb;or&rsqb; if she could take frequent breaks to keep her legs elevated. At this point this appears to be a permanent long-term condition although it has only been ongoing for the last several months&hellip;.</quote></para></ftnote> Here the record shows that the Grievant provided Dr. Newman's second letter to the local Human Resources (HR) manager on or about August 18, 2014.</p>
<p class="continued">Almost a month and a half later, when the Grievant reported to work the meaning of October 3, 2014, she was instructed to report to the facilities' personnel office. Upon arriving at the personnel office, the local HR manager asked Ms. Wells if she had received a letter in September from Dart Container. After responding that she had not received any letter from Dart, the local HR manager explained that Ms. Well's request for further accommodation was denied. The local HR manager then called her Regional HR manager and the two HR managers and the Grievant had a three-way discussion about the Grievant's situation. This discussion concluded with the Grievant being told to go home, go back to see her doctor(s) to see if there were any other accommodations that could be suggested; and, that they &lsqb;the local HR manager, the regional HR manager, and the Grievant&rsqb; would have another conversation on October 10<sup>th</sup>.<ftnote num="35"><para>The September letter the local HR manager asked whether or not the Grievant had received, which she then explained to Ms. Wells was the Company's formal denial of her August 18, 2014, submittal of medical documentation and request for further accommodation, was actually received in the mail delivered after she returned home from work on October 3<superscript>rd</superscript>. That letter, from Dart LOA/ADA Specialist, Shari Sweeney, provided as follows: <quote>&hellip;On 8/18/14 you submitted medical documentation requesting the following disability accommodation: to use a sit-down type forklift, to work from a seated position for at least 30 minutes after each hour worked in a standing position, &lsqb;and&rsqb; frequent breaks to keep your legs elevated&hellip; After reviewing your request and engaging in an interactive dialogue, unfortunately, we find we must deny your request for the following reasons: 1. Due to the safety and ergonomic concerns encountered with the sit-down type of fork-lifts a safety-based decision was previously made to eliminate them from the plant by the end of 2014. There currently are 2-3 sit-down type of forklifts remaining in the distribution center which will also be eliminated by the end of the year for safety reasons. Despite the pending elimination of said fork-lifts deemed to be less safe, we still made inquiries of employees in those positions as to whether they might voluntarily exchange positions with you. We found no employees willing to make the exchange. Therefore, a sit-down type of fork-lift is not available. (2) After reviewing your current job functions, there are not a sufficient number of duties that can be done from a seated position to fill 30 minutes after each 1 hour worked standing on your feet. The ability to stand regularly (up to 67-100&percnt; of the time) is an essential function of your job. Under the ADA a <quote>qualified individual</quote> is a person who is able to perform all of the essential functions of the job with or without accommodation. (3) At this time there are no open positions for which you are qualified, nor are we aware of any such positions opening in the foreseeable future&hellip;We believe we have made every effort to provide reasonable accommodation as requested and have exhausted all possibilities. Consequently, at this time we believe you are unable to perform the essential functions of your position With or without reasonable accommodation&hellip;While we have made every effort to include you in the accommodation process it is possible that you have additional information that you feel we should consider. If so please present this additional information to your HR representative for review&hellip;Thank you for your cooperation in this process&hellip;.</quote> During the meeting/discussion with the local HR manager and Regional HR manager the Grievant inquired about being moved to a packer or production job, or being moved to the warehouse. All rejected by the HR folks claiming there were no vacant positions for which Ms. Wells qualified. At the end of the meeting/discussion Ms. Wells was told to go home and they would have another conference call on October 10<superscript>th</superscript>&hellip;That they would call her.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">On October 10, 2014, the local HR and Regional HR managers called the Grievant. The Regional HR manager asked Ms. Wells if she had been back to see her doctor. Ms. Wells said she had. The Regional HR manager then asked if there were any changes or any restrictions lifted. The Grievant responded that there were no changes in her medical condition and the restriction continued as previously explained by her doctor, Dr. Newman. The Regional HR manager then told Ms. Wells, &ldquo;since &lsqb;her&rsqb; doctor didn't lift &lsqb;her&rsqb; restrictions that they &lsqb;the Company&rsqb; did not have a job for &lsqb;her then&rsqb; or in the future&hellip;&rdquo; and said good bye.</p>
<p class="continued">Later the same day, October 10, 2014. the Business Agent for the International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT), Local 528, emailed the Dart/Solo local HR manager requesting information about Ms. Wells' termination.</p>
<p class="continued">On or about October 15, 2014, the Grievant received a letter from the local HR manager, dated October 10, 2014, identified as a separation of employment that provided:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&lsquo;&ldquo;Attached you will find your &ldquo;State of Georgia Department of Labor Separation Notice&rdquo;<ftnote num="36"><para>The attached State of Georgia Department of Labor Separation Notice, dated October 10, 2014, showed the reason for separation as being <quote>unable to return from leave</quote></para></ftnote> that you may take to your local Department of Labor Unemployment Office to file for Unemployment Benefits.</p>
<p class="continued">You will also receive a packet from the Solo Cup Company Benefits department that will explain your available options for your current insurance coverage. Your benefits terminate at midnight on the date of your separation of employment</p>
<p class="continued">If any further information is needed please feel free to contact the local Human Resources department&hellip;&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Subsequently, on October 16,2014, Ms. Wells, with the assistance of the Union, filed her formal grievance, citing Article 9 and 10 of the parties' CBA and providing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;On Oct 15, 2014, I received a separation notice from Dart/Solo Cup signed 10-10-14 that I no longer was employed at Dart/Solo Cup. This separation notice is improper and unfair and unjust The Company did not have just cause to terminate me. Separation notice states that my reason for separation was unable to return from leave. I was not on leave. It also states that my last day worked was 9-10-14. I request to be allowed to drive a sit down forklift in the warehouse and was denied by Jennifer Davis. &lsqb;Remedy Requested&rsqb; To be made whole for all back wages and benefits.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>III. POSITION OF THE PARTIES</b><ftnote num="37"><para>Throughout the summation of the parties' position the Arbitrator has chosen to not show every cited reference to testimony as recorded/documented on the Arbitrator's audio file, copies of which were provided to each party for their reference and use, or to list each legal or reference citation&hellip;Only those references and/or citations the Arbitrator deems significant will be documented in the endnotes. Nevertheless, the failure to note any reference or citation does not mean that the Arbitrator has not read and fully considered the evidence presented by the parties.</para></ftnote></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. The Company/Employer.</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Company/Employer offers that the issues to be addressed by the Arbitrator are:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Did Company's management have the right to change the forklift equipment used in the Augusta, Georgia facility in an effort to improve ergonomic and safety results, and if not what shall be the remedy?</p></li>
<li><p>Was Grievant discriminated against because of her alleged disability in violation of Article 27 of the Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA), and, if so, what shall be the remedy?</p></li>
</ol>
<p class="continued">The Company also offers that the relevant provisions of the CBA are: Article 2-Recognition, Article 5-Management Rights, Article 9-Job Posting, Article 10-Complaints, Article 11-Arbitration, Article 27-Feir Employment Practices and Equal Opportunities, Article 31-Safety and Health, and Article 34-Scope of Agreement<ftnote num="38"><para>See Arbitrator/Joint exhibit AJ-3 Labor Agreement Between SOLO Cup Operating Corporation, Augusta, Georgia and The International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT) Local 528, effective April 1, 2012 through March 31, 2016&hellip;Where the Arbitrator deems it necessary for clarity provisions and/or excerpts from the parties' collective bargaining agreement will be cited either in the text of this decision/award or in its endnotes. However, not showing the full text or excerpt of any provision does not mean the Arbitrator has not read, noted, or referred to the parties CBA. The Arbitrator Incorporates all of the parties CBA by reference in this decision/award.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">The Company's position and arguments are summarized as follows.</p>
<p class="continued">The Company's version of the events leading up to the Grievant's termination is basically the same as presented above. However, it stresses that in 2013, the Plant Manager of the Augusta facility was charged with the responsibility of replacing the leased forklifts used in the facility with purchased forklifts. Accordingly, in keeping with the Company's safety-focused culture, the Plant Manager, in conjunction with the facility's safety experts, investigated the best forklift options for the facility. After considering data about the history of forklift-related accidents and injuries in the facility<ftnote num="39"><para>See Union exhibit U-6.</para></ftnote>, the physical configuration of the workspace in the facility, OSHA ergonomic guidance, and research related to the. ergonomic benefits of a stand-up style forklift, the decision was made to replace the leased, sit-down style forklifts with stand-up style forklifts.</p>
<p class="continued">According to the Company; the stand-up style forklifts offer significant-ergonomic benefis and the compact design that is better suited to a workspace like the Augusta facility, which requires a tighter turning radius for safe forklift operation. Additionally, the stand-up forklift provides greater visibility, increasing the operator's ability to maneuver through the work area safely.<ftnote num="40"><para>See Employer exhibit 1.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">The Company argues that under the provisions of Article 5 of the parties' CBA as conceded by the Union in its opening statement at the arbitration hearing, the Company had the right to select equipment for use in the facility, and the selection of. stand-up.styla forklifta was within the scope of that right.</p>
<p class="continued">According to the Company, the introduction of stand-up forklifts was announced to the Augusta workforce in early 2014, and the safety and ergonomic benefits were explained to the workforce at that time. Training was conducted with production forklift operators in March 2014; and after receiving certification on the stand-up forklifts, operators were encouraged to work partial shifts on the new lifts to allow workers an adjustment period.</p>
<p class="continued">As to the Grievant's claim that the Company failed to properly accommodate her, the Company explains that</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>In March 2014, when the Grievant complained of back, leg, and ankle pain; requested a leave of absence; and, that she be allowed to use a sit-down style forklift as a disability accommodation when she returned to work.</p>
<p>Here the Company maintains it followed its standard procedures, and assigned a dedicated Leave of Absence/Americans with Disabilities Act Specialist (LOA/ADA Specialist) in the corporate office to review and respond to Grievant's request(s). Following internal procedures, as well as the letter and spirit of the ADA the assigned LOA/ADA Specialist reviewed the Grievant's request - Including the Grievant's preferred accommodation, a return to using a sit-down style forklift; as well as, the alternative accommodation of working for fifteen minutes off of the forklift for every hour spent working on the forklift.</p>
<p>Based on the return to work restrictions from the Grievant's medical doctor, the Company determined that it could provide accommodation for the Grievant, but not her preferred accommodation &mdash; a return to the old-style, sit-down forklift &mdash; because the LOA/ADA Specialist determined it would impede the facility's ability to realize the important ergonomic and safety gains sought in the switch to stand-up forklifts.</p>
<p>Instead, the Company granted the doctor's alternate accommodation, working for fifteen minutes off of the forklift for every hour spent working on the forklift, and implemented that accommodation upon the Grievant's return to work on May 2,2014.</p></li>
<li><p>On August 18, 2014, the Company received a darifying doctor's note dated August 7, 2014, stating that it was based on the Grievant's May 23,2014, doctor's visit This new note indicated that the Grievant was unable to stand for more than one hour after which she would need to be seated for at least thirty-minutes and keep her legs elevated. The restriction was identified as permanent.</p>
<p>The Company maintains its response to the August 18,2014 request was slowed by the fact that the LOA/ADA Specialist who had been working on the Grievant's case resigned her position mere days before the letter was received. And, the newly assigned LOA/ADA Specialist had to get acquainted with the case. The Company explains that the new LOA/ADA Specialist again worked with local management safety, and human resources professionals to investigate the feasibility of reintroducing a sit-down style forklift into the production area of the facility as a possible accommodation. However, after significant review, including review of actual, year-to-date safety gains in the facility including the fact that there had been six forklift-related incident reports filed in calendar year 2013, and only one year-to-date in 2014, the determination was made that stand-up forklifts were the safest machines for the production area of the facility and that the safety risks of reintroducing a sit-down forklift were too great and would reverse the significant gains that had been made in the safety results of the facility.</p>
<p>The company argues that jeopardizing the safety of other employees in the workplace when it had announced the safety goals of the new forklifts, and had proof of the benefits realized from the switch to stand-up forklifts, was determined to be an undue burden on business operations.</p>
<p>Review of the doctor's alternative accommodation, that the Grievant would need to be allowed to sit for thirty-minutes with her legs elevated after each hour standing, was deemed unviable.</p>
<p>Finally, as required under the ADA the Company considered whether there were open positions meeting her medical restrictions within the facility for which the Grievant was qualified. There were none.</p>
<p>Because separation of employment was an unwelcome outcome, the Company claims it provided the Grievant with an additional opportunity to provide new accommodation options for consideration. On October 3, 2014, the local HR Manager and Regional HR Business Partner met with the Grievant to communicate the outcome of the ADA accommodation review, and to ask her if she had any additional accommodation ideas. When she did not have any immediately, they informed her that they would give her one week to speak to her doctor and inform them of any additional accommodation ideas. She was informed that she would be off work on leave during that time period.</p></li>
<li><p>On October 10,2014, the HR Manager and Regional HR Business Partner spoke to the Grievant to determine if she had any additional accommodation ideas they could consider. She reported that she did not. At that point, with no further accommodation opportunities to consider, the Grievant was informed that her employment was being separated.</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">The Company argues that the plain language of Article 5; Section 1 of the CBA allows management the right &ldquo;to change or eliminate existing methods of operations, <i>equipment</i> or facilities&hellip;.&rdquo; Furthermore, it argues the Union confirmed this clear right in its opening statement at the Arbitration hearing when the Union's Counsel commented that the &ldquo;Company does have the right to select equipment&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">As to the Union's argument that the Company abused its discretion by selecting the stand-up forklift to replace the sit-down style forklifts based on the fact that there have been lawsuits filed against the manufacturer of the lifts selected - The Company maintains that even a cursory reading of the cases cited by the Union<ftnote num="41"><para>See Union exhibit U-1.</para></ftnote> indicates that none of the cases provide a decision on the merits and that they do not in any way conclude the forklifts selected for use in the Augusta facility are unsafe; and that any contention otherwise would appear to be irrationally misleading. The Company then argues that</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>The McEuin v. Crown Equipment Corp., case involved an earlier model of the Crown stand up forklift that was replaced in 2007 by the newer models in use in the Augusta facility;</p></li>
<li><p>In the Walden v. Crown Equipment Corp., case the court considered not the design of the Crown stand up forklift, but rather Crown's appeal on the admission of certain expert testimony;</p></li>
<li><p>. In Congilaro v. Crown Equipment Corp., Crown motioned to exclude two of the plaintiffs expert witnesses and Its motion for summary judgment Ultimately, the court disqualified one of the expert witnesses in this decision What the Union did not provide in the Arbitration hearing was the April 2013 jury trial, resulting in a finding in favor of Crown, or the plaintiffs September 2013 appeal of the jury decision which was also decided-in favor of Grown<ftnote num="42"><para>2013 WL 5346714</para></ftnote>;</p></li>
<li><p>In Robinson v. Crown Equipment Corp., Crown moved to exclude plaintiffs expert witness, and was denied. No merits decision could be found;</p></li>
<li><p>In Malbrough v. Crown Equipment Corp., Crown moved for, and was denied, summary judgment No decision on the merits could be found;</p></li>
<li><p>In Martin v. Crown Equipment Corp., Crown moved for, and was granted, summary judgment as to punitive damages. Further, this decision outlines the American National Standards Institute's (&ldquo;ANSI&rdquo;) voluntary power industrial truck standards for stand-up foridrfts. ANSI's safety standards, which are followed by the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (&ldquo;OSHA&rdquo;), read as follows: Stand-ups, rear entry end control, narrow aisle, and reach trucks shall be designed with open operator compartments to permit ingress and egress. This allows the operator, where possible, a free and easy egress from the truck in the event of an imminent tip-over or of-the-dock accident in finding for Crown on the punitive damages issue, the court noted that &ldquo;Crown's compliance with ANSI's highly-respected standards, which OSHA has adopted, is strong evidence of the reasonableness of Crown's conduct&rdquo; It is difficult to imagine how the Union contends that Crown's reasonableness in design is proof of abuse of discretion in selecting a similar style forklift for the Company's Augusta facility;</p></li>
<li><p>In <i>Mahon v. Crown Equipment Corp</i>., Crown moved for reconsideration of an earlier denial of summary judgment based on the decision in <i>Martin</i>, above. The court denied the motion based on the fact that <i>Martin</i> was not binding precedent in California. No merits decision was available; and finally,</p></li>
<li><p>In <i>Dymnioski v. Crown Equipment Corp</i>., the court found that the plaintiff failed to state a valid claim, and the decision provided by the Union simply allowed the plaintiff leave to amend the claim. However, in the successor case the court granted summary judgment to Crown.<ftnote num="43"><para>2013 WL 2297035</para></ftnote></p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">After commenting on the cases cited by the Union at hearing, the Company concludes that even if the case law cited did support the Union's contention, which it surely does not, the proper standard of review regarding the safety of equipment selected under a company's management rights prerogative is merely one of good faith as defined in <i>Scott Paper Company, Southern Operators and United Paperworkers International Union, Local 423</i> (FMCS Case No. 79K/02763; Simon, 1979) which found:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;So long as the agreement does not restrict management regarding a specific act or action leading to efficiency, and MORE RECENTLY <i>safety</i>, is that the management of the company has a fixed obligation to reduce unnecessary cost and to provide the safest possible working conditions for all of its employees. It is noted, however, that the management decision must be made in good faith and that it acted reasonably in view of the particular existing conditions and has not discriminated or infringed upon the legitimate rights of any employee. (Emphasis in original).</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Company argues that it exercised good faith decision-making in selecting the Crown stand-up forklifts by researching forklift options, safety and ergonomic issues related to forklift use, the layout of the production areas of the Augusta facility, and the accident reports involving forklift trucks in the facility. The research to which the Augusta, Georgia Plant Manager testified indicated that stand-up lifts offer a significant ergonomic benefit to the driver because the step height is lower to enter and exit the lift, entry and exit is limited to one movement rather than four to enter a sit-down lift, and there is no need for the driver to twist her trunk to view the direction of travel when driving with forks trailing. Further research indicated that the smaller footprint and tighter turning radius of the standup forklifts would likely reduce building damage, and, more importantly, the risk of a pedestrian collision in the small aisle ways in certain areas of the plant</p>
<p class="continued">While the Union claimed repeatedly during the arbitration hearing that there was no history of injuries or accidents in the Augusta facility when sit-down style forklifts were in use, the Union's own exhibit six contradicts this assertion In fact, the exhibit indicates that there were ten incident reports filed involving the use of sit-down style forklifts preceding the introduction of stand-up style forklifts.</p>
<p class="continued">The Company's maintains that reviewing the equipment selection decision under the proper standard of review &mdash; compliance with the CBA and good faith &mdash; clearly demonstrates the Company's compliance, and requires a finding that the first issue in this Arbitration must be decided in the affirmative.</p>
<p class="continued">The Company agrees that it has an obligation to comply with both the federal Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) and the Fair Employment Practices and Equal Opportunities provisions of the CBA Furthermore, it agrees this obligation includes the ADA<b>'S</b> requirement to provide reasonable accommodation for a qualified individual with a disability to allow her to perform the essential functions of her position.</p>
<p class="continued">As summarized above, the Grievant made a request for an ADA-covered accommodation related to her use of the newly introduced stand-up forklift in March 2014. This request was handled by one of the Company's dedicated LOA/ADA Specialists, who engaged in an interactive process to determine and assess possible reasonable accommodations. Ultimately, the Grievant's doctor indicated two accommodation possibilities that he believed would meet Grievant's physical limitations while allowing her to perform the job duties listed in her job description. The doctor suggested either (1) a return to a sit-down style fork lift, or (2) allowing the Grievant to spend 15 minutes performing duties off the forklift after every hour spent working on the stand-up forklift</p>
<p class="continued">Accordingly, the LOA/ADA Specialist determined that it was best to offer the Grievant the doctor's second option as an approved accommodation rather than reintroducing equipment that the company had deemed to be less safe for the work environment. This decision was supported by the research that the Plant Manager had conducted on the benefits of the stand-up style forklifts in the Augusta work environment and by consideration of the potential for liability to the company if it reintroduced the equipment that had been deemed less safe and later a forklift/pedestrian accident did occur.</p>
<p class="continued">Here the Company points out that while the ADA requires an employer provide reasonable accommodations to qualified individuals with disabilities, an employer is not required to provide the requester with her preferred accommodation. In <i>Lewis v. Zilog, inc</i>., the court held that an individual with a disability &ldquo;is not entitled to the accommodation of her choice, but only to a reasonable accommodation.&rdquo;<ftnote num="44"><para>908 F. Supp. 931, 948 (1995)</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">As outlined above, in late June 2014<ftnote num="45"><para>See Union exhibit U-15 and Employer exhibit E-7.</para></ftnote>, the Grievant provided a new doctor's note that indicated that &ldquo;it would be markedly better for &lsqb;Grievant&rsqb; to go back to a sit-down style forklift&rdquo; Recognizing this as a new accommodation request under the ADA the Company's LOA/ADA Specialist provided Grievant with new ADA accommodation paperwork. After a month had passed with no response from the Grievant a letter was sent to her indicating that she had stalled the interactive accommodation process, but that she could begin the process again at any time by responding to the previous request for information.</p>
<p class="continued">On August 18, 2014, Grievant provided a new doctor's note dated August 7, 2015, that was responsive to the Company's June request for information. The August 7 note identified the Grievant's need to be off her feet with her legs elevated as often as possible, and indicated that having to stand all day was exacerbating her medical condition. The doctor indicated two accommodation possibilities that he believed would meet the Grievant's physical limitations: (1) being seated for thirty minutes after each hour worked on the forklift, or (2) a return to a sit-down style forklift.</p>
<p class="continued">Again, the Company's LOA/ADA Specialist considered possible accommodations. As for providing a thirty-minute break each hour to allow the Grievant to sit with her feet elevated, the LOA/ADA Specialist determined that the request was unreasonable under the ADA The LOA/ADA Specialist then considered the request that the Grievant be allowed to return to a sit-down style forklift Again, the conclusion was that this accommodation would not be granted As before, the Company's LOA/ADA Specialist reviewed the safety gains that had been made in the facility in the period since stand-up forklifts had been introduced and found that significant gains had in fact been achieved. As can be seen in the occupational injury reports submitted as Union exhibit six; there were six incident reports filed due to forklift accidents during calendar year 2013, and only one in the first eight months of 2014. Again considering the safety goals of the company, and the liability and risk of reintroducing equipment that had been found to be less safe, the LOA/ADA Specialist determined that reintroduction of a sit-down style forklift would be an undue hardship<ftnote num="46"><para>Undue hardship is defined In the ADA as:</para>
<ordered-list token="lc-roman" bind-char="paren" bind-to="left-right">
<item><para>In general. - The term <quote>undue hardship</quote> means an action requiring significant difficulty or expense, when considered in light of the factors set forth in subparagraph (B).</para></item>
<item><para>Factors to be considered in determining whether an accommodation would impose an undue hardship on a covered</para></item>
<item><para>entity, factors to be considered <italic>include:</italic></para>
<ordered-list token="lc-roman" bind-char="paren" bind-to="left-right">
<item><para>the nature and cost of the accommodation needed under this chapter;</para></item>
<item><para>the overall financial resources of the facility or facilities involved In the provision of the reasonable accommodation; the number of persons employed at such facility; the effect on expenses and resources, or the impact otherwise of such accommodation upon the operation of the facility;</para></item>
<item><para>the overall financial resources of the covered entity; the overall size of the business of a covered entity with respect to the number of its employees; the number, type, and location of its facilities; and</para></item>
<item><para>the type of operation or operations of the covered entity, including the composition, structure, and functions of the workforce of such entity; the geographic separateness, administrative, or fiscal relationship of the facility or facilities in question to the covered entity.</para></item>
</ordered-list></item>
</ordered-list></ftnote> on the operations of the business under the ADA</p>
<p class="continued">In both the initial review for accommodation and the second review, the Company's LOA/ADA Specialists' determinations were grounded in the following rationale: (1) potentially jeopardizing a facility's safety program by reversing safety-specific initiatives, particularly when said program is showing positive results, is inherently imprudent; and (2) future injuries on reintroduced sit-down forklifts could expose the Company to untold liability after publically broadcasting to its workers that said forklifts were a less safe equipment option. The LOA/ADA Specialists' reliance on speculative, yet foreseeable, harm was not an unreasonable approach, particularly since the law encourages proactive measures, and &lsquo;does not require &lsqb;an employer&rsqb; to wait for a serious injury before eliminating a direct threat&rdquo; Jarvis v. potter, 500 F.3d 1113,1124 (10th Cir. 2007).</p>
<p class="continued">After both, the initial and second accommodation requests determination was made, in accordance with the requirements of the ADA, the Company's LOA/ADA Specialist continued to work with management to try to determine any other possible accommodations that would allow the Grievant to perform the essential functions of her job. This included looking for open positions in the facility for which the Grievant was qualified: none were identified; as well as consideration of a transfer to a forklift operator position in the warehouse where sit-down style lifts were still in use, even though they were scheduled for replacement with stand-up style forklifts within two to three months. Unfortunately, there were no open positions in the warehouse.</p>
<p class="continued">However, in an attempt to make every effort to find a way to accommodate the Grievant's physical limitations, which is legally required to demonstrate a good faith interactive process under the ADA the Company's LOA/ADA Specialist directed the forklift drivers in the warehouse be asked if they would be willing to swap positions with a forklift operator in the production area. Here, the Company maintains that asking the warehouse forklift drivers to consider swapping positions was a function of the ADA interactive process, directed by the LOA/ADA Specialist in order to fulfill the Company's legal obligations under federal law, an issue beyond the scope of the CBA And, the Company agues the solicitation was not intended, and in fact did not encroach upon the Union's right as the exclusive bargaining agent on matters contained in the CBA According to the Company, under the ADA, the LOA/ADA Specialist has a legal obligation to explore all conceivable accommodation options, and that responsibility cannot legally be constrained or indicated to a third party. Nevertheless, despite the inquiry, no employee was willing to swap positions.</p>
<p class="continued">At this point the LOA/ADA Specialist recognized that the Company had no further options to consider and drafted a letter to the Grievant indicating that it could not offer any reasonable accommodations to allow her to perform the essential functions of her job. The local HR manager and regional HR business partner met with Grievant on October 3,2014, to discuss the outcome of the accommodation review, and to determine if she had any additional accommodation ideas that the Company had not yet considered: Grievant reported that she did not have any additional ideas. The local HR manager and regional HR business partner told Grievant that they would give her a week to determine if there were any other accommodations that she would like the Company to consider. The Grievant was not actively at work for that one week period.<ftnote num="47"><para>Grievants time records offered as Appendix H of the Company's Post-hearing brief,</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">On October 10, 2014, the local HR manager and regional HR business partner again spoke with the Grievant to determine if she had any additional accommodation ideas that the Company could consider; she did not At that time, the Company separated Ms. Wells' employment.</p>
<p class="continued">The Company points out that during closing remarks, the Union's Counsel contended that because all of the Grievant's doctors had stated that a transition back to a sit-down style forklift would be beneficial to her medical condition, it was a reasonable accommodation However, the Company maintains that is not the proper standard of review under the ADA Instead, an ADA a accommodation is reasonable if it allows the employee to perform the essential functions of the job without undue hardship on the operation of the business. Just as, according to the Company, the Union appears to believe that if an individual files a lawsuit claiming a manufacturing defect there is proof of a manufacturing defect; it appears also to believe that if a doctor makes a recommendation for a possible accommodation (based on medical knowledge, not business operation knowledge), it makes the suggestion a reasonable accommodation under the ADA. According to the Company, neither of these beliefs is accurate.</p>
<p class="continued">The Company argues that in reviewing the totality of the record, it is indisputable the Company held a reasonable belief that (1) a stand-up forklift was a safer piece of equipment for its specific work environment, and (2) that returning a sit-down lift to the work environment would pose a significant risk of substantial harm to the health and safety of the Augusta workforce.</p>
<p class="continued">Establishing its reasonable belief that the stand-up lift was the safer alternative, the Company offered uncontroverted testimony that its Plant Manager led an effort to investigate the safest forklift options for the facility. The effort and investigation was precipitated by the pending termination of leased forklifts and the decision was made after considering data about the history of forklift-related accidents and injuries in the facility, the physical configuration of the work environment, OSHA ergonomic guidance, and research related to the ergonomic benefits of a stand-up style forklift. This thoughtful review took into account the ergonomic benefits, compact design, and tighter turning radius of stand-up forklifts. The review and decision were not influenced by any single employee, but rather was made for the collective good and safety of the workforce.</p>
<p class="continued">The ultimate decision on the reasonableness of reintroducing a sit-down lift to the work environment fell to the Company's Leave and Disability Manager. This manager's testimony likewise established a reasonable belief that returning a sit-down lift to the work environment would pose a significant risk of substantial harm to health and safety of the Augusta workforce. The Leave and Disability Manager's testimony established her determination was made in good-faith. Even the Union's Counsel acknowledged such in his closing remarks, stating that she was free from ill intent in making her determination.</p>
<p class="continued">The Company acknowledges that the Union, and perhaps even the Arbitrator, may disagree with its underlying belief that the stand-up lift was the safer option or that the risk of reintroducing the sit-down lift to the work environment posed enough risk that doing so would pose an undue hardship.</p>
<p class="continued">Importantly, however, such disagreement, from Grievant and Fact Finder alike, is legally immaterial in determining whether the Company's reasonable belief affords is an affirmative defense to claims of disability discrimination. As the 10&ast; Circuit Court of Appeals recently held in <i>EEOC v. Beverage Distributors, LLC</i>, an employer can avoid liability by establishing its reasonable belief that an employee posed a significant risk to the health and safety of me workforce. (780 F.3d 1018 (2015)). See also <i>Jarvis v. Potter</i> (stating that the fact-finder does not independently assess whether it believes that the employee posed a direct threat, but determines &lsqb;instead&rsqb; whether the employer's decision was objectively reasonable.) The court in <i>EEOC v. Beverage Distributors</i> held: In sum, Beverage Distributors could avoid liability by showing that it reasonably determined that: (1) Mr. Sungaila posed a significant risk of substantial harm to the health or safety of Mr. Sungaila and/or other employees; and (2) risk could not be eliminated or reduced by reasonable accommodation.</p>
<p class="continued">Applying the Court's rationale in EEOC v. Beverage <i>Distributors</i> to the present matter, the Company's reasonably held belief that; (1) a stand-up forklift was a safer piece of equipment for its specific work environment; and (2) that returning a sit-down lift to the work environment would pose a significant risk of substantial harm to health and safety of the Augusta workforce, should absolve it of liability, regardless of how much Monday meaning quarterbacking is done around its aforementioned reasonable beliefs and determinations.</p>
<p class="continued">As for the Union's argument regarding bumping rights - Citing Article 9, Section 4 of the CBA the Union contends that the Grievant should have been moved to the warehouse rather than terminated because she had a right to bump a warehouse forklift operator based on her seniority. Alternatively, the Union contends that the Grievant should have been able to bump into a Group 1 position.</p>
<p class="continued">According to the company, this argument is net supported by the clear text of the CBA. Article 9, Section 4 which allows an employee in a Group 2 position (which includes both production and warehouse forklift operators) to &ldquo;bid down or laterally for bona fide health reasons&hellip;&rdquo; Here according to the Company, the use of file word &ldquo;bid&rdquo;distinguishes the right in Section 4 from the right to &lsquo;bump&rdquo; an employee that is defined in Article 9, Section 1. According to the Company, Section 1 allows &ldquo;&lsqb;e&rsqb;mployees in the same department and classification&rdquo; to &ldquo;move to the shift of their preference based upon seniority.&rdquo; Accordingly, the Company maintains that the use of &lsquo;bid&rdquo; in Section 4 requires an open position to which the employee can bid; and according to the Company there were no open forklift operator positions in the warehouse. Further, according to the Company, bumping as defined in Section 1 requires that the employee bumping a less senior co-worker, must be in the same department and classification. On this point the Company maintains that while the forklift operators in production and warehouse are in the same pay classification as demonstrated in the wage rate schedule in the CBA, they are in distinct departments as evidenced by unique job descriptions and, importantly, by the Grievart's insistence to the LOA/ADA Specialist during at least five phone calls that the warehouse forklift operator job description that the LOA/ADA Specialist provided to her with her ADA and FMLA paperwork was &ldquo;nothing like what she does on a daily basis.&rdquo; For the Company, it is troubling that during the Grievant's cross examination in the arbitration hearing, when there is a benefit to an arbitration finding that the warehouse Grievant denied making any statement that the warehouse job description was not the same as her position.</p>
<p class="continued">For the foregoing reasons, the Company respectfully requests that the Arbitrator DENY the grievance.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. The Union/Grievant.</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Union/Grievant offers that the issue to be addressed by the Arbitrator is:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Whether there was &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; for the discharge of the Grievant? If not, what is the appropriate remedy?</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">The Union also offers that the relevant provisions of the CBA are: Article 5-Management Rights, Article 8-Seniority, Article 9-Job Posting, Article 20-Leave of Absence, Article 27-Fair Employment Practices and Equal Opportunities, and Article 35-Separabifity.<ftnote num="48"><para>See Arbitrator/Joint exhibit AJ-3 Labor Agreement Between SOLO Cup Operating Corporation, Augusta, Georgia and The International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT) Local 528, effective April 1, 2012 through March 31, 2016&hellip;Where the Arbitrator deems it necessary for clarity provisions and/or excerpts from the parties' collective bargaining agreement will be cited either in the text of this decision/award or in its endnotes. However, not showing the full text or excerpt of any provision does not mean the Arbitrator has not read, noted, or referred to the parties CBA The Arbitrator incorporates all of the parties CBA by reference in this decision/award.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">The Union's position and arguments are summarized as follows.</p>
<p class="continued">According to the Union, the facts in this case are simple and straightforward. The Grievant and her doctors all requested, due to her severe back and ankle problems, that she be granted an accommodation in the equipment that she used to perform her forklift job. The accommodation request was for a sit-down forklift. The evidence shows that Grievant and her coworkers had successfully used sit-down forklifts for over twenty-five years with no serious injuries or accidents. The Employer denied these requests for accommodations solely on the grounds that the Crown stand-up lifts which the Employer acquired are safer and ergonomically better for the forklift drivers. However, the overwhelming record evidence shows the opposite. Indeed, Crown stand-up forklifts, for over a decade, have been the subject of repeated lawsuits where forklift drivers have lost limbs and have been seriously injured due to the fact that these lifts do not adequately protect the forklift drivers. Moreover, OSHA has posted a warning on its website stating the stand-up lifts can and do cause injuries due to inadequate protection due to &ldquo;under-ride&rdquo; hazards. The evidence also shows that the Grievant and a number of her coworkers experienced severe physical problems while driving the stand-up lifts. The evidence is overwhelming that the safety and ergonomic concerns raised by the Employer in the denial of the Grievant's accommodation requests are pre-textual and not supported in reason or fact. Moreover, the denial of the Grievant and her doctors' accommodation requests resulted in her involuntary separation and discharge. Therefore, the Union submits that the discharge of the Grievant is absolutely unjust and that she should be reinstated, granted the accommodation that she requested and made whole for ail of her losses.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union points out that the Grievant was hired by Dart Container Corporation, Solo Cup Operating facility in Augusta, Georgia on March 29,1982. She worked thirty-two years, her entire work career, with this Employer. In addition, she was the Union steward at this plant since 1990, approximately twenty-four years and during the majority of this time she was a forklift driver. Furthermore, the evidence shows that during her entire tenure of employment, the Grievant has never been given any major discipline. She has never previously been suspended or discharged. She has never had an accident driving the forklift. And, the Grievant was the most senior forklift driver at the Augusta Plant at the time of her discharge.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union maintains that sit-down lifts have been used at the Augusta Plant for over twenty-four years prior to 2014, and during this entire period, there has not been one single OSHA reportable accident or injury caused by the sit-down fork lifts. Furthermore, Union witnesses at the hearing testified that the sit-down lifts have been comfortable to drive and use; and forklift drivers have not suffered foot, knee or ankle problems with the sit-down forklifts.</p>
<p class="continued">Additionally, the Union paints out that in February of 2014, when the Employer announced that it was going to replace the sit down forklifts with stand-up lifts; at least three sit-down lifts were to be retained for a short period of time. These three sit-down lifts were to be kept for work associated with the warehouse until the end of 2014. Then one sit-down lift which is a scissor lift was to be kept permanently.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union also argues that all of the forklift drivers at the Augusta plant are in the same job classification and the Grievant was the most senior forklift driver. According to the Union, one group of forklift drivers operates forklifts which keep the production lines supplied with material to produce the product. These forklift drivers remove the product from the extrusion area of the plant and transport it to the print area and the warehouse areas of the plant for further processing and/or storage. These forklift drivers also deliver material to the trophy room where most of the finished product is produced. The other group of drivers stock finished product in the warehouse or on trailers. The Union contends that while the Grievant's normal job assignment was to service the plant, the evidence shows she has performed the forklift job in all areas of the plant and warehouse and that she is fully capable to perform all aspects of the forklift job. The Union further argues that basically, all of the forklift drivers perform the same type of work, hauling and moving product and supplies and all are within the same job classification. They merely have different areas to service.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant and all the other forklift drivers who serviced the plant were provided stand-up Clark 5500 forklifts in February of 2014 to drive and use in the performance of their jobs. Three sit-down lifts were retained to service the warehouse and the sit down scissor lift was kept to move rolls of paper.</p>
<p class="continued">While the basic facts about the events occurring from February to October 2014 outlined above in the Background section are not disputed, like the Company, the Union presented its version as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant began driving a stand-up Clark 5500 lift in February of 2014. She testified that she was given very minimal training in the operation of this lift. This training was sufficient to enable her to satisfy the OSHA forklift license requirement.</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">As pointed out above, by March 2014, the Grievant began experiencing problems with her back, ankle and legs. She testified that her feet felt like they were &ldquo;on fire,&rdquo; that her ankles were severely aching, she was experiencing swelling, and also suffering with severe back pain. The Grievant further testified that during the some twenty-four years she had driven the sit-down lift, she had never experienced any of these type problems, at least to the extent that she was having while driving the stand-up lift</p>
<p class="continued">To operate the Clark 5500 standup lift, the Grievant, and another forklift operator both, testified you are required to stand in the same position on the lift with both feet on the floor for the entire twelve-hour work shift According to the Union, testimony confirmed that it was this standing for an extended period of time that caused the Grievant's major discomfort and problems significant enough for her to seek medical attention.</p>
<p class="continued">In March 2014, the Grievant went to her chiropractor Dr. Darrell Boutwell for her problems; and Dr. Boutwell provided her a written statement explaining that</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Ms. Wells had been a patient since 2003; and she has chronic tower back and left sacroiliac pain due to degenerative arthritic condition. It is our strong recommendation that Ms. Wells refrain from long periods of standing or walking in her job. If there are any questions please do not hesitate to contact us in the office.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Grievant submitted a written request for accommodation to the Employer on March 11, 2014. in response to the question on the Employer's Request for Disability Accommodation form, what is the accommodation you are requesting, the Grievant answered: standard sit-down truck. Her request explained that the stand-up lift was causing her feet to go numb and there was pressure on her back, thighs and calves with her ankles swelling. <i>Id</i>. Not only did chiropractor Boutwell support this Request for Accommodation, she also went to Orthopedist Dr. Robert Gambrell who also recommended in writing on April 11, 2014, to the Employer that the Grievant be returned to the sit-down lift because the stand-up lift was causing her major medical problems. In this regard, Dr. Gambrell stated:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Tamela is under my care for low back pain. She has significant pain in her back and her left ankle causing her difficulties performing her job. She also has a history of a left ankle injury that has left her with arthritis in her ankle. Her back and her ankle feel better with rest&hellip; My recommendation would be that she return to her old type of forklift to be able to sit down. She should avoid prolonged standing at work&hellip;She could sit for 10-12 hours but should have relatively limited standing.</p>
</blockquote></blockquote>
<p class="continued">&bull; The Grievant was out of work five-weeks from on or about March 21,2014, until on or about April 28,2014, due to problems with her back, feet and ankles. Both doctors clearly stated in writing to the Employer that the Grievant should be returned to the sit-down lift to perform her forklift job. Dr. Boutwell went on to state in writing on April 24, 2014, to the Employer that if the Grievant was required to operate the stand-up lift that she be given a fifteen-minute period each hour in which she did not drive. He also stated that he recommended no lifting over twenty-five pounds.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Grievant submitted both Doctors' written statements and requests for accommodation to the Employer. On March 11, 2014, the Employer granted the request for fifteen-minute periods off of the lift each hour. However, it would not put her back on the sit-down lifts as recommended by both doctors. She was put back on the Clark 5500 stand-up lift contrary to the recommendation of the doctors. The doctors both made it clear that the solution to the Grievant's problems was to put her on the sit-down lift, but the Employer refused to honor the doctors and the Grievant's requests for accommodation associated with the sit-down lift.</p>
<p class="continued">As discussed above, the evidence established that all during this period in 2014 the Employer had three sit-down lifts being used at the plant to service the warehouse and it also had one sit-down lift that was a scissor lift which was in the area of the plant in which the Grievant worked. It is undisputed that the Grievant is and/or was the most senior forklift driver at the Augusta facility and she was in the same job dassificafion as the forklift drivers who serviced the warehouse who were using sit down lifts in the performance of their jobs. All of these jobs are within the same job dassificafion. The evidence is clear that if the Grievant had been given one of the sit-down forklifts to drive as requested by her and her doctors that no one would have been displaced. The only change that was needed was to provide her a sit-down lift to drive. She could have used this lift to perform her job duties as she had done for the past twenty-four years or she could have serviced the warehouse using the sit-down lifts. It is undisputed that she had performed the warehouse forklift work in the past and was fully qualified to do it Moreover, if the Employer was not willing to permit the Grievant to use one of the three sit-down lifts, it could have modified the scissor lift so she could perform her job on that lift. Further, it had the option to obtain another sit-down lift to accommodate the Grievant. The Employer did not exercise any of these options in an effort to accommodate her.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">&bull; On April 28, 2014, the Grievant returned to work from short term leave and as discussed above again began to drive the stand-up forklift. Thereafter, on May 23, 2014, she was examined by her family doctor, Dr. Danny Newman. According to the Grievant, Dr. Newman advised the Grievant that she was suffering from severe edema with swelling in her legs and ankle. Dr. Newman in writing recommended to the Employer that the Grievant be accommodated by moving her to a sit down forklift.</p>
<p class="continued">&bull; On August 7, 2014, the Grievant again saw Dr. Newman. In writing, Doctor Newman advised the Employer that he recommended that she be moved to a sit-down forklift and that she could work the entire twelve-hour shift without restrictions if that accommodation was granted. He went on to state in writing that if the Grievant continued to be assigned to work on the stand-up lift that it would be necessary for her to have thirty-minutes each hour off of the standup lift in order to keep the edema in her legs from being a consistent problem.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Grievant submitted the written request for accommodations prepared by Dr. Newman in writing to management on or about August 7, 2014. On September 26, 2014, the Grievant's request for accommodation was denied by the Employer. Management advised the Grievant in writing that her request to be accommodated by permitting her to use a sit-down forklift in the performance of her duties was denied. She was advised in writing that she could not work on the sit-down lift due to &ldquo;safety and ergonomic&rdquo; concerns. The evidence shows that the Employer's Corporate Human Resources Department concluded that the sit-down lifts were unsafe and should not be driven. According to the testimony of Dart's ADA/LOA Specialist, the Grievant's request for accommodation was denied because it was her understanding that the sit down lifts were unsafe and ergonomically unsuitable.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">&bull; On October 3, 2014, the Grievant was called into a meeting with management. The Grievant met with the local plant HR manager and her supervisor, the Regional HR manager, was on the phone for a conference call. During this meeting, management asked the Grievant if she had received any written communication from Dart concerning her doctor's requests for accommodation. The Grievant advised the management officials that she had not received anything in writing or in the mail relating to this most recent accommodation request. She was advised by them that she should go back to her doctor to see if he had any further recommendations as to her ability to work because her request for accommodations to be placed on the sit-down lift was denied.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">According to the Grievant, during that meeting she requested not only to move to a sit-down lift but also to be moved to a packer job. Both of these requests for accommodation were denied. She also advised management that there was a sit-down lift that had been tagged and was sitting idle in the plant not being used and she was requesting to use that lift in the performance of her job. That request was also denied. According to the Grievant, the October 3, 2014, meeting ended with her being advised to go back to her doctor to see if he would change the restrictions which he had cited were required if she drove a stand-up lift.</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant complied with management's request and met with Doctor Danny Newman. The Grievant advised Dr. Danny Newman of what management had stated to her and that she would not be placed on a sit-down lift to work. According to the Grievant, Dr. Newman advised her that he could not revise his restrictions as to what she could do if she worked on the stand-up lift.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">&bull; On October 10, 2014, management called the Grievant as previously arranged. During the conference call with the local HR manager and the regional HR manager, the Grievant advised the managers that her doctor would not revise his restrictions on her. She was then told she was being separated from her employment, and several days later received in the mail a Notice of Discharge which provided as the reason for separation &ldquo;Unable to Return from Leave.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Grievant upon receiving the Notice of Discharge immediately contacted the Assistant Business Agent for Local 528 who in turn contacted the Employer's local HR manager and was advised by the HR manager that the Employer had asked the workers who were forklift drivers servicing the warehouse if any of them were willing to drive the stand-up lifts to accommodate the Grievant and none of these forklift drivers were willing to drive her stand-up lift. The Local's Assistant Business Agent was also advised that because none of these forklift drivers would agree to drive the stand-up lift that the Grievant and her doctors' requests for accommodation were denied. Here, testimony showed that the Union representative advised the HR manager that the Grievant was the most senior forklift driver at the Augusta Plant and that she should be assigned to the sit-down lift due to her seniority standing. He further advised that under Article 9, Section 4, of the collective bargaining agreement the Grievant should be able to bid down and/or laterally for a bona fide health reason or upon agreement of the parties. The Union representative further advised the HR manager that the Union was agreeing to the Grievant being assigned the sit-down lift and the Union had the authority to consent to such and not the workers. However, the HR manager refused to return the Grievant back to work and let the discharge stand.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union argues that in the present situation, the Employer and the Union agreed in Article 5 of the parties' collective bargaining agreement that the Employer can discharge a worker only for &ldquo;just cause.&rdquo; On this point, the Union points out that the term &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; is a broad term which does not have a precise definition and allows for consideration of a number of factors. Here, Arbitrator Jonathan Dworkin in <i>Thermo King Corp</i>. 102 LA 612, 614-615 (Dworkin 1993) dealt with the discharge of a worker under a &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; provision of a collective bargaining agreement wherein the Grievant was allegedly disabled and the union asserted that the employer could not discharge the grievant without attempting to make a reasonable accommodation for the Grievant's disability under the Americans with Disabilities Act. In discussing the &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; standard and how it should be applied in conjunction with the Americans with Disabilities Act, Arbitrator Dworkin wrote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">When contract negotiators restrict an employer's disciplinary authority with the single term, &ldquo;just cause,&rdquo; they open each discipline grievance to arbitral intrusion. They license arbitrators to do precisely what the Supreme Court sought to restrain &ndash; fashioning decisions based on individual ideas of industrial justice. While the words &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; may seem straight forward and simple, they are not. They embody a profusion of concepts and ideals about what is a just penalty.</p>
<p class="continued">It is well settled that discipline is not just if it is manifestly unfair. But how does one decide what is &ldquo;fair&rdquo; and &ldquo;unfair?&rdquo; Where does one look for guidelines and principles? One source is arbitral &ldquo;precedent&rdquo; &ndash; the maxims set forth in nearly a half-century of published decisions on the subject. While the decisions are not carved in granite, they have been followed so long and so regularly as to create a presumption that negotiators intend to keep on following them when they agree that employees can be discharged only for just cause.</p>
<p class="continued">Another obvious resource for deciding what does or does not form just cause is basic societal values. The right of handicapped people to hold jobs they can perform was a societal value long before Congress made it a law. Arbitrators expressed it decades before ADA was enacted. Reasonable accommodation, the fundamental employer obligation under the Act, has long been recognized as an element of just cause by arbitrators. If anything, arbitrators have been more permissive than ADA.</p>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator agrees that technically, he cannot decide whether Thermo King violated the Act when it discharged Grievant. That is a question for the courts. But he is empowered and obligated to decide if Grievant's penalty was just and fair. In making that determination, it is appropriate to look to the Act for guidance. Accordingly, it is held that the Union's ADA-based arguments are germane to this dispute. The Company's motion to dismiss them is denied.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Additionally, in the subject case, the Union argues the determination of whether the Employer had &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; to terminate the Grievant herein is closely intertwined with the question of whether the Employer improperly discriminated against her in violation of Article 27 of the CBA dealing with fair employment practices and equal opportunities. That Article in Section 1 states as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">There shall be no discrimination by either the Company or the Union against any employee because of race, creed, color, age, sex, disability or national origin, in the administration and application of this Agreement.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">In the CBA, therefore, the Union argues that the parties have expressly incorporated &ldquo;disability discrimination.&rdquo; The Union submits that the Americans with Disabilities Act and/or the principles in the ADA must be followed in deciding whether there has been &ldquo;disability discrimination&rdquo; and &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; for the discharge. These are standards that should be used by the Arbitrator in determining &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; and disability discrimination herein. This is consistent with the well-developed thrust of arbitral opinion. <i>See e.g. Elkouri, How Arbitration Works</i>, Sixth Edition at 816-817. In this regard, <i>How Arbitration Works</i> supra at 616-817 states as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Along these lines, a significant issue is the degree to which the rights of an employee with a disability are limited by the collective bargaining agreement. Another issue is how to apply the ADA in instances where the agreement specifically covers disabled employees but fails to specify what type of accommodations the employer must make. In one case, where the contract required an employer to place an employee who was Incapacitated for regular work due to non-work injury in &ldquo;any work he can do,&rdquo; the arbitrator held that the term must be interpreted in harmony with the ADA's requirement that the employer make &ldquo;reasonable accommodations&rdquo; for employees with physical limitations.</p>
<p class="continued">As the ADA has been developed further through litigation and interpretation by the courts and the EEOC, arbitral resolution of disability cases has undergone a sea change. Increasingly, arbitral decisions are informed by ADA case law, the statute's implementing regulations, EEOC guidelines, and parallel state laws.</p>
<p class="continued">Arbitrators have repeatedly held that employers must reasonably accommodate employees who have physical or mental impairments, and have looked to the ADA for guidance. The right to a reasonable accommodation has been found not only where the collective bargaining agreement expressly incorporates the ADA, or includes a nondiscrimination clause covering disability, but also under a general &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; provision. In one case, where the union had invoked the ADA and the employer raised defenses available under the Act, the arbitrator applied the ADA because the contract contained a nondiscrimination clause and a conflict of law provision.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">According to the Union, Labor arbitrators have repeatedly applied the disability discrimination principles of the Americans with Disabilities Act in deciding whether &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; existed for discharge under a collective bargaining agreement. <i>See South Peninsula Hospital</i>, 120 LA 673, 679 (Landau 2004) (because the contract prohibits disability discrimination as defined by law, it is appropriate to apply the relevant legal principles from the ADA to determine whether there was just cause for the termination); <i>GTE North, Inc</i>., 113 LA 665, 672 (Brodsky 1999) (compliance with the ADA can be viewed as a component of just cause, a necessary element for discharge. <i>Thermo King Corp</i>., 102 LA 612, 615-616 (Dworkin 1993) (the concept of reasonable accommodation is an element of just cause for discharge); <i>Meijer Inc</i>., 103 LA 834, 838 (under a contract requiring just cause for disciplinary action against an employee, rights established by law, such as the ADA, must be taken into consideration in determining whether just cause exists.).</p>
<p class="continued">As discussed above, Article 27 of the parties' CBA provides that there shall be no discrimination&hellip; by the Company&hellip; against any employee because of disability. The Americans with Disabilities Act, 42 U.S.C. Section 12112(b) (5)<ftnote num="49"><para>See Albertson's Inc. Case No. 95-26025 p. 20-21 (Miller 1996)</para></ftnote> (A) defines the term &ldquo;discriminate&rdquo; as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&hellip;not making reasonable accommodations to the known physical or mental limitations of an otherwise qualified individual with a disability who is an applicant or employee, <i>unless such covered entity can demonstrate that the accommodation would impose an undue hardship on the operation of the business of such covered entity</i> (Emphasis added)</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">To further support its case, the Union argues that:</p>
<p class="continued">Arbitrators have repeatedly held that such nondiscrimination provisions as that in Article 27 wherein the parties have agreed not to discriminate because of disability requires them to &ldquo;reasonably accommodate&rdquo; disabled employees and to comply with the requirements of the Americans with Disabilities Act. They hold that where a discharge is involved, that the consequence of a failure to reasonably accommodate a worker's disability is an unjust discharge. <i>See Albertson's Inc</i>., Case No. 95-26025 (Miller 1996) (where CBA provides that the Union and the Employer agree not to discriminate against any employee due to handicap and the ADA defines discrimination as not making reasonable accommodations, the Employer discriminated against the grievant by not reasonably accommodating his handicap). <i>Sacred Heart Medical Center</i>, (Tapp 2009) (because the Employer failed to accommodate the Grievant's disability and such conduct is prohibited by the nondiscrimination provision of the CBA and the Americans with Disabilities Act the termination of the Grievant was improper).</p>
<p class="continued">In the Eleventh Circuit Court of Appeals, which includes Georgia, the courts have held that to establish a claim of disability discrimination, a worker must prove three elements: (1) that he or she has a disability within the meaning of the Americans with Disabilities Act; (2) that with or without reasonable accommodations, he or she can perform the essential functions of the job he or she holds; and (3) that he or she was discriminated against because of his or her disability. <i>Mazzeo v Color Resolutions International</i>, 746 F. 3d 1264, 1367 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir. 2011?7); <i>Holly v. Clairson Industries, LLC</i>, 492 F. 3d 1247, 1256 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir. 2007); <i>Jemigan v. Bellsouth Telecommunications, LLC</i>, 17 F. Supp. 3d 1317, 1321 (N.D. Ga 2014).</p>
<p class="continued">Upon a showing by the worker that a reasonable accommodation exists, the burden shifts to the employer to prove that the worker's requested accommodation imposes an undue hardship. <i>Jemigan</i> supra at 1321.</p>
<p class="continued">The Americans with Disabilities Act defines the term &ldquo;disability&rdquo; as (1) a physical or mental impairment that substantially limits one or more of an individual's major life activities, (2) a record of such an impairment, or (3) being regarded as having such an impairment as described in subsection (1). <i>Mazzeo v Color Resolutions International</i>, 746 F. 3d 1264, 1268 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir. 2014); 42 U.S.C. Section 12102 (1). Under the Act as amended effective January 1, 2009<ftnote num="50"><para>Congress made significant changes to the Americans with Disabilities Act by enacting the ADA Amendments Act of 2008 which became effective January 1, 2009. <italic>See Mazzeo</italic> at p. 1267. The amended Act applies to the Grievant's claims which all arose after January 1, 2009. <italic>Id</italic>. When Congress enacted the ADAAA, it indicated that one of the amendments purposes was to convey that the question of whether an individual's <italic>impairment</italic> is a disability should not demand extensive analysis. <italic>Id</italic> at 1262. Congress made clear that it was intent that earlier Supreme Court's interpretations of phrases defining what constitutes a disability such as <quote>substantially limits</quote> are overruled and the ADA is to be construed broadly in terms of extensive coverage and is not meant to be a demanding standard. <italic>Mazzeo</italic> at 1257</para></ftnote>, major life activities include but are not limited to&hellip;.sleeping, walking, lifting&hellip;.and bending.</p>
<p class="continued">Here, the Union points out that two doctors and a chiropractor who were and/or are the Grievant's treating physicians submitted statements to the Employer stating that the Grievant has major back and ankle problems and had a history of such impairments which impacted the Grievant's ability to work, stand and lift more than twenty-five pounds.<ftnote num="51"><para>Dr. Boutwell stated that the Grievant had been a patient of ours since 2003 and that she has chronic tower back and left sacroiliac pain due to degenerative arthritic condition. Dr. Gambrell stated that the Grievant has a history of a left ankle injury that has left her with arthritis in her ankle. Dr. Newman stated the Grievant had bilateral lower extremity edema with venous insufficiency and chronic swelling which he described as a permanent long term condition. See Union exhibits U-17 through U-2424</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">Since the passage of the Amendments to the Americans with Disabilities Act in 2009 the courts have consistently found that workers with similar physical problems as that of the Grievant have a &ldquo;disability&rdquo; as contemplated by the Americans with Disabilities Act. <i>See Mazzeo v Color Resolutions</i> supra (plaintiff was disabled who had degenerative disc disease which included herniated disc and torn ligaments with 10 pound weight restriction); <i>Cohen v CHLN Inc</i>., 2011 WL 2713737 (E.D. Pa. 2011) 2011 WL 2713737 (E.D. Pa. 2011) (plaintiff who suffered from back and leg problems was disabled); <i>Fleck v. WILMAC Corp</i>. 2011 WL 1899198 (E.D. Pa. 2011) (the plaintiff who had a chronic ankle injury was disabled.).</p>
<p class="continued">The Grievant has been suffering from back and ankle problems since 2008 and she has constantly been under the care of the chiropractor. When she was required to stand twelve-hours operating the stand-up lift these conditions flared up and resulted in the standing and lifting limitations imposed by the doctors. Therefore, there is a clear record of evidence establishing that the Grievant has a disability within the meaning of the Americans with Disabilities Act. Moreover, she has been regarded as having such an impairment by the Employer because the Employer has in the past granted some of her requests for accommodation.</p>
<p class="continued">The Americans with Disabilities Act defines a &ldquo;qualified individual&rdquo; as an individual with a disability who, with or without, reasonable accommodation, can perform the essential functions of the employment position that such individual holds or desires. <i>See Mazzeo</i> at 1267, 1268 42 U.S.C. Section 1211(8). In this case, the evidence clearly establishes that the Grievant can perform the essential functions of the forklift job with reasonable accommodations. All three of her treating physicians stated in the documents that they submitted to the Employer that the Grievant can perform the forklift job so long as she is permitted to drive a sit down forklift.</p>
<p class="continued">In <i>Holt v Olmsted Township Board of Trustees</i>, 43 F. Supp. 2d 812, 823 (N.D. Ohio 1998) the court held that since the plaintiff had served twenty years in the job in question there was no dispute that she was qualified to perform the job. Here, the Grievant performed all aspects of the forklift job using the sit down lift for in excess of twenty-four years. There is and cannot be any dispute that she can perform all essential functions of the job if she is permitted to use the sit-down lift as recommended by her treating doctors.</p>
<p class="continued">The only real issue is whether the Employer should be required to keep in service a sit-down forklift as a reasonable accommodation to the Grievant or whether the Employer should have permitted the Grievant to perform the duties performed by warehouse forklift drivers instead of discharging her.</p>
<p class="continued">Although the Americans with Disabilities Act does not fully define &ldquo;reasonable accommodation,&rdquo; it does state that this concept includes the following: job restricting, part-time or modified work schedules, reassignment to a vacant position, acquisition or modification of equipment or devices, appropriate adjustment or modification of examination training materials or policies, the provision of qualified readers or interpreters, and other similar accommodations for individuals with disabilities. <i>See Skerski v Time Warner Cable</i>, 257 F. 3d 273, 284 (3<sup>rd</sup> Cir. 2001); 42 U.S.C. Section 12111(9)(B).</p>
<p class="continued">Both arbitrators and the courts have held that employers, as part of the reasonable accommodation obligation, must provide disabled workers special equipment and/or modified equipment to enable them to perform the essential functions of the job. <i>See GTE North</i>, 113 LA 1047, 1052 (Daniel 1999) (employer did not have just cause to discharge telephone technician, who had problems with leg and could not climb ladders where it could have accommodated that restriction by providing a bucket truck to the workers). <i>Bartee v. Michelin North America Inc</i>., 374 F. 3d 906 (10<sup>th</sup> Cir.) 2004 (although employer provided a cart to get around the plant, Plaintiff required a larger one); <i>Skerski v Time Warner Cable Co</i>., 257 F. 3d 273, 285-286 (3d. Cir. 2001) (employee whose panic disorder prevented climbing might have been accommodated by the use of bucket truck). <i>Shannon v. Verizon New York Inc</i>., 519 F. Supp. 2d 304, 309 (N.D.N.Y. 2007) (disabled plaintiff able to perform job of field technician which has 100 pound weight requirement through the use of bucket truck); <i>Jackanin v Mount Sinai Hospital</i>, 2003 WL 402443 (S.D.N.Y. 2003) (factual dispute existed as to whether employer failed to reasonably accommodate disabled workers by providing adaptive computer equipment); <i>Fol</i> v <i>City of New York</i>, 2003 WL 21556938 at 8 (S.D.N.Y 2003) (factual issue for jury existed whether employer accommodate disabled employee's request to have ergonomic work station).</p>
<p class="continued">In the present case, the evidence is clear that the Grievant and her coworkers had been driving sit-down lifts for some twenty-four years. The Employer, however, decided to do away with the sit-down lifts and to use stand-up lifts because they were viewed as safer and more ergonomic. The Union submits, however, that even though the Employer decided to go to stand-up lifts it was under a duty to reasonably accommodate the Grievant and her doctors' requests that she be given a sit-down lift to perform her duties.</p>
<p class="continued">There is no question that if the Employer had honored the Grievant and her doctor's accommodation requests that she could have performed ail the essential functions of the forklift job. Indeed, the fact that this work had been performed for the previous twenty plus years with the drivers using sit-down lifts is proof positive that all aspects of the forklift job could be done on a sit-down lift. The Grievant's doctors made it very clear in their statements to the Employer that if the Grievant was assigned to a sit-down lift that she would not need any further accommodation in performing her job.</p>
<p class="continued">In the present situation, there are a number of ways that the Employer could have accommodated the Grievant and her doctors' requests for this reasonable accommodation. If it did not have a sit-down lift, then it could have rented one. The cited cases show that employers have been required to make such expenditures to accommodate disabled workers. The evidence shows, however, that the Employer did have sit-down lifts at the time of the Grievants discharge. At least three such lifts were being driven by forklift drivers who serviced the warehouse. There was a sit-down lift that was taken out of service and could have been repaired. Moreover, the Employer had a sit-down scissor lift available at the time of the Grievant's discharge which was used to move rolls of paper.</p>
<p class="continued">Upon a showing by a disabled worker that a reasonable accommodation exists, the burden shifts to the employer to prove the worker's requested accommodation imposes an &ldquo;undue hardship.&rdquo; <i>Jemigan v Bellsouth Communications</i>, 17 F. Supp. 3d 1317, 1321 (N.D.Ga 2014). The ADA defines &ldquo;undue hardship&rdquo; as &ldquo;an action requiring significant difficulty or expense in light of various factors set forth in 42 U.S.C. Section 12111 (10)(B). These factors essentially include the nature and cost of the accommodation, the size and financial resources of the covered entity, and the impact of the accommodation on the operation of the facility, including the impact of the ability of other employees to perform their duties and the impact on the facility's ability to conduct business.</p>
<p class="continued">Determining undue hardship &ldquo;requires a fact-specific, individualized inquiry. <i>Nunes v Walmart Stores</i>, 164 F. 3d 1243, 1247 (9<sup>th</sup> Cir. 1999). It requires &ldquo;concrete evidence.&rdquo; <i>Morton v United Parcel Service</i>, 272 F. 3d 1249, 156-157 (9<sup>th</sup> Cir. 2001). Assumptions or opinions are not sufficient to establish undue hardship. <i>Anderson v General Dynamics</i>, 589 F. 2d 397, 402 (9<sup>th</sup> Cir. 1979) (religious discrimination).</p>
<p class="continued">In the present case, Dart's Corporate, LOA/ADA Specialist ultimately made the decision as to whether or not the Grievant's request to be accommodated by permitting her to drive a sit-down forklift should be granted. According to the evidence the Grievant's request for accommodation was denied not because of any economic reason but because it was the LOA/ADA Specialist's understanding that it was unsafe to use the sit-down lift. The Company's September 26, 2004, letter to the Grievant denying her request to perform her job on a sit-down lift cited &ldquo;due to safety and ergonomic concerns&rdquo; as the basis for the accommodation denial.</p>
<p class="continued">The evidence clearly shows that this corporate representative based her decision and conclusion that it was unsafe to use the sit-down lift on unfounded assumption and speculation. Cross examination at the Arbitration hearing revealed the LOA/ADA Specialist believed that it was unsafe to continue to use the sit-down lift in the Augusta plant, yet she could not give any specific facts to support this conclusion. Indeed, she admitted that she was unaware of whether or not there had been any OSHA reportable accidents at the Augusta plant associated with the use of sit-down lifts; and, she was not aware of the significant problems with safety associated with the stand-up lifts.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union put into evidence instance after instance in which fork lift drivers had been seriously injured driving stand-up lifts similar to and/or exactly the same as the Clark 5500 lifts in operation by the Employer at the Augusta plant.<ftnote num="52"><para>See Union exhibit U-1</para></ftnote> Additionally, the Union offered evidence and expert testimony explaining why sit-down lifts were much safer than stand-up lifts; and that no one had been injured driving a sit-down lift at the Augusta plant which was of such nature to constitute an OSHA reportable accident.</p>
<p class="continued">In rebutial, the Employer offered little clear evidence to justify its assertion that the sit-down lifts were unsafe. The only forklifts shown to be unsafe at this plant are the stand-up lifts put into operation in 2014. Indeed, not only do the numerous lawsuits over this type of stand-up lift show how unsafe these lifts are, the evidence shows that a number of workers have experienced significant discomfort and physical problems due to the stand-up lifts since they have been put into operation at the Augusta Plant. In addition to the Grievant's testimony another long-term forklift operator also testified in detail concerning the severe physical problems suffered when using the Clark 5500 stand-up lifts; and, both testified that that they were aware of coworkers who had similar problems.</p>
<p class="continued">The Employer argues that the Plant Manager thoroughly investigated the stand-up lifts and in good faith determined that they were safer that sit-down lifts. The Plant Manager testified that he reviewed the OSHA website during his investigation. However, that review failed to notice that OSHA had posted on its website a warning concerning stand-up lifts and how forklift drivers have been severely injured when they back into low hanging stationary objects while driving standup-lifts.<ftnote num="53"><para>See Union exhibit U-3&hellip; a Safety and Health information Bulletin dated July 27, 2009 entitled <quote>Standup Forklift</quote> under-ride Hazards. That Internet posting states that one of the potential hazards faced by standup. Forklift operators is the crushing hazard that can arise when traveling in a standup lift to a facility where there are horizontal racks or beams.</para></ftnote> Moreover, the Plant Manager testified that he was unaware that any lawsuits had been filed against the manufacturer of the Crown stand-up forklift in question due to the design flaws in these lifts and the injuries forklift drivers have had while driving the forklifts. These lawsuits go back more than a decade and information relating to them is readily available on the internet.</p>
<p class="continued">The Employer bore the burden of proof to show that the accommodation sought by the Grievant caused an undue hardship. The Union submits that it absolutely failed to meet its burden. Indeed, the overwhelming evidence is that if any lifts were shown to be unsafe herein they were the Crown 5500 stand-up lifts, not the sit-down lifts.</p>
<p class="continued">It is the Union's position that the Employer even if it did not have a sit-down lift available for the Grievant to drive was required to lease and/or purchase this equipment in order to accommodate the Grievant's disability. The Union cited a number of cases where employers have been required to obtain, purchase or lease the necessary equipment to accommodate a disabled worker's needs and request for accommodation. Moreover, as the evidence clearly shows, that at the time of the Grievant's discharge the Employer had three sit-down lifts which were driven by the forklift drivers who worked in the warehouse section of the plant.</p>
<p class="continued">The evidence clearly shows that the Grievant was the most senior forklift driver in the plant and she had more seniority than these three warehouse forklift drivers. The Grievant requested that she be assigned to one of these forklifts and/or the warehouse forklift jobs. Here, the Employer, instead of talking with the Union concerning this accommodation request, went to the three forklift drivers who serviced the warehouse and asked them if they were willing to permit the Grievant to drive their assigned sit-down lifts and/or to perform their assigned duties.</p>
<p class="continued">On this point, the Union submits that the Employer was legally required to bargain over these matters with it and not the workers in question. <i>See Paul Mueller Company</i>, 332 NLRB 332 (2000) (supervisors polling employees as to their preferences as to their schedules unlawful direct dealing in violation of 8(a)5 of NLRA because employer never consulted with Union about proposed changes or asked its permission to discuss matters directly with employees); <i>The Detroit Edison Company</i>, 370 NLRB 564 (employer's distribution of memo to employees seeking to ascertain the employee's personal preference about the work station each employee wished to be <i>assigned unlawful, since action constituted direct dealing):</i></p>
<p class="continued">The ADA in 42 U.S.C. Section 12111(9)(8) provides in part&hellip;the term reasonable accommodation may include job restructuring, part time or modified work schedules, reassignment to a vacant position, acquisition or modification of equipment or devices. Here, the Grievant was the most senior forklift driver. She requested to be given a sit down lift to perform her normal duties and/or to be moved to performing her duties in the warehouse so she could use a sit down lift. Technically, she was not seeking a reassignment to another position. Rather, she was asking the Employer to restructure her job. The restructuring would permit her job to be performed using a sit-down lift as opposed to a stand-up lift. This type of accommodation falls clearly within the definition of a reasonable accommodation under the ADA.</p>
<p class="continued">Alternatively, she was seeking to be moved to the warehouse to perform the warehouse function of the forklift driver position. Arbitrator Richard L. Kanner in <i>City of Deabom Heights</i>, 101 LA 809, 815 (Kanner 1993) held that where a Police Lieutenant with a disability sought to move from midnight to day shifts to accommodate his disability that such action involved a &ldquo;job restructuring&rdquo; and not a reassignment to another position. The basis for this conclusion was that since this Police Lieutenant remained a Lieutenant after the job restructuring he was not reassigned to another position but rather to another shift.</p>
<p class="continued">There is nothing in the parties' CBA which prohibits the Employer from moving a worker from one location to another. The Grievant was not seeking to be reassigned to another position or job. She was seeking to remain a forklift driver but to perform her forklift job in the warehouse. All the forklift drivers worked together as a crew. Some workers servicing the plant production; some serviced the warehouse.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union submits that the compelling evidence shows that the Grievant has a disability as defined by the Americans with Disability Act; she was qualified for the forklift job with reasonable accommodation. The evidence is also clear that but for the denial of the reasonable accommodation of permitting the Grievant to use a sit-down forklift to perform her job that she would not have been discharged. Moreover, the Employer failed to prove that the requested accommodation would result in &ldquo;undue hardship.&rdquo; Thus, the Union has proven discrimination against the Grievant due to her disability and unjust discharge. Therefore, the Union submits that the Arbitrator should sustain the grievance.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union submits that the Arbitrator should order the Employer to reinstate the Grievant with full back pay, seniority and benefits to her former position of forklift driver and require the Employer to accommodate her disability by providing her a sit-down forklift to drive in the performance of her job.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union contends the discharge herein cannot stand. The Grievant was unjustly discharged. The Union requests that the Arbitrator sustain the grievance based on the conditions specified above. Finally, the Union asks the Arbitrator to retain jurisdiction over this matter if there is any dispute as to remedy.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>IV. STATEMENT OF THE ISSUE(S)</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The parties were unable to fully agree on the issue(s) to be addressed by the Arbitrator. Accordingly, it was agreed that each party, in its post-hearing brief, would submit its suggested statement of the issue or issues and the Arbitrator would then frame the issue(s) to be addressed.<ftnote num="54"><para>Per Arbitrator notes and audio file:</para>
<table-group columns="1" content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title/></head>
<body>
<table width="585">
<tr>
<td width="30%"><p></p></td>
<td width="70%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Have the parties communicated in advance of the hearing in an attempt to agree to a joint submission of the statement of the issue or issues to be addressed?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>We have not</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>We have not and it's probably a just cause issue&hellip; Whether there's just cause for the discharge of the Grievant, if not what is the appropriate remedy. We do have other Issues too, reasonable accommodation&hellip; But ifs probably assumed in the&hellip;! just dent want the Arbitrator to just see this as a just cause Issue.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Particularly since there's no discipline per se, at issue, or alleged misconduct The just cause Is barefy applicable.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>it does apply to discharge, she was separated, there was a discharge.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Okay, what we win do then&hellip; the parties can submit to me, in the post-hearing briefs, what they want as a statement of the issue(s), and then if the parties agree to allow the Arbitrator to frame the statement of the issue(s), I will do that.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>The parties are submitting the issues&hellip; we can do that in or briefs, that would be agreeable?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Arbitrator:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Right and we'll be doing briefs, too&hellip; But otherwise, are the parties giving me the authority to frame the issue(s)?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Grievant's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Yes.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Yes.</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</html>
</table-group></ftnote> As provided above&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">The Company/Employer offers that the issues to be addressed by the Arbitrator are:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Did Company's management have the right to change the forklift equipment used in the Augusta, Georgia facility in an effort to improve ergonomic and safety results, and if not what shall be the remedy?</p></li>
<li><p>Was Grievant discriminated against because of her alleged disability in violation of Article 27 of the Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA), and, if so, what shall be the remedy?</p></li>
</ol>
<p class="continued">The Union/Grievant offers that the Issue to be addressed by the Arbitrator is:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Whether there was &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; for the discharge of the Grievant? If not, what is the appropriate remedy?</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">Accordingly, in accordance with the agreement reached by the parties, through their respective Counsels, during the pre-hearing administrative conference to authorize the Arbitrator to frame the issues(s)&hellip;<b>The Arbitrator, therefore, frames the issue(s) as:</b></p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i>Did the Company violate provisions of the parties' collective bargaining agreement and/or any provisions of Federal law when it separated the Grievant, Ms. Tamela R. Wells, from employment on October 10, 2014. If so, what is the remedy?</i></p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>V. SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE, DISCUSSION, ANALYSIS, AND FINDINGS</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The record of the matter before the Arbitrator consists of the swom testimony of seven witnesses examined by the parties' Counsels and the Arbitrator during a hearing conducted April 22, 2015; and some one-thousand, one-hundred, and fifty-eight (1,158) pages of documentation offered and accepted while the hearing record was open, which was comprised of twelve (12) Arbitrator/Joint exhibits, eight (8) Company/Employer exhibits, and eighteen (18) Union/Grievant exhibits.<ftnote num="55"><para>Arbitrators exercising their own authority may request any additional documentation and information they have a reasonable basis to believe is <italic>germane</italic> to the case &lsqb;See Eikouri &amp; Elkouri, How Arbitration Works 6<superscript>th</superscript> Ed Ch.83.D p353&rsqb;. Often in the arbitration process matters are assumed or accepted without discussion or citation of authority, in that arbitrators often use arbitral notice; nevertheless, this Arbitrator, like other <quote>finders of facts,</quote> cannot ignore all of his prior teaming and experience, as explained in Converters Ink, 68 LA 593 (Sembower 1977), <quote>that is what the parties take into account when they complement him with their mutual selection as arbitrator.</quote></para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="left"><b>DISCUSSION, ANALYSIS, AND FINDINGS.</b></h4>
<p class="continued">This matter is before the Arbitrator on appeal by the Union under the provisions of Article 11 of the parties' CBA. As explained above, on October 16, 2014, Ms. Tamela Wells filed a formal grievance under the provisions of Article 10 of the parties' CBA over her separation from employment as a forklift operator at Dart Container Corporation, Solo Cup Operating facility in Augusta, Georgia. The grievance cited violation of Articles 9 and 10 of the parties' CBA, and provided among other things that the Company did not have just cause to terminate the Grievant. During the pre-hearing administrative conference the parties stipulated that the matter was properly before the Arbitrator and that there were no arbitrability questions.<ftnote num="56"><para>In response to the Arbitrator's request for a copy for the complete grievance file, the only document provided was the completed IBT Local 528 Grievance Report Form completed by Ms. Wells and filed October 16, 2014 showing receipt by management the same day. The parties' CBA, Article 10 provides for a three-step procedure. However, the grievance form does not provide documentation of the three-step process. Testimony provided that there was some sort of a meeting/hearing held on the grievance. However, neither management nor the Union provided any further documentation of the grievance procedure and both Counsels told the Arbitrator that what had been provided was all that there was. Accordingly, they confirmed/stipulated that the matter was properly before the Arbitrator and that there were no arbitrability issues, procedural or substantive.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">In May 2012, Dart Container Corporation acquired the Solo Cup Company and its manufacturing facility in Augusta, Georgia. For a number of years, prior to being acquired, the Solo Cup Company's Augusta facility leased sit-down style forklifts; and, these leased vehicles continued in operation after Dart Container purchased Solo Cup Company and its facility. Subsequently, with the leases on the sit-down forklifts about to expire, management at the Augusta facility decided not to renew the equipment leases and to purchase new stand-up style forklifts. The matter before the Arbitrator stims from the Company's decision to replace leased sit-down forklifts in use at its Augusta, Georgia facility with purchased stand-up forklifts.</p>
<p class="continued">The evidence shows in 2013 the Augusta Plant Manager was charged with the responsibility of replacing the leased forklifts used in the facility with purchased forklifts. Accordingly, in keeping with the Company's safety-focused culture, the Plant Manager, in conjunction with the facility's safety experts, investigated the best forklift options for the facility. After considering data about the history of forklift-related accidents and injuries in the facility, the physical configuration of the workspace in the facility, OSHA ergonomic guidance, and research related to the ergonomic benefits of a stand-up style forklift, the decision was made to replace the teased, sit-down style forklifts with stand-up style forklifts. These new stand-up forklifts were delivered in early February 2014<ftnote num="57"><para>The evidence shows that the Company was leasing eight Yale manufacture sit-down forklifts model number ERC045VG with a weight/capacity of 4,500 pounds. Five of these Yale sit-down lifts were dropped from service on March 17, 2014 and returned to the vendor. Two other Yale sit-down lifts were removed from service and returned to the vendor on December 19, 2014; and one Yale sit-down lift was removed from service when its service contract expired on August 11, 2014, but was not removed from the facility and sent back to the vendor until January 5, 2015. These eight Yale lifts were replaced by five new Crown stand-up forklifts model number RC55330-30-180TT with a weight/capacity of 3,000 pounds were delivered to the facility in early February 2014; and two Yale stand-up lifts model ESCO4OACN with weight/capacity of 4,000 pounds were delivered December 10, 2014. Finally, the eight replacement lift was a Toyota sit-down carton/clamp forklift model number BFBCHU25 with a weight/capacity of 5,000 pounds which is owned by Dart and was moved to Augusta from another facility.</para></ftnote>; and shortly thereafter the Company provided training and driver certification for all its Augusta facility forklift operators.<ftnote num="58"><para>The record shows that training/certification was provided to 30&plus; individuals during the period March 5-7, 2014, and additional employees were trained/certified on April 10, 2014.</para></ftnote> The Plant Manager testified that he briefed the employees on the new equipment<ftnote num="59"><para>See Employer exhibit, E-1.</para></ftnote>, and, that after the training they maintained both sit-down and stand-up lifts during a transition period through March to give the operators an opportunity to become acquainted with the new lifts. Then in early April the sit-down lifts &ldquo;went away.&rsquo;</p>
<p class="continued">As thoroughly outlined above, shortly after the introduction of the new Crown model RC5530 stand-up forklifts, the training and certification of the forklift operators, and the transition from use of the sit-down lifts to full time use of the stand-up lifts; in March 2014, the Grievant started experiencing back, leg, and ankle pain; complained about the problems and requested a leave of absence: and, submitted her initial request that she be allowed to use a sit-down style forklift as a disability accommodation when she returned to work.</p>
<p class="continued">Here the Company assigned a, Leave of Absence/Americans with Disabilities Act Specialist (LOA/ADA Specialist) in the corporate office to review and respond to Grievant's request. Following internal procedures, the assigned LOA/ADA Specialist reviewed the Grievant's request &ndash; Including the Grievant's preferred accommodation, a return to using a sit-down style forklift; as well as, the alternative accommodation of working for fifteen minutes off of the forklift for every hour spent working on the forklift. Based on the return to work restrictions from the Grievant's medical doctors, <i>the Company's LOA/ADA Specialist determined that</i>: (1) <i>Ms. Wells had a Qualifying disability that limits a major life function;</i> (2) <i>she was qualified to perform the essential functions of her position;</i> (3) it could approve and provide the alternate accommodation suggested by Ms. Wells' doctors, of working for fifteen minutes off of the forklift for every hour spent working on the forklift; and (4) it would implemented the approved accommodation upon the Grievant's return to work on May 2, 2014. The Grievant's preferred accommodation &mdash; a return to the old-style sit-down forklift was not accepted/approved because the LOA/ADA Specialist determined it would impede the facility's ability to realize the important ergonomic and safety gains sought in the switch to stand-up forklifts.<ftnote num="60"><para>See Employer exhibits E-5 and E-6, and Union exhibits U-9, U-10U-11, U-12, and U-13.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">About a month after returning to work on her regular twelve-hour schedule, and working in accordance with the approved accommodation, on May 23, 2014, the Grievant went to her primary care physician for her annual physical.<ftnote num="61"><para>This physical was for personal reasons and not required by the Company.</para></ftnote> During this examination her doctor inquired about the swelling in her legs and ankles, and Ms. Wells explained her work situation. As a result of his examination, the primary care physician provided Ms. Wells a written statement explaining the results of his examination and recommending that the Grievant not be required to stand all day long and allowed to return to operating a sit-down forklift.<ftnote num="62"><para>See Union exhibit, U-15.</para></ftnote> On June 24, 2014, the Grievant provided the Company her primary care physician's May 23<sup>rd</sup> written statement explaining her medical condition and the physician's opinion that it &ldquo;&hellip;would be better if the patient did not have to stand all day long&rdquo; and again suggesting a return to a sit-down forklift.</p>
<p class="continued">Accepting this May 23<sup>rd</sup> written statement as a <i>new accommodation request</i>, the Company's LOA/ADA Specialist sent a letter to the Grievant the same day, June 24, 2014, requesting further information. According to the Company, the Grievant failed to acknowledge or respond to the June 24<sup>th</sup> request. So after thirty-days passed with no communication from the Grievant, on July 25, 2014, the LOA/ADA Specialist sent a letter informing the Grievant that the request was being closed based on the Grievant stalling the interactive process, but that she could restart the process at any time by submitting the requested information.<ftnote num="63"><para>See Employer exhibits, E-7 and E-8.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">On August 7, 2014, the Grievant went back to see her primary care physician for a follow-up appointment. On this visit the doctor gave Ms. Wells a second letter providing that she could not stand for more than one hour without being able to be seated for thirty minutes, and again recommending that she be able to return to a sit-down forklift.<ftnote num="64"><para>See Union exhibit, U-16.</para></ftnote> Here the record shows that the Grievant provided this second letter to the local Human Resources (HR) manager on or about August 18, 2014.</p>
<p class="continued">Almost a month and a half later, when the Grievant reported to work the meaning of October 3, 2014, she was instructed to report to the facilities' personnel office. Upon arriving at the personnel office, the local HR manager asked Ms. Wells if she had <i>received</i> a letter in September from Dart Container. After responding that she had not received any letter from Dart, the local HR manager explained that Ms. Well's request for further accommodation was denied. The local HR manager then called her regional HR manager and the two HR managers and Grievant had a three-way discussion about the Grievant's situation. This discussion concluded with the Grievant being told to &ldquo;go home, go back to see her doctor(s) to see if there were any other accommodations that could be suggested;&rdquo; and, that they &lsqb;the local HR manager, the regional HR manager, and the Grievant&rsqb; would have another conversation on October 10<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<p class="continued">Upon returning to her residence, in the daily mail delivery, the Grievant received the letter from Dart that the local HR manager had discussed with her. That letter, dated, September 26, 2014, provided in part:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">On 8/18/14 you submitted medical documentation requesting the following disability accommodation:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>To use a sit-down type of forklift.</p></li>
<li><p>To work from a seated position for at least 30 minutes after each hour worked in a standing position.</p></li>
<li><p>Frequent breaks to keep your legs elevated.</p></li>
</ul>
<p class="continued">After reviewing your request and engaging in an interactive dialogue, unfortunately, we find we must deny your request for the following reasons:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">1. Due to the safety and ergonomic concerns encountered with the sit-down type of forklifts a safety-based decision was previously made to eliminate them from the plant by the end of 2014. There currently are 2-3 sit-down type of forklifts remaining in the distribution center which will also be eliminated by the end of the year for safety reasons. Despite the pending elimination of said forklifts deemed to be less safe, we still made inquiries of employees in those positions as to whether they might voluntarily exchange positions with you. We found no employees willing to make the exchange. Therefore, a sit-down type of forklift is not available.</p>
<p class="continued">2. After reviewing your current job functions, there are not a sufficient number of duties that can be done from a seated position to fill 30 minutes after each 1 hour worked standing on your feet. The ability to stand regularly (up to 67-100&percnt; of the time) is an essential function of your job. Under the ADA a &ldquo;qualified individual&rdquo; is a person who is able to perform all of the essential functions of the job with or without accommodation.</p>
<p class="continued">3. At this time there are no open positions for which you are qualified, nor are we aware of any such positions opening in the foreseeable future.</p>
<p class="continued">We believe we have made every effort to provide reasonable accommodation as requested and have exhausted all possibilities. Consequently, at this time we believe you are unable to perform the essential functions of your position with or without reasonable accommodation.</p>
<p class="continued">While we have made every effort to include you in the accommodation process it is possible that you have additional information that you feel we should consider. If so please present this additional information to your HR representative for review&hellip;&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">On October 10, 2014, the local HR and regional HR managers called the Grievant. The regional HR manager asked Ms. Wells if she had been back to see her doctor. Ms. Wells said she had. The regional HR manager then asked if there were any changes or any restrictions lifted. The Grievant responded that there were no changes in her medical condition and the restriction continued as previously explained by her doctor. The regional HR manager then told Ms. Wells, &ldquo;since &lsqb;her&rsqb; doctor didn't lift &lsqb;her&rsqb; restrictions that they &lsqb;the Company&rsqb; did not have a job for &lsqb;her then&rsqb; or in the future&hellip;&rdquo; and said good bye.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union's primary argument in this appeal is that the separation of the Grievant from her employment, her discharge, was not for just cause, as required by Article 5 of the parties' CBA, because the Grievant was discriminated against in violation of Article 27 of the parties' CBA, in that the Company did not provide a reasonable accommodation as required by the ADA.</p>
<p class="continued">While acknowledging that the Company had the right under the CBA to change the equipment used in the facility, that is, to move from using sit-down forklifts to using stand-up forklifts; the Union argues that because the Company failed to accommodate the Grievant's request, as stipulated by her physicians, to be allowed to use a sit-down forklift, which would have all-but eliminated her medical problems, it discriminated against the Grievant both under the ADA and the CBA.</p>
<p class="continued">While identifying Article 5 of the CBA as one of the relevant provisions of the contract, the Company has expressed no specific position on the just cause provision; its justification for, and defense of, the action separating the Grievant from her employment boils down to arguments that the Company(&lsquo;s):</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>had every right under Article 5 of the CBA to change the equipment used at the facility from sit-down type forklifts to stand-up type forklifts;</p></li>
<li><p>management exercised good-faith decision making in selecting the new stand-up forklifts for use at the Augusta facility by appropriately:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>reviewing and considering the facility's safety, health, and accident record;</p></li>
<li><p>researching the safety, ergonomic, and operational factors of the different types of forklifts available on the market; and</p></li>
<li><p>determining that stand-up style forklifts offered a safer and better operational fit for the Augusta facility;</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>did not discriminate against the Grievant in violation of Article 27 of the CBA because it acted appropriately and within the provisions of the ADA, in that:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>after being made aware of the Grievant's medical problems, it worked with, and engaged the Grievant in an interactive dialogue, to identify and offer accommodation;</p></li>
<li><p>for the first request for accommodation, it found that the Grievant had a qualifying disability, was qualified to perform the essential functions of her position with accommodation; and, accepted/approved/apply the alternate accommodation recommended by her doctors (e.g., while operating a stand-up forklift, being allowed to work off the lift for fifteen minutes after every hour on the lift); and</p></li>
<li><p>for the second request for accommodation, while determining that the two possible accommodations recommended by the Grievant's physicians were not reasonable (e.g., being allowed to return to using a sit-down lift which management had determined to be less safe than the stand-up lifts; and being allowed to be off her feet for thirty-minutes, sitting with her feet elevated, after every hour standing while operating the stand-up lift, because review of the Grievant's current job functions found that there were not a sufficient number of duties that could be done from a seated position to fill thirty-minutes after each hour worked standing on your feet) continued the interactive process in an attempt to identify a reasonable accommodation. Therefore&hellip;</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>had no choice but to separate the Grievant from her employment since her medical conditions had not changed; she and her doctors were not able to offer any other accommodations, therefore the collaborative and interactive process halted; and, since she could not continue to perform the essential functions of her job with or without accommodation. And, therefore,</p></li>
<li><p>had just cause to separate the Grievant.</p></li>
</ol>
<p class="continued">The Union argues that in the present situation, it and the Employer agreed in their collective bargaining agreement that the Employer must have &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; for discharging or separating an employee from employment. This agreement is documented in Article 5, the Management Right's clause which provides in part &ldquo;Except as expressly modified by the specific provisions of the Agreement, and subject to the grievance and arbitration procedure provided herein, the Company also has the right to promote, suspend, demote, discipline or <i>discharge for just cause</i> or transfer employees.&rdquo; As the Company has not disputed the Union's position, the Arbitrator finds that the separation of the Grievant from her employment (her discharge) must have been for just cause.</p>
<p class="continued">As pointed out by the Union the term &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; does not have a precise definition, and Arbitrators are usually required to consider different factors when defining and applying the term in different situations. Even though the parties' CBA does not define the term &ldquo;just cause,&rdquo; in this case, the parties, and their agreement, authorize the Arbitrator to hear and determine the issue(s). While an Arbitrator cannot &ldquo;add to, detract from, alter or otherwise amend in any way the provisions of the Agreement&rdquo;; by selecting the undersigned to hear and determine the issue(s) the parties are asking him to give meaning to the term &ldquo;just cause,&rdquo; and to draw upon his knowledge, experience, wisdom, and appropriate references to fairly decide the matter. Therefore, what constitutes &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; is a question the Arbitrator is to decide.</p>
<p class="continued">The elements or factors that need to be considered when giving meaning to the term &ldquo;just cause,&rdquo; vary depending on the action taken by the employer. Where as in this case, the CBA has a clear &ldquo;cause&rdquo; provision, with or without a delineating adjective like &ldquo;just&rdquo; or &ldquo;sufficient,&rdquo; that provision includes a number of substantive and procedural elements. Primary among its substantive elements is the requirement that enough proof exists that the employee engaged in the conduct for which he or she was discharged. For example, where an employee's actions or conduct result in discharge being a form of discipline, like most other Arbitrators, the undersigned usually applies some form of Daugherty's &ldquo;seven tests&rdquo; in determining whether or not the elements of &ldquo;cause&rdquo; have been met.<ftnote num="65"><para>Koven, Adolph M. And Susan L. Smith <quote>Just Cause: The Seven Tests</quote> Page 10, Colorace Publications Inc., San Francisco, CA 1985; See also <italic>Discipline and Discharge in Arbitration</italic> (Norman Brand Ed. 1998). Courts and commentators cite numerous sources for the Daughterty test, including Grief Bros. Cooperage Corp (1964), 42 LA 555 and Whirlpool Corp. (1972) 58 LA 421. Whatever its exact origins, and regardless of whether the concept is labeled <quote>good cause,</quote> <quote>just cause,</quote> or some other similar term, there is no dispute that the seven tests were established and refined by Daugherty and that they have been used routinely for over 30 years</para></ftnote> For, non-disciplinary separations, other elements or factors need to be considered.</p>
<p class="continued">In the case at-hand, the parties' agreement also has a general &ldquo;fair employment practices and equal opportunity&rdquo; clause, Article 27, which prohibits the Employer, as well as the Union, from discriminating against any employee based on various factors including disability. Here, citing <i>Thermo King Corporation</i>, the Union points to Arbitrator Dworkin's decision/award<ftnote num="66"><para>102 LA 612, 614-615 (Dworkin 1993) as discussed offered in the Union's post-hearing brief.</para></ftnote> considering of a just cause provision where, as with the subject case, the Grievant alleged and the Union asserted that the Employer could not discharge the Grievant without attempting to make a reasonable accommodation for the Grievant's disability under the provisions of the ADA. While other arbitration decisions/awards, published or not, are not binding, every Arbitrator weighs the value of such cited dedsions/awards based on the similarity of the terms and situation addressed to the facts presented in the case at hand.</p>
<p class="continued">Both parties point to Article 27 of their CBA as relevant, the Union has argued that the provisions and principles of the ADA should be followed in determining &ldquo;just cause;&rdquo; and, the Company has not refuted that position. Accordingly, the undersigned concurs with the Union's position that the provisions and principles of the ADA should be followed and considered in determining if the Employer had &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; to separate the Grievant. Clearly, the weight of arbitral opinion since the enactment of the ADA has been to apply the ADA in instances where the agreement specifically covers disabilities but fails to address accommodations.</p>
<p class="continued">The ADA provides that &ldquo;&lsqb;n&rsqb;o covered entity shall discriminate against a qualified individual with a disability because of that disability&hellip;&rdquo; in regard to various aspects of employment inducing&hellip;discharge.<ftnote num="67"><para>42 U.S.C. &sect;12112(a)</para></ftnote> In addition, the ADA provides that the term &ldquo;discriminate&rdquo; includes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;&hellip;not making reasonable accommodation to the known physical or mental limitations of an otherwise qualified individual with a disability&hellip;<i>unless &lsqb;it&rsqb; can demonstrate that the accommodation would impose an undue hardship on the operation of &lsqb;its&rsqb; business</i>&hellip;.&rdquo; &lsqb;Emphasis added&rsqb;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Here, the Employer has the burden to prove &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; for the discharge; the Union has the burden to prove discrimination; the applicable quantum of proof is a preponderance of the evidence.<ftnote num="68"><para>As provided in Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, How Arbitration Works at 948-950 (6<superscript>th</superscript> Ed. 2003) Most arbitrators apply the preponderance of the evidence standard to ordinary discipline and discharge cases.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">Accordingly, to prove discrimination by sustaining its claim of failure to provide reasonable accommodations, the Union must prove that:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>the Grievant has a disability, as defined by the ADA;</p></li>
<li><p>despite her disability, she was qualified for the position held, with or without reasonable accommodation; and</p></li>
<li><p>if accommodation was required, she was denied a reasonable accommodation.</p></li>
</ol>
<p class="continued">The ADA defines the term &ldquo;disability&rdquo; as:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>A physical or mental impairment that substantially limits one or more of an individual's major life activities;</p></li>
<li><p>A record of such an impairment; or</p></li>
<li><p>Being regarded as having such an impairment as described in subsection 1.</p></li>
</ol>
<p class="continued">In the case at hand, the evidence clearly shows that: (1) three different medical providers, the Grievant's chiropractor, orthopedist, and primary care physician, found that she suffered back and ankle problems, had a history of such impairments, and that recent work conditions exacerbated the problems manifesting in increased swelling in the legs, venous insufficiency and edema; and, (2) the Company concurred and found the Grievant had a disability as defined by the ADA. Furthermore, the Company's actions after making its initial determination that the Grievant had a covered disability showed it continued to regarded her as having such a disability. Accordingly, as to the first prong of the inquiry, the Arbitrator finds the Grievant, Ms. Wells, had and continues to have a disability as defined by the ADA.</p>
<p class="continued">As for whether or not the Grievant, despite her disability, was or is qualified for the position she held, with or without accommodation &mdash; The ADA defines a &ldquo;qualified individual&rdquo; as an individual with a disability who, with or without, reasonable accommodation, can perform the essential functions of the employment position that individual held or desired. Here, the Grievant performed all aspects of her position as a forklift operator at the Dart/Solo Augusta facility for some twenty-four years until the equipment she was required to operate was changed from a sit-down style lift to a stand-up style lift; and, could continue performing the essential functions of her job with reasonable accommodation. There can be no question that the Grievant, prior to the introduction of the stand-up forklift, was qualified to perform all aspects, induding the essential functions, of the position of forklift operator. Furthermore, the Company, in addressing the Grievant's initial request for accommodation, found that she met the ADA definition of a &ldquo;qualified individual&rdquo; because she could perform the essential functions of her job, with or without accommodation, when it approved the initial request granted, and applied the accommodation of fifteen minutes off the stand-up lift for every hour on the lift. However, in denying her second request the Company determined she was not a &ldquo;qualified individual&rdquo; because she could not perform the essential functions of her job without accommodation.</p>
<p class="continued">As to the essential functions of the position the Grievant held and desired, the Company argues that there are two different forklift jobs, each located in a different &ldquo;department&rdquo; and having its on position description<ftnote num="69"><para>The Union argues that all forklift operators In the August facility are the same and perform the same, perform the same duties and functions, and that the CBA does not make any distinctions between forklift operators&hellip;The Company addressed this issue in its post-hearing brief under the title of <quote>Factual Inaccuracles</quote> arguing that there were two different forklift positions and that the duties and essential functions differ, and provided copies of both position descriptions. The Company provided copies of two position descriptions (PDs), one with the title <quote>forklift operator,</quote> the other with the title <quote>receiving power truck operator.</quote> The first PD (forklift operator) provides that the <quote>essential duties and responsibilites</quote> are:</para>
<ordered-list token="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<item><para>Service various production departments with packaging materials and raw materials.</para></item>
<item><para>Read scheduled, accurately record movement of packaging materials on movement sheets, using addition, subtraction, multitiplication, and division.</para></item>
<item><para>Operate carousel, assist in clearing conveyer jams, palletize cases, wrap pallets, baler, trash compactor, and run production tickets.</para></item>
<item><para>The second PD (receiving power truck operator located in the warehouse) provides that the <quote>essential duties and responsibilities</quote> are:</para></item>
</ordered-list>
<ordered-list token="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<item><para>Unload inbound trucks.</para></item>
<item><para>Check in material, i.e., count items damage.</para></item>
<item><para>Stores material in assigned areas.</para></item>
<item><para>Delivers materials to manufacturing and spare parts.</para></item>
</ordered-list>
<para>In addition both PCs provide a general job summary. The two PDs describe different job requirements (education, work experience, certificates, skills) but provide the same physical requirements (except for vision requirements which differ between the two PDs), woridng conditions, etc. The first PD (forklift operator was last revised June 13, 2012; the second PD (receiving power truck operator) was last revised June 3, 2008.</para></ftnote> Review of the two position descriptions (PDs) shows that one (titled receiving power truck operator) last revised in 2008, covers positions located in the warehouse only, and has different essential duties and responsibilities than; the second PD (titled forklift operator) last revised in 2012 and covering positions servicing &ldquo;various departments.&rdquo; It is noted, however, that neither PD describes the &ldquo;primary&rdquo; function or duty of an employee assigned to perform the described work, that is, &ldquo;to drive/operate a forklift.&rdquo; Clearly the more recent PD, the one for forklift operator, appears to be the more inclusive. Finally, each PD has a provision providing that &ldquo;The physical demands described&hellip;are representative of those that must be met by the employee to successfully perform the essential functions of the job. &lsqb;And that&rsqb; Reasonable accommodations may be made to enable individuals with disabilities to perform the essential functions.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">Based on the evidence available, as to the second prong of the inquiry, the Arbitrator finds, as the Company found regarding the Grievant's initial request for accommodation, that the Grievant, Ms. Wells, did and does meet the ADA definition of a &ldquo;qualified individual.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">The only reason the Company found that the Grievant did not meet the definition of a &ldquo;qualified individual&rdquo; in reviewing and deciding her second request for accommodation, was that it denied the accommodations requested. <i>So to decide this matter it is necessary to review the Company's decisions in the second request</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">Clearly, the genesis of the Grievant's separation/discharge was management's decision to change the forklifts used at the Augusta facility from a sit-down type to a stand-up type. The Grievant had worked numerous years using a sit-down forklift without suffering the medical problems that manifested in a short period of time after being required to switch from the sit-down lift to a stand-up lift. Furthermore, after each of the Grievant's three different medical providers, a chiropractor, orthopedist, and her primary care physician, examined her, all attributed her medical problems to prolonged standing in the almost stationary position required to operate the stand-up forklift over an extended twelve-hour shift. And, while suggesting an alternative accommodation, all recommended that allowing the Grievant to return to using a sit-down forklift was preferred since it would not just lessen her medical problems, but would most likely eliminate them.</p>
<p class="continued">Much has been presented and argued regarding the Company's decision to change from the use of sit-down forklifts to stand-up forklifts. Here the Arbitrator agrees with the Company, as basically stipulated to be the Union at the hearing and in its briefs that management did and does have the right under the provisions of Article 5, of the CBA, to &ldquo;change or eliminate existing methods of operations, equipment or facilities&hellip;.&rdquo; This provision clearly provides that management had the right, for whatever reason, to move from the use of leased sit-down forklifts to the use of self-owned stand-up forklifts. Furthermore, the Arbitrator does not doubt that the Augusta Plant manager did attempt to conduct some review and investigation to determine the product he felt would best meet the Company's needs in Augusta. And, while the compact design of the selected stand-up forklift, may have been determined as better suited to a workspace like the Augusta facility; whether or not the newly purchased stand-up forklift is safer than the previously leased sit-down forklift requires more evidence than simply the opinion of the Plant manager, and more importantly the LOA/ADA Specialist.</p>
<p class="continued">Regarding the Plant manager's review and study in preparation for the purchase of the new stand-up forklifts, the ONLY evidence provided by the Company was the manager's testimony. Not a single piece of documentation, outside of the briefing slides<ftnote num="70"><para>Employer exhibit, E-1.</para></ftnote> and vendor provided manuals<ftnote num="71"><para>Arbitrator/Joint exhibit, A/J-6.</para></ftnote> was offered into evidence to support the manager's testimony regarding his pre-purchase review, analysis, and investigation. There was no evidence provided that the Plant manager sought advice from anyone or any place outside of the Company and the vendor in his efforts to research available forklifts, their advantages/disadvantages, safety record, or anything else.</p>
<p class="continued">In its post-hearing brief the Company provided that it chose &lsquo;&ldquo;not to address the testimony of the Union's proffered forklift &ldquo;expert,&rdquo; as the witness' testimony confirmed he had not visited the facility, nor did he have any knowledge of the Company's operations&hellip;;&rsquo;&rdquo; and, dismissed that testimony as &ldquo;immaterial&rdquo; to the questions presented. However, it failed to offer any evidence that the Union witness's testimony regarding the &ldquo;safety&rdquo; of sit-down and stand-up forklifts in general was incorrect of should not be considered. That witness clearly testified that much of the information he provided the Union, including the judicial cases cited, was readily available on the internet. Yet, the company provided no similar evidence for its position. In an effort to determine if the witness was correct, the Arbitrator was able to identify and locate considerable information on the safety of forklifts in general,<ftnote num="72"><para>Including the OSHA Safety and Health Bulletin SHIB 07-27-2009 on Standup Forklift Under-ride Hazards, offered into evidence by the Union (part of U-1); as well as more specific information relating to the safety of stand-up forklifts &lsqb;e.g. a report issued by the National Academy of Forensic Engineers in June 2008 titled <quote>Forensic Engineering Assessment of Safety for Stand Up Forklifts</quote> by Richard M. Ziernicki and Ben T. Rallsback.&rsqb;</para></ftnote> as well as, guidance on deciding between sit-down and stand-up forklifts<ftnote num="73"><para>For example, Kelby Ergo Design a full service workplace process improvement, efficiency and ergonomics consulting firm based in the Twin Cities metro area of Minneapolis, Minnesota, in 2014 put out a document providing considerations for deciding between sit-down and stand-up forklifts suggesting things to consider for in each, such as that&hellip;Sit-down Forklift Physical Demands: low energy expenditure, neck rotation and extension, trunk twisting (driving in reverse), and whole body vibration transmitted through pelvis to the spine. Verses Traditional Stand-up Forklifts Physical Demands: higher energy expenditure due to more physically active work, whole body vibration absorbed by the legs, some stability provided by hip rest/pads, less trunk twisting, knee stress. And, Sit-down Forklift Safety Considerations: driver protected by vehicle frame (from falling objects) and seat belt, pedestrians can be run over by rear wheels if too close to moving forklift, blind spot located in rear quadrant when driving in reverse If driver doesn't/can't twist trunk and rotate head/neck for full view. Verses Traditional Standup Forklifts Safety Considerations: driver may or may not be protected by vehicle frame, foot crush injuries may occur when drivers extend foot out, mast elements may create blind sport. As well as other considerations.</para></ftnote>, in one simple internet inquiry; which clearly showed, as the Union's witness testified, that there are advantages and disadvantages to both sit-down and stand-up forklifts; as well as between makers and models of each type lift.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union offered into evidence copies of the Company's OSHA Form 300, Log of Work-Related Injuries and Illnesses for the years 2010 through 2014; and internal Company Supervisor Report of Occupational injury or Near Miss, for the years 2011 through 2014, it requested and received from the Company. The Company referred to the Union's exhibits both during the hearing and in post-hearing briefs but did not expand on or further explain that information. Cross examination of the Plant manager clearly showed he was not aware of the various judicial opinions offered into evidence by the Union; nor of the OSHA Safety and Health Bulletin issued on stand-up forklifts. Whether or not the particular cases cited by the Union specifically concerned the style lift purchased by Dart or resulted in findings against the Crown Equipment Company is not material. However, one would expect even a nominal research effort, particularly one that was supposed to have included looking at the OSHA website, as the Plant manager testified having done, would have found the safety and health bulletin. The point is, the Company failed to offer concrete evidence to support its manager's testimony.</p>
<p class="continued">As for the facilities past safety record &ndash; The Company, in its post-hearing rebuttal discounts and refutes the Union's assertions and argues that the evidence shows the safety results the Company experienced after the introduction of stand-up style forklifts reinforces that the switch has led to a safer workplace. However, the Arbitrator's review of Union exhibits five and six revealed <i>none of the incidence reported on the OSHA Form 300s provided for the years 2010 through 2014 involved forklift operators or receiving truck operators</i>. If any of these incidents involved the operation of a forklift, that forklift was apparently not operated by a forklift operator, but another employee (e.g., a packer, pressman, machine operator, etc.) using the forklift on an occasional basis. As for the eleven (11) Supervisor Reports of Occupational Injury or Near Misses provided for the period 2011 through 2014, seven (7) involved what was identified as PTO drivers (only three of which could be identified as forklift operators) having incidents between 2011 and 2013; and, two (2) involved PTO drivers (both identified as forklift operators) incidents in 2014. Accordingly, while the record does show that there were only two incidents that occurred since the Introduction of the stand-up lifts, one in April and one in June 2014 and both involved forklift operators; the Arbitrator finds the evidence does NOT clearly show marked improvement in safety between what occurred before the introduction of stand-up forklifts and after the introduction of stand-up forklifts, since the data only covered two months after the Introduction of the new forklifts.</p>
<p class="continued">With regard to the Company's denial of the Grievant's request that she be allowed to return to using a sit-down forklift &mdash; the first time because the LOA/ADA Specialist determined&hellip;</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;&hellip;it would impede the facility's ability to realize the important ergonomic and safety gains sought in the switch to stand-up forklifts;&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">and the second time because the LOA/ADA Specialist determined&hellip;</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;Due to the safety and ergonomic concerns encountered with the sit-down type of fork-lifts safety-based decision was previously made to eliminate them from the plant by the end of the of 2014. There currently are 2-3 sit-down type of fork-lifts remaining in the distribution center which will also be eliminated by the end of the year for safety reasons. Despite the pending elimination of said fork-lifts deemed to be less safe, we still made inquiries of employees in those positions as to whether they might voluntarily exchange positions with you. We found no employees willing to make the exchange. Therefore, a sit-down type of fork-lift is not available.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Company argues that &ldquo;the LOA/ADA Specialists' determinations were grounded in the following rationale: (1) potentially jeopardizing a facility's safety program by reversing safety-specific initiatives, particularly when said program is showing positive results, is inherently imprudent; and (2) future injuries on reintroduced sit-down forklifts could expose the Company to untold liability after publically broadcasting to its workers that said forklifts were a less safe equipment option.&rdquo; Citing <i>Jarvis v. Potter, 500 F.3d 113, 1124 (10<sup>th</sup> Cir. 2007)</i> the Company argues the &ldquo;LOA/ADA Specialists' reliance on speculative, yet foreseeable, harm was not an unreasonable approach, particularly since the law encourages proactive measures, and does not require &lsqb;an employer&rsqb; to wait for a serious injury before eliminating a direct threat.&rdquo; Noting that &ldquo;the Union and perhaps even the Arbitrator may disagree,&rdquo; the Company goes on, citing <i>EEOC v. Beverage Disfrib. Co. LLC, 780 F.3d 1018; U.S. App. LEXIS 4067</i>, as well as <i>Jarvis</i>, to caution that &ldquo;disagreement, from Grievant and Fact Finder alike, is legally immaterial in determining whether the Company's reasonable belief affords it an affirmative defense to claims of disability discrimination.&rdquo;</p>
<p class="continued">Both cases cited by the Company involve the issue of &ldquo;direct threat&rdquo; Under the law a &ldquo;direct threat&rdquo; involves a significant risk of substantial harm to the health and safety of the person or others that cannot be eliminated or reduced by reasonable accommodation.&rdquo;<ftnote num="74"><para>29 C.F.R &sect;1630.2(r).</para></ftnote> As explained by the Court in <i>EEOC v. Beverage</i>, and <i>Jarvis</i>, the existence of a direct threat is an affirmative defense to a statutory claim of discrimination. For this defense, the defendant (the Employer) has to show that it <i>reasonably determined that the plaintiff</i> (the party raising the discrimination claim) <i>posed a direct threat</i>. The fact-finder does not independently assess whether it believes that the <i>employee posed a direct threat</i>, but determines instead whether the employer's decision was <i>objectively reasonable</i>.</p>
<p class="continued">It is important to note, that the cases cited concern the &ldquo;direct threat&rdquo; of the employee or person, not a threat from a piece of equipment In its arguments, the Company has failed to make the distinction between: (1) whether it believes the Grievant posed or poses a direct threat herself; (2) whether the concern is that the sit-down forklift posed or poses a direct threat because management deemed it an unsafe piece of equipment; or (3) if the direct threat is posed by allowing the Grievant to again drive a sit-down lift. If the Company is asserting that the Grievant poses a direct threat, it has failed to provide any evidence or argument that this is the case. If the Company is asserting that the sit-down lift poses the direct threat, it is misapplying the &ldquo;direct threat&rdquo; defense. If it is asserting that allowing the Grievant to return to operating the sit-down lift poses the &ldquo;direct threat&rdquo; again it's misapplying the defense and cannot support such an assertion because the evidence shows that the Grievant drove a sit-down lift for some twenty-four years without any accidents or injuries.</p>
<p class="continued">In requesting to be allowed to use a sit-down forklift the Grievant and her medical providers believed the request to be reasonable since there were sit-down forklifts available; and, as the Union points out, the Courts and Arbitrators have held that employers, as part of the reasonable accommodation obligation must provide special <i>and/or</i> modified equipment to enable disabled workers to perform the essential functions of their jobs.</p>
<p class="continued">It is true that the Company did not have to provide the preferred accommodation requested by the Grievant, to be allowed to use a sit-down forklift; and, as it did in the Initial request, where more than one accommodation was suggested by the employee, can choose the accommodation it finds reasonable, so long as it is effective. Where the employee offers only one accommodation, in the interactive process envisioned by the ADA, it is anticipated that the employer will offer alternative suggestions and discuss their effectiveness with the employee. In the subject case, however, the evidence suggests the &ldquo;interactive process&rdquo; followed by Dart was mostly one-sided, the Company waiting for the Grievant and/or her medical providers to suggest the accommodation and the Company reacting to that request When at the end the Grievant and her medical providers could only recommend one accommodation, allowing the Grievant to use a sit-down lift, the Company made no further accommodation suggestions it simply separated the Grievant. While it claimed it looked for other positions that the Grievant was qualified for and no openings were available, or were projected to be available; it could have &ldquo;thought-outside-the-box&rdquo; and been a little proactive by suggesting changing the Grievant's work schedule from a twelve hour schedule to an eight hour schedule; and, while it is not required to create a new position it could have restructured the Grievant's position; or, while no employees volunteered to exchange positions with the Grievant, the Company could have exercised its management right as provided in Article 5 and transferred the Grievant and one of the warehouse receiving power truck operators to and from each other's position.<ftnote num="75"><para>The Arbitrator notes that bath the Company and Union addressed management's questioning of the forklift drivers in the warehouse to see if they would be willing to swap positions with a forklift operator in the production area. The Company argues that &ldquo;Asking the warehouse forklift drivers to consider swapping position was a function of the ADA interactive process, directed by the LOA/ADA Specialist in order to fulfil the Company's legal obligations under the federal law, an issue beyond the scope of the CBA. It was not intended, and in fact did not encroach upon the Union's right as the exclusive bargaining agent on matters contained in the CBA. The Union submits that the Company was legally required to bargain over these matters with it and not go directly to the employees; and provided a National Labor Relations Board opinion addressing a similar situation <italic>Paul Mueller Company, 332 NLRB 332 (2000)</italic>. Since this issue was not included in the subject Grievance and the Union did not asked the Arbitrator to consider the matter, the Arbitrator will not address the matter.</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">While the Company did not have to show the Grievant that providing her requested accommodation would present an undue hardship to the Company, <i>it needed to show the Arbitrator that providing the requested accommodation would require an undue hardship as defined and envisioned by the ADA</i> &ndash; And, while the Company, in its post hearing brief provided that the LOA/ADA Specialist(s) determined that &ldquo;reintroduction of a sit-down style forklift would be an undue hardship on the operations of the business under the ADA&rdquo; &ndash; Simply <i>put, the Company did not provide any evidence to the Arbitrator that the Grievant's reouested accommodation. to be allowed to use a sit-down forklift required significant difficulty or expense, or attempt to address the factors outlined in the ADA</i><ftnote num="76"><para>Undue hardship is defined in the ADA as:</para>
<block-quote><para>(A) In general &mdash; The term <quote>undue hardship</quote> means an action requiring significant difficulty or expense, when considered in light of the factors set forth in subparagraph (B).</para>
<para>(B) Factors to be considered in determining whether an accommodation would impose an undue hardship on a covered entity, factors to be considered include</para>
<block-quote><para>(i) the nature and cost of the accommodation needed under this chapter;</para>
<para>(ii) the overall financial resources of the facility or facilities involved in the provision of the reasonable accommodation; the number of persons employed at such facility; the effect on expenses and resources, or the impact otherwise of such accommodation upon the operation of the facility;</para>
<para>(iii) the overall financial resources of the covered entity; the overall size of the business of a covered entity with respect to the number of its employees; the number, type, and location of its facilities; and</para>
<para>(iv) the type of operation or operations of the covered entity, including the composition, structure, and functions of the workforce of such entity; the geographic separateness, administrative, or fiscal relationship of the facility or facilities in question to the covered entity</para></block-quote></block-quote></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">As the Union points out, the Courts have ruled determining undue hardship &ldquo;requires a fact-specific, individualized inquiry<ftnote num="77"><para>Nunes v. Walmart Stores, 164 F.3d 1243, 1247 (9<superscript>th</superscript> Cir. 1999)</para></ftnote>; based on concrete evidence;<ftnote num="78"><para>Morton v. Untied Parcel Service, 272 F.3d 1249, 156-157 (9<superscript>th</superscript> Cir. 2001)</para></ftnote> and that assumptions or opinions are not sufficient to establish undue hardship.<ftnote num="79"><para>Anderson v. General Dynamics, 589 F. 2d 397, 402 (9<superscript>th</superscript> Cir. 1979</para></ftnote></p>
<p class="continued">While, the Company argues the Arbitrator should accept the LOA/ADA Specialist's determination because she relied on &ldquo;speculative, yet foreseeable, harm;&rdquo; the fact is the decision was based on pure speculation and nothing but speculation and personal opinion &mdash; The unsubstantiated, unsupported opinion of the Plant manager that the stand-up lifts were safer than the sit-down lifts, as well as, the equally unvalidated opinion of the LOA/ADA Specialists. Clearly, the LOA/ADA Specialists' decisions, particularly with regard to allowing the Grievant to use a sit-down forklift, were not based on objectively determined facts &ndash; Or at least the evidence does not point to any concrete factual evidence.</p>
<p class="continued">The Company failed to show by a preponderance of &ldquo;factual and case specific&rdquo; evidence that granting the Grievant's accommodation request to be allowed to use a sit-down forklift was unreasonable because it would require &ldquo;significant difficulty,&rdquo; not merely speculated problems based on unfound opinion; or expense, considering the nature and cost of the accommodation, the overall financial resources of the facility and Company, and other factors identified in the ADA.<ftnote num="80"><para>42 U.S.C. &sect;1211(10)(A)&hellip;factors to be considered Include &mdash;</para>
<ordered-list token="lc-roman" bind-char="paren" bind-to="left-right">
<item><para>the nature and cost of the accommodation needed under this chapter;</para></item>
<item><para>the overall financial resources of the facility or facilities involved in the provision of the reasonable accommodation; the number of persons employed at such facility; the effect on expenses and resources, or the impact otherwise of such accommodation upon the operation of the facility;</para></item>
<item><para>the overall financial resources of the covered entity; the overall size of the business of a covered entity with respect to the number of its employees; the number, type, and location of its facilities; and</para></item>
<item><para>the type of operation or operations of the covered entity, including the composition, structure, and functions of the workforce of such entity; the geographic separateness, administrative, or fiscal relationship of the facility or facilties in question to the covered entity.</para></item>
</ordered-list></ftnote> In fact, during direct examination when the Plant manager was questioned about the decision to purchase the new sit-down fork lifts he testified that cost was not an issue and said &ldquo;how do you place a dollar value on the safety of your workforce.&rdquo;<ftnote num="81"><para>Per Arbitrator notes and audio file:</para><table-group columns="1" content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title/></head>
<body>
<table width="585">
<tr>
<td width="30%"><p></p></td>
<td width="70%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>So the decision &lsqb;to purchase the new stand-up forklifts&rsqb; was not reactive to one or more injuries Involved with fork trucks.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Plant manager.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>No. I run a program and i've been in manufacturing nearly 25 years, and I always thought of myself as a proactive critical thinker. And I run a proactive program I don't; 1 think that you as a business leader you miss the boat if you're only ever reacting to incidents after they occur. The trick is to prevent the incidents from ever occurring in the first place. And that's kind of my thought process when I looked at these stand up lifts was seeing the ergonomics issues kind of on the rise in the facility that ultimately lead to injuries. What could we do to mitigate that risk and this was the big one.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Was cost in any way part of the consideration at the time of the decision?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Plant manager</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>No. I mean, and here again <i>how do you place a dollar value on the safety of your workforce</i>. You've got the cost of the lifts. I will say that <i>since Dart acquired Solo Cup I don't want to say that money is not an issue, but Dart is welt capitalized</i> and I had no problems making the business case to make this kind of transition to stand ups. &lsqb;Emphasis added&rsqb;</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Were the standup lifts significantly less expensive than sit down lifts?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Plant manager:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>They were basically the same price. They were right around &dollar;30,000 apiece. I don't recall exactly what that specific number is but like I said cost realty wasn't much of an Issue. Again you're buying a piece of equipment, you're no longer leasing it, so the thought process is when you buy it you own it, you're going to have to live with it, so do your homework, and that's what we did.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Company's Counsel:</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Were the individualized circumstances or preference of any single employee considered during your decision making process?</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>Plant manager.</p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>No, I make decisions collectively, for the good of the company, the good of the site. Since I came to Augusta that's what I've always, i have plant wide meetings pretty much every month and we talk about safety, quality, service, costs, and my commitment to <i>keeping my 225 employees employed</i>. And you do that by running a safe plant with the highest quality, with the best service, and you do it efficiently so that Its profitable for the company to keep us there. Because my job relies on that facility as well. So it was the right move for the site as a whole. &lsqb;Emphasis added&rsqb;</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</html>
</table-group></ftnote> On this point the evidence shows the Company spent in the neighborhood of &dollar;210,000.00 purchasing seven new stand-up forklifts,<ftnote num="82"><para>The Plant manager testified that the cost of the sit-down and stand-up lifts were about the same, &dollar;30,000 each, and he purchased two Yale standup forklifts, model ESC040ACN, and five Crown stand-up forklifts, model RC5530-30-180TT&hellip;At approximately &dollar;30,000 each that's &dollar;210,000.00.</para></ftnote> and relocated the &ldquo;carton clamp&rdquo; sit-down forklift from another Dart facility &ndash; But refused to spend &dollar;30,000 (about 15&percnt; of the cost of the seven new forklifts) for a sit-down lift for the Grievant to use; or to rent a new sit-down forklift, or even relocate a sit-down lift for the Grievant to use from one of Darts' other facilities.</p>
<p class="continued">Accordingly, the Arbitrator finds that the Company failed to provide the Grievant a reasonable accommodation and failed to show that providing the accommodation requested by the Grievant would pose an undue hardship.</p>
<p class="continued">Here the Arbitrator notes that the Grievant and Union has argued throughout this action that a sit-down forklift was available, in the facility, from the date of the Grievant's initial request through the date of the Grievant's separation AND the Company refused to provide one of the available sit-down forklifts to the Grievant as an accommodation for &ldquo;reasons of safety.&rdquo; Yet, the evidence shows in April 2014 when another fortdift operator complained that she was having issues with a lot of pain in her left knee and ankle, that the issues were preexisting, but it was &ldquo;only since we went from the Yale sit down&hellip;fork lifts to the stand-up Crown forklifts that she has been unable to handle the pain. So she was directed to use the one Yale forklift left&hellip;to make it more accommodating for her.&rdquo; While the record also shows that the forklift operator was informed this was not a permanent solution, she was directed to see HR in regard to the issue. Still, if the use of a sit-down lift <i>on a temporary basis</i> to accommodate this forklift operator who was having knee and ankle pain from operating the stand-up lift was allowed, it should have been allowed for the Grievant, even if on a temporary basis until some other reasonable accommodation could have been worked out.</p>
<p class="continued">Having found that the Company failed to provide the Grievant a reasonable accommodation; the Arbitrator finds the Company discriminated against the Grievant in violation of the ADA and Article 27 of the parties' CBA.</p>
<p class="continued">Accordingly, the Arbitrator finds that the Company <i>did not</i> have just cause to separate the Grievant from her employment.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>VI. DECISION AND AWARD.</b></h4>
<p class="continued">The Arbitrator has strived to ensure both parties have had an opportunity to present sufficient evidence to support their case, through pre-hearing submissions, hearing testimony and offered evidence, and post-hearing briefs and rebuttals. Having considered all the evidence submitted, the following decision is rendered.</p>
<p class="continued">As to the issue before the Arbitrator&hellip;</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b><i>Did the Company violate provisions of the parties' collective bargaining agreement and/or any provisions of Federal law when it separated the Grievant, Ms. Tamela R. Wells, from employment on October 10, 2014</i>.</b></p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">The answer is yes.</p>
<p><b><i>If so, what is the remedy?</i></b></p>
<h4 align="left"><b>AWARD</b></h4>
<p class="continued"><b>As presented above, the Arbitrator finds the Union HAS shown by the preponderance of the evidence that the Company did not provide a reasonable accommodation for the Grievant and, therefore, discriminated against her. The Employer has NOT met its burden of proof and shown by the preponderance of evidence that it had just cause to separate the Grievant.</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Accordingly, the grievance is sustained.</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>The Company, Dart Container Corporation, is ordered to fully reinstate the Grievant, Ms. Tamela Wells to her position as a forklift operator in the Solo Cup Operating facility in Augusta, Georgia with full seniority and all pay and benefits as previously received; and back pay from the date of separation to the date of this decision.</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Upon Ms. Wells' reinstatement, the Company, Dart Container Corporation, is also ordered to provide the Grievant with a sit-down style forklift to use to perform her work as a forklift operator.</b></p>
<p class="continued">Finally, based on the request of the Union as presented in its post-hearing brief, the Arbitrator retains and reserves jurisdiction for a period not-to-exceed six-months to resolve any remaining issues regarding the implementation of this decision and award. This six-month time frame can be extended by request and agreement of both parties.</p>
<p class="continued">The FINDINGS, DECISION, AND AWARD OF THE ARBITRATOR as presented above are made pursuant to the provisions of Article 11 of the parties' collective bargaining agreement, and are final and binding on both parties.</p>
<p class="continued">In accordance with the provisions of Article 11, Section 2, of the CBA, the Arbitrator's fees and expenses will be billed to, and are to be paid in full by, the LOSING party, the Company, Dart Container Corporation.</p>
<p class="continued">Accordingly, Dart Container Corporation is directed to pay the total fees, compensation, and expenses of the undersigned Arbitrator as outlined above and presented by invoice under separate cover.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>
