<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between Norwalk Board of Education And UPSEU</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No. 2015-A-0127</p>
<p>January 11, 2017.</p>
<p>The parties at the start of the proceedings presented the statement of the issue as follows: &ldquo;Is the grievance arbitrable?&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="left">RELEVANT CONTRACT LANGUAGE</h4>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE XI GRIEVANCE PROCEDURE</h4>
<p class="continued">Section 11.01&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Step 1</p>
<p class="continued">The employee with or without the Union representative, shall take up the grievance or dispute with the Director of Facilities or his/her designee within ten (10) days of the grievance or the employees knowledge of its occurrence&hellip; The Director or his/her designee shall attempt to adjust the matter and shall respond to the employee within ten (10) working days after a meeting with the grievant or his representative&hellip;</p>
<p class="continued">Step 2</p>
<p class="continued">If the grievance has not been settled, it shall be presented in writing by the employee or local Union official to the Superintendent of Schools or his designee within five (5) working days after the director's response. The Superintendent or his/her designee shall respond in writing to the employee and Union President within five (5) working days.</p>
<p class="continued">Step 3</p>
<p class="continued">If the grievance is still unsettled, the Union may, within fifteen (15) days after the reply of the Superintendent or his/her designee is due, by written notice to the other, request arbitration by the State Board of Mediation and Arbitration. Said Board shall hear and act on such dispute in accordance with its rules and regulations.</p>
<h4 align="left">RELEVANT CONNECTICUT GENERAL STATUTES</h4>
<p class="continued">Section 31-97(b) No panel of said board may consider any claim that one or more of the issues before the panel are improper subjects for arbitration unless the party making such claim has notified the opposing party and the chairman of the panel of such claim, in writing, at least ten days prior to the date of the hearing, except that the panel may consider such claim if it determines there was cause for the failure of the party to comply with said notice requirement.</p>
<h4 align="left">RELEVANT REGULATIONS OF CONNECTICUT STATE AGENCIES</h4>
<p class="continued">Section 31-91-23(b) A party claiming the dispute is not arbitrable shall submit notice of such claim and the reasons therefor, to the board and to the opposing party at least ten days prior to the initial hearing date.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 31-91-27(a) Where the board has scheduled a case a party may within 15 days of receipt of the hearing notice request one postponement per case by: (1) obtaining from the opposing party an agreement for the postponement, (2) confirming a new mutually acceptable hearing date, (which must be at least three months but not longer than six months from the date of the postponement request), and (3) notifying the case manager, who originally scheduled the case, of the agreement to postpone and the new mutually acceptable hearing date.</p>
<h4 align="left">FACTS</h4>
<p>This grievance concerns a claim that the Norwalk Board of Education (BOE) violated the parties' contract by the use of other than bargaining unit employees to perform bargaining unit custodial work. The BOE's denial of the grievance led to this proceeding.</p>
<p>The issue involves the timing of the BOE's arbitrability challenge to the State Board of Mediation and Arbitration (SBMA). The grievance was filed on June 24, 2014 concerning work performed by a contractor that spring. The BOE gave its step two denial of the grievance on July 21, 2014. The union on July 29, 2014 gave notice to the BOE of its intent to submit the grievance to arbitration which was submitted on October 3, 2014. The SBMA on September 8, 2015 gave notice of an October 13, 2015 hearing which was postponed by the agreement of the parties. The SBMA on August 9, 2016 gave notice of a new hearing date on October 12, 2016. The BOE asserted by letter on September 26, 2016 that the grievance is not arbitrable because it was filed more than ten days after the grievance or the employee's knowledge of its occurrence in violation of the contract. The BOE also asserted at the October 12, 2016 hearing that the grievance is not arbitrable because it was filed to the SBMA too late in violation of the contract.</p>
<h4 align="left">POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</h4>
<p>The BOE maintains that it complied with the regulatory requirement of a timely filing of an inarbitrability claim before the initial hearing date because its filing was more than ten days before the first actual date of the hearing. The BOE's regulatory construction is supported by precedent. The grievance is not arbitrable because it was filed late at both steps one and three. Moreover, only a court, not this panel, can determine the arbitrability of this grievance.</p>
<p>The union maintains that the BOE failed to make a timely challenge of arbitrability by the plain language of the regulation. The union's construction of the regulation is supported by precedent. The grievance should be considered timely filed at both steps one and three.</p>
<h4 align="left">DISCUSSION</h4>
<p>The initial hearing date assigned by the SBMA was October 13, 2015. The case did not proceed on the initial hearing date due to the request for a postponement to a new hearing date. The postponement does not negate the fact that October 13, 2015 was the initial hearing date.</p>
<p>The BOE failed to file its arbitrability challenge ten days before the initial hearing date. The BOE's September 26, 2016 challenge, while more than ten days before the October 12, 2016 hearing, was nearly one year after the initial hearing date.</p>
<p>The BOE's construction of the regulations is contrary to their plain language. The regulations refer to a section 31-91-23(b) initial hearing date and, upon a postponement as in this case, a section 31-91-27(a) new hearing date. The ten day arbitrability challenge requirement specifically applies to the initial hearing date by the terms of regulation 31-91-23(b).</p>
<p>The BOE's regulatory construction is contrary to the evident purpose of the regulation to promote prompt arbitrability challenges by requiring filing early in the proceedings. The purpose of the regulation is shown by the use of the phrase &ldquo;initial hearing date.&rdquo; It must be assumed that there is a purpose to the use of each phrase in a regulation.</p>
<p>The union's argument is supported by <i>Town of Westbrook &amp; UPSEU/COPS</i>, SBMA No. 2009-A-0817, Nov. 8, 2010. The SBMA in this case with similar facts to the present ruled that the town failed to file a timely arbitrability challenge in violation of the regulation. The SBMA noted the difference in the language of the statute which requires filing ten days before the date of the hearing and the language of the regulation requiring filing ten days before the initial hearing date. The SBMA easily could have repeated the language of the statute in its regulation had it intended for the BOE's filing to be timely. The difference in language further shows the regulatory purpose of promoting arbitrability challenges early in the proceedings.</p>
<p>The BOE's failure to challenge arbitrability within ten days of the initial hearing date is contrary to the contract as well as the regulations. The parties at step three of their contract agreed to be bound by the rules and regulations of the SBMA in resolving grievances.</p>
<p>Precedent cited by the BOE is not persuasive. The Superior Court in <i>Town of Clinton &amp; United Public Service Employees Association</i>, 2207 WL 1470451, reversed a SBMA ruling of regulation 31-91-23(b) noncompliance due to failure to file a timely arbitrability challenge. The SBMA erred in not extending the ten day computation to allow for an extra day when the terminal day fell on a weekend. The union did not argue that the regulation required filing ten days before the initial hearing date assigned by the SBMA. Neither the Superior Court nor the SBMA decisions have any discussion of the dispute presented by the issue in the present case.</p>
<p>The source of the SBMA's authority to determine arbitrability is the agreement of the parties. The parties agreed at the start of the hearing and presented to the panel the statement of the issue &ldquo;&lsqb;i&rsqb;s the grievance arbitrable?&rdquo; The parties' intent to have the SBMA decide arbitrability is clear.</p>
<p>The BOE's failure to comply with the regulatory and contractual requirement to present a timely arbitrability challenge renders the BOE's claims of an untimely filing of the grievance and an untimely filing for arbitration with the SBMA moot. The BOE would have had to have filed a timely arbitrability challenge for its claims to be considered.</p>
<h4 align="left">INTERIM AWARD</h4>
<p>The grievance is arbitrable.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>
