<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>UNITED STATES STEEL CORPORATION Minntac Plant and UNITED STEELWORKERS Local Union No. 1938</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No. USS-48,124</p>
<p>Grievance No. MIN-14-0026</p>
<p>August 23, 2016.</p>
<p>David A. Petersen, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>BACKGROUND</i></h4>
<p>1/ In this grievance from the Minntac Plant it is charged that the Company has failed to provide Personal Protective Equipment (PPE) appropriate to environmental conditions, in violation of Article 3, Section D of the September 1, 2012 Minnesota Ore Operations Basic Labor Agreement.</p>
<p>2/ Article 3, Section D of the 2012 Agreement provides as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">ARTICLE THREE &ndash; HEALTH, SAFETY AND THE ENVIRONMENT</p>
<p align="center">&ast; &ast; &ast;</p>
<p class="continued">Section D. The Right to Adequate Personal Protective Equipment</p>
<p class="continued">The Company will provide, without cost to the Employee, effective protective equipment in good working order, appropriate to environmental conditions,<ftnote num="1"><para>The phrase <quote>appropriate to environmental conditions</quote> was added to Article 3, Section D in the 2012 Agreement.</para></ftnote> when required by law or regulation or when necessary to protect Employees from injury or illness. Consideration will be given for environmental conditions. Such equipment includes, but is not limited to, goggles, hard hats, safety glasses, hearing protectors, face shields, respirators, special-purpose gloves, protective clothing and harnesses. The Company may assess a fair charge to cover negligent loss or willful destruction by the Employee.</p></blockquote>
<p>3/ Grievant, a Labor Grade 2 Utility Technician in Fire Protection, works outside from time to time during the winter months in harsh weather conditions shoveling snow from around fire hydrants and checking/servicing fire systems on mine equipment. Grievant is issued firefighting gear, considered to be specialized PPE, and he is issued a long-sleeved shirt and a long-sleeved sweatshirt and a fire retardant jacket, but he is not issued a winter jacket and bibs.</p>
<p>4/ Grievant testified that his outside work assignments involving the shoveling of snow from around fire hydrants and checking/servicing fire systems on mine equipment during the winter months exposes him to extremely harsh weather conditions and yet he is not provided with or given access to all the personal protective clothing appropriate to those environmental conditions. Grievant said he requested an insulated jacket and bibs be provided and made available for his use in the winter months but his request was denied. Grievant stated that Managers and employees who work outside on mobile equipment during the winter months have been provided cold weather gear, and he recalled that even one of his co-workers had been provided cold weather gear some years earlier. The witness asserted that he filed the Complaint Form giving rise to this case in February 2014, signing on the Employee's Signature line, in order to secure the additional PPE he believed was due under Article 3, Section D of the 2012 Agreement.</p>
<p>5/ The Vice President of the Local Union, who is also the Grievance Chair, testified he was involved in this grievance and had signed the Complaint Form on the Committeeman's Signature line. The Vice President stated that at a meeting of the Joint Safety Committee shortly after the filing of this grievance he presented Management representatives with the Article 3, Section D language in the 2012 Agreement and argued that employees working as Agglomerator and Crusher attendants should be provided with winter gear due to their exposure to the harsh weather conditions, including temperatures of up to thirty or more degrees below zero, when dumping material. The witness recalled that Management accepted his argument and then bought winter gear, one of each size from Small to 3X, and stored this gear in a locker where it was available to the one employee scheduled per shift on the attendant assignment. The witness agreed that, in Fire Protection, there could be four employees scheduled per shift and those employees could range in size from Small to an estimated 5X. The witness noted that Managers have been and are provided with winter gear and he claimed that the newer Managers have been less inclined to provide employees with winter gear.</p>
<p>6/ The Manager of Emergency Services testified via telephone and said Grievant works in his department and that in the winter about twenty percent of Grievant's shift time is spent outside. The Manager acknowledged that Grievant is exposed to cold weather conditions when he is shoveling snow from around fire hydrants and checking/servicing fire systems on mobile equipment. The witness stressed, though, that on such occasions Grievant usually is not outside for more than thirty minutes at a time and Grievant has the opportunity to warm up by getting back into his pickup truck or going inside a building. The Manager noted that Grievant is provided with basic PPE for his job, including fire-rated jacket and pants and hooded and non-hooded sweatshirts and a long-sleeved t-shirt, and Grievant is also provided with a hardhat and gloves and boots. He noted, too, that Grievant is permitted to wear other clothes underneath the clothing he is provided.</p>
<p>7/ The Department Manager of Safety and Industrial Hygiene testified that no law or regulation requires the Company to provide winter coats to employees. The Department Manager said a Complaint was filed with MSHA (Mine Safety and Health Administration) in November 2015 alleging in part that the Company was not providing appropriate winter gear to miners, but MSHA ultimately found the &ldquo;nature of the hazard complaint is not within MSHA's jurisdiction.&rdquo; The Manager also said no records were found of any cold weather injuries such as frostbite or hypothermia having been reported at Minntac or Keetac in the past. The witness acknowledged that the Company has provided hats and gloves and winter steel toe metatarsal boots as an accommodation of the environment, yet he denied that winter boots or winter jackets and bibs are required to be provided under Article 3, Section D of the Agreement.</p>
<p>8/ In rebuttal, the President of the Local Union testified that MSHA's finding on the November 2015 Complaint was based on the fact MSHA has no specific standard dealing with the provision of appropriate winter gear for miners. The President said MSHA recommends winter jackets and bibs be provided but cannot enforce this recommendation.</p>
<p>9/ On this record the Union contends Grievant and other Fire Protection employees are entitled, under Article 3, Section D of the 2012 Agreement, to be provided with all adequate cold weather gear appropriate to the extreme cold weather conditions which exist when they work outside during the winter months. The Union stresses that the Company specifically agreed during the 2012 negotiations to add the new phrase &ldquo;appropriate to environmental conditions&rdquo; in the first sentence of Article 3, Section D describing when employees would be provided effective protective equipment, and the Union urges that cold weather gear which it defined here as winter jackets and bibs are necessary to protect employees from injury or illness in these particular circumstances. The Union notes that cold weather gear has been provided to Managers as well as to some bargaining unit employees in the past and it seeks to have such gear provided and available in this case. The Union requests the grievance be sustained.</p>
<p>10/ The Company maintains that Article 3, Section D of the Agreement does not obligate Management to provide Grievant with what it characterizes as unspecified winter gear. The Company does not believe the addition of the phrase &ldquo;appropriate to environmental conditions&rdquo; in the first sentence of Article 3, Section D of the 2012 Agreement impacted its obligation in this regard, noting that a reference to &ldquo;environmental conditions&rdquo; appeared in Article 3, Section D of the prior Agreement as well and yet no such claim of entitlement to winter gear for a Fire Protection employee was made at that time. And the Company denies that any practice or local working condition enforceable under Article 5, Section A of the Agreement entitles Grievant to be provided with a winter jacket and bibs.</p>
<p>11/ The Company asserts that PPE is typically issued to protect an employee against potential injury or illness related to hazards inherent in or created by mill and mine operations, not against discomfort related to weather conditions. In support of its position the Company cites USS-7333-S, a decision of the Board on a 1968 Section 14 (Safety and Health) grievance from the Transportation Department at Fairfield Works requesting that Car Repairmen and Inspectors be provided with boots as were provided to train crews who also work in rainy and muddy conditions. The Company relies on the Findings in that case which read in part:</p>
<blockquote><p>Absent a controlling practice, Grievants are entitled to protection only against man-made hazards to health and person. The conditions must be created by or result from the Company's operations. The mere possibility of adverse weather conditions is not enough. The Company's duty to furnish the item in question is not limited to cases involving a risk of bodily injury. A dangerous health condition would also give rise to the duty. However, the condition must be more than the normal hazard inherent in Grievants' work. There is no health hazard merely because Grievants may be caused some hardship or be uncomfortable.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>12/ The Company urges that, in accordance with USS-7333-S, an employee's discomfort resulting from cold weather conditions is not sufficient justification for additional PPE. The Company asserts that Grievant works outside on a sporadic and limited basis and it contends that in the winter months Grievant is exposed to no greater than normal hazard attributable to mill or mine operations and to no greater weather-related hazard than he would be when shoveling his own driveway. It also recalls that Grievant can wear whatever additional clothes he chooses on this work assignment and that he has the opportunity to warm-up in his vehicle or inside a building. Finally, it notes that according to the undisputed testimony of one of its witnesses neither Minntac nor Keetac has a record of any hypothermia or frostbite injury having occurred on the property. The Company requests the grievance be denied.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>FINDINGS</i></h4>
<p>13/ Grievant, who was the only employee other than the Local Union Vice President/Grievance Chair to have signed the Complaint Form giving rise to this case, alleges the Company is failing to provide proper and adequate PPE appropriate to environmental conditions. Grievant contends the Company should provide and make available to him a winter jacket and bibs for his use when he is required to work outside during the cold weather months at Minntac. Grievant relies on Article 3, Section D of the 2012 Agreement.</p>
<p>14/ Article 3, Section D of the 2012 Agreement reads in part: &ldquo;The Company will provide, without cost to the Employee, effective protective equipment in good working order, appropriate to environmental conditions, when required by law or regulation or when necessary to protect Employees from injury or illness. Consideration will be given for environmental conditions. Such equipment includes, but is not limited to, goggles, hard hats, safety glasses, hearing protectors, face shields, respirators, special-purpose gloves, protective clothing and harnesses.&rdquo;</p>
<p>15/ The Board acknowledges that Article 3, Section D, as it existed in the Agreement prior to the 2012 Agreement specified that &ldquo;environmental conditions&rdquo; were to be given &ldquo;consideration&rdquo;, but the Board believes the addition of the new phrase &ldquo;appropriate to environmental conditions&rdquo; in the first sentence of Article 3, Section D of the 2012 Agreement must be recognized and assessed in determining whether Grievant's requested winter gear here &ndash; even though not shown to be required by law or regulation &ndash; is to be provided as being protective equipment necessary to protect him from injury or illness while working outside in the extreme cold at Minntac during the winter months. Regardless of how the third sentence of Article 3, Section D (i.e., &ldquo;Consideration will be given for environmental conditions.&rdquo;) was or is interpreted, the new phrase (i.e., &ldquo;appropriate to environmental conditions&rdquo;) in the first sentence now clearly qualifies the type of protective equipment which is to be provided either when required by law or regulation or when necessary to protect against injury or illness. In the context of Grievant's case the Board is of the opinion that a winter jacket and bibs constitutes protective equipment appropriate to environmental conditions and that this protective equipment is reasonably necessary to protect him from injury or illness within the meaning of Article 3, Section D of the 2012 Agreement. On that basis it is determined this grievance will be sustained.</p>
<p>16/ The Board does not find USS-7333-S, decided under the language in Article 14 of the 1968 Agreement, to preclude this determination under the language in Article 3, Section D of the 2012 Agreement. Section 14 obligated the Company to &ldquo;continue to make reasonable provisions for the safety and health of its employees&rdquo; and to provide &ldquo;protective devices, wearing apparel, and other equipment necessary properly to protect employees from injury &hellip; in accordance with practices now prevailing in each separate plant or as such practices may be improved from time to time&rdquo;. Section 14 also obligated the Company to provide &ldquo;goggles; gas masks; face shields; respirators; special purpose gloves; fireproof, waterproof, or acidproof protective clothing when necessary and required&rdquo;. In USS-7333-S the Board found no prevailing practice in the plant of providing the grieving employees with boots and no showing that these boots fell within the &ldquo;listed categories&rdquo; of specific items to be provided and were &ldquo;necessary and required&rdquo; or otherwise qualified as an item to be provided under the Company's general obligation &ldquo;to make reasonable provisions for the safety and health of its employees&rdquo;. In the present grievance, Article 3, Section D obligated the Company to provide effective protective equipment appropriate to environmental conditions when necessary to protect employees from injury or illness, and the Board concludes on the facts of Grievant's case that the Company failed to do so. The Board is of the opinion that a dangerous health condition, not merely some hardship or discomfort, exists when Grievant is exposed to the extremely harsh weather conditions at Minntac in the performance of his required work outside during the winter months for twenty percent of his shift. The Board believes the Company is obligated under these particular circumstances to provide the requested PPE for this hazard, as it has and does for some others, in recognition of this hazard which is beyond the normal hazard inherent in Grievant's work.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>AWARD</i></h4>
<p>17/ The grievance is sustained.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>
