<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION BETWEEN: DAVIDSON TRANSIT ORGANIZATION, Employer, and LOCAL 1235 AMALGAMATED TRANSIT UNION, Union.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>October 11, 2016.</p>
<p>Gerard A. Fowler, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>OPINION AND AWARD</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><b>ISSUE</b></h4>
<p>Did the Company have just cause to discharge Grievant, and if not, what is the proper remedy?</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>STATEMENT OF THE GRIEVANCE</b></i></h4>
<p>This grievance arises under the terms of the Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA) between Davidson Transit Organization (hereinafter &ldquo;Company&rdquo; or &ldquo;Employer&rdquo;) and the Amalgamated Transit Union, Local 1235 (hereinafter &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) effective July 1, 2012 to June 30, 2015. The subject grievance was filed by the Union on or about November 3, 2015 as a result of the discharge of Lester Owens, Grievant, for failure to report an accident.</p>
<p>The arbitration of the grievance took place at the Holiday Inn Express in Nashville, Tennessee on May 12, 2016. Both parties were represented by counsel and full opportunity was provided for the examination and cross examination of witnesses. A court reporter was present and took a verbatim transcript. Subsequent to the hearing the parties provided the Arbitrator with briefs of law and fact, and the hearing portion of the matter was declared closed.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>RELEVANT CONTRACT PROVISIONS</i></h4>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 3</h4>
<h4 align="center">MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</h4>
<p class="continued"><i>Section A.</i> The Company will exercise the exclusive right to set its policy; to manage its business in the light of experience, good business judgment and changing conditions; &hellip; to make reasonable rules and regulations governing the operation of its business and the conduct of its employees; to enforce discipline for violation of rules and other misconduct; to discharge employees for good cause; &hellip;. The foregoing provisions shall prevail, provided however that nothing in this sections shall be deemed to supersede or displace and other specific sections of this Agreement.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Section B.</i> Upon implementation of any new rules or regulations, the Company shall give written notice to the Union in advance of the effective date of such rule or regulation. The Company will meet with the Union to discuss proposed rule changes prior to implementation of any rule or regulation. The Company will notify the Union as soon as possible but no longer than 24 hours after implementation. Rules and regulations will be placed in a conspicuous place for reference by employees.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 5</h4>
<h4 align="center">EMPLOYEE DISCIPLINE</h4>
<p class="continued"><i>Section A.</i> An employee will not be discharged, suspended or otherwise disciplined, nor will entries be made against his service record without good cause &hellip;.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Section E.</i> The Union and the employees agree that &hellip; they will observe and conform to the rules and regulations of the Company; &hellip; that they will at all times give the riding public equal business courtesy and respectful consideration and treatment, &hellip; and that they will use their influence, good will and best endeavors to protect the property of the Company and promote its interests to the end that the transportation system may grow in popularity and increase in efficiency, volume and scope, and that the revenue and resulting profit from its operation may become greater.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 7</h4>
<h4 align="center">GRIEVANCE PROCEDURE</h4>
<p class="continued"><i>Section A.</i></p>
<p>STEP 2. If the answer of the immediate supervisor or department head or his designee in Step 1 is unsatisfactory, the employee and/or the Union shall submit the grievance in writing to the Chief Operating Officer or his designee within five (5) days of the receipt of the department head's or his designee's written reply in Step 1.</p>
<p>Within ten (10) days after such submission, the grievance shall be taken up at a meeting between the Union representatives and representatives designated by the Company. During the step #2 meeting representatives will discuss the grievance in an effort to understand and resolve the grievance. The Company shall give an answer in writing to the Union within five (5) days of the meeting.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Section B.</i> Saturdays, Sundays, holidays, the employee's off days, and days off due to sickness or vacation shall be excluded in the calculation of time limits provided in Step 2. Such time limits may be extended by mutual agreement between the parties at the step the grievance is in. All time limits here refer to the date of delivery, not mailing date.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 8</h4>
<h4 align="center">ARBITRATION</h4>
<p class="continued"><i>Section A.</i> The arbitrators shall have no power to add to, or subtract from, or modify any of the terms of this Agreement, nor shall it substitute its discretion for that of the Company or the Union where such discretion has been retained by the Company or the Union.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 14</h4>
<h4 align="center">BULLETIN BOARD</h4>
<p class="continued"><i>Section B.</i> It is necessary to post bulletins on the Company's bulletin board from time to time, some of which take effect immediately, and the employees agree to read all new bulletins each day to a complete understanding of the orders before going to work.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<h4 align="center">ARTICLE 22</h4>
<h4 align="center">SAFETY AND ACCIDENT PREVENTION</h4>
<p class="continued"><i>Section B.</i> All accidents whether trivial, minor or serious, occurring on or about a vehicle; &hellip; all accidents involving Company automobiles and trucks &hellip; shall be promptly and fully reported by the employee to his immediate supervisor and/or the Safety Department immediately from the scene when physically able &hellip;. The reports shall be on the forms provided by the Company for that purpose, and all rules of the Company with respect to accidents, procuring information and prompt reporting will be fully complied with by the employee.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Section C.</i> The Union and the employees agree to cooperate wholeheartedly and fully with representatives of the Company in reporting accidents &hellip;. Each employee making an accident report will be paid a minimum of thirty (30) minutes at his regular straight time rate for making the initial report and a minimum of thirty (30) minutes for each additional report required by the Company.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>D.T.O. DISCIPLINARY POLICY FOR PREVENTABLE ACCIDENTS</b></h4>
<p class="continued">D. DTO CLASSIFICATONS FOR PREVENTABLE ACCIDENTS</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Major Preventable Accident:</i> Accidents in which the employee is, based on National Safety Council Guidelines, responsible for the accident. Where an operator has become involved in the accident through recklessness and/or through a showing a disregard for bus safety and motor vehicle operation. The presence of extensive property damage, extensive physical injury or fatalities will weigh heavily in making this a dischargeable offense at any step in the disciplinary sequence. Any preventable accident with a total property damage or injury cost exceeding &dollar;1,000.00 will be automatically deemed a Major Preventable Accident.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Section A.</i> The Company will exercise the exclusive right to set its policy; to manage its business in the light of experience, good business judgment and changing conditions; &hellip; to make reasonable rules and regulations governing the operation of its business and the conduct of its employees; to enforce discipline for violation of rules and other misconduct; to discharge employees for good cause; &hellip;. The foregoing provisions shall prevail, provided however that nothing in this sections shall be deemed to supersede or displace and other specific sections of this Agreement.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Section B.</i> Upon implementation of any new rules or regulations, the Company shall give written notice to the Union in advance of the effective date of such rule or regulation. The Company will meet with the Union to discuss proposed rule changes prior to implementation of any rule or regulation. The Company will notify the Union as soon as possible but no longer than 24 hours after implementation. Rules and regulations will be placed in a conspicuous place for reference by employees.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>BACKGROUND OF THE GRIEVANCE</b></i></h4>
<p>Grievant, a hostler, was discharged by the Company following an incident on October 14, 2015. While moving a bus in the Nestor Yard around 9 p.m. that evening, Grievant collided with a light pole on his way to the fuel bay. Due to fear of losing his job, he failed to report this accident and finished servicing the bus in accordance with the job description. During the pull out the next morning, damage to the handicap ramp on the bus in question was discovered. After a review of the records and the video aboard the bus, it was determined that Grievant was the person who had been driving the bus in question when the damage occurred. Grievant was summoned to the property the next day where he admitted that he caused the damage and failed to report it to management. The Company terminated Grievant on October 27, 2015 and the Union filed a grievance protesting the discharge on or about November 2. Management denied the grievance at Step 1 on November 6 and the Union moved it properly to step 2. On November 19, 2015 the parties met for the formal step 2 meeting but no decision was issued. The following day, November 20, The Company Chief Operating Officer India Birdsong called Union President Patrick Green asking for an extension of the contractual time limits to answer. Green agreed to give the Company through the Thanksgiving holiday to issue a formal response to the grievance. When management had still not issued a decision after more than 2 weeks, President Green hand delivered a letter to the Company on December 7, 2015 stating that the Union was viewing the grievance as being granted. Management claimed that they emailed him the paperwork denying the grievance the Friday before but they were using the wrong email address. The grievance was moved without resolution through all the steps outlined in the CBA. On May 12, 2016 the parties met and conducted binding arbitration before a tripartite Board of Arbitration (the &ldquo;Board&rdquo;), chaired by Arbitrator Fowler.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>POSITION OF THE COMPANY</b></i></h4>
<p>The Company maintains that just cause existed to discharge Grievant for failure to report an accident. Testimony indicated that Grievant was aware of Memo &num; 2011&ndash;SF&ndash;009, which required employees to immediately report any accident even if there was no damage to a supervisor and complete an accident form. Testimony for the Company indicated that even though Grievant was aware of this requirement he did not report the fact that he backed into a streetlamp, which damaged the buses wheelchair ramp, forced the floor above the wheelchair ramp to bulge, scratched the paint of the bus, and took chunks out of the base of the light pole on October 14, 2015. Further testimony indicated that due to grievance decision not to report the accident to a supervisor or complete an accident form, the Employer did not learn about the accident until the damage was discovered the next morning by an operator doing a pre-trip inspection. The operator who discovered the damage was Fernando Parmer, the Union vice president.</p>
<p>An investigation was conducted by Earl Rhodes and Bobby Irvine, members of the Employer's Safety Team. Rhodes testified that the first light pole he walked to had purple paint on it, which matched the purple paint on the bus. Rhodes also found yellow paint from the base of a light pole in front of the base of the light pole and on the bus. Further, Rhodes found concrete dust on the bus and an indentation by the wheelchair ramp. After retrieving the video maintained by the Company recording activity on the lot, Irvine discovered footage of Grievant backing the bus into a light pole the night before. As a result of their investigation Rhodes and Irvine recommended that Grievant be discharged. The recommendation stated, in pertinent part:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">During our investigation, it was determined on 10/14/15 at 7:47 p.m., you (Lester Owens) were operating bus 737 in a backing mode on the lot and backed into a contract block that positioned a light pole. The video confirms you had clear knowledge of the accident because you stopped, got out and investigated if any damage occurred. You then got back on the bus 737 and proceeded to the fuel bay. When you arrived at the fuel bay, you notice more damage was sustained involving the wheelchair ramp. You probe and fueled bus 737 then parked it inside the body shop area. Once you parked it, you assessed the damages again to the ramp.</p></blockquote>
<p>As part of their investigation the Company interviewed Grievant and provided an opportunity for him to tell his side of the story. In the letter requesting Grievant's side of the story, the Employer stated it had reason to believe that Grievant may have violated its reasonable expectations, policies of the CBA by failing to report an accident on October 14, 2015. The Employer further told Grievant the consequences if its beliefs were true, to ensure that Grievant had every opportunity to state why discharge would be inappropriate if the allegations were true. The Company pointed out at this time that the damage was approximately seven thousand dollars which made it a major preventable accident. After considering all the available evidence the Company discharged Grievant on October 27, 2015.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>POSITION OF THE UNION</b></i></h4>
<p>The Union does not dispute that on the night of October 14, 2015 Grievant during the course of his shift, backed one of the buses into a pole while on the way to get it fueled, Nor is there any question that Grievant failed to report this incident. The Union points out that when approached by management the following day Grievant admitted his mistake and expressed remorse for his actions. Further, the Union indicated that they properly followed the grievance procedure continually asking that the discharge be converted to a thirty (30) day suspension as had been done with other employees in the past. The Union maintains that the Company failed to issue the second step denial in a timely fashion thus granting the grievance under article 7 of the CBA.</p>
<p>The Union maintains that the facts of this grievance demonstrate very clearly that the Company violated the time limits procedure for no justifiable reason. Following Grievant's termination on October 27, 2015 a grievance was properly filed on November 2. The grievance was denied at the first step on November 6, 2015 in the second step procedure was initiated whereby a meeting was scheduled for November 19.</p>
<p>The Union acknowledges that on Friday, November 20, 2015 COO India Birdsong phoned Union president Green asking for an extension which he granted through the Thanksgiving holiday. Birdsong testified that Green allowed her extension for her entire Thanksgiving vacation. The Union points to evidence presented by the Company which consisted of a print out of a one minute call on November 20 at 10:45 PM to support their position. The Union maintains that Green was in fact operating a bus at that time according to his official work schedule. The Union argues that it is against Company policy for an operator to answer his phone while in motion except for emergencies and Birdsong testified that a phone call from her was not an emergency. The Union indicates there was no record introduced of all the phone calls made that day by Birdsong, in particular any calls made or not made later in the day. Green testified that a number of matters were discussed during an afternoon phone call on November 20 including the subject grievance and that he granted Birdsong an extension through the Thanksgiving holiday not her entire vacation.</p>
<p>The Union elicited testimony indicating that Thanksgiving was November 26 and Birdsong began her vacation on Monday, November 22. Birdsong testified that she was back in town on December 1 and in the office no later than December 2. It was not until Friday, December 4 that any communication was even set out from the Company concerning this grievance well past her return from vacation in over a week after the Thanksgiving holiday.</p>
<p>The Union argues that waiting a full fifteen days after the second step meeting and seven days past the end of the extension granted by the Union is a direct violation of the CBA. Article 7, section B does allow for extensions but only by mutual agreement. The Union acknowledges there was an extension given through the Thanksgiving holiday but does not account for the full week after the holiday that the Company did not issue a formal response. At the hearing, Birdsong testified that the Union did not raise any new issues at the second step hearing and she just needed to review the file and the video again. Since there is no dispute about the accident nor any mitigating factors it is beyond the comprehension of the Union why management needed fifteen days to deny the grievance. By not presenting the Union with a formal response by the agreed-upon extension deadline of November 30 the grievance was granted under the contract; therefore, Grievant should be reinstated with full back pay and benefits. The Union presented evidence indicating that the Company was given proper notice that the issue in this case had time limits on December 7, 2015 before the matter was moved arbitration. Accordingly, the Union maintains that Grievant should be in reinstated to his former position minus a thirty (30) day suspension with full back pay and benefits.</p>
<p>In response to the Company's argument that they provided notice to the Union by email concerning the request for an extension, the Union points out that December 4 is well past the extended deadline to issue such a denial. Secondly, the email address that it was sent to is wrong and there was no delivery to the Union that date anyway. A printout of the correct email address from December 4, 2015 shows it was conducting Union business on that account at the time but received no communication from Birdsong or Marlow. The Union maintains that the implication of the Company testimony was that while they were the one sending correspondence to the wrong email address, it was the Union's fault that they did not tell the Company of their mistake.</p>
<p>The Union argues that essentially the Company is arguing that the Union is supposed to have notified management that all of the email sent to the wrong account for which they did not have access to needed to be resent even though it is impossible for the Union to have no. The Union maintains this is a completely illogical argument and a shoddy attempt by management to pass the blame on a mistake entirely of their own doing. The Union points out that they have had the same email address since the 1980s and each president and executive board member has access to it. Green's business card clearly has the proper Union email address printed on it.</p>
<p>Finally, the Union repeats their argument set forth at the beginning of the grievance that Grievant should not be discharged but receive a thirty (30) day suspension. The Union faults the Company's argument that all employees committing a similar violation have been discharged. They point out that the people on the list provided by the Company are bus operators and not maintenance employees.</p>
<p>The Union points to two analogous cases. In November 2008, Rodney Jackson was moving a bus on the Nester lot when it collided with a parked bus. Jackson got out and attempted to conceal the damage before walking away. He never reported the incident and the Company suspended him for thirty (30) days. Another employee, Marc Little, was driving a van through the wash bay at Nester on March 16, 2011 when he collided with the wash rack and the mirror of the bus was knocked off. Little did not report the accident and was only given a ten (10) day suspension. Neither of the maintenance employees who had unreported accidents at the Nester lot were terminated. Past practice clearly shows that Grievant should not have been discharged but only suspended for thirty days.</p>
<p>In summary, the Union argues that the Company is without any justifiable reason for violating the contractually agreed upon time limits in failing to issue a formal second step response to the grievance. Despite the Company's claim that the notice was sent out on time, it was at least a week late and the Union never received notice of the denial because the Company was using an incorrect email address through no fault of the Union. Grievant should have been disciplined in the same manner as other maintenance employees and given a thirty (30) day suspension. For those reasons, the Union requests that Grievant be reinstated with full back pay, benefits and seniority minus a thirty day suspension.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>DECISION</b></i></h4>
<p>This arbitration centers on whether the Company properly discharged Grievant. In discharge cases, arbitrators determine two factors: (1) proof of wrongdoing; and (2) whether the penalty was reasonable. Elkouri and Elkouri, <i>How Arbitration Works</i>, BNA, Wash. D. C. 6<sup>th</sup> edition. (2003) p. 948. On the first factor, the Employer bears the burden to prove that the employee committed the act deserving termination by a preponderance of the evidence. <i>Rock-Tenn Co.</i>, 127 LA 390 (Englit, 2010) (finding that unless the conduct in question was criminal, Employers must prove by a preponderance of the evidence that the employee committed the conduct in question).</p>
<p>The first prong of the test is easily resolved. There is no dispute as to whether or not Grievant committed the offense which caused the Company to discharge him. His admission and the video of the incident are conclusive in this regard.</p>
<p>Having resolved the first prong of the test we are faced with the issue of whether or not the penalty was reasonable. The most serious contention in this regard is the Union's argument that the Company was not timely in pursuing the grievance process and thereby forfeited their right to discipline Grievant. The Union's argument in this procedural argument appears to ignore the fact that India Birdsong obtained a verbal extension from Patrick Green for the Step Two written response well in advance of its due date. The facts indicate that on November 20, 2016 Birdsong told Green that she was going on vacation for the next week and a half (for the Thanksgiving holiday) and she would submit a Step Two written response within a week after she returned from her vacation in response. Green stated he was busy as well, and he approved the verbal request for extension of time. Accordingly, the Step Two written response was due on or before December 9, 2015 because Grievant was on vacation the next week and a half (November 22 through December 2) and a week later would have been Wednesday, December 9, 2015.</p>
<p>The evidence further indicates that on Friday, December 4, 2015 Ashley Marlow, Birdsong's assistant, mailed and emailed the Step Two written response to Green, but the email address was incorrect. Marlow and Birdsong had been using the wrong email address for almost 6 months unbeknownst to them. Despite the mistake, Green received the step two response on December 8, 2015. In support of the Union's claim that the response was untimely, Green stated he did not receive a response within five days of the Step Two hearing, which completely ignored the agreed-upon extension.</p>
<p>Even assuming arguendo a shorter time period was agreed upon, confusion on the part of the parties did not slow down the case for purposes of going to arbitration and is not an appropriate basis to find a procedural violation. <i>Veolia Transportation, Inc.</i>, 134 LA 892 (Connolly, March 2, 2015). Green testified the Union was not scheduled to vote on advancing this dispute to arbitration until the second Monday of the month, which would have been December 14, 2015 (TR 180, 181). Green had Birdsong's Step Two written response at least by December 8, 2015, and a result, no harm, no foul, no inconvenience, or prejudice occurred (EX 1, p. 20, 22, TR 44-45, 165, 180, 181, 183). The Union also failed to raise the procedural issue in its notice to the Arbitrator, which is also a basis for denying the procedural claim. Id. Accordingly this procedural argument of timeliness lacks merit.</p>
<p>In contesting Grievant's discharge the Union argues that all five employees who failed to report an accident after the employer implemented Memo &num; 2011&ndash;SF&ndash;009 on March 23, 2011 were bus drivers and not maintenance workers. There is nothing in the Memo to distinguish bus drivers from maintenance drivers who drive buses as a part of their duties. The evidence indicated that Grievant was aware of Memo &num; 2001&ndash;SF&ndash;009, which required employees to immediately report any accident (even if there was no damage) to a supervisor and complete an incident form. Despite this awareness, Grievant did not report the fact that he had backed into a streetlamp which damaged the buses wheelchair ramp, forced the floor above the wheelchair ramp to bulge, scratched the paint of the bus and took chunks out of the base of the light pole on October 14, 2015; causing approximately seven thousand dollars in damages.</p>
<p>The Union included in its argument of the case the proposition that Grievant should be subject to no more than a thirty day (30) suspension. However, extensive authority in both the arbitral field and before the courts affirms the view that an arbitrator cannot substitute his judgment for the Company's as to the appropriate penalty when proof of violation of Company rules is found. See <i>Contico International, Inc. v. Local 160, Leather Goods, Plastics and Novelty Workers, AFL-CIO</i>, 738 F.Supp. 1262 (E.D. Mo. 1990). Also, it is axiomatic that when an employee is found to have engaged in conduct warranting discipline, the decision as to the appropriate measure of discipline lies in the discretion of management and should not be disturbed by the arbitrator absent a definitive finding that such discretion has been abused. See, e.g., <i>Leestown Co.</i>, 102 LA 979 (Sergent, 1994). Or, as stated by Arbitrator Bothwell, an arbitrator should not &ldquo;substitute his judgment for that of management unless he finds the penalty is excessive, unreasonable, or that management has abused its discretion.&rdquo; <i>Franz Food Products, Inc.</i>, 28 LA 543, 548 (Bothwell, 1957); <i>Akron City Hospital</i>, 113 LA 146, 150 (Chattman, 1999) (quoting <i>How Arbitration Works</i>, Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, 5th Ed. 1997, pp. 644-645). As Arbitrator Fullmer acknowledged: &ldquo;It is not the arbitrator's job to substitute his judgment for that of an employer in imposing disciplinary penalties.&rdquo; <i>Benjamin Logan Board of Education</i>, 105 LA 1168, 1174 (Fullmer 1995). Other arbitrators have taken a similar position, as demonstrated by the language of Arbitrator Hilpert in <i>Robert Shaw-Fulton Controls Co.</i>, 36 LA 4, 7 (Hilpert, 1961):</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&hellip;it is not the function of an arbitrator to commute a discharge, or other severe penalty, to a lesser penalty merely because he, who has, and had, no managerial responsibility in the matter, believes he would have imposed a lesser penalty, or because he found that other employer-companies have, in similar circumstances, imposed a lesser penalty.</p></blockquote>
<p class="continued">Likewise Arbitrator McCoy in <i>Goodyear Tire &amp; Rubber Co.</i>, 5 LA 30, 36 (McCoy, 1946) stated:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">&hellip;I would probably have imposed a layoff instead of a discharge had I been the foreman. But, I am not the foreman, and I have no right to substitute my discretion for a discretion that is vested in management unless the facts show an abuse of discretion by management.</p></blockquote>
<p>No such unreasonable or excessive penalty, nor abuse of discretion, occurred here. The Employer must be permitted the right to discipline employees in the exercise of its management rights and responsibilities. Arbitrators have repeatedly ruled that once it is proven there was just cause to discipline, the grievant must then prove that there was good justification for the actions in question. <i>Department ofAir Force</i>, 83 LA 953, 956 (Fox, 1984); <i>Hawaiian Telephone</i>, 59 LA 930 (Gipson, 1972); <i>Mississippi Line Co.</i>, 29 LA 559 (Vandegraffe, 1957). Thus, the Tri Partite Panel must acknowledge and employ burden shifting in the instant case.</p>
<p>There is no evidence of arbitrary or capricious action on the part of the Company in this matter. For many years now, the Company has strictly enforced its safety requirements and expectations. This is obvious not only because the Company discharged all five employees that failed to report an accident after the policy was implemented in 2011, but the Employer also has discharged employees for what the Union claimed were minor violations. See <i>Davidson Transit Organization</i>, 12-1 ARB &para; 5570 (Suardi, Aug. 22, 2016) (Arbitrator Suardi upheld the discharge of the union president after he violated the Company's safety policy for using his cellphone while the transit vehicle was at a slow speed.). It has been demonstrated that safety was and is a top priority to the Company.</p>
<p>Accordingly, based upon the reasoning set forth supra the grievance must be denied in its entirety, and it shall be so ordered.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>In accord with the analysis supra, the Grievance is denied in its entirety.</p>
<p>So ordered.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>