<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the matter of arbitration between: GENERAL MILLS, INC., Wellston, Ohio and UFCW LOCAL 1059</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>FMCS No. 16-54196-6</p>
<p>Date of Award: July 25, 2016.</p>
<p>Mitchell B. Goldberg, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>OPINION AND AWARD</b></h4>
<h4 align="left">I. <i>Introduction and Background</i>.</h4>
<p>This is a labor arbitration proceeding conducted under the terms and conditions of the parties' collective bargaining agreement (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo;). Article 11 sets forth a multi-step grievance procedure culminating in binding arbitration in the event the grievance is not resolved in the earlier steps (Section 2). Section 3 provides that &ldquo;the arbitrator's fees shall be paid by the party against whom the judgment is rendered.&rdquo; The arbitrator must &ldquo;declare which party is deemed to have lost and therefore is responsible for such costs. If the arbitrator is unable or fails to make such a determination, the cost will be shared equally by the parties.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Company's manufacturing plant in Wellston, Ohio manufactures frozen pizzas for retail sale in supermarkets, groceries and other retail establishments. The Union is the exclusive representative for all of the production and maintenance employees, including those who work on the three production lines for the frozen pizzas. Judy Trainer, a full-time line worker on Line 4<ftnote num="1"><para>There are three production lines, Line 1, Line 2 and Line 4.</para></ftnote> on the first shift, filed a grievance on February 17, 2016 alleging that the Company violated the CBA when it implemented a new work schedule for Line 4 that imposed 12-hour work shifts after the Union membership voted down and opposed the implementation of the new schedule. It further alleged that the CBA was being violated because the Company was not paying the CBA overtime rate of time and one-half the hourly rate for employees working over 8 hours in a workday, even when the employees are assigned or scheduled to work other lines in the plant. The grievance seeks a monetary recovery of lost overtime pay, and an order that the Company cease its implementation of the 12-hour per day work schedule for Line 4.</p>
<p>The Company denied the grievance throughout each step and the matter proceeded to binding arbitration on July 21, 2016. There was no reported transcription of the proceeding. The parties presented testimonial evidence and joint documentary exhibits. They stipulated that all procedural and substantive requirements of the grievance/arbitration procedures and CBA were met that are necessary to bring this matter to a final and binding resolution.</p>
<h4 align="left">II. <i>Facts</i>.</h4>
<p class="continued">Article 5 - Hours of Work provides for weekly pay periods and for overtime pay for more than 8-hours per day, for more than 40-hours per week, and for work during the 6<sup>th</sup> and 7<sup>th</sup> workday in a week with certain limitations. However, due the Company needed to increase its production workload due to an increased consumer demand for its products. It proposed and the Union agreed to an amendment to the CBA and Article 5. The parties executed an agreement on October 30, 2015 that introduced a trial work schedule for Line 4 on a 2-week fixed scheduled basis that is referred to as a &ldquo;2-3-2 Work Schedule Trial.&rdquo; Four crews were established, each to work 12-hour shifts. Two crews would work the day shift, and two crews would work the night shifts. Each crew would work a 2-week fixed schedule cycle of 2 consecutive 12-hour shifts; then 3 scheduled 12-hours shifts off; work for 2 consecutive shifts; off for 2 scheduled shifts; work for 3 scheduled shifts; and, then off for 2 scheduled shifts. Overtime pay was changed to time and one-half the hourly rate for work over 12 hours per day, and for more than 40 hours per week.</p>
<p>Employees working on Line 4 who objected to working the new trial schedule were given the option of not working the 2-3-2 schedule and would be reassigned to other lines. The trial was to last for 6 months, beginning in February 2016 and ending in August 2016.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>The Contractual Interpretation Issue</i></h4>
<p>The &ldquo;Notice&rdquo; language on page 3 of the agreement states:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">&ast; The company will provide at least two weeks' notice to employees upon change to or from this schedule arrangement.</p>
<p class="continued">&ast; The company and the union understand and agree that this Letter &lsqb;Agreement&rsqb; does not obligate the company or its union to establish, maintain, or continue the 2-3-2 work schedule with respect to all or any part of the plant workforce.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i>Positions</i></h4>
<p>Approximately one week before the Company intended to implement the new schedule, the Union informed the Company that its membership voted to not comply with the new schedule, and to invoke what it believed was its right to not obligate itself or the workforce to the new schedule under the &ldquo;Notice&rdquo; language.</p>
<p>The Company disagreed with this Union decision after it had relied upon the October 30 Agreement and engaged in considerable effort, both in time and expense, to implement the new schedule. It hired and expended funds to train 25-30 new employees to staff its production requirements for Line 4. It interprets the &ldquo;Notice&rdquo; language as merely a recitation that there was no obligation on the part of either the Company or the Union to establish a new schedule after the expiration of the trial period, or to maintain or continue the new schedule with Line 4 employees or any other employees in the plant after the expiration of the trial period.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>III. Evidence, Discussion and Findings</i>.</h4>
<h4 align="left"><i>Contract Interpretation Principles</i></h4>
<p>The Union has the burden of proof in a contract interpretation dispute. It must persuade the arbitrator that its position is the correct interpretation of the agreement, and of the parties' intent. The arbitrator's role is to weigh the evidence and determine whether the Union has met its burden by a preponderance or greater weight of the evidence.</p>
<p>The starting point in interpreting the parties' intent is their chosen words or language that was used to express their intent. The words and their plain or ordinary meaning are important, but the Restatement (Second) of Contracts, while focusing heavily upon the language, goes further and addresses the context in which the words are used, and the surrounding and prevailing circumstances. It states that meanings can &ldquo;almost&rdquo; never be plain except in a context. One must look at the relevant evidence of the situation and relations of the parties, the subject matter of the transaction, preliminary negotiations and statements made therein, usages of trade, and the course of dealing between the parties. &ldquo;But, after the transaction has been shown in all its length and breath, the words of the integrated agreement remain the most important evidence of intention.&rdquo;<ftnote num="2"><para><italic>Restatement (Second) of Contracts</italic>, Section 212, cmt B (1979).</para></ftnote></p>
<h4 align="center"><i>Preliminary Negotiations &ndash; The Focus Group</i></h4>
<p>The Union was well aware of the Company's need to meet its production demands. Discussions occurred in the negotiations for the CBA relative to the prospect of new production lines being added. The Union was aware of the Company's plan to add new machinery to increase its production capability. The Union leadership who eventually signed the Trial Agreement met with a peer group of members in order to determine the membership's concerns that would be addressed with the Company in the negotiations for the new Agreement. The members' main concern was obtaining a schedule that would accommodate a reasonable balance between working on machinery and equipment that would run for 27 straight days on a 24/7 basis before needing maintenance, and retaining enough time off for rest, and family time outside of the workplace. The Union, with the continued communications with the peer group, negotiated and accepted the terms of the Agreement, believing that the trial schedule reasonably addressed its concerns.</p>
<p>It is important to note that there is no language in the Agreement conditioning the Union's acceptance of the new trial schedule on a vote or ratification of the membership. The Union leadership who signed the Agreement as the exclusive bargaining agent or representative of the membership had the complete and unrestricted authority to bind its membership to the terms of the Agreement on a collective basis.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, as with many labor agreements, there remained some clarification issues that needed to be addressed and resolved. Mr. McMenamin addressed these issues in an email to Mr. Fluharty and Mr. Quickel on January 26, 2016. The intent of the email was to clarify the post-execution issues that were raised by the Union, including the confirmation that the Agreement is limited to the 6-months time period set forth in the Agreement and that the Agreement or schedule does not apply to any production lines other than Pizza Line 4. By this time, the Company had undertaken considerable expense in preparing for the trial schedule, including the hiring and training of new employees.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>The Possible Ambiguity In The Notice Provision</i></h4>
<p>It is possible to find a latent ambiguity in the Notice provision if that provision is considered in a vacuum. A latent ambiguity is one that has clearly understood words on its face, but the words as applied could be subject to different meanings. Can either party, by application of the words &ldquo;de-obligate&rdquo; their performance of the trial schedule at any time, or may they only do so after the expiration of the trial period? I find that if one looks beyond the notice clause and considers the entire Agreement, the overall purpose of the Agreement, and the communications between the parties both before and after the execution of the Agreement, one can only reasonably conclude that neither party may terminate or exit the Agreement until after it expires. It is unreasonable to believe that the parties agreed and intended that the Union, after meeting with its peer group, negotiating with the Company, agreeing to the trial terms, and then executing the Agreement, had the right the very next minute, the next day, or at any time, to de-obligate itself and walk away from its negotiated commitments under the signed Agreement. There is a 2-weeks notice requirement for a change in the schedule, but that notice requirement applies only to a Company requested change.<ftnote num="3"><para>The contract interpretation maxim: The expression of one thing excludes the other (<italic>expressio unius est exclusio alterius)</italic> would apply here. This means that the expression that the <quote>Company</quote> may change the schedule upon 2-weeks advance notice, excludes the notion that the Union may also be permitted to change the schedule.</para></ftnote> Arbitrators will always give a reasonable meaning to contractual terms instead of one that produces an unreasonable result.<ftnote num="4"><para><italic>The Common Law of the Workplace, The Views of Arbitrators</italic>, 2<superscript>nd</superscript> Ed., NAA, Theodore J. St. Antoine, BNA, Section 2.13, p. 81 (2005).</para></ftnote> I find from the evidence that both parties as a matter of good faith intended that the trial period would remain in place in order for each of them to make an informed decision as to how best to address their respective interests in dealing with the new workload requirements.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>Estoppel</i></h4>
<p>Even if the Agreement was interpreted in a manner other than by my above finding, the Union, under the evidence presented in this record would be bound to meet the terms of the Agreement during the trial period under the doctrine of Promissory or Equitable Estoppel. This doctrine prohibits one party to a contract or agreement (the Union) from changing its agreement or position when the other party (the Company) relied upon the terms of the Agreement by acting upon the other's assurances to its detriment. This occurred when the Company proceeded to comply with its obligations under the Agreement. It expended considerable time and effort in planning and executing the new work schedule. It converted Line 4 to the new schedule, and hired and trained 25-30 new employees to work the new trial schedule. Most if not all of these actions occurred until it was notified only one week before the schedule was to be implemented that the Union objected to it, based upon a vote taken by its membership.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i>Findings and Conclusion</i></h4>
<p>The evidences supports the finding that the 2-3-2 Work Schedule Trial is a valid and enforceable contract or agreement that amends, supplements, or modifies the CBA in accordance with its terms. The Notice language on page 2 is intended to provide that only the Company may change the schedule by providing at least 2-weeks notice, but unless the Company changes the schedule, the existing schedule remains during the 6-months trial term. The language further clarifies the agreement that neither party is obligated to establish, maintain, or continue the schedule after the expiration of the trial period with Line 4 or any part of the plant workforce.</p>
<h4 align="left">IV. <i>Award</i>.</h4>
<p class="continued">The grievance is denied. The Arbitrator's fees shall be paid by the Union in accordance with Article 11, Section 3 of the CBA.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>