<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF THE ARBITRATION BETWEEN International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, Local 953 And Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>AAA case No. 01-16-0003-7473</p>
<p>March 6, 2017.</p>
<p>Joseph L. Daly, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>OPINION AND AWARD</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b><i>JURISDICTION</i></b></h4>
<p>In accordance with the Collective Bargaining Agreement between Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services and IBEW, Local 953, September 1, 2013-August 31, 2016; and the Proposed Terms and Conditions of Settlement of the Labor Agreement Between Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services and Local Union 953, IBEW to become effective September 1, 2016 until the decision in this binding arbitration is made, the interest arbitration issue was submitted to Joseph L. Daly, Arbitrator, on February 22, 2017, No post-hearing briefs were filed by the parties. The decision was rendered by the Arbitrator on March 6, 2017.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b><i>ISSUE AT IMPASSE</i></b></h4>
<p>IBEW, Local 953 states the issue as:</p>
<p class="continued">In this interest arbitration, arising under Article IV, Subtitle B of the Collective Bargaining Agreement, the parties ask the arbitrator to decide whether their CBA should include due deduction (AKA dues check off) language or not?</p>
<p class="continued">Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services states the issue as:</p>
<p>Did Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services have an obligation to continue dues deductions and add the provision to the contract (for the first time), after a decision in the case of <i>International Association of Machinists District 10 and Local Lodge 873 v. Wisconsin, Number 16-cv77-wmc (2016 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 89976, at &ast;16) W.D. Wis. July 12, 2016</i>.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>POTENTIALLY RELEVANT CONTRACT LANGUAGE</b></i></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">ARTICLE II</p>
<p class="continued">Duration and Modification</p>
<p class="continued">1. This agreement, when signed by the proper officials of the Cooperative and the Union, shall become effective as of September 1, 2013, for a period to and including August 31, 2016, and shall continue from year to year thereafter subject only to cancellation by written notice, or in the alternative, to re-opening by written request for amendment or amendments, with such notice of certified mail to the other on or before 60 calendar days prior to any anniversary date of September 1, subsequent to September 1, 2016. Both parties waive and relinquish any and all right to request any change or addition to the written contract terms at any time other than amendments or cancellation as of any anniversary date as set out above. In the event amendments are requested, the terms of amendment shall be submitted by either party to the other along with the written notice requesting amendment and the terms of this agreement shall remain in full force and effect until amended terms are executed, or awarded upon arbitration as hereinafter provided for, and any such amendments relating to pay rates shall be effective as of the anniversary date at which requested.</p>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE III</p>
<p class="continued">Union and Cooperative Security</p>
<p class="continued">1. As a condition of employment, all employees subject to the provisions of this agreement, except those classified as miscellaneous unskilled, shall become members of the Union 30 days after date of employment and shall remain members thereafter by prompt payment of dues so long as they remain on the payroll in classifications covered by the agreement. Those classified as Miscellaneous unskilled shall become members, within six (6) months from the date of employment and shall remain members as previously provided. Failure to comply with the foregoing conditions shall be considered grounds for discharge.</p>
<p class="continued">ARTICLE IV</p>
<p class="continued">Grievance Procedure; Arbitration; No-Strike Clause</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Subtitle B - Arbitration</i></p>
<p class="continued">Declaration of intention. It is hereby declared to be the purpose and intent in establishing an arbitration procedure (hereinafter provided for) that said procedure shall be used only as a last resort and only after the Cooperative and the Local Union have exhausted all of the devices associated with and related to negotiations and the normal processes of collective bargaining.</p>
<p class="continued">Any grievance not resolved in the Third Step and/or any difference respecting amendments to the contract requested as provided in Section I of Article II may at the request of either party be referred to an Arbitrator, hereinafter provided for, who shall have authority to make an award determining such grievance or difference which shall be final and binding on all parties hereto. The Arbitrator shall have no authority to hear or decide violations of the no-strike, no-lockout clause alleged against the Union or Cooperative nor to hear or decide issues of representation and determination of proper unit; (which shall be decided by the processes under applicable Federal and/or State statutes), nor any authority to alter, modify or change the terms of the contract at any time excepting at any anniversary date as provided for in Section 1 of Article II.</p>
<p>Any request or notice of request for amendment or amendments to this agreement shall be deemed an election by the party making such request or giving such notice, to submit any difference with respect to such amendment or amendments, which cannot be resolved by negotiation to arbitration under this subtitle.</p>
<p class="continued">&hellip;the award of the Arbitration shall be made within 45 days of the close of testimony.</p>
<p class="continued">Proposed Terms and Conditions of Settlement</p>
<p class="continued">Of the Labor Agreement Between</p>
<p class="continued">Pierce Pepin Cooperative Services</p>
<p class="continued">And</p>
<p class="continued">Local Union 953, IBEW</p>
<p class="continued">To Become Effective September 1, 2016</p>
<p class="continued">All terms, conditions, and practices of the Labor Agreement between the IBEW, Local Union 953, and Pierce Pepin Cooperative Services expiring August 31, 2016, are to remain unchanged except as stated below:</p>
<p class="continued">2. Article III, Union and Cooperative Security, Section 1.</p>
<p class="continued">Section 1 of Article III will be deleted and the following language inserted:</p>
<p class="continued">The parties will submit to the interest arbitration already requested concerning union dues deduction, the question of the reversion to a closed shop formerly described in Article III, section 1 and will abide the decision of the arbitrator.</p>
<p class="continued">Additional items discussed outside the Collective Bargaining Agreement;</p>
<p class="continued">2. Union Dues</p>
<p class="continued">It is agreed and understand that the Parties will submit the question of continuing, ending, or altering the practice of dues deduction to binding interest arbitration, and the Parties agree to abide by the arbitrator's award. Until such time as an award is issued or the Parties mutually execute an alternative agreement as to union dues, the Parties agree to the following <i>interim</i> procedure:</p>
<p class="continued">The Cooperative will continue deducting and remitting employee's dues to the Union.</p>
<p class="continued">In the event that an employee requests a revocation of his or her dues authorization, the Cooperative may cease deducting dues 30 days after such request.</p>
<p class="continued">The Union agrees not to challenge the cessation of union dues.</p>
<p class="continued">The Parties further agree that this interim procedure will not be precedent setting, and that neither Party waives or forfeits any argument or challenge regarding the deduction of union dues that may be made at the interest arbitration or at any point following the award or execution of a mutual alternative dues deduction agreement.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>POTENTIALLY APPLICABLE WISCONSIN STATUES</b></h4>
<p class="continued">Wis. Stat. &sect;11.04(3)</p>
<p class="continued">(a) No person may require, as a condition of obtaining or continuing employment, an individual to do any of the following:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Refrain or resign from membership in, voluntary affiliation with, or voluntary financial support of a labor organization,</p></li>
<li><p>Become or remain a member of a labor organization.</p></li>
<li><p>Pay any dues, fees, assessments, or another charges or expenses of any kind or amount or provide anything of value, to a labor organization.</p></li>
<li><p>Pay to any 3<sup>rd</sup> party an amount that is in place of, equivalent to, or any portion of dues, fees, assessments, or other charges or expenses required of members of, or employees represented by, labor organization.</p></li>
</ol>
<p class="continued">(b) This subsection applies to the extent permitted under Federal law. If a provision of a contract violates this subsection, that provision is void.</p>
<p class="continued">Wis. Stat. &sect;947.20 Right to Work. Anyone who violates s. 111.04(3)(a) is guilty of a Class A misdemeanor.</p>
<p class="continued">Wis. Stat. &sect;939.51(3) Penalties for misdemeanors are as follows:</p>
<ol type="lc-letter" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>For a Class A misdemeanor, a fine not to exceed &dollar;10,000 or imprisonment not to exceed 9 months or both.</p></li>
</ol>
<h4 align="left"><b>INTRODUCTION</b></h4>
<p>Until 2015 Wisconsin had historically been a &ldquo;closed shop&rdquo;, a place of work where membership in a union is a condition for being hired and for continued employment, But in 2015, with the election of a new legislature, Wisconsin became a &ldquo;right-to-work&rdquo; state, relating to or promoting a worker's right not to be required to join a labor union or to pay dues to a labor union.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dues check off&rdquo; had been the norm between IBEM, Local 953 and Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services since 1982 (35 years), But since the 2015 change in Wisconsin law from &ldquo;closed shop&rdquo; to &ldquo;right-to-work&rdquo;, Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services perceived a risk posed by the application of the new Wisconsin law. The risk being that Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services feared being sued and dragged into fights between employees, the union and right-to-work advocacy groups.</p>
<p>Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services is also concerned about the potentiality of violating the Wisconsin criminal law if it cooperates with the union in deducting dues from the members' wages and transferring those dues to the union, As a consequence of these concerns, the union and Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services agreed &lsqb;see &ldquo;Proposed Terms and Conditions Of Settlement Of The Labor Agreement Between Pierce-Pepin. Cooperative Services and Local Union 953, IBEW To Become Effective September 1, 2016&rdquo;&rsqb; that Section 1 of Article III of the Collective Bargaining Agreement, i.e. &ldquo;as a condition of employment, all employees subject to the provisions of this agreement, accept those classified as miscellaneous, unskilled, shall become members of the union 30 days after date of employment&hellip;&rdquo; will be deleted. And that &ldquo;&lsqb;t&rsqb;he parties will submit to the interest arbitration already requested concerning union dues deduction, the question of the reversion to a closed shop formally described in Article III, Section 1 and will abide the decision of the arbitrator.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services has not stipulated that &ldquo;Local 953 has met the contract requirements for invoking binding interest arbitration because it has not submitted the demand in writing for the relief requested of a contract amendment to require continued dues deductions by PPCSI.&rdquo; &lsqb;Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services Proposed Findings of fact at 2&rsqb;.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>POSITION OF IBEW, LOCAL 953</b></h4>
<p>The position of the union is:</p>
<p>1. Dues check off has been the norm between these parties since 1982;</p>
<p>2. The basis for Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services objection to dues check off in the 2016 bargaining sessions was their perception of risks posed by the application of Wisconsin law. Any such risk has been alleviated by the December 2016 decision in <i>Machinist District 10 and Local Lodge 873 v. Wisconsin No. 16-cv-77-wmc, 2016 US. Dist, LEXIS 89976, at &ast;16 (W.D. Wis. December 28, 2016)</i>. Any such risk has been alleviated by the decision which held that Wisconsin's dues check off provisions are preempted by the Labor Management Relations Act (LMRA), the four major historical United States Statutes which provided employees shall have the right to form and join unions and bargain collectively. The LMRA provides which action or inactions constitute an unfair labor practice by employer and union. The LMRA establishes the process, of elections (conducted by the National Labor Relations Board, NLRB), to determine the desires of the employees for representation, and outlines the NLRB's powers. Generally, the LMRA covers the private sector. Government agencies are excluded. Two exceptions are national banks and mail contractors. &lsqb;See generally, Legal Resource Library at <i>www.resources.lawinfo.com</i> as of February 28, 2017&rsqb;</p>
<p>3. Bureau of Labor Statistics studies from 1959 and 1982 have established that:</p>
<ol type="lc-letter" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Dues check off in private industry is a norm by an overwhelming margin;</p></li>
<li><p>Dues check off in right-to-work states is a norm by an overwhelming margin.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>4. NLRB ruling from 2000 (citing a 1995 Bureau of National Affairs study of collective bargaining agreements) recognized that 95&percnt; of the collective bargaining agreements were found to contain dues-check off provisions, &lsqb;See <i>Hacienda Hotel and Sahara Nevada Corporation</i>, cases 28-CA-13274 and 28-CA-13275 &lsqb;July 7, 2000&rsqb;;</p>
<p>5. Summary of dues check off data concerning Local 953 in Wisconsin and elsewhere, and IBEW locals in Wisconsin, establish that dues checkoff is the norm by an overwhelming margin;</p>
<p>6. Dues checkoff data concerning Local 953 and Wisconsin Electric Coops establish dues checkoff as the norm;</p>
<p>7. Dues checkoff data concerning all Local 953 collective bargaining agreements establish dues checkoff as the norm;</p>
<p>8. Dues checkoff data concerning all IBEW Locals with Wisconsin Coop contracts establish dues checkoff as the norm;</p>
<p>9. Dues checkoff data concerning IBEW Locals in right-to-work states establish dues checkoff as the norm;</p>
<p>10. Labor arbitration decisions endorse the policy and opinions for dues checkoff: that &ldquo;it is common labor relations knowledge&hellip;that dues checkoff provisions do contribute significantly to harmonious and stable relationships between the &lsqb;collective bargaining&rsqb; parties.&rdquo; <i>Baptist Hospital of Gadsden</i>, Inc., 65LA249 (Arb, Robert B. Meberly, July 5,1975; See also New York <i>City Transit System</i>, 4LA604 (Arb. Arthur S. Meyer, Chair, September 9, 1946);</p>
<p>11. Wisconsin labor arbitration authority establishes that inclusion of dues checkoff language in a collective bargaining agreement is proper as it reflects long standing dues checkoff practice between bargaining partners (See <i>Wilmot Grade School District</i>, 1991LA Supp. 112201 (Arb, Byron Yaffe, 1991) &ldquo;The association's &lsqb;sic&rsqb; persuasively argues that its dues deduction proposal simply codifies current practice in the district and the district has failed to offer a persuasive reason why said practice should not be codified.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In view of the evidence, the union contends that dues checkoff is overwhelmingly the norm between these parties, between Local 953 and comparable employers; and between IBEW Locals and comparable employers in right-to-work and non-right-to-work states, in view of the arbitral authority endorsing the inclusion of collective bargaining dues checkoff provisions, the union requests that the arbitrator direct the inclusion of a simple dues checkoff language in the Collective Bargaining Agreement between Local 953 and the Pierce-Pepin Electric Cooperative.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>POSITION OF PIERCE-PEPIN COOPERTIVE SERVICES</b></h4>
<p>1. Wisconsin law has dramatically changed, For 35 years The parties collectively bargained under a closed shop law. But in March 2015 Wisconsin became the 25<sup>th</sup> right-to-work state in the United States. Prior to this if an employee did not join the union within 30 days the employer was required to terminate the employee. This was also in the contract. But with the change in law both the union and the employer recognize that Article III Section 1 needed to be removed from the contract.</p>
<p>What does this change mean for the collection of union dues? Does the right-to-work law in Wisconsin now prohibit Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services from participating in the withholding of union dues from the IBEW Local 953 represented employees at Pierce-Pepin?</p>
<p>2. The employer today thinks that it has an interest not knowing who is a union member and who is not, who is paying dues and who is not. Pierce-Pepin and the CEO of Pieree-Pepin feel that they are in the middle of two strongly motivated, opposing forces. The key concern of the employer and the CEO is the risk each face if Pierce-Pepin continues to participate in the withholding of union dues, The employer is concerned that it is in the &ldquo;erossfire&rdquo; between right-to-work organizations, the union, and potential criminal liability.</p>
<p>3. Further, there has never been language in the contract that make dues collection a part of the contract. While Pierce-Pepin understands the union's needs to have members pay dues, it does not want to be required to deduct those dues for fear of the language In the Wisconsin statute &ldquo;pay any dues, fees, assessments, or other charges or expanses, of any kind or amount, or provide anything of value, to a labor organization.&rdquo; Wis. Stat. 11.04(3)(a)(3). And, especially, Pierce-Pepin and its management are in fear of facing potential criminal liability bemuse &ldquo;&lsqb;A&rsqb;nyone who violates s. 111.04(3)(a) is guilty of a Class A misdemeanor,&rdquo; As far as Pierce-Pepin is concerned &ldquo;Wisconsin in the present political atmosphere has greatly increased the risks to this employer&rdquo; &lsqb;Argument of Counsel on behalf of Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services during arbitration hearing&rsqb;. The fear of this risk is simply too great.</p>
<p>4. The authority of the arbitrator should not extend to imposing on this employer a risk of both civil and criminal liability. The employer's evaluation of the level of risk should be its own. The employer neither wants to favor nor disfavor the union. The change in the law raises the risk for Pierce-Pepin and its management. This is an uncertain environment filled with stress, fear and unease. It is difficult to do a risk assessment of this situation due to the law and the cases presently moving through the courts.</p>
<p>5. The employer is not getting any compensation if it were to withhold the union dues and forward them to the union. The union is getting a &ldquo;favor&rdquo; if the employer is required to do so. This would be in direct violation of the law. The law is in a state of flux and the employer should not be required by an arbitrator to do something it is no longer willing nor legally allowed to do.</p>
<p>6. Past practice cannot be binding in this case. The law has changed. The contract has ended. The employer has notified the union it does not intend to continue withholding the union dues. This is an interest arbitration. The employer has given notice and is willing to bargain. But it does not want to take the risk nor break the law. Even if this has been a long standing past practice, the change in the law has made it a requirement that such a past practice ends. Again, the employer feels in the middle of a state of law in flux. The law clearly states that the employer cannot provide anything of value to the labor organization. A deduction of dues provides something of value to the union. By withholding union dues the employer would be expending some resources, yet the union has not offered any compensation for expending such resourees. In the past, when Wisconsin was a closed shop, the employer had a value in knowing who was a member of the union, but now under this new law the employer does not.</p>
<p>Further, it Is easy for the union to have its members sign an authorization from each member's bank to allow direct deposit from the member's bank to the union. The employer does not want to know who is in the union and who is or is not paying membership dues. It simply cannot favor or disfavor the union.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i><b>DECISION AND RATIONALE</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. Past practice.</b></h4>
<p>While it has been past practice since 1982 for the employer to withhold union dues when the member signs an authorization form to allow the employer to do so, the law has now changed. This has forced both the union and the employer to eliminate Article III Section 1 which read that &ldquo;all employees subject to provisions of the agreement shall become members of the union 30 days after date of employment and shall remain members thereafter by prompt payment of dues&rdquo;, Nothing in the contract ever spoke to the requirement that the employer withhold union dues. Yet, past practice has been that the employer has done so and forwarded the dues to the union for each member who has signed the authorization form, Clearly, that provision had to be eliminated due to the change in law.</p>
<p>But that elimination does not answer the question in this interest arbitration arising under Article IV, Subtitle B of the Collective Bargaining Agreement. The question this arbitrator must answer is: whether the Collective Bargaining Agreement should include dues deduction (also known as dues checkoff) language or not. The employer has notified the union it does not wish to continue the past practice in light of the change in law and the employer's assessment that it faces both civil and criminal risks.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. Case Law</b></h4>
<p>On August 27, 2015, the. National Labor Relations Board, in <i>Lincoln Lutheran of Racine, 362 NLRB No.188</i>, overturned 53 years of precedent holding that, like most other terms and conditions of employment, an employer's obligation to checkoff union dues <i>continues</i> after expiration of a collective bargaining agreement that contains such a provision. While the Collective Bargaining Agreement between IBEW, Local 953 and Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services does not contain a specific checkoff provision, the past practice of the parties has been to do so. Therefore, while <i>Lincoln Lutheran may</i> not be directly applicable, the parties did agree in light <i>of Lincoln Lutheran</i> in its Proposed Terms and Conditions of Settlement effective September 1, 2016, to &ldquo;continue deducting and remitting employee's dues to the Union&rdquo; and await the decision in this instant arbitration case. This case is on appeal.</p>
<p>In December 2016 US Distriet Court for the Western District of Wisconsin Judge William M. Conley held in <i>International Assocication of Machinists District 10 and Local Lodge 873 v. Ray Allen and James R. Scott</i>, Case No. 16-cv-77-wmc, that section nine of 2015 Wisconsin Act 1, codified as Wis. Stat. &sect;11.06(1)(i) is unconstitutional under the supremacy clause of the United States Constitution, as preempted by &sect;302 of the Labor Management Relations Act, codified as 29 U.S.C. &sect;186(c)(4), In other words, the 30-day part of the Wisconsin dues checkoff provisions is preempted by LMRA. The Wisconsin law allows an employee 30 days to no longer pay into the union. But the LMRA permits dues checkoff authorizations that are irrevocable for up to one year, 29 U.S.C. &sect;186(c)(4). Judge Connolly held that the Wisconsin 30-day rule allowing the ending of dues checkoff authorizations is unconstitutional because of the preemption doctrine.</p>
<p>In <i>International Union of Operating Engineers Local 139 and International Union of Operating Engineers Local 420 v. Brad Schimel, James R. Scott, and Anthony Arnold</i>, United States Distriet Court for the Eastern District of Wisconsin Judge J. P. Stadtmueller held that the NLRA does not preempt the Wisconsin law. This case does not answer the question presented in this arbitration matter. This case is on appeal.</p>
<p>In <i>International Association of Machinists District 10 and its Local Lodge 1061, United Steelworkers District 2, and Wisconsin State AFL-CIO v. State of Wisconsin, Scott Walker, Brad Schimel, James R. Scott, and Rodney G. Pasch</i>, &lsqb;find proper citation&rsqb;, Wisconsin Dane County Circuit Court Judge William C. Foust held that Act 1 was an unconstitutional takings under Wisconsin Constitution &ldquo;the property of no person shall be taken for public use without just compensation therefore.&rdquo; Wis, Const, Art, I Section 15. Consequently, the law itself was declared unconstitutional by Judge Foust. This ease also does not answer the question presented at this arbitration. This case is on appeal.</p>
<p>As stated above, each of the above cases have been appealed. There is no question the law is in a state of flux. However, these cases do not address the specific question presented in this arbitration. Obviously, the law being in a state of flux causes Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services and its management team strong anxiety and some understandable fear. Pierce-Pepin and its CEO properly ask the question, what potential civil and criminal liabilities might be faced in-light of the 2015 Wisconsin right-to-work law and the past practice, since 1982, of dues withholding by the employer and forwarding those dues to the union</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>C. Potential Risk to Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services</b>.</h4>
<p>None of the above court cases answers the questions of risk raised by the employer the CEO of potential civil or criminal risk if it continues dues checkoff. While the law is in a state of flux, the union has proved by a fair preponderance of the evidence that dues checkoff in the private industry is the norm both in closed shop states and in right-to-work states. An NRLB ruling from 2000 <i>Hacienda Hotel, Inc</i>, Cases 28-CA-13274 and 28-CA-13275, July 7, 2000 citing a 1995 Bureau of National. Affairs study of &ldquo;<i>Major Collective Bargaining Agreements: Union Security and Dues Checkoff Provisions</i>&rdquo;, US Department of Labor, Bulletin 1425-21, May 1982, recognizes that 95&percnt; of the collective bargaining agreements wore found to contain dues-checkoff provisions.</p>
<p>Local 953 has established that dues checkoff is the norm by an overwhelming margin. Dues checkoff data concerning all IBEW locals with Wisconsin Coops establish dues checkoff as the norm. Dues checkoff concerning IBEW locals in right-to-work states establish dues checkoff as the norm. Labor arbitration decision endorse the policy for dues checkoffs. The policy behind dues checkoff is that they &ldquo;contribute significantly to harmonious and stable relationships between the. &lsqb;collective bargaining&rsqb; parties.&rdquo; <i>Baptist Hospital of Gadsden, Inc., 65LA248</i> (Arb. Robert B. Meberly, 1975).</p>
<p>While the &ldquo;risk&rdquo; or &ldquo;fear of risk&rdquo; is rational, a careful analysis of the law, the case law, and the norms show that the &ldquo;risk&rdquo; is based more on &ldquo;fear of risk&rdquo; than on credible data. The data does not support that the change in the Wisconsin law from &ldquo;closed shop&rdquo; to &ldquo;Tight-to-work&rdquo; has raised the risk, it certainly has raised &ldquo;fear of change,&rdquo; But &ldquo;fear of change&rdquo; does not support proof of a credible, factually based raised risk. While it is true that lawsuits may come in this politically charged environment concerning closed shop versus right-to-work, that is simply the cost of doing business in this society at this present time. Fear of lawsuits in a politically charged environment is quite different from a credible, factually based risk of violation of the law, the contract and/or the Constitution. While uncertainty can cause stress, fear and unease, uncertainty is quite different from proof of a credible, factually based risk of violation of the law, A careful assessment of law, facts, statutes, norms, contracts, and past practice shows that the &ldquo;fear of risk&rdquo; does not credibly or factually support &ldquo;favoring or disfavoring&rdquo; the union, The law is clear. It is legal in a close shop state and a right.to.work state such as Wisconsin for an employer to deduct union dues when an employee has a valid, signed authorization font, In this case, each of the represented employees have signed such a form, In essence, the employee Is simply telling the employer to assign part of her/his wages to the union, As a Finding of Fact and a Conclusion of Law authorized dues deduction/check-off in Wisconsin is neither &ldquo;favoring&rdquo; nor &ldquo;disfavoring&rdquo; the union.</p>
<p>The statistics presented by the union further support this finding. Fair interpretation of the statisties show that moat employers and unions have agreed to dues checkoff, it is the norm both in Wisconsin and throughout the United States, in closed shop states and in right-to-work States.</p>
<p>While past practice does not answer the question; 35 years of continuous legal practice does justify the inclusion of words in the CBA to describe this practice to make clear that the arbitrator is ordering Pieree-Pepin Cooperative to deduct union dues/check-off dues by inclusion of the clarifying language into the CBA. The parties have submitted this issue to this arbitrator in an interest arbitration case. The arbitrator has the authority given by the parties and arbitration law to add language into the final agreement to clarify this obligation and to relieve the employer and the CEO of concern of violation of any Wisconsin civil or criminal.</p>
<p>Today the law of Wisconsin, the norms, and, yes, even the law in a state of flux, permits dues deductions under Wisconsin right-to-work law. Wis. Stat. &sect;111.04(3)(a). That law states that &ldquo;no person may require, <i>as a condition of obtaining or continuing employment</i>, an individual to &hellip; (3) pay any dues, fees, assessments or other charges or expenses of any kind or amount or provide anything of value to a labor organization&rdquo; (emphasis added). The dues checkoff is not a condition of obtaining or continuing employment. If a member chooses not to pay union dues or continue to be a member of the union, she/he may certainly obtain or continue employment. The employer is not and should not terminate the employee. The union must not ask that an employee be not hired or fired because the employee does not favor the union. The union is simply asking the employer to turn over the money that the employee <i>has authorized by singing the authorization form</i> telling the employer to withhold the money and forward it to the union, This neither favors nor disfavors the union. Further, criminal liability could only attach if the employer refused to hire or fired an employee for refusing to pay union dues, which the employer plainly will not do. Therefore, the employer may easily avoid any criminal pitfall, &ldquo;Checkoff authorizations irrevocable for one year after dato do not amount to compulsory unionism as to employees who wish withdraw from membership prior to that time.&rdquo; <i>SeaPak, 300 F.Supp. at 1201</i>.</p>
<p>The Wisconsin's &ldquo;right-to-work&rdquo; statute holds no criminal sanctions for proper dues deduction. Consequently, as a Finding of Fact and a Conclusion of Law there is no reasonable or credible risk to Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services or its management of civil or criminal liability under Wisconsin Statutes for dues deductions administered by the employer and forwarded to the union when each member of the union has signed the proper authorization form.</p>
<p>This is an interest arbitration. The parties have reached an impasse on the specific issue of dues deductions/checkoff. The parties have agreed to empower the arbitrator to determine the impasse. Part of the determination is to decide whether to clarify that there is now going to continue to be a dues deduction in the contract. Typically, in an interest arbitration, an arbitrator will try to determine what would have occurred if the parties had continued negotiating to resolution. In this case while the law is still in flux, the law, the facts, the norms, NLRB decisions, and case law indicate that dues deductions both in closed shops and in right-to-work states are legal and not contrary to law when the employees sign proper authorization forms. The employee is simply asking the employer to withhold a certain amount of money and forward it to the union. It does not indicate in any manner that the employer is favoring or disfavoring the union. The employer is doing what the employee has asked the employer to do with the employee's own money. Since the employer already has a system of withholding money to pay state and federal taxes, social security, health inaurance, pension contributions, direct deposit, etc., it takes minimal effort and time to now withhold and forward union dues upon request of the employee. This &ldquo;deminimus&rdquo; effort does not favor or disfavor the union.</p>
<p>It does not place the employer at credible risk of violating the Wisconsin right-to-work statutes or the criminal laws of Wisconsin. The employer is not making it, &ldquo;a condition of obtaining or continuing employment&rdquo; if the employee does not want to pay union dues any further.</p>
<p>If IBEW Local 953 and Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services had continued to bargain to finality in this contract, it is reasonable and rational that they would have included a clarifying provision in the contract related to voluntary written authorization for the deduction of union dues and the administration of those dues by the employer to be forwarded to the union. The clarifying provision in the contract &lsqb;taking into account the law, norms, policy behind dues deductions/checkoff, arbitral precedent, and continued positive labor-management relationships between this union and this employer&rsqb;, shall read:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">Upon the receipt of a voluntary written authorization and after 30 working days, Pierce-Pepin Cooperative Services, Inc. will deduct the uniformly leveled dues from the pay of each IBEW member consistent with applicable law.</p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>