<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION between DS Services of America, Inc. and Teamsters Local Union No. 250</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>January 19, 2017.</p>
<p>John M. Felice, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>NATURE OF THE GRIEVANCE</b></i></h4>
<p>The undersigned Arbitrator was selected by the parties to hear and decide a matter in dispute between DS Services of America, Inc., hereinafter referred to as &ldquo;Company&rdquo;, and Teamsters Local Union No. 250, hereinafter referred to as &ldquo;Union&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The dispute is properly before the Arbitrator in accordance with the Collective Bargaining Agreement, hereinafter referred to as &ldquo;CBA&rdquo;, between the parties.</p>
<p>On October 25, 2016, a hearing was held in Pittsburgh, PA, at which time a full opportunity to introduce evidence and examine and cross-examine witnesses was afforded to both parties. Post hearing briefs were filed by the parties on December 7, 2016.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>ISSUE</b></i></h4>
<p>Was Matt Ransom, hereinafter referred to as &ldquo;the Grievant&rdquo;, discharged for just cause, if not, what shall be the remedy?</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>BACKGROUND</b></i></h4>
<p>The Grievant was discharged on June 3, 2016 for his repeated failure to wear a seatbelt while operating a company vehicle. Thereupon, the Grievant filed a grievance, on June 6, 2016, protesting the discharge. The Company, after reviewing the matter, denied the grievance.</p>
<p>When the parties were unable to resolve the dispute by means of the grievance procedure they submitted the matter to the undersigned arbitrator for final and binding disposition.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>PERTINENT CONTRACT PROVISIONS</b></i></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>Article IV, Management Rights, Section 1.</b> &ldquo;It is agreed that the operation of the plant and the direction of the employees, including, but not limited to, the making and enforcing of rules of conduct, including safety rules and testing for alcohol and drugs to ensure orderly, safe and efficient operations, the determining of competency, the right to hire, to discharge for any cause, to lay off for lack of work, are rights vested exclusively in the management of the Company.</p>
<p class="continued">&ldquo;<b>Article XVI, Grievance Procedure, Section 4.</b> &ldquo;It is expressly understood that the Arbitrator shall have no power to add to or subtract from, change or modify any provision of the Agreement but shall be authorized only to interpret the existing provisions of the Agreement and apply them to the specific facts of the grievance or dispute.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>CONTENTIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<p>The Union contends that the Company failed to impose, a suspension prior to the discharge of the Grievant, thus violating a basic tenet of progressive discipline. Further, it asserts that the Company does not have a written policy requiring loaders, the position held by the Grievant, to wear seatbelts. Accordingly, the Union requests the grievance be sustained and that the Grievant be reinstated with full back pay and made whole.</p>
<p>The Company contends that it reserves the right to operate its business and provide for the safety of employees and the right to adopt a seatbelt requirement to reduce the potential for injuries, death and property damage. It further asserts that the Grievant was a short-term employee who willfully disregarded the Company's seatbelt rule, despite the Company's repeated efforts through counseling, verbal and written warnings, to remediate the Grievant's behavior. The Company asserts it had just cause to discharge the Grievant. Accordingly, the Company requests that the instant grievance be denied.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>FINDINGS AND CONCLUSION</b></i></h4>
<p>The Grievant was employed by the Company in the position of loader. The Grievant's duties included driving 26,000 to 33,000-pound route delivery trucks around the Company's facility often referred to as &ldquo;the yard&rdquo;. Fueling the trucks, pulling the trucks into the warehouse space for loading and unloading, taking the trucks to checkers to assure they were loaded properly and moving the trucks and parking them so that the trucks were ready for the route sales representatives to make deliveries the following day.</p>
<p>For safety reasons, the Company requires all employees including loaders to wear seatbelts when operating company vehicles or when a vehicle is in motion. It was undisputed on the record that this safety rule applies whether or not the employee is on Company property or on public roads. Unrebutted testimony also reveals that the seatbelt rule applies regardless of the type of vehicle being operated, whether it is a forklift, yard dog or route delivery trucks. The record reveals that loaders, including the Grievant, were aware of the requirement to wear a seatbelt from their time of hire.</p>
<p>The Discipline and Work Rules Policy in the associate handbook, which the Grievant acknowledged receiving, provides, inter alia, that the Company follows a disciplinary process, which involves verbal coaching/counseling, written warning, final written warning, termination, but the Company retains the discretion to escalate the process by imposing immediate termination. Said policy provides that failure to follow safety rules constitutes conduct that could result in immediate termination of employment. In addition, the work rules provide that violating safety rules or engaging in conduct that creates a health, safety, or security hazard could result in disciplinary action up to and including termination. Company representatives testified that they verbally counsel employees to correct behavior without proceeding to formal disciplinary action. However, if the counseling does not remedy the problem, they would then issue a documented verbal warning, written warning and final warning prior to invoking termination.</p>
<p>In the instant case, the Company determined, through clips received from Drive Cam, that the Grievant was not always wearing his seatbelt while operating a company vehicle. The Company utilizes a third-party event recording system called Drive Cam in their route delivery trucks. Drive Cam captures on video, among other things, unsafe driving behaviors such as failure to wear a seatbelt, distracted driving, speeding, tailgating, etc. The third-party vendor provides the Company with Drive Cam video clips depicting unsafe behaviors so that the Company can address them with its employees. The overall goal is to identify unsafe behaviors and provide employees with coaching and corrective actions to remediate such behaviors in the future. The Union argued that the Drive Cam clips, used as evidence in the discharge of the Grievant, were used in a punitive fashion. However, no evidence of a probative value was adduced to demonstrate that the use of the Drive Cam was for punitive purposes.</p>
<p>The Company's Production Manager, James Sobieralski, spoke to the Grievant several times to remind him that he was required to wear a seatbelt when operating a company vehicle. When the Grievant's behavior continued, Sobieralski met with Grievant and issued a written coaching/counseling warning on August 14, 2015. The coaching/counseling document explicitly instructed the Grievant that Company policy required employees to wear seatbelts, at all times, while their vehicle is in motion. Neither the Union nor the Grievant filed a grievance regarding this warning. Four (4) days after receiving the coaching/counseling document, the Drive Cam showed the Grievant was again not wearing his seatbelt while pulling the route delivery truck into the warehouse. On August 19, 2015, the Grievant was issued a verbal warning for this violation. Once again, the document specified that, for safety reasons, the Grievant was required to wear a seatbelt when driving a company vehicle. In addition, the warning stated that future incidents of this violation will result in further disciplinary action. The Grievant indicated on the verbal warning that he agreed with this notice and he checked the box indicating that he did not request a meeting with the next level of management to appeal the verbal warning, nor was any grievance filed.</p>
<p>On January 8, 2016, the Grievant was issued a written warning based on clips received from the Drive Cam where the Grievant was found to be driving the company vehicle without wearing a seatbelt on two (2) additional occasions. The written warning stated, &ldquo;it is imperative that you understand the importance of following Company policy, which is employees must wear seatbelts at all times when in a company vehicle.&rdquo; The written warning further stated any future reoccurrences may result in further disciplinary action, up to and including termination. The Grievant, at that time, did not claim a lack of knowledge of, or disagreement with, the Company's seatbelt rule. Further, no grievance was filed challenging the written warning.</p>
<p>Approximately one week later, after receiving a written warning for failure to wear a seatbelt, the Drive Cam again verified that the Grievant was operating a company route delivery truck without wearing a seatbelt. Five (5) days later, based on clips from the Drive Cam, the Grievant was again driving a route delivery truck without wearing his seatbelt. The next step in the Company's discipline policy was a final written warning. On January 21, 2016, the Grievant was given a final written warning. Once again, he was instructed that he must wear a seatbelt at all times when driving a company vehicle and the next incident could lead to termination. The Grievant did not deny that he violated the safety rule. No grievance was filed regarding this final written warning.</p>
<p>Throughout the period, May 20, 2016 to May 27, 2016, after receiving his final written warning, the Drive Cam recorded that the Grievant was again operating a company route delivery truck without wearing a seatbelt on three (3) different days. As a result, on May 31, 2016, the Grievant was suspended pending an investigation. During the suspension, the Grievant disputed that he should not be required to wear a seatbelt. In unrebutted testimony, the Grievant said that if he gets fired, &ldquo;it is because the rules are stupid, that he did not need to wear a seatbelt and that the Company should do what you gotta do&rdquo;. Despite the Company's repeated efforts to require the Grievant to wear a seatbelt, the Grievant simply refused to do so because he did not agree with the seatbelt rule. Even in the final investigatory meeting prior to his discharge, the Grievant insisted that he did not need to wear a seatbelt because the rule was among other things, &ldquo;stupid&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The thrust of the Union's argument is that fastening seatbelts every time a loader moves his vehicle is inconvenient since they enter and exit their vehicles a significant number of times per shift. Notwithstanding that the Grievant found it inconvenient, the Company has the responsibility to ensure a safe workplace and requiring the use of a seatbelt is a reasonable safety requirement. The Grievant testified &ldquo;it doesn't take too long to put on the seatbelt and that it was worth the time it took&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The Union also argues that without a suspension preceding the discharge, the Grievant could not reasonably be expected to realize that his job was in jeopardy, and that the purpose of progressive discipline is to gradually increase the severity of punishment so that the employee understands that continued violations will lead to discharge. However, the Grievant had sufficient notice of the seatbelt rule and the consequences for failing to wear the seatbelt. By the time the Grievant was discharged, he had personally received four (4) written warnings that said, clearly and unequivocally, that he was required to wear a seatbelt, while operating company vehicles. The Grievant never challenged or disputed the requirement that he wear a seatbelt upon receipt of those warnings. When Sobieralski issued a final warning and indicated that the next incident of this nature may lead to termination, the Grievant did not deny violating the seatbelt rule or indicate any lack of understanding as to his status in the disciplinary process. There is no provision in Company policy or the CBA that specifies that a suspension must be issued prior to the discharge of any employee.</p>
<p>The Union argues that the requirement to wear a seatbelt was not always enforced. However, Sobieralski testified unrebutted that he has been consistently counseling employees, including loaders who were found to have not worn their seatbelts. Sobieralski testified in counseling two (2) other loaders. Subseqently, they remediated their behavior and continued to wear a seatbelt.</p>
<p>The Union asserts that the Grievant was subjected to disparate treatment by referring to a route sales representative, David Spolan, who was allowed to operate a truck without wearing a seatbelt. Spolan was governed by a bargaining unit separate and apart from the local Union in the instant case. However, it was undisputed that Spolan did not wear seatbelts for a period of time, approximately two (2) years. The Company tried to replace the seatbelt on his vehicle several times before they got one big enough to fit the Grievant. Spolan testified that the Company &ldquo;finally got a regular seatbelt installed that would fit me&rdquo;. Spolan, in unrebutted testimony, admitted that once the Company got a seatbelt that fit, he starting wearing a seatbelt.</p>
<p>Spolan further testified that the Company would not allow him to drive without a seatbelt once they started enforcing the seatbelt rule in 2014 which was before the Grievant was hired by the Company. No evidence of a probative value was adduced to demonstrate that the Company has not consistently enforced the seatbelt requirement during the time period the Grievant was employed by the Company. The Grievant himself admitted in testimony that he knew of the requirement to wear a seatbelt in August 2015. There was no evidence adduced to suggest that the Company treated the Grievant in an arbitrary or capricious manner, or that the Grievant was held to a different standard than similarly situated employees.</p>
<p>The Union raised the discipline imposed on Lamont Davis, who was also a loader, for not wearing a seatbelt as another example of disparate treatment. However, a review of the record reveals that he was treated consistent with the way the Grievant was treated when the Company discovered that Davis was operating a Company vehicle without wearing a seatbelt on numerous occasions. It was undisputed on the record that the Company proceeded through this same process of informal counseling, verbal warning, written warning, final written warning and then termination.</p>
<p>In the instant case, the Grievant had ample opportunity to abide by the Company's safety rule that requires all employees to wear a seatbelt while driving company vehicles. The pivotal consideration in this case is the inquiry into the propriety of the Grievant's discharge based on him engaging in a deliberate and willful refusal to carry out management's instruction. This act constitutes insubordination which inextricably requires an act of disobedience. The Grievant's behavior rises to a level above mere disobedience and demonstrates a willful defiance in failing to submit to authority. Arbitrators generally employ a standard in such matters by requiring that a direct and unequivocal instruction be given to the employee. In the instant case, the Grievant was clearly given such instruction of the Company's safety rule and he decided to totally ignore the seatbelt requirement.</p>
<p>This is a clear case where the Grievant resorted to self-help, rather than to the grievance procedure. Most arbitrators affirm that employees must not take matters into their own hands, but must obey management's instruction, carry out the instruction, even when they believe that it may be in violation of the labor agreement and then turn to the grievance procedure for relief.</p>
<p>Arbitrable authority clearly provides that employees must avail themselves of the grievance procedure for matters subject thereto in lieu of taking matters into their own hands. The only exception to the general rule, which is not evident in the instant case, is where obedience to an order would expose the employee to a serious health or safety hazard. To the contrary, in the instant case, the wearing of a seatbelt was to protect the Grievant from potential health or safety hazards. After reviewing the entire record in the instant case, the Arbitrator finds that the Company had just cause to discharge the Grievant.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>On the basis of the foregoing, and after considering the facts and evidence submitted in the instant case and the arguments proffered by the parties' in their respective post-hearing briefs, the grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>