<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between: VILLAGE OF CAHOKIA, ILLINOIS, Employer, and INTERNATIONAL UNION OF OPERATING ENGINEERS, Union.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Grievant: Joi Fuller FMCS&num; 15-03658-A</p>
<p>April 1, 2016.</p>
<p>George L. Fitzsimmons, Arbitrator</p>
<table width="585" columns="1">
<caption><i>TABLE OF CONTENTS</i></caption>
<tr>
<td width="5%"><p></p></td>
<td width="85%"><p></p></td>
<td width="10%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>I. BACKGROUND <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>II. ISSUE <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>III. RELEVANT DOCUMENTS <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>IV. SUMMARY POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>5</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>A. COMPANY <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>5</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>B. UNION <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>5</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>V. SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>5</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>VI. DISCUSSION AND DECISION <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>6</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>VII. AWARD <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>9</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>I. BACKGROUND</b></i></h4>
<p>Cahokia, Illinois (hereinafter &ldquo;Employer&rdquo;) is a village located in St. Clair County, Illinois. The International Union of Operating Engineers, Local 5201, (hereinafter &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) represents bargaining unit members including Grievant, Joi Fuller. The Employer and Union entered into a Collective Bargaining Agreement (hereinafter &ldquo;Contract&rdquo;) which was in full force and effect at all relevant times herein. (Jt.Ex.1). This dispute herein involves Grievant's discharge by the Employer. Following that discharge, the Grievant filed the grievance herein (Jt.Ex.2). The parties stipulated that there were no procedural questions and the grievance was properly before Arbitrator Fitzsimmons for decision.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>II. ISSUES</b></i></h4>
<p>Whether there is a just cause requirement in the Miscellaneous Contract?</p>
<p>Was Grievant discharged for just cause? If not, what shall be the remedy?</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>III. RELEVANT DOCUMENTS</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="center"><i>ARTICLE III &ndash; HIRING CLAUSE</i></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">The parties recognize the fact that the Union's knowledge and experience with the industry here involved, together with the sources of competent manpower available to it, can be of assistance to the Employer in recruiting needed Employees. It is, therefore, agreed that whenever Employees are to be hired the Employer shall include the Union among the persons, firms or corporations to be notified and shall afford the Union an opportunity to recommend job applicants. The Employer further agrees that it will give such applications due consideration consistent with the provisions of applicable State and Federal labor laws.</p>
<p class="continued">All notifications of needed Employees shall specify the name and location of the job in question, the probable duration of the job, the class or classes of Employees to be hired, the number of Employees required in each class, the probable length of employment of those in each class, and the experience and qualifications desired of Employees.</p>
<p class="continued">The Employer shall notify the Union whenever Employees are hired, giving their names and addresses, the date of employment, and the job classifications to which they are assigned.</p>
<p class="continued">The probationary period for new hires will be ninety (90) days.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i>ARTICLE IV &ndash; SCOPE</i></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><i>SECTION 1.</i> This agreement shall cover Employees engaged in the performance of &ldquo;Miscellaneous Employees&rdquo; for the Village of Cahokia. The term within the meaning of this Agreement shall be held to be the service of Clerks, Secretaries, Golf Course Mechanics and Code Enforcement Officers.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i>ARTICLE V &ndash; SENIORITY</i></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><i>SECTION 6.</i> New Employees seniority will be attained at the end of a 90-day probation period <i>(which may be extended for an additional thirty (30) days by mutual agreement of the parties)</i>, which at that time, the Mayor will review and talk to the trustees for approval.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>SECTION 8.</i> Part-time and Temporary Employees</p>
<ol type="lc-letter" bind-char="period" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Part-time Employees are defined as Employees who work fewer that forty (40) hours per week. Such Employees performing work within the scope of this Agreement shall be included in the bargaining unit.</p></li>
<li><p>Temporary Employees performing work within the scope of this Agreement shall have no call-back right nor will they accumulate seniority <i>or receive fringe benefits</i> until completion of their probationary period. <i>Upon mutual agreement of the parties, the 90-day probationary</i> period <i>may be extended by an additional thirty (30) days.</i></p></li></ol></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i>ARTICLE XV &ndash; GRIEVANCE AND ARBITRATION PROCEDURE</i></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Should any differences arise between the Village and the Union or any Employees covered by this Agreement as to the meaning, interpretation, or application of this Agreement, such differences shall be settled in the following manner:</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Step 1.</i> The aggrieved Employee or Employees shall first take the matter to the Union steward, who in turn, will take up the grievance with the supervisor within two (2) working days of the event being grieved. If a satisfactory resolution is not reached with the supervisor, the Employee shall submit such grievance in writing to the Union representative.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Step 2.</i> The Union representative shall refer the written grievance to the Village's designated representative. If a satisfactory resolution is not reached promptly, either the Union or the Village upon written notice to the other party may refer the grievance to arbitration as provided hereinafter.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Sten 3.</i> Any grievance not resolved between the parties as provided hereinabove may be referred to an arbitrator. In the event the Union and the Village are unable to agree upon an impartial arbitrator within ten (10) days upon written notice of arbitration, the parties may jointly or individually request that the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service (FMCS) submit a panel of five (5) arbitrators. Each party shall strike the names of two persons on the panel list, the first party to strike being selected by the toss of a coin. The remaining name shall be the person to be named as arbitrator. The decision of the arbitrator shall be final and binding. The fee and expenses of the arbitrator shall be borne equally by the Union and the Village. (Jt.Ex.1).</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>IV. SUMMARY POSITION OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>Employer</i></h4>
<p>1. That there is no just cause provision in the Miscellaneous Contract.</p>
<p>2. That Grievant is a probationary employee who was terminated within ninety days after being hired as a full-time clerk in the Water &amp; Sewer Department.</p>
<p>3. That Grievant was not hired legally.</p>
<p>4. That Grievant's employment was terminated for just cause.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>Union</i></h4>
<p>1. That the just cause provision in the Miscellaneous Contract is implied and limits the Employer's right to discipline employees.</p>
<p>2. That the Employer must prove by a preponderance of the evidence that it had just cause to terminate Grievant's employment.</p>
<p>3. That the hiring of Grievant was lawful and done pursuant to the Village Ordinances.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>V. SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE</b></i></h4>
<p><i>Curtis McCall</i> testified he was elected Mayor of Cahokia, Illinois on April 7, 2015 following a hotly contested election. He ran on a platform of revitalizing the city and reforming its policies. He did not officially take office until May 12, 2015. Thereafter, he determined that the former Mayor had made new hires and transfers between the date of the election and the date he took office. In particular he learned that Grievant, Joi Fuller, a part-time employee of the City for three years, had been hired as a full-time Clerk in the Water &amp; Sewer Department on April 28, 2015. (Emp.Ex.4). Grievant had worked part-time in that Department since January, 2014 and was not a dues paying member of the Union until she became a full-time employee on April 28, 2015. Grievant first paid Union dues on May 8, 2015. He also reviewed Grievant's time cards during 2014-2015 and found numerous errors and inconsistencies. (Emp.Ex.11). He partially based Grievant's termination on time card discrepancies. However, the terminated her without cause as he determined she was a &ldquo;new hire&rdquo; and still in her ninety day probationary period.</p>
<p><i>McCall</i> further testified on cross-examination that his new hires included five employees with felony convictions. He admitted that he terminated seven employees who were Union members and none of those terminations related to job performance. He also admitted that the Contract does not state that the ninety day probationary period begins when an employee begins paying Union dues. Grievant had an excellent work history with no discipline or job performance issues during her three years working for the Village. He understood that the Union's position is that Grievant was not a new hire subject to the ninety day probationary period as she worked for the Village for more than three years.</p>
<p><i>Gary Cornwell</i> testified he served as Mayor for four years until he was defeated in the April 28, 2015 election. He continued his duties as Mayor until May 12, 2015 when Curtis McCall took office. He first hired Grievant on March 27, 2012 as a part-time employee in the Village Fitness Center. Grievant was an excellent employee who received positive reviews from her, supervisors and volunteered without pay on numerous Village holiday events. In January 2014 he appointed Grievant to work as a part-time Clerk in the Water &amp; Sewer Department where she worked thirty-two hours weekly. She performed the same duties as the two full-time Clerks in that department. He identified the provision in the Contract which stated that part-time employees &ldquo;shall be included in the bargaining unit.&rdquo; (Jt.Ex.I,Sec.8(a)). He determined to elevate Grievant to a full-time Clerk for several reasons. First, historically there were three full-time Clerks in the Water &amp; Sewer Department. Second, the City had additional funds available due to retirements and completion of capital projects. (T. 133-134). At the meeting on April 28, 2015 the trustees passed an ordinance hiring Grievant on a full-time basis. (Emp.Ex.4) (T.134-137). He did not vote on her hiring. Immediately thereafter he called the Union business agent and also sent him a letter regarding Grievant's hiring. He did not consider Grievant a &ldquo;new hire&rdquo; subject to the ninety day probationary period as she was employed by the Village for more than three years. (T.137-141). He admitted that he took a different position several years earlier when Wes Wofford was hired full-time. In that case the Union filed a grievance but the case never went to arbitration as Wofford settled his case against the Employer and did not return to work. (Emp.Exs.13,14) (T.175-178). He identified the job bid sheet for the full-time Clerk position which was posted on February 25, 2015 six weeks before he was defeated for reelection. (Union.Ex.10).</p>
<p><i>Chad Goldschmidt</i> testified he has been employed by the Union for sixteen years and now serves as the Union's Business Representative. (T.193-196). He attended a meeting with the Mayor and the Village attorney several weeks after the Mayor terminated Grievant. No mention was made of any issues with job performance or time card irregularities as a reason or Grievant's termination.</p>
<p><i>Michael Parkinson</i> testified he served as Business Representative for the Union for seventeen years. He is very familiar with the Contract herein which includes part-time and full-time employees in the bargaining unit. (T.204-206). If he knew that Grievant had been performing bargaining unit work as a part-time employee in the Water &amp; Sewer Department he would have told her to pay Union dues. (T.206-207). On April 28, 2015 Mayor Cornwell notified him that Grievant was now a full-time employee. Grievant was not subject to the ninety day probationary period for <i>new</i> hires as she had been employed by the Village for three years. He was not aware that the Miscellaneous Contract did not contain a &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; provision. (Jt.Ex.1) (T.230-234). The Village arbitrated a discharge case in 2005 under substantially the same Contract and the Arbitrator applied a just cause requirement in his award. (Union Ex.8; T.212). He is familiar with the case of Wes Wofford where Mayor Cornwell took a position contrary to his position herein. The Union filed a grievance and took the position that Wofford was not subject to the ninety days probationary period after transfer to a different department since he had been employed by the Village for a long time in a different department. Wofford settled his claim against the Village and resigned. (Union Exs.10,11).</p>
<p><i>Grievant</i> testified she began working for the Village as a part-time Clerk at the Fitness Center on March 27, 2012. (T.235-236). In January, 2014, she began working as a Clerk in the Water &amp; Sewer Department working 32 hours weekly. She performed the same duties as the two full-time Clerks. (T.236-239). She learned of a job bid posting dated February 25, 2015 for a full-time Clerk position in the Water &amp; Sewer Department and applied for that position. (T.243-247). She attended the April 28, 2015 meeting where the Board of Trustees passed Ordinance 15-1280 hiring her to that full-time position. (T.248). She has volunteered for numerous non-paying civic events in the Village. She has never been disciplined nor has she ever been questioned about her job performance. She was never questioned about her time cards until long after her termination. She was surprised when she was notified on June 19, 2015 that she was being placed on administrative leave. She was terminated by the Mayor on June 23, 2015. She met with the Mayor on July 3, 2015 and he told her that her termination was not based on her job performance but was &ldquo;political.&rdquo; (T.259-262).</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>VI. DISCUSSION AND DECISION</b></i></h4>
<p>Since this is a discharge case the burden is upon the Employer to prove it had just cause to terminate Grievant's employment. Discharge is the most extreme industrial penalty since the Grievant's job, seniority and other benefits under the Contract are at stake. <i>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, &ldquo;How Arbitration Works.</i>, 5<sup>th</sup> Edition, 1997. When applying the principle of just cause to justify the termination of an employee, there are two situations for the Arbitrator to examine. The first is an offense that is the final step in the progressive discipline process. The second is a single incident of very serious misconduct. <i>Midwest Coca-Cola Bottling Co.</i>, 94-1 ARB (1993). In the present case, the Arbitrator must decide whether Grievant's alleged misconduct justified her discharge.</p>
<p>The great majority of the facts in this case are not disputed. Grievant began working for the Employer on March 27, 2012 as a part-time clerk in the Fitness Center. She worked continuously until January, 2014 when she transferred to the Employer's Water and Sewer Department where she worked 32 hours weekly as a part-time clerk. She performed the same duties as the two full-time clerks in that Department. She learned of a job bid posting dated February 25, 2015 for a full-time clerk in the Water and Sewer Department and applied for that position. She attended the Board of Trustees meeting on April 28, 2015 where the Employer's Board of Trustees passed Ordinance &num;15-1280 hiring her as a full-time Clerk. (Emp.Ex.4). She first realized her position was in jeopardy when she was notified on June 19, 2015 that she was being placed on administrative leave. She was discharged by the Mayor at the Board of Trustees Meeting June 23, 2015. She has never been disciplined during her three years of employment with the Village. She participated in numerous voluntary non-paying civic activities during that time period. She was never advised of any complaints regarding job performance or time card issues at the time of her discharge.</p>
<p>The Union has represented employees in the Village of Cahokia, Illinois for more than forty years. There are two separate bargaining units and each bargaining unit has a separate Contract. The Operators Contract covers employees who perform physical work for the Street, Water &amp; Sewer, and Parks Departments and the Electricians. (Emp.Ex.1). The Miscellaneous Contract covers Code Enforcement Officers and Clerks including the Grievant herein. (Jt.Ex.l). The Operators Contract contains an express just cause provision. The Miscellaneous Contract does not contain an express just cause provision. The evidence was undisputed that neither the Village nor the Union was aware of the absence of the just cause provision in the Miscellaneous Contract. There was no evidence that the issue had ever been raised in contract negotiations nor had the Village ever contended it could discharge an employee under the Miscellaneous Contract without just cause. In a prior arbitration the Village was required to prove it had just cause to terminate an employee under the Miscellaneous Contract. (Union Ex.8). Even though the Miscellaneous Contract does not contain an explicit just cause provision labor arbitrators have long and routinely held that just cause is an implicit component of the labor contract. <i>Elkouri &amp; Elkouri, How Arbitration Works</i> (7<sup>th</sup> Ed. 2012). There is a long history in labor arbitration that an employer cannot discharge or discipline an employee without just cause and the just cause requirement applies even when it is not explicitly mentioned in the contract. As Arbitrator herein I find that there is a just cause provision implied in the Miscellaneous Contract. (Jt.Ex.1).</p>
<p>The Employer held a municipal election on April 7, 2015 and the incumbent Mayor, Gary Cornwell, was defeated by Curtis McCall. Mr. Cornwell continued to fulfill his duties as Mayor until the next regular monthly meeting on May 12, 2015. Mayor McCall was upset that the incumbent Mayor had recommended Grievant for full-time employment after the April 7, 2015 election which the Board of Trustees approved on April 28, 2015. Mayor McCall testified he had the right to terminate Grievant &ldquo;without cause&rdquo; because he claimed she did not become a member of the bargaining unit she first paid union dues on May 8, 2015. Since she was not a member of the bargaining unit Mayor McCall determined her to be a &ldquo;new hire&rdquo; and still serving on her ninety day probationary period. McCall further testified that if the Arbitrator determined there was a &ldquo;just cause&rdquo; requirement relating to her discharge that there were numerous irregularities in her time cards in the eighteen months prior to her discharge which resulted in her being paid for time she had not worked. He admitted that the time card issue was never raised until sometime after her discharge and after the grievance herein was filed.</p>
<p>In reviewing the circumstances surrounding Grievant's elevation to a full-time position in the Water &amp; Sewer Department, I find that the Employer fully complied with all applicable ordinances of the Village and her hiring was proper. Grievant was working 32 hours weekly for 16 months as a clerk doing the same work as the two full-time clerks. That Department historically was staffed by three full-time clerks. Evidence at the Hearing proved that additional funds had become available due to retirements and the completion of a major capital project. The bid job position was posted on February 25, 2015 which was more than six weeks before the April 7, 2015 election. Mayor Cornwell continued to perform his duties as Mayor until May 12, 2015. The Board of Trustees passed the Ordinance hiring Grievant before Mayor McCall took office.</p>
<p>Ordinance #2009-1145 cited by the Employer for the proposition that Grievant was illegally hired does not require a different finding. At the Hearing an undated and unsigned version of Ordinance #2009-1145 was presented by Mayor McCall. Mayor McCall was not on the Employer's payroll in 2009. Neither Mayor Cornwell or any other employee of the Village testified that said Ordinance was ever properly enacted. Furthermore, Mayor Cornwell only recommended that Grievant be hired as a full-time employee in the Water &amp; Sewer Department. Mayor Cornwell did not vote on her hiring. The Board of Trustees hired Grievant on a vote of 5-1. As Arbitrator I find that Grievant was legally hired by the Employer's Board of Trustees.</p>
<p>Since it is undisputed that Grievant was performing bargaining unit work as a part-time clerk in the Water &amp; Sewer Department I find that Grievant is a member of the bargaining unit and is covered by the Contract herein even though she was not a dues paying member of the Union at the time of her elevation to full-time work. Since Grievant was performing bargaining unit work for sixteen months in that Department she had already completed her contractual ninety day probationary period and could not be discharged except for just cause.</p>
<p>The Contract herein applies to all the Village clerks without any limitation as to their part-time or full-time status. (Jt.Ex.1). The Contract defines seniority for part-time employees as &ldquo;Employees who work fewer than forty hours per week.&rdquo; The Contract further states: &ldquo;Such Employees performing work within the scope this Agreement <i>shall be</i> included in the bargaining unit.&rdquo; (Jt.Ex.1; Art.V. Sec. 8). Grievant was a part-time employee for sixteen months prior to being hired to full time status. Grievant was clearly a part-time employee and a member of the bargaining unit entitled to just cause protection before and after she was elevated to full-time employment on April 28, 2015.</p>
<p>I further find that the Employer has completely failed to sustain the burden of proof that Grievant is guilty of such misconduct as to justify her discharge. The Mayor gave no reason for her discharge. No allegations of misconduct were even made prior to her discharge. Sometime after Grievant's discharge and the filing of the Grievance herein the Employer alleged that Grievant failed to properly complete her time cards in the months before her discharge resulting in her being paid for work she had not performed. Grievant was never advised of any time card irregularities until after her discharge and she testified that other employees in the Water &amp; Sewer Department filled out the time cards in a similar manner and were not disciplined.</p>
<p>I find that Grievant was a member of the miscellaneous clerks bargaining unit regardless of her pay or the fact that union dues were never withheld from her pay until after she became a full-time employee. I further find that Grievant became a full-time clerk in the Water &amp; Sewer Department as a result of the vote of the Board of Trustees on April 28, 2015. Grievant continued to be covered as a member of the bargaining unit as she had during the previous sixteen months she worked as a part-time clerk in that department. As a result, she was entitled to the contractual protection of just cause before her employment could be terminated. At no time before her discharge was Grievant ever advised of any misconduct in her work performance, attendance, or irregularities in her time cards.</p>
<p>I find that the Employer has failed to prove by any credible evidence that it had just cause to discharge Grievant.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>The grievance filed herein is sustained. The Employer is ordered to make the Grievant whole including back pay, seniority and benefits. The Employer is further ordered to reinstate Grievant to her full-time position as a clerk in the Water &amp; Sewer Department.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>