<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF ARBITRATION BETWEEN FAA Employer and PAACE Union</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case Number: FMCS 16-55364</p>
<p>November 29, 2016.</p>
<p>Stephen Crable, Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>I. <i>STATEMENT OF THE CASE</i></b></h4>
<p>On December 15, 2015, the Professional Association of Aeronautical Center Employees (&ldquo;PAACE&rdquo; or &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) filed a grievance on behalf of Jack Gillis (&ldquo;Grievant&rdquo; or &ldquo;Gillis&rdquo;), an employee of the Federal Aviation Administration (&ldquo;FAA&rdquo; or &ldquo;Employer&rdquo;). In the grievance, the Union alleged, among other things, that the FAA violated Article 49 Section 11 of the collective bargaining agreement between the FAA and PAACE (&ldquo;Agreement&rdquo; or &ldquo;PAACE Agreement&rdquo;) and Section 2.11C of the Human Resource Policy Manual (&ldquo;Manual&rdquo; or &ldquo;HRPM&rdquo;) by offering Grievant a base salary upon his return to a field job that was less than his then current base salary as an instructor at the FAA Academy. The Employer denied the grievance, and the Union progressed the dispute to arbitration. The parties subsequently utilized the services of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service to select the undersigned Arbitrator to resolve the dispute. The Arbitrator held a hearing on September 13, 2016, in Oklahoma City, OK. During the hearing, both parties presented witnesses, offered exhibits and made arguments. A certified shorthand reporter transcribed the testimony at the hearing, and the parties submitted written briefs on November 2, 2016.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>II. <i>STATEMENT OF THE ISSUE</i></b></h4>
<p>The Union and Employer disagreed on the questions at issue. In the Arbitrator view, the issues to be decided are:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="paren" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Whether the current dispute is a proper grievance, subject to arbitration, within the meaning Article 7 of the Agreement;</p></li>
<li><p>Whether the Employer violated Article 49, Section 11 of the Agreement and Section 2.11C of the Manual when it established a lower <i>grade/level</i> for the Grievant after he returned to a field position in Dallas than his <i>grade/level</i> as an instructor at the FAA Academy;</p></li>
<li><p>Whether the Employer violated Article 49, Section 11 of the Agreement and Section 2.11C of the Manual when it established a lower <i>base pay</i> for the Grievant after he returned to a field job in Dallas than his <i>base pay</i> while he worked as an instructor at the FAA Academy; and,</p></li>
<li><p>Whether the Employer violated Article 49, Section 5.B.4 of the Agreement by failing to fully counsel Grievant regarding his return rights prior to Grievant accepting the position at the Academy.</p></li>
<li><p>What should be the appropriate remedy if the FAA violated Article 49, Section 11 and/or Section 2.11C of the Manual in either of the above described circumstances.</p></li>
<li><p>What should be the appropriate remedy if the FAA violated Article 49, Section 5.B.4 of the Agreement by failing to fully counsel Grievant regarding his return rights prior to Grievant accepting the Instructor position at the Academy.</p></li></ol>
<h4 align="center"><b>III. <i>POSITION OF THE PARTIES</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. <i>UNION</i></b></h4>
<p>The Union argues the grievance is properly before the Arbitrator and denies the grievance should be processed under the PASS Agreement (the agreement between the FAA and Professional Aviation Safety Specialist) rather than under the PAACE Agreement. At the time the grievance arose, Grievant was working under the PAACE Agreement, and all key aspects of the dispute arose during Grievant's employment at the Academy while working under the PAACE Agreement. Accordingly, the Union concludes the grievance is properly before the Arbitrator, and the Grievant's pay entitlements should be determined under the PAACE Agreement.</p>
<p>In the Union's view, the question at issue is whether the FAA's job offer to Grievant on December 12, 2015 violated the Collective Bargaining Agreement; and if so, what shall be the remedy? The Union asserts that the FAA violated both the letter and spirit of the PAACE Agreement and FAA Manual by the manner in which the FAA established Grievant's base pay when he left the Academy and returned to a field job in Dallas. The Grievant's base salary in Dallas was approximately &dollar;13,000 a year less than either his base salary as an Instructor at the FAA Academy in Oklahoma City or his base salary when he worked in the field at Tulsa before he transferred to the Academy. When the Grievant competed for and held an instructor job at the FAA Academy in 2012, he was allowed to bring his existing base pay rate, plus a small increase, to his position at the Academy. As a condition of moving to an instructor position, Grievant signed a return and retention employment agreement (&ldquo;3R Agreement&rdquo;) which guaranteed his right to return to a comparable job in the field after he completed his tour(s) of duty at the Academy. Although the 3R Agreement contemplated that Grievant would be an instructor for at least 2 tours of duty, the Grievant left after the first tour because the Employer refused to offer him a second tour. In view of the Employer's refusal to offer a second tour of duty, Grievant's return to the field was an &ldquo;involuntary&rdquo; move, not a voluntary one. Because the move was involuntary, the Union argues the Agreement and the Manual required the Employer to offer the Grievant either the amount of his base pay at the time he came to the Academy or the amount of his base pay at the time he left the Academy. The Employer offered him neither. Instead, the FAA set his base pay approximately &dollar;13,000 less than either of these base rates. The Union concludes that the grievance should be granted, and the Grievant should be made whole for his loss of pay. Finally, PAACE asserts his base rate going forward should be adjusted to the amount of his base pay immediately prior to joining the Academy or the amount of his base pay at the time he left the Academy as an instructor.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. <i>EMPLOYER</i></b></h4>
<p>The FAA argues that the issues to be decided are: Whether the grievance was properly filed in accordance with Article 7 of the parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA); Whether the Arbitrator has jurisdiction to reach the merits of the dispute; Whether the grievance is procedurally defective or otherwise barred from further pursuit or arbitration; Whether management violated Article 49 of the CBA and Human Resource Policy Manual (HRPM) COMP-2.11C on December 9, 2015 when Grievant was given a <i>tentative</i> job offer to the position of Airway Transportation Systems Specialist, FV-2101-H and his base salary set at &dollar;79,849; Whether the demanded remedy is appropriate and limited to the terms and conditions of the CBA.</p>
<p>Starting with the procedural arguments, the FAA asserts that the grievance should be dismissed on procedural grounds. The dispute centers on whether Grievant's base pay is proper at his current assignment at Love Field in Dallas. Pay and other conditions of employment for FAA employees at Love Field are governed by a collective bargaining agreement between FAA and PASS, not between PAACE and the FAA. Grievant's pay claim must be processed under the PASS Agreement, not the PAACE Agreement. The FAA made Grievant a tentative job offer to Grievant while he still worked under the PAACE agreement but he was not harmed, if at all, until the FAA gave Grievant a final job offer. By the time the Grievant accepted the final job offer and it took effect, Grievant worked under the PASS Agreement. Thus, Grievant had no claim under the PAACE Agreement.</p>
<p>Moreover, after Grievant reported to his new duty location in Dallas in August of 2014, he filed a grievance under the PASS Agreement that makes the same or similar arguments and demands as the current grievance. As such, the Grievant is improperly attempting to receive the most advantageous outcome by filing two comparable grievances under two different labor Agreements. In summary, the Grievant can't claim rights under the PAACE Agreement because the PAACE Agreement cannot determine the Grievant's appropriate pay in a bargaining unit represented by another Union and covered by a different collective bargaining agreement.</p>
<p>Assuming arguendo the grievance can be processed under the PAACE Agreement, the Employer argues the grievance should be denied. The Employer urges that the Union, as the moving party, has the burden to show through a preponderance of evidence that management violated of the terms of the CBA and HRPM COMP-2.11C, that the demanded remedy is proper and that the remedy is found in the terms and conditions of such Agreement.</p>
<p>According to the FAA, the language of the Agreement, the Manuel, and the 3R Agreement Grievant signed upon accepting an instructor position at the Academy are clear and unambiguous. Each of these documents supports the conclusion that Grievant was entitled to his <i>grade/level</i> immediately prior to the Academy assignment or his <i>grade/level</i> at the time his return rights are exercised, whichever is <i>lower.</i> In this case, Grievant's grade/level of pay just prior to his moving to the Academy was Grade H in the FV Core Compensation Plan. When Grievant exercised his return rights, his grade/level was Grade 13 in the FG pay plan. Since Grievant's Grade H pay designation under the FV system pay was lower than his Grade 13 pay under the FG pay system, his pay grade/level upon leaving the Academy was properly set at Grade H. While the Union argues that Grievant's actual basic pay at the time he accepted the instructor job at the Academy exceeded Grade H and that his actual basic pay should be protected, Article 49, Section 11.A protects &ldquo;grade/level&rdquo; not base pay. The FAA notes the Grievant's base pay in a field job in Tulsa, just before he moved to the FAA Academy, was higher than the maximum amount for Grade H as a result of a pay retention event. When Grievant voluntarily came to the Academy and achieved a base pay higher than his base pay in the Tulsa field job, he lost the pay retention protection he enjoyed at Tulsa for pay. Since the Agreement, the Manual and the 3R Agreement protect only the grade/level of pay, not the amount of basic pay, the FAA properly set the Grievant's pay grade as &ldquo;H&rdquo; and the grievance should be denied.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>IV. <i>RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF THE AGREEMENT</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>Article 49 REEMPLOYMENT, RESTORATION AND RETURN RIGHTS (3-R PROGRAM)</b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>Section 1.</b> This Article describes the Administrative Return Rights policy and procedures for employees who occupy covered instructor positions at the FAA Academy. It also supersedes FAPM 352-1, Chapter 4, Reemployment Rights for FAA Academy Instructors, dated May 19, 1993.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Section 2.</b> Provides the option of offering return rights when the FAA Academy has identified certain Technical Instructor positions as: 1) hard to fill; 2) requiring unique knowledge and/or skills; and 3) requiring field currency; and/or 4) one where specific circumstances warrant an offer of return rights.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Section 4.</b> Definitions for this Article; Administrative Return Rights: Rights granted by the Administrator in keeping with the best interest of the Agency. These rights are not based on any statutory or legal requirements, but represent a written contract between the agency and the employee that guarantees his/her return to the parent organization after completing the agreed upon tour of duty</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued">C. Instructor: A non-managerial employee at the FAA Academy, who is engaged in the conduct, evaluation, control, of technical training (excluding occupational groups such as FG-300 and FG-1700 which are not normally recruited from FAA field facilities) and who performs one or more of the following duties as a regular recurring part of his/her assignment:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="paren" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>instructing students in resident courses, the FAA distance learning program, or in nonresident training programs conducted by the Academy in field locations;</p></li>
<li><p>planning and developing training programs;</p></li>
<li><p>developing course content and related material for use in resident training, nonresident training programs, distance learning, and facility training programs; and</p></li>
<li><p>evaluating the content and effectiveness of resident/nonresident, distance learning, and facility technical training programs.</p></li></ol>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued">D. Parent Organization: The FAA employing jurisdiction from which an employee was selected for an Academy Instructor assignment.</p>
<p class="continued">E. Tour of Duty: The initial tour of duty at the FAA Academy is 3 years.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Section 5.</b> Responsibilities;</p>
<p class="continued">A. Assistant Administrator for Human Resource Management (AHR-1 or designee): AHR is responsible for providing program guidance and assistance and for mediating and resolving conflicts between the FAA Academy and the parent organization.</p>
<p class="continued">B. Office of Human Resource Management for the Aeronautical Center (AMH): The Director of this office will designate a return rights coordinator who shall have a thorough knowledge of the program and provide program guidance and assistance at the local level. In addition, this office is responsible for:</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">4. Counseling employees prior to accepting assignments to the Academy and ensuring that they are thoroughly and completely aware of their return rights, benefits, and obligations before their personnel action becomes effective.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued">F. Employees:</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">2. Submitting a written response to the Academy's request for a decision to exercise, extend, or forfeit (whichever is applicable) no later than 90 days prior to the end of their tour or within 30 days of receipt of the request, whichever provides the employee the maximum response time. If the instructor fails to submit the required documentation indicating his/her intent, he/she will be returned to the parent organization at the end of the contract.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Section 9.</b> Scheduling employees for return;</p>
<p class="continued">A. After Completing One Tour: Employees are normally expected to serve two tours. However:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">1. the Director of the Aeronautical Center or his/her designee may disapprove a second or third tour and return an employee to his/her parent organization when it is determined to be in the best interests of the agency, or</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Section 11.</b> Grade/level entitlement;</p>
<p class="continued">A. An instructor who completes one (1) but not two (2) consecutive tours of duty is entitled to return to a position equal to the grade/level held immediately prior to the FAA Academy assignment or the grade/level held at the time return rights are exercised, whichever is lower. Note: This does not preclude the parent organization from offering the employee a position at the grade/level attained upon assignment to the Academy.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>V. <i>RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF THE MANUEL or HRPM</i></b></h4>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><b>Human Resource Policy Manual (HRPM)</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Volume 2: Compensation Systems and Classification</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Comp-2.11C</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Demotions, Pay Band Retention, and Pay Retention in the Core</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Compensation Plan</b></p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>3. Definitions:</b></p>
<ol type="lc-letter" bind-char="paren" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p><b>Career Enhancement Assignment:</b> the competitive assignment to a position that is designed to broaden the experience and qualifications of individuals to further the DOT/FAA/LOB/SO mission.</p></li>
<li><p><b>Base Pay:</b> An employee's salary <b>excluding</b> locality pay and additional pay of any kind such as premium pay.</p></li>
<li><p><b>Demotion:</b> The movement from one pay band to a lower pay band (i.e., change to lower pay band). The movement from other pay plans to positons in the Core Compensation Plan may also be considered demotions for the purposes of this policy chapter when the core compensation position is at a lower pay band or the action will result in a lower base pay.</p></li>
<li><p><b>Pay Band Retention:</b> An employee's right to retain his/her current pay band, when placed in a lower pay band, such as a result of a qualifying event noted in Section 6.</p></li>
<li><p><b>Pay Retention:</b> An employee's right to retain his/her base pay when their base pay would be reduced as a result of a qualifying event noted in Section 8.</p></li>
<li><p><b>Reasonable Offer: &ast;&ast;&ast;</b></p></li>
<li><p><b>Reduction in Pay Band or Pay for Personal Cause: &ast;&ast;&ast;</b></p></li></ol>
<p class="continued"><b>4. Roles and Responsibilities &ast;&ast;&ast;</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>5. Types of Demotions to Core Compensation Plan Positions:</b></p>
<p class="continued">a. <b>Career Enhancement:</b> The competitive assignment to a position that is designed to broaden the experience and qualification of individuals to further the DOT/FAA/LOB/SO mission.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>b. Voluntary:</b> A reduction in pay band/grade or base pay that is initiated by the employee for his or her benefit, convenience or personal advantage. This occurs when an employee requests a demotion or applies for and accepts a new position that is in a lower pay band or results in a reduction in base pay.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>c. Involuntary, Management Action:</b> A reduction in pay band/grade or base pay resulting directly from an action (not for personal cause) initiated by an agency official which may adversely affect the employee's pay band or base pay. This occurs when an employee is involuntarily assigned from their position of record to a new position in a lower pay band.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>6. Pay Band Retention:</b> Pay band retention is mandatory for demotions other than those which are voluntary (at the employee's request) or for personal cause.</p>
<p class="continued">Pay Band Retention will be granted when a demotion through one of the following involuntary Management Actions occurs:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Demotion through Reduction-in-Force (RIF) procedures or due to the employee accepting a demotion in lieu of involuntary separation through RIF procedures.</p></li>
<li><p>An employee declines either a formal offer to transfer with his/her function (Transfer of Function) outside of his/her current commuting area&hellip;.</p></li>
<li><p>Reclassification of the employee's position resulting in a lower pay band.</p></li>
<li><p>Demotions to a lower banded position that is specifically being offered by management in order to implement a reorganization/realignment that has been announced in writing and that would require the application of RIF procedures.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">Circumstances surrounding the above action must be justified in writing by the Line of Business/Staff Office (LOB/SO). The servicing HRMO must concur with the action.</p>
<p class="continued">Pay band retention will be granted for a demotion under circumstances described in this section provided the employee has:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Permanently held the pay band or grade (i.e., FG-12 if coming from under a different pay system) for a minimum of 52 consecutive weeks; or</p></li>
<li><p>Permanently held a combination of higher pay bands or grades for a minimum of 52 consecutive weeks.</p></li></ul>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>7. Termination of Pay Band Retention.</b></p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>8. Pay Retention:</b> An employee receives pay retention for an indefinite period beginning on the date of his/her entitlement. Pay retention will be granted as a result of a qualifying event noted below:</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="paren" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Expiration of pay band retention, unless base pay can be accommodated within the new pay band.</p></li>
<li><p>Employee is affected by an involuntary management actions, as reflected in Section 6, but the employee is ineligible for band retention because h/she does not meet the 52-week service requirement.</p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay when selected for a special placement program for developmental purposes under an established career development plan (e.g., upward mobility) that specifies pay retention entitlements.</p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay in order to participate in a formal FAA initiated pre-development program.</p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay to participate in a Career Enhancement assignment under the provisions of <i>EMP-1.29</i> or <i>EMP-1.29a (ATO-CE/CP).</i></p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay when selected for a position that the agency has determined is hard to fill.</p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay when the employee no longer meets a specific condition or requirement of employment (including medical standards) established by the agency.</p></li>
<li><p>Employee is involuntarily and permanently assigned by management from their position of record to a different position in the same pay band, or from a position in another pay plan to a position in the Core Compensation Plan. This action occurs when an employee's skills can be better used in a different position within or outside of the organization.</p></li>
<li><p>Employee is converted (agency initiated conversion) to the Core Compensation Plan from another FAA pay plan and his/her base pay immediately after conversion exceeds the new band maximum.</p></li></ol>
<p class="continued"><b>9. Termination of Pay Retention:</b> Pay retention is terminated if the employee:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Becomes entitled to a base pay that is equal to or higher than the employee's retained base pay.</p></li>
<li><p>Declines a reasonable offer of a position for which base pay is equal to or higher than the employee's retained base pay.</p></li>
<li><p>Voluntarily vacates the position for which pay retention was authorized.</p></li>
<li><p>Is demoted for personal cause (the employee's base pay is set within the new band).</p></li>
<li><p>Is demoted at the employee's request (the employee's base pay is set within the new band).</p></li>
<li><p>Has a break in service of one workday or more.</p></li>
<li><p>Has completed 3 consecutive years on one or more Career Enhancement assignment under the provisions of <i>EMP-1.29</i> or <i>EMP-1.29a (ATO-CE/CP).</i></p></li></ul></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><b>V. <i>BACKGROUND</i></b></h4>
<p>The Grievant began working for the FAA in Boston as a radar automation technician. His job involved supporting the computer systems and equipment that monitor airport weather, security areas, flight movements and a variety of other critical data systems. Grievant spent 12 years in Boston and 13 years in Tulsa working on a variety of significant projects. In 2012 Grievant worked as an Airway Transportation Systems Specialist (&ldquo;ATSS&rdquo;) in Tulsa. In June, 2012, he, along with several hundred other applicants, applied for a vacancy announcement as an Electronics Technician instructor at the FAA Academy in Oklahoma City. The FAA Academy selected Grievant as one of two successful applicants for the position. The Grievant signed a 3R Agreement as a condition of filling the positon, and he assumed his new positon as an Academy instructor in September 2012.</p>
<p>A 3R Agreement creates reemployment, restoration and return rights for an employee who accepts an instructor positon at the Academy, subsequently leaves the Academy and returns to his parent organization or another organization within the FAA. In Grievant's case, his 3R Agreement specified an initial 3-year tour of duty, ending on September 8, 2015. If Grievant left the Academy before his 3-year tour ended, the 3R Agreement specified that Grievant forfeited any reemployment rights with the FAA. If the Grievant left the Academy after one tour of duty, but not two, the 3R Agreement entitled Grievant to reemployment rights at his parent organization, that is, the organization he left prior to joining the Academy staff. The 3R Agreement also provided a mechanism for setting Grievant's grade/level of pay if he left after one tour of duty at the Academy, and a different, more favorable, mechanism if he left after two or more tours of duty at the Academy.</p>
<p>Paragraph 6 of the Grievant's 3R Agreement provided the method for determining his grade/level upon leaving the Academy:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">An instructor who completes one but not two consecutive tours is eligible for return either at the grade/level held immediately prior to the Academy assignment or at the grade/level held at the time when return rights are exercised, whichever is lower.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Immediately prior to filling the instructor vacancy at the Academy, the Grievant worked in Tulsa as an ATSS. He worked under the FV pay plan and his pay grade/level was Grade H. However, his actual base pay of &dollar;93,022 exceeded the maximum for Grade H, apparently due to a pay retention agreement put into place sometime after October 2003. Upon moving to the Academy, Grievant worked under the FG pay plan at Grade 13. His base pay at the Academy was &dollar;93,175, approximately &dollar;150 more than his base pay in Tulsa as an ATSS.</p>
<p>As Grievant approached the end of his initial tour of duty at the Academy, he requested a second tour. Even though the FAA frequently offers a second tour as an Academy instructor, the FAA retains the discretion to offer or withhold a second tour. In this case, the FAA did not approve his request for a second tour, and Grievant began the process of returning to his parent organization. The Grievant considered his request an involuntary one since he wanted to stay at the Academy. The FAA considered the request voluntary since Grievant returned pursuant to his 3R Agreement which he voluntarily signed when he voluntarily moved to the Academy. The FAA identified 10 possible locations and positons that were available in Grievant's parent organization and conveyed that information to the Grievant. All the positions carried a pay grade/level of Grade H.</p>
<p>From among the 10 locations the FAA offered Grievant, he ultimately selected an Airway Transportation System Specialist position at Dallas Love Field. In a June 7, 2016, final offer letter (which offered the same pay grade/level as a preliminary offer letter dated December 9, 2015), the FAA specified that the Dallas position carried a pay grade/level of H. The actual base pay for a Grade H position and the base pay the FAA offered Grievant was &dollar;79,849. The base pay offer was less than Grievant's base pay of &dollar;96,004 as an Academy instructor and less than his base pay of &dollar;93,000 as an ATSS in Tulsa immediately prior to his Academy instructor assignment. The June 7 offer specified a report date of June 26, 2016. Grievant objected to the amount of his base pay, having previously filed a grievance on December 9, 2015 challenging the amount. However, he ultimately accepted the June 7 offer and reported later in June to his new duty assignment at Love Field.</p>
<p>After Grievant reported to Love Field, he filed a grievance under the PASS Agreement raising the same or similar issues to the issues in the present dispute. As noted, the FAA employees at Love Field are covered by a different collective bargaining agreement with a different union from the employees at the FAA Academy.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>VI. <i>DISCUSSION AND OPINION</i></b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>A. Procedural Issue</b></h4>
<p>The Arbitrator concludes that the Grievant's claim arises under the terms of Article 7 of Agreement between PAACE and the FAA and that the dispute is within the Arbitrator's jurisdiction pursuant to the PAACE Agreement. Article 7, Section 2 of the PAACE Agreement defines a grievance as any complaint by a bargaining unit employee &ldquo;&hellip; concerning any matter relating to the employment of the employee.&rdquo; Article 7, Section 2 also defines a grievance as any complaint &ldquo;&hellip;by the Union or Employer concerning&hellip; the interpretation, application, enforcement or breach of this Agreement&hellip;&rdquo; or &ldquo;&hellip;any claimed violation, misinterpretation, or misapplication of any law, rule or regulation&hellip;.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The present dispute falls squarely within the definition of a grievance under the Article 7, Section 2 of the Agreement. PAACE disputed and the Grievant challenged the FAA's method of determining Grievant pay while he was still employed as an instructor at the Academy and covered by the PAACE Agreement. This dispute flowed from an interpretation of the PAACE Agreement and the meaning of the 3R Agreement. The Grievant signed the 3R Agreement which brought him under the PAACE Agreement as an Instructor at the Academy and established the method for determining Grievant's pay upon leaving the Academy. The FAA's assertion that Grievant could not challenge the preliminary offer and could only challenge the final offer is not persuasive. The method the FAA used for setting the Grievant's base pay was the same in both the preliminary and final offer, and there is no credible basis for concluding that the preliminary offer was not grievable.</p>
<p>Additionally, while the PASS Agreement is part of the record before the Arbitrator, PASS did not appear at the arbitration and did not take any position on this matter. Accordingly, the Arbitrator does not decide what applicability, if any, the PASS Agreement might have for this grievance or other similar disputes that straddle the border of the PASS and PAACE Agreements. Rather, the Arbitrator considers the limited issue of whether the pay the FAA offered Grievant, while he was still an employee of the Academy and not yet covered by the PASS Agreement, violated the FAA/PAACE Agreement.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. Reduction of Grievant's Pay Grade/Level Under the Agreement and Manuel</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><i>1. Agreement</i></h4>
<p>Article 49 of the Agreement, <i>Reemployment, Restoration and Return Rights (3-R Program)</i>, details the rights of an employee who returns to his parent organization after completing a tour of duty as an Academy instructor. Regarding the employee's pay entitlement upon returning to his parent organization, Article 49, Section 11 provides.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">A. An instructor who completes one (1) but not two consecutive hours of duty is entitled to return to a position equal to the <i>grade/level held immediately prior</i> to the FAA Academy assignment or the <i>grade/level held at the time</i> return rights are exercised, <i>whichever is lower.</i> Note: This does not preclude the parent organization from offering the employee a position at the grade/level attained upon the assignment to the Academy. <i>(emphasis supplied)</i>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The language of Article 49, Section 11A speaks directly to Grievant's circumstances. Prior to successfully competing for a position as an Academy instructor, Grievant's grade/level was &ldquo;H&rdquo; under the FV Plan. After he joined the Academy and until the time he left the Academy, Grievant's grade/level was &ldquo;13&rdquo; under the FG Pay Plan. When Grievant left the Academy, the pay for the &ldquo;H&rdquo; grade/level was &dollar;78,849, which was less than &dollar;96,004, the pay associated with his grade/level of &ldquo;13&rdquo; at the Academy. In the months before Grievant left the Academy, the FAA offered the Grievant a Grade H position, the lower of the relevant grade/levels referenced in Article 49, Section 11A. In doing so, the Employer complied with the clear language of the Agreement.</p>
<p>Moreover, this method of determining Grievant's pay grade/level upon returning to the field is precisely the method contained in paragraph 6 of the Grievant's 3R Agreement. Grievant signed the 3R Agreement upon accepting an instructor position at the Academy in September of 2012. Paragraph 6 of the 3R Agreement provides, &ldquo;An instructor who completes one but not two consecutive tours is eligible to return either at the <i>grade/level held immediately prior</i> to the Academy assignment or the <i>grade/level held at the time</i> when return rights are exercised, <i>whichever is lower</i>.&rdquo; <i>(emphasis supplied)</i>. This methodology is precisely the one used by the Employer in determining Grievant's grade/level when he left the Academy and returned to the field in June 2016.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>2. Manual</i></h4>
<p>Assuming arguendo that Grievant's return to the field was &ldquo;involuntary&rdquo;, as argued by the Union, and not &ldquo;voluntary&rdquo;, as argued by the FAA, the Employer's Human Resource Policy Manual 2.11C does not require a finding that the Employer improperly established Grievant's pay grade/level as an &ldquo;H&rdquo; rather than a &ldquo;13&rdquo;. Paragraph 6 of the HRPM provides that <i>pay band retention</i> is <i>mandatory</i> for demotions that are <i>involuntary.</i> However, the Grievant's circumstances meet none of &ldquo;Involuntary Management Actions&rdquo; that are required to trigger the band retention protection. The &ldquo;Involuntary Management Actions&rdquo; specified in Paragraph 6 of the HRPM as triggers are: a RIF, a Transfer of Function, a Reclassification of employee position, or a Reorganization. Since none of these consideration is presented by this dispute, the Grievant's &ldquo;13&rdquo; grade/level as an Academy instructor was not eligible for retention under Section 2.11C of the Manual.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>B. Reduction of Grievant's Base Pay Under the Agreement and Manual</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><i>1. Agreement</i></h4>
<p>The Union notes that the Grievant's base pay at the time he left the field and became an Academy instructor in September 2012 was &dollar;93,022 and that his base pay at the Academy increased to &dollar;93,175. The Union argues that the FAA was required to offer the Grievant a base pay comparable to either of these amounts when he left the Academy and returned to the field. The short answer to this argument is that Article 49, Section 11A speaks to the Grievant's <i>&ldquo;grade/level&rdquo;</i>, not the Grievant's <i>base pay.</i> Accordingly, the Agreement did not require the FAA to pay the Grievant the amount of the base pay he was making at the Academy. Nor did it require the FAA to pay Grievant the amount of base pay he was making before he came to the Academy. The Manual as well as the Agreement treat base <i>pay band</i> retention and <i>base pay</i> retention as two distinct, and not interchangeable, concepts. Compare Manual Section 2.11C, paragraphs 6 and 8.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>2. Manual</i></h4>
<p>Whether the Manual, as contrasted to the Agreement, protected the Grievant's base pay (not grade/level) is a closer question. Unlike the Agreement, the Manual provides protection for base pay under the circumstances defined in the Manuel. Paragraph 8, Pay Retention, provides: &ldquo;&hellip;Pay retention will be granted as a result of a qualifying event noted below:&rdquo; The qualifying events include (paragraph numbering supplied):</p>
<ol type="digit" bind-char="paren" bind-to="right-only">
<li><p>Expiration of pay band retention, unless base pay can be accommodated within the new pay band.</p></li>
<li><p>Employee is affected by an involuntary management actions, as reflected in Section 6, but the employee is ineligible for band retention because h/she does not meet the 52-week service requirement.</p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay when selected for a special placement program for developmental purposes under an established career development plan (e.g., upward mobility) that specifies pay retention entitlements.</p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay in order to participate in a formal FAA initiated pre-development program.</p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay to participate in a Career Enhancement assignment under the provisions of <i>EMP-1.29</i> or <i>EMP-1.29a (ATO-CE/CP).</i></p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay when selected for a position that the agency has determined is hard to fill.</p></li>
<li><p>Reduction in pay band/grade level or base pay when the employee no longer meets a specific condition or requirement of employment (including medical standards) established by the agency.</p></li>
<li><p>Employee is involuntarily and permanently assigned by management from their position of record to a different position in the same pay band, or from a position in another pay plan to a position in the Core Compensation Plan. This action occurs when an employee's skills can be better used in a different position within or outside of the organization.</p></li>
<li><p>Employee is converted (agency initiated conversion) to the Core Compensation Plan from another FAA pay plan and his/her base pay immediately after conversion exceeds the new band maximum.</p></li></ol>
<p>Only 3 of these qualifying events, 1, 2 and 9, are even marginally relevant, but none of them clearly applied to Grievant's circumstances. Paragraph 1 is inapplicable because the protection of Grievant's &ldquo;H&rdquo; pay grade/level did not just expire. Paragraph 2 requires an involuntary management action as defined in Paragraph 6 of the HRPM. As noted in VI. A. above, Grievant's circumstance were not covered by any of the involuntary management actions listed in the HRPM. Finally, there is no evidence establishing that the FAA &ldquo;converted&rdquo; the Grievant as contemplated by Paragraph 9.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>C. FAA Obligation under Article 49, Section 5.B.4 to Provide Counselling</b></h4>
<p>Article 49, Section 5.B.4 of the Agreement imposes a significant burden on the Employer to educate an Employee about his employment rights prior to the time he accepts a job at the Academy. The Agreement requires the FAA to provide:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">5. <i>Counseling</i> employees prior to accepting assignments to the Academy and <i>ensuring that they are thoroughly and completely aware of their return rights, benefits, and obligations</i> before their personnel action becomes effective. <i>(emphasis supplied)</i></p>
</blockquote>
<p class="continued">Given the pay retention protection which Grievant enjoyed for several years prior to his transfer to the Academy, it was not immediately obvious, without interpreting several provisions of the Agreement and Manual, that Grievant would lose his pay retention protection upon accepting a position at the Academy. The Grievant testified, without contradiction, that the FAA did not explain the potential pay consequences of accepting the Academy position before he accepted the position. That is, a substantial reduction in his base pay upon leaving the Academy due to the expiration of his pay retention protection. The FAA's failure violated the mandate in Article 49, Section 5.B.4 to &ldquo;thoroughly and completely&rdquo; counsel the Grievant regarding his &ldquo;return rights, benefits and obligations&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Determining a remedy for this violation is more problematic. Given the desirability of an Instructor position, it is possible the Grievant may still have accepted the position even if he had been made aware of the potential for a reduction in his base pay. It is also possible that he might have turned the position down and continued to enjoy pay retention protection in the job he held in Tulsa. Although Grievant testified that he would not have accepted the Academy assignment if he had been advised of the risk to his base pay, this testimony falls into the category of &ldquo;20/20 hindsight&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Accordingly, the Arbitrator remands the question of remedy to the parties, suggesting the parties pay particular attention to the Grievant's rate of pay going forward. If the parties do not agree on a remedy within 30 days of the date of this Preliminary Award, the parties should so advise the Arbitrator. A Final Award addressing remedy will issue within 30 days of being so advised. To that end, the Arbitrator retains jurisdiction of this dispute pending a resolution by the parties or issuance of a remedy.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>VII. <i>PRELIMINARY AWARD</i></b></h4>
<p class="continued">The grievance is denied in part and granted in part. The FAA did not violate Article 49, Section 11 of the Agreement and 2.11C of the Manual when it paid the Grievant a lower grade/level of pay and a lower base pay after he returned to a field job rather than the grade/level and base pay he received while he worked as an instructor at the FAA Academy. The FAA violated Article 49, Section 5.B.4 of the Agreement by failing to fully counsel Grievant regarding his return rights prior to Grievant accepting the position at the Academy. Consistent with the discussion above, the issue of remedy is remanded to the FAA and PAACE for 30 days, with the Arbitrator retaining jurisdiction to issue a remedy if the Parties fail to agree on a remedy.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>