<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between: NESTLE USA, CONFECTIONS AND SNACK DIVISION, Company, and INTERNATIONAL BROTHERHOOD OF TEAMSTERS, LOCAL 200, Union.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Grievant: Ken Jenson FMCS&num; 15-54422-6</p>
<p>March 3, 2016.</p>
<p>George L. Fitzsimmons, Arbitrator</p>
<table width="585" columns="1">
<caption><i>TABLE OF CONTENTS</i></caption>
<tr>
<td width="5%"><p></p></td>
<td width="85%"><p></p></td>
<td width="10%"><p></p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>I. BACKGROUND <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>II. ISSUE <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>III. RELEVANT CONTRACT PROVISIONS <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>3</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>IV. SUMMARY POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>6</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>A. COMPANY <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>6</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>B. UNION <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>6</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>V. SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>6</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>VI. DISCUSSION AND DECISION <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>9</p></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top"><p>VII. AWARD <fill/></p></td>
<td align="left" valign="top"><p>13</p></td>
</tr>
</table>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>I. BACKGROUND</b></i></h4>
<p>Nestle USA Confections and Snacks Division (hereinafter &ldquo;Company&rdquo;) produces multiple chocolate products at its facility in Burlington, Wisconsin. The International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 200, (hereinafter &ldquo;Union&rdquo;) represents 450 bargaining unit employees including Ken Jenson (hereinafter &ldquo;Grievant&rdquo;). The Company and Union entered into a Collective Bargaining Agreement (hereinafter &ldquo;Contract&rdquo;) which was in full force and effect at all relevant times herein. (Jt.Ex.1). The matter at issue here is the Union's contention that the Company violated the Contract when it failed to recall Grievant from a temporary layoff. The parties stipulated that there were no procedural questions and the grievance was properly before Arbitrator Fitzsimmons for decision.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>II ISSUE</b></i></h4>
<p>Did the Company violate the Contract when it failed to recall Grievant from temporary layoff? If so, what shall be the remedy?</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>III. RELEVANT CONTRACT PROVISIONS</b></i></h4>
<p align="center">ARTICLE 14</p>
<p align="center">MANAGEMENT RIGHTS</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued"><i>Section. A.</i> The management of the plant and the direction of its workforce are solely and exclusively the functions of the management of this Company subject only to any specific provision of this Agreement. All the rights, functions, and prerogatives of management which are not modified by one or more explicit provisions of this Agreement are reserved and retained exclusively by the Company. Any of the rights, powers and authority that the parties had prior to the signing of this Agreement are retained by the parties, except those specifically abridged, delegated, granted or modified by this Agreement.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Section B.</i> The Company has the authority to determine and direct the policies, modes, methods of operating the business. The sole and exclusive rights of management, except to the extent modified by this Agreement, include but are not confined to the right to determine the methods, materials, and processes to be employed; to discontinue or automate processes or operations; to determine the qualifications of its employees and to select new employees; to determine the size and composition of its workforce; to determine production schedules; to determine the number and type of equipment, machinery, materials, products and supplies to be used, operated, manufactured, processed, sold or distributed; to hire, promote, transfer, assign, layoff and recall employees to work; to discharge or otherwise discipline employees; to determine and/or redetermine the assignment of work; to schedule the hours and days to be worked on each job and each shift; to make and change plant rules; to introduce new and different or improved methods and production standards; to contract for goods and services. (Jt.Ex.1).</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i>LETTER OF UNDERSTANDING</i></h4>
<p align="center">RE: TEMPORARY LAYOFF PROCEDURES</p>
<p align="center">January 27, 2011</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">The Company and the Union acknowledge that when production needs warrant a temporary reduction in labor, it is in both parties best interest to pursue Temporary Layoff procedures that capitalize on volunteers whenever and wherever possible and respects seniority whenever possible. As such, the following procedure was developed. For purpose of this agreement, temporary is defined as six weeks or less in duration, with a start date and an end date.</p>
<p class="continued">Step One &ndash; Voluntary Process:</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>The Company will post the number of positions, by classification, being laid off in a given department(s). The posting will be up for a minimum of forty-eight (48) hours and will include a deadline date for those Associates wanting to take advantage of a Temporary Layoff option.</p></li>
<li><p>Those associates volunteering for layoff do not have the option of returning to work prior to the announced recall date unless production requirements warrant a recall, in which case those associates who were temporarily laid off will be given the first option to return to work provided an option is available. It is the Associate's responsibility to make the Company aware of any address or telephone changes so that they can be reached if circumstances change and they are required to return to work,</p></li>
<li><p>Failure to return from layoff, as originally scheduled, will result in termination of employment.</p></li>
<li><p>Those Associates in the affected department(s) who do not wish to take advantage of the Temporary Layoff must complete and submit a &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Job Alternative Form&rdquo; to Human Resources by the deadline date indicated above. Associates must be immediately capable and willing to perform in the positions indicated on their forms.</p></li>
<li><p>In conjunction, the Company will post a notice to all departments indicating a Temporary Layoff is occurring in the Plant and that any other Associate willing to take a Temporary Layoff for that particular time period must fill out and submit a &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Request Form.&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p>After an analysis of needed labor in the Plant, a determination will be made if there are sufficient volunteers from the affected department(s) to cover the reduced labor needs. If not, the process would continue by reviewing requests from Associates <i>outside</i> of the affected department(s). The Company has the right to retain sufficient &ldquo;Qualified&rdquo; and/or &ldquo;Capable&rdquo; Associates. As such, the Company maintains the right to deny any request for Temporary Layoff or to cancel any previously granted request to retain sufficient &ldquo;Qualified&rdquo; and/or &ldquo;Capable&rdquo; Associates to safely meet production requirements.</p></li>
<li><p>The &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Alternative Forms&rdquo; and the &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Request Forms&rdquo; will be analyzed in an effort to place all Associates wanting to work into positions made available by those Associates <i>outside</i> of the affected department willing to accept a Temporary Layoff.</p></li>
<li><p>Associates from the affected department(s) desiring to stay working are placed in seniority order. A review of their individual &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Job Alternative Form&rdquo; is done in an effort to place them on a different position during the layoff period.</p></li>
<li><p>When more than one Associate from the outside affected Department(s) holds a position of interest to someone from the affected Department(s), seniority is the determining factor with the highest senior Associate being replaced and selected for Temporary Layoff. This process continues until all Associates from the affected department(s) desiring to work are placed. Placements will be on an individual's current shift, if possible. Alternatively, the Associates can be placed on an alternative shift if they so choose or they can reconsider the option to take a Temporary Layoff.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">Step Two &ndash; Bump Process</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>Should the above process not garner the needed number of Associates to meet our reduced labor demands, Associates remaining from the affected Department(s) that want to remain working and could not find a match with other available volunteers may exercise seniority to take another job that they are immediately capable to perform. Any Associate thereby displaced shall follow the same procedure until a point is reached where an Associate has nowhere else to bump, as they are not immediately capable and/or they do not have the seniority to bump another. At this point, said Associate will be temporary involuntarily laid off. However, Management reserves the right to retain and assign said Associate to necessary and value added work.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">Step Three &ndash; Temporary Involuntary Lay-Off</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>After the steps outlined above, any Associate that does not have a placement will be re-reviewed in an effort to place them in a position that they are immediately capable to perform from the Temporary Layoff Request Form turned in during Step One of this process.</p></li>
<li><p>From there, Associates that do not have a placement will be temporarily involuntary laid off from the Plant as noted above.</p></li></ul>
<p class="continued">Step Four &ndash; Posting</p>
<ul type="disc">
<li><p>A final posting is put up that would indicate the Associates who will be out on Temporary Layoff for the following workweek and where those Associates from the affected department(s) will be placed during the layoff period. (Jt.Ex,1).</p></li></ul>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>IV. SUMMARY POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</b></i></h4>
<h4 align="left">A. <i>UNION</i></h4>
<p>That the Company violated the LOU of the Contract by failing to recall Grievant from temporary layoff after a more senior employee was unable to perform the duties ofthe Utility A position and left work.</p>
<h4 align="left">B. <i>COMPANY</i></h4>
<p>That the Union failed to prove by a preponderance of the evidence that the Company violated a specific provision of the Contract including the LOU when it chose not to backfill the Utility A position after a more senior employee who bumped Grievant was unable to perform the duties of the job.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>V. SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE</b></i></h4>
<p><i>Todd McMahon</i> testified he has been employed by the Company for thirty-six years and also serves as a Union Steward. He served on a Union/Management committee that developed a plan to implement procedures whenever the Company announced temporary layoffs. (T.21, 22). This plan was eventually included in the Contract in 2012. (Jt.Ex.1). In December, 2014 the Company announced temporary layoffs during the weeks of January 5, 2015 and January 19, 2015. Walter Antongiorgi, an employee with more seniority than Grievant, bumped Grievant from his position as a Utility A operator in Department 13 on the first shift. (T.22-25). Grievant chose not to complete the form known as the &ldquo;Temporary LayoffJob Alternative List.&rdquo; (Co.Ex.1). By failing to do so Grievant chose not to accept a different job and accepted the one week layoff. (T.24). Grievant had sufficient seniority that he could have bumped into other first shift jobs or he could have bumped into the Utility A position on the second or third shifts. On January 5, 2015 Antongiorgi reported to work at the Utility A position in Department B but told his supervisor shortly after work began that he was unable to do the work unless he was given additional training. (T.26-28). Since the layoff was only for one week the Company sent Antongiorgi home because no training was available that week. <i>McMahon</i> found out what had occurred the next day and asked management to recall Grievant who wanted to return from layoff. (T.28,29). The Company did not recall Grievant from layoff and Grievant's Utility A position was handled all week by four Operator Support personnel in his department. (T.28-32).</p>
<p>On cross-examination <i>McMahon</i> admitted there had been at least one hundred separate temporary layoffs in the three years since the 2012 Contract. (T.35,36). The situation with Antongiorgi was the first occasion where an employee who declared himself ready and able to perform a job but was unable to do so. (T.36). He also admitted that the Company does not always recall employees on temporary layoff if another employee does not appear for work. The Company makes the decision whether another employee is needed to fill the vacancy or whether the work can be handled by existing employees in the department. (T.39-41).</p>
<p><i>Rick Beilke</i> testified he is employed as the Company's Operations Manager. He is responsible for operations and production at the Company's Burlington, Wisconsin facility. (T.60,61). In December 2014 the Company was in the process of completing a very productive year but was planning for the two week post-holiday shutdown beginning December 23, 2014. (T.63-65). The Company determined that it had four months morsel product in inventory so it determined to temporarily layoff ninety-eight employees utilizing the Temporary Layoff Procedures set out in the Contract (Jt.Ex.1). After a number of employees took voluntary layoff for the week of January 5, 2015 there still remained employees who did not accept the layoff and who chose to bump into other jobs based on their seniority. Antongiorgi bumped Grievant out of his Utility A in Department B position and Grievant was placed on temporary layoff as he chose not to complete the &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Job Alternative Form.&rdquo; (T.63-67).</p>
<p><i>David Lauf</i> testified he was the Production Supervisor at the Company's Burlington, Wisconsin facility at the relevant times herein. (T.68). He supervised Grievant in the Utility A position in Department B. There is one Utility A position on each shift. The Company also trains Support Operators who learn four positions and fill in for absent employees in that Department. (Co.Ex.2). The Support Operator performed the Utility A position on weekends. (T.68-72). Sometimes when the Utility A worker was absent Support Operators performed his duties. On January 5, 2015 Antongiorgi approached him forty-five minutes into the shift and told him he could not perform the Utility A job without additional training. Lauf determined that Support Operator personnel could perform the Utility A work for the remainder of the week. (T.72-83).</p>
<p><i>Toni Hansen</i> testified she is employed by the Company as H.R. Manager. (T.84). She explained the lengthy process involving both the Company and Union that resulted in the &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Procedures.&rdquo; (T.85-87)(Jt.Ex.1). Before the January 5, 2015 temporary layoff the Company had more than one hundred temporary layoffs in the three previous years. The layoffs for the weeks of January 5, 2015 and January 19, 2015 were scheduled more than a month earlier. (T.87-90). The Company determined 98 employees would be laid off the week of January 5, 2015. (T.91). Grievant was bumped from the first shift Utility A position by Antongiorgi. Grievant could have bumped into the Utility A position on the second or third shift or bumped into another job that week but he chose not to do so. Grievant completed the &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Job Alternative Form&rdquo; but did not list on that form any other job he would be willing to accept during that one week layoff.</p>
<p>On the morning of January 5, 2015 <i>Hansen</i> was advised of Antongiorgi's sudden inability to perform the Utility A work. She discussed the situation with Supervisor Lauf who told her that there was no need to fill the Utility A positon as the four Support Operators could perform their own duties and cover the Utility A duties. The Company has never recalled an employee from a one week temporary layoff. If she restarted the bidding process there were other employees with greater seniority than Grievant who could have bumped into the Utility A position. She determined that there was no need to recall Grievant as the four Support operator employees could cover his duties that week. (T.91-106).</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>IV. DISCUSSION AND DECISION</b></i></h4>
<p>The question to be decided by the Arbitrator in this dispute is whether the Company violated the LOU of the Contract when it denied Grievant's request to be recalled from temporary layoff. Both the Company and the Union have argued the merit of their respective positions in their excellent post-hearing briefs. The Union asks that the grievance be sustained and the Grievant made whole. The Company asks that the grievance be denied since the Union failed to prove a violation of a specific provision of the Contract.</p>
<p>The burden is upon the Union in this Contract interpretation case as its grievance seeks to interpret the Contract. The Union must prove by a preponderance of the evidence that the Company violated a specific provision of the Contract. It is the Arbitrator's duty to determine the intent of the parties as expressed in the Contract. If the disputed Contract language is clear and unambiguous, the Arbitrator will give such language its plain meaning. However, if the disputed language is reasonably susceptible to more than one meaning, the language may be considered ambiguous and the Arbitrator may choose to rely on other interpretive aids such as bargaining history or past practice of the parties.</p>
<p>The great majority of the facts in this case are undisputed. The Company employs more than 450 bargaining unit members at its plant in Burlington, Wisconsin. Because of the somewhat cyclical nature of the Company's products, the Company has frequent temporary layoffs. The Company and Union negotiated a multi-step and complex process as to how to handle temporary layoffs during the 2012 contract negotiations. The Company and Union documented this process in a Letter of Understanding (hereinafter &ldquo;LOU&rdquo;) that became part of the Contract herein (Jt.Ex.1). The Temporary Layoff Procedure permits bargaining unit members to choose for each particular week of a temporary layoff:</p>
<p>A. Whether to take a voluntary layoff or not.</p>
<p>B. If bumped out of their position by a more senior employee, whether to work in any other position or accept the temporary layoff.</p>
<p>C. If they choose to work, in what shifts and positions would they be willing and immediately capable of performing the work.</p>
<p>Seniority is respected in the temporary layoff procedure by allowing senior employees who are bumped out of their job to bump junior employees from their job. The only qualification is that the senior employee must be immediately capable of performing that job without any need of training. The senior employee who desires to bump a junior employee must complete a form entitled &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Job Alternative Test.&rdquo; This form allows the senior employee to list the jobs they wish to perform and on which shift. (Co.Ex.1). The Company and Union worked through the LOU process on more than one hundred temporary layoffs since 2012 without any problems.</p>
<p>In December, 2014, the Company announced temporary layoffs for the weeks of January 5, 2015 and January 19, 2015. The temporary layoff involved 150 employees. Grievant chose not to submit a &ldquo;Temporary Layoff Job Alternative Form&rdquo; which meant that, in the event of his layoff, he would only work his particular job on his particular shift. Grievant was bumped from his Utility A position by Walter Antongiorgi for the week of January 5, 2015. This meant that Grievant was accepting that one week layoff. When Antongiorgi began working the Utility A job on Monday, January 5, 2015 he almost immediately began having difficulties and told his supervisor that he would be unable to do the job unless he was given several days training. This was the first time since the 2012 LOU that an employee bumped into a position that he was not &ldquo;immediately capable&rdquo; of performing the job. Antongiorgi left the job and took off the entire week.</p>
<p>The Company supervisors immediately met to discuss whether the Utility A position needed to be backfilled for the remainder of the week. The Company determined that it did not need to backfill the Utility A position for several reasons. First, the Company had a four month backlog of existing inventory. Second, all the Support Operators in Grievant's department were working and fully capable of performing the duties of the Utility A position. The Support Operators handled their own duties and the duties of the Utility A operator efficiently without anyone working overtime that entire week.</p>
<p>The Union filed the grievance herein on behalf of Grievant, Ken Jenson. (Jt. Ex.2). The grievance alleged that, the Company violated the LOU by failing to recall Grievant to work the Utility A position after Antongiorgi admitted he was not ready and immediately capable to perform the job. Grievant seeks to be paid for the hours he was not recalled to work during the week of January 5, 2015. The Company denied the grievance and filed their Step One and Step Two Responses. (Jt.Exs.3,4).</p>
<p>As I stated previously the burden is upon the Union to prove that the Company violated a specific provision of the Contract. The Company and Union worked diligently to draft the LOU which became part of the Contract herein. The LOU was a good faith attempt to devise an orderly process to handle the many temporary layoffs that are caused by the seasonal nature of the Company's business. The LOU provides a detailed step by step approach which respects seniority rights wherever possible. The grievance filed herein does not claim that Grievant was improperly laid off. Rather, that Grievant should have been recalled from the temporary layoff when Antongiorgi determined that he was mistaken in his belief that he could perform the Utility A job and he left work. This scenario had never occurred in the three years since the LOU became part of the Contract.</p>
<p>It is the duty of the Arbitrator to determine the intent of the parties by interpreting the language of the Contract. In examining the language contained in the LOU, I find that there is no specific contractual language which covers the situation herein. In more than one hundred temporary layoffs since 2012 no employee who declared himself &ldquo;ready and immediately capable&rdquo; of performing a job has ever been unable to do so. Since there is no specific contractual language I may utilize interpretative aids such as bargaining history or past practice to determine the intent of the parties if there is any relevant ambiguous language in the Contract. No relevant bargaining history has been proved by the Union and there is no past practice as this situation has never occurred previously.</p>
<p>Under the circumstances, I hold that the Management Rights Clause of the Contract prevails. (Jr.Ex.1, Art.14). That provision authorizes the Company to &ldquo;determine the size and composition of the workforce&rdquo; and &ldquo;to recall employees to work.&rdquo; The Company determined that &ldquo;the size and composition of the workforce&rdquo; in Department B was capable of performing the Utility A duties the remainder of that week. The Company also determined there was no need &ldquo;to recall employees to work&rdquo; in Department B as that work could be capably handled by Support Operators. I find that the Union has failed to prove by a preponderance of the evidence that the Company violated the Contract.</p>
<h4 align="center"><i><b>VII. AWARD</b></i></h4>
<p>The grievance filed herein is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>