<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>IN THE MATTER OF THE ARBITRATION BETWEEN American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees, Council 65 and Local 94, Union and Hibbing Public Utilities Commission, Hibbing, Minnesota Employer.</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>BMS Case No. 17-PA-0142</p>
<p>February 21, 2017.</p>
<p>Janice K. Frankman, J.D., Arbitrator</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>OPINION AND AWARD</b></h4>
<h4 align="left"><b>JURISDICTION</b></h4>
<p>The hearing in this matter was held on November 29, 2016. The Arbitrator was selected to serve pursuant to the parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement and the procedures of BMS. Counsel stipulated at the hearing that the Arbitrator's jurisdiction extends to consideration of relevant statutory law and cases interpreting it. The parties were afforded a full and fair opportunity to present their cases. Joint Exhibits 1-3 and Union Exhibit 1 were received into evidence. The parties also stipulated to the receipt into the record of a notebook containing eight (8) tabs identifying various categories of documents and information. The parties submitted Post-hearing Briefs dated and posted on December 22, 2016, which were received on December 27, when the record closed and the matter was taken under advisement.</p>
<h4 align="left"><b>ISSUES</b></h4>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Did the Employer (&ldquo;Commission&rdquo; &ldquo;Utility&rdquo;) violate provisions of Minnesota State law and the parties' Collective Bargaining Agreement (&ldquo;CBA&rdquo;) when it required the Grievant to submit to random drug testing? If so, what is the remedy?</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>BACKGROUND AND SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE</b></h4>
<p>Shawn Cox (&ldquo;Grievant&rdquo; &ldquo;Cox&rdquo;) holds the position Instrument/Results Technician in the Commission's Instrumentation/Results Department. He is President of the Union Local. On March 23, 2016, he was asked to participate in a Random Drug &amp; Alcohol Testing Program, which had become effective on January 1, 2015. He submitted to the testing and filed this Grievance, claiming violation of State law.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>The Commission</i></h4>
<p>The Commission is the decision making body of the Hibbing Public Utilities which was established in 1895. It oversees all projects and programs, reviews and approves budget and determines Utility projects. &ldquo;(The Utility) owns and operates a cogenerating power plant which provides both steam and electricity for distribution to (its) service area. The Utility also furnishes water and natural gas services to the City of Hibbing proper.&rdquo; <i>www.hpuc.com/about</i> at &ldquo;Hibbing PUC&rdquo; tab. An additional page at the same tab details each of the four product services, describing customers and the areas served, building facilities, distribution systems, product sources, source relationships, equipment, capacity, and product and service usage.</p>
<p>The Utility is a highly regulated entity. Many employees are required to have specialized training and education and to hold licenses or certification in their areas of expertise. In its operation, the Utility is required to comply with rules and regulations promulgated by a number of federal and state agencies which focus on health and safety concerns.</p>
<p>Peter Karakash is Safety and Environmental Coordinator for the Utility. He developed the HPU Safety Sensitive Job Tasks page detailed below at page 6. In his testimony at hearing, he referred to DOT Office of Pipeline Safety Part 199 regulations with regard to a mandated drug testing program.</p>
<p>The Grievant's Job Description is detailed below at pages 6-8. Testimony offered by the Utility addressed his work and the importance of it relative to health and safety issues and concerns which apply to him, his co-workers and the community the Utility serves.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>The Parties' Relationship; CBA and Policy</i></h4>
<p>The parties' current CBA became effective on January 1, 2015, extending through December 31, 2017. Negotiation of the Contract terms began in 2014. The Grievant was a part of the negotiating team. He did not vote in support of the Contract when it was put to a Union vote. The Contract contains a new provision at Article XV, Section 14 which directs establishment of a random drug testing program and expansion of the Commission's Policy Number EMPL114 Non-Mandated Drug &amp; Alcohol-Free Workplace Policy for Minnesota. The new Contract provision and relevant Policy provisions follow:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><b>Section 14. RANDOM DRUG TESTING</b></p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">HPUC will establish a random drug testing program, in addition to the Drug and alcohol Free Workplace Policy (EMPL114). <i>All employees, union and management, will be included in this random drug testing program</i>. An outside firm will administer the program, informing HPUC staff of those employees who have been selected for random drug testing. All other aspects of the random drug testing program will conform to the Drug and Alcohol Free Workplace Policy EMPL114). (emphasis added)</p></blockquote>
<p align="right">Joint Exhibit 1, page 28</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Drug and Alcohol Testing</b></p>
<p class="continued">HPUC will conduct drug and alcohol testing of job applicants and employees in order to achieve a safe and productive work environment. The Company will conduct such testing within the parameters of any applicable state and federal laws..&hellip;</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Definitions</b></p>
<p align="center"><b>&ast;&ast;&ast;</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Safety&ndash;sensitive position</b>&mdash;-means a job, including supervisory or management position, in which impairment caused by drug or alcohol usage, would threaten the health or safety of any person. <i>HPUC has determined that all positions at the utility are comprised of safety sensitive functions</i>.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Types of Testing</b></p>
<p class="continued">The types of testing performed by HPUC include, but are not limited to, the following:</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Pre-Employment Drug Testing</b></p>
<p align="center"><b>&ast;&ast;&ast;</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Reasonable Suspicion Drug and Alcohol Testing</b></p>
<p align="center"><b>&ast;&ast;&ast;</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Random Drug and Alcohol Testing</b></p>
<p class="continued">Employees in safety-sensitive positons will be subject to random, unannounced drug and alcohol testing. Employees subject to random testing will have an equal probability of being neutrally selected for such testing. HPUC does not have the right to waive the selection of any employee who has been randomly chosen.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>Treatment Program Testing (Follow-up Testing)</b></p>
<p align="center"><b>&ast;&ast;&ast;</b></p>
<p class="continued"><b>Reservation of Rights</b></p>
<p class="continued">HPUC reserves the right to administer this policy and interpret, change, or rescind the policy in whole or in part with consent of the collective bargaining agreement. In addition, changes to applicable state and federal laws or regulations may require HPUC to modify or supplement the policy without notice. HPUC reserves the right to apply the amended requirements immediately; however HPUC will make every effort upon receipt of changes to send a written notification of changes to all employees.</p>
<p align="right">Joint Exhibit 2, pages 6, 8-10 and 15</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><i>Grievance; Grievance Procedure</i></h4>
<p>Cox was directed to report for drug and alcohol testing on March 23, 2016. He complied, and all testing was negative. On April 11, 2016, he filed this Grievance:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><b>STATEMENT OF GRIEVANCE:</b></p>
<p class="continued"><i>List applicable violation</i>: On Wed. March 23 I was asked to participate in the random Drug &amp; Alcohol testing program according to Article XV Section 14of our current bargaining agreement and Policy EMPL057 anti drug alcohol. The action violates the attached State Statutes for Minnesota that I have included and all other applicable language in the current Bargaining Agreement and or Policies.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Adjustment required</i>: To follow the law defined by the State statutes attached and make the employee whole in all respects.</p>
<p align="right">Union Exhibit 1</p></blockquote>
<p>The Grievance was denied at Step 1 by Cox' supervisor, Bob Nyberg, Director of Power Production: &ldquo;Grievance denied. Article XV Section 14 of current agreement to allow HPUC to do random drug testing.&rdquo; <i>id</i>. A Step 2 denial was issued on April 8, 2016, by Scott Hautala, General Manager: &ldquo;To be discussed at future meeting with Mark Mandich.&rdquo; <i>id</i>.</p>
<p>Correspondence was exchanged between the parties beginning on April 4, 2016, when Union Counsel Teresa Joppa wrote to Hautala citing several Minnesota State Statutory provisions in support of her assertion that the Utility's Drug and Alcohol Testing Policy violates state law. Specifically, she cited Minn. Stat. &sect;&sect;181.951 Subds. 1 and 4; 181.950, subd.13; and 181.955<ftnote num="1"><para>All relevant provisions of Minn. Stat. Chapter 181 are cited and quoted below at pages 9 and 10.</para></ftnote> concluding that only safety sensitive positions can legally be subject to random drug testing. Her letter was followed by Hautala's Step 2 response set out just above.</p>
<p>By letter dated April 22, 2016, Hautala thanked Union member, Mark Mandich, for attending a meeting on April 15, to discuss the Grievance. He denied the Grievance and referred the Union to its right to appeal his denial. He concluded that Cox performed safety sensitive job duties and therefore was included in the drug testing program:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">The Instrumentation and Results Technician performs &lsquo;safety&ndash;sensitive&rsquo; job duties, including &ndash; but not limited to &ndash; installing/repairing/calibrating high temperature/pressure instrumentation and controls; uses hazardous materials such as calibration gases; works with electrical systems; and operates a HPU-supplied vehicle on public roads. A failure in any of these areas is likely to cause real risk of harm to the employee or to others if the Technician was impaired.</p>
<p align="right"><i>See</i>, Grievance Documents tab</p></blockquote>
<p>By letter dated May 26, 2016, captioned &ldquo;Step 5 &ndash; Impartial Arbitration of Grievances related to Random Drug Testing&rdquo;, Joppa advised Hautala that the Union was &ldquo;appealing the grievances concerning random drug testing&rdquo;. A Form directed to the Bureau of Mediation Services dated the same date identified the &ldquo;Nature of the Dispute&rdquo;, &ldquo;Union is grieving &lsquo;Random Drug Testing&rsquo; policy &plus; testing of non-safety sensitive personnel&rdquo;.</p>
<p>By letter dated June 1, 2016, Commission Counsel Andy Borland responded to Joppa advising that the Commission would agree to Step 4 Non-binding Mediation noting that there had not been agreement to skip the Step and inquiring whether she preferred to submit a Petition for Mediation Services to BMS. Her Joint Petition dated 6-10-2016 set out the nature of the dispute and unresolved issues:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Union grieved Employer policy which allows for Random Drug Testing of <i>All</i> Employees which Union claims violates State Statute/Employer tested employee on a random basis under policy &plus; Union grieved that drug/alc. test is not allowed by Statute &ndash; Statute requires exhaustion of all remedies before other legal challenges&rdquo; <i>id</i>.</p></blockquote>
<p>By letter dated August 26, 2016, Joppa wrote to Borland and Hautala with regard to selection of an arbitrator:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="continued">..&hellip; The statute regarding remedies specifically names grievances and arbitration as a step before going to court over a violation of the statue if there is a collective bargaining agreement in place.</p>
<p class="continued">I remain hopeful that the PUC will work with us to identify which jobs actually are &lsquo;safety sensitive&rsquo; and which are not but until then we need to continue on with this process<fill character="floating-rule" width="10"/> <i>id</i>.</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><i>Safety Sensitive Job Tasks; HPUC Union Positions</i></h4>
<p>As noted above, Peter Karakash, prepared a graph captioned &ldquo;HPU Safety Sensitive Job Tasks&rdquo; which identifies thirty (30) positions held by 81 union employees. A line for each position sets out which of the eight identified job tasks applies to the employee or employees in a particular position. The job tasks include, &ldquo;Drives Company Vehicles&rdquo;, Operates Turbines or Boilers&rdquo;, &ldquo;Works in Proximity of Conveyers and/or Mechanical Equipment&rdquo;, &ldquo;Works in Proximity of Exposed Electrical (&plus;50v)&rdquo;, &ldquo;Operates Heavy Equipment, Aerial Lifts or Forklifts in Proximity of Others&rdquo;, &ldquo;Manually Handles Hazardous Chemicals&rdquo;, &ldquo;Authorized and involved in Switching/Tagging, LOTO and/or Confined Space Entry&rdquo; and &ldquo;Operates Overhead Cranes or Hoists&rdquo;.</p>
<p>All positions include the task &ldquo;Drives Company Vehicles&rdquo;. The first four (4) positions (cashiers, billing specialist, and service clerk) which include five (5) employees do not include any of the other seven identified tasks.</p>
<p>The Grievant is one of three employees identified in the &ldquo;Instrumentation&rdquo; class. Tasks identified for the class include &ldquo;Drives Company Vehicles&rdquo;, &ldquo;Works in Proximity of Conveyors and/or Mechanical Equipment&rdquo;, &ldquo;Works in Proximity of Exposed Electrical (&plus;50v)&rdquo; and &ldquo;Authorized and involved In Switching/Tagging, LOTO and/or Confined Space Entry&rdquo;. His supervisors include the Instrument Foreman and the Director of Engineering. A detailed Job Description sets out his Primary Function(s), Equipment, Unusual Job Conditions and Working Procedure(s). Particularly relevant provisions follow:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><i>Primary Function</i>: Installs, repairs, and adjusts recording, regulatory, and control instruments such as pressure, flow, and combustion meters and gauges; protective relaying; troubleshooting; and repair of communication systems, SCADA systems, CEM and COM systems, Data Acquisition Systems (DAS), DELTA V Distributive control Systems (DCS) and Programmable Logic Control (PLC) systems, Reverse osmosis (RO) water treatment systems. <i>Responsible for compliance with all OSHA, Utility, and regulatory agency safety regulations and requirements as applicable to the duties of the job</i>. (emphasis added)</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Equipment</i>: Test instruments; meters; electronic and pneumatic devices; soldering equipment; pneumatic, hand, and power tools; pipe wrenches; printed circuits; ladder; computer equipment; laptop and hand held instrument communicators and associated communication networks and cables.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Unusual Job Conditions</i>: Dirt, noise, heat, cold, dampness. Climbs stacks year round for calibration and maintenance of CEMS and COMS equipment, enter manholes and tunnels year round in all weather conditions to calibrate, troubleshoot and repair various instruments utility wide.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Working Procedure</i>:</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued">4. Inspects, installs, maintains and repair pressure gauges, temperature recorders, dial thermometers, recorders, combustion controls, regulators, electronic circuitry, printed circuits, analyzers and flow meter system for the water, gas, steam, electric, plant, and distribution. Understanding and knowledge of various systems in each utility department including Power Plant, Steam Distribution, Gas, Water plant, and Electrical Generation is required to repair and troubleshoot systems utility wide.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued">6. Calibrates instruments and gauges. Checks operating reports for inconsistencies and checks instruments. Analyzes operating logs and charts to determine efficiency and reliability of instruments. Understand and utilize Microsoft Excel software to Program and Compile reports including the monthly Plant Report and LEA operations report.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued">8. Maintains SCADA system, programmable logic controllers (PLCs), Distributive Control Systems (DCS), telephone equipment, electronic protective relaying systems, water treatment systems.</p>
<p class="continued">9. Maintains, calibrates, and repairs CEM and COM equipment and makes necessary adjustments to ensure compliance with the Title V Air Quality Permit.</p>
<p class="continued">10. Understands, maintains, and repairs distributive control systems (DCS) and uses it as a toll to diagnose and repair process control problems. Understands and can modify and/or program process control loops and parameters within the Delta V VCS control system. Can troubleshoot and repair communications problems between the Delta V system and various PLC controllers that provide data to it.</p>
<p class="continued">11. Understand the controls and theory of operation for the Reverse Osmosis water treatment system. Troubleshoot and repair R.O. system control problems.</p>
<p class="continued">12. Calibrate and Maintain records for Personal Air Monitors used by all crews as part of the safety program for confined space entry. Maintain the calibration equipment to ensure proper calibrations can be performed as required.</p>
<p class="continued">13. Perform office alarm system testing on a periodic basis as required.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p align="right">Joint Exhibit 3</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><i>Union Case</i></h4>
<p>Union testimony offered in support of this Grievance, was provided by the Grievant; Mark Reger, Meter Tech Foreman and former Union President; and by Jeffrey Stokes, on rebuttal. Stokes has been Instrument Foreman since 2007. He supervises Cox and one new apprentice. Each of them described their work, and contended that theirs are not safety sensitive positions.</p>
<p>Cox testified that he never works on machines which are in operation. He characterized his work as a reporter or recorder, who compiles data and prepares reports, monitors equipment and acts as a problem solver, directing others who perform maintenance and problem-solving tasks.</p>
<p>Stokes described the proprietary rights which the equipment vendors hold, and that the Utility buys &ldquo;service bank hours&rdquo; from them. He testified, &ldquo;The way I run the department, I will not do anything involving operational changes.&rdquo; Stokes also discussed earlier classification as &ldquo;safety sensitive&rdquo; under Pipeline Safety requirements which was withdrawn following State inspection.</p>
<p>The three Union witnesses were three of the five employees on the Union negotiation team for the current CBA. They each provided some description of the negotiation with regard to the random drug testing provision. None of them had read the law. They described conversation concerning employees who they believed were targeted for drug testing, referring to the opportunity for &ldquo;reasonable suspicion&rdquo; testing and the perceived resistance of individuals to &ldquo;sign their name&rdquo; to a complaint against an employee. They believe that the random testing provision, applied to <i>all</i> employees, addressed the issue so that no one needed to take personal responsibility for an employee being directed to testing.</p>
<p>Stokes, in particular, described the negotiations about the drug testing provision. He recalled companies coming in to explain drug testing and procedure on three occasions. He could not recall whether the Contract language which was adopted by Union vote was the same throughout the negotiations. He testified that wage and drug testing issues were focal points during the Contract negotiations and that he, like Cox, &ldquo;did not vote for the CBA because of the drug testing issue and others&rdquo;.</p>
<h4 align="left"><i>Relevant Provisions of State Law; Interpretation</i></h4>
<p>The Minnesota Drug and Alcohol Testing in the Workplace Act (&ldquo;DATWA&rdquo;) was enacted in 1987. Limited amendments to the Law have been adopted, most recently in 2011. A Federal court decision resulted in pre-emption of two provisions in 1990, and other federal and state court cases have considered issues and provided some interpretation relevant to this case. The Law sets out &ldquo;Definitions&rdquo;, and addresses &ldquo;Authorized Drug and Alcohol Testing&rdquo;, &ldquo;Policy Contents; Prior Written Notice&rdquo;, &ldquo;Reliability and Fairness Safeguards, Privacy&rdquo;, &ldquo;Confidentiality, and Privilege Safeguards&rdquo;, &ldquo;Construction&rdquo;, &ldquo;Remedies&rdquo; and &ldquo;Federal Preemption&rdquo;. Relevant portions of those provisions follow:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued"><b>181.950 DEFINITIONS</b></p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p>Subd. 11. <b>Random selection basis.</b> &ldquo;Random selection basis&rdquo; means a mechanism for selection of employees that (1) results in an equal probability that any employee from a group of employees subject to the selection mechanism will be selected and (2) does not give an employer discretion to waive the selection of any employee selected under the mechanism.</p>
<p>Subd. 12. <b>Reasonable suspicion.</b> &lsquo;Reasonable suspicion&rsquo; means a basis for forming a belief based on specific facts and rational inferences drawn from those facts.</p>
<p>Subd. 13. <b>Safety-sensitive position.</b> &lsquo;Safety-sensitive position&rsquo; means a job, including <i>any</i> supervisory or management position, in which an impairment caused by drug or alcohol usage would threaten the health or safety of <i>any</i> person.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>181.951 AUTHORIZED DRUG AND ALCOHOL TESTING.</b></p>
<p>Subd. 1. <b>Limitations on testing.</b> (a) An employer may not request or require an employee or job applicant to undergo drug and alcohol testing <i>except</i> as authorized in this section. (emphasis added)</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p>Subd. 4. <b>Random testing.</b> An employer may request or require employees to undergo drug and alcohol testing on a random selection basis only if (1) they are employed in safety-sensitive positions, or (2) they are employed as professional athletes if the professional athlete is subject to a collective bargaining agreement permitting random testing but only to the extent consistent with the collective bargaining agreement.</p>
<p class="continued"><b>181.952 POLICY CONTENTS; PRIOR WRITTEN NOTICE.</b></p>
<p>Subdivision 1. <b>Contents of the policy.</b> An employer's drug and alcohol testing policy must, at a minimum, set forth the following information:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">(1) The employees or job applicants subject to testing under the policy;</p></blockquote>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>181.955 CONSTRUCTION.</b></p>
<p>Subdivision 1. <b>Freedom to collectively bargain.</b> Sections 181.950 to 181.954 shall not be construed to limit the parties to a collective bargaining agreement from bargaining and agreeing with respect to a drug and alcohol testing policy <i>that meets or exceeds, and does not otherwise conflict with, the minimum standards and requirements for employee protection provided in those sections</i>.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p class="continued"><b>181.956 REMEDIES</b></p>
<p>Subdivision 1. <b>Exhaustion.</b> An employee or collective bargaining agent may bring an action under this section only after first exhausting all applicable grievance procedures and arbitration proceeding requirements under a collective bargaining agreement; provided that, an employee's right to bring an action under this section is not affected by a decision of a collective bargaining agent not to pursue a grievance.</p>
<p align="center">&ast;&ast;&ast;</p>
<p align="right"><b>MN Statute DATWA 181.950</b> Tab</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><i>League of Minnesota Cities Information Memo</i></h4>
<p>A <b>Drug and Alcohol Testing Toolkit for the City Workplace</b> was provided by the League of Cities on 11/18/2016. In an &ldquo;Overview of federal and state drug testing laws&rdquo;, the League Memo states:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Minnesota's 1987 Drug and Alcohol Testing in the Workplace Act (DATWA) applies to all employers, including cities, with one or more employee. DATWA does not require drug and alcohol testing, but for cities choosing to test, the law governs drug and alcohol testing of employees in the workplace, outlining specifically when, where, and under what circumstances an employer can test non-DOT employees for alcohol or drugs. A city choosing to conduct drug and alcohol testing on non-DOT employees will follow the procedures outlined in state law.</p>
<p align="right"><b>LMC Guide to Drug/AlchTesting 2016</b> tab at page 1</p></blockquote>
<p>In discussing the requirements of any policy adopted under the Law, the League Memo cited to <i>Law Enforcement Labor Services Inc., Local No. 158 et al and Sherburne County et al</i>, 695 N.W. 2d 630 (Minn. Ct. App. 2005) and concluded as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Employers do not have a duty to bargain over the <i>establishment</i> of drug and alcohol testing policies; they do, however, have a duty to bargain over the <i>implementation</i> of such policies. <i>The Minnesota Court of Appeals clarified that the decision whether to establish or amend a random drug testing policy for employees is an inherent managerial right and, thus, is not subject to mandatory bargaining</i>. In addition, the decision to test some categories of employees, <i>such as those in safety-sensitive positions</i>, is inseparable from the establishment of the policy and, therefore, is also not subject to bargaining. <i>But the implementation of the policy (for example, amending a policy that previously allowed only for-cause testing to include random testing) is subject to bargaining</i>. id. at page 7 (emphasis added)</p></blockquote>
<h4 align="left"><b>OPINION AND FINDINGS</b></h4>
<p>This is a unique case, arising from inclusion of a provision in the parties' current CBA which calls for establishment of a new provision in an existing alcohol and drug testing policy. Although the provision establishing random alcohol and drug testing had been the subject of collective bargaining, this Grievance was filed, alleging that the provision is illegal and therefore unenforceable. The Union's case centers around the Commission's unilateral identification of <i>all</i> employees, including managers and supervisors, as &ldquo;safety sensitive&rdquo; employees. It disputes the individual Grievant's inclusion in the group, and has argued that he filed the Grievance on behalf of the bargaining unit as a class action, seeking damages where appropriate and findings as to which employees are properly identified as holders of &ldquo;safety sensitive&rdquo; positions.</p>
<p>The Law requires that any random testing policy expressly apply <i>only</i> to employees who hold safety sensitive positions. It provides a broad definition of a &ldquo;safety sensitive position&rdquo; as <i>any</i> job or position &ldquo;in which an impairment caused by drug or alcohol usage would threaten the health or safety of <i>any</i> person.&rdquo; Minn. Stat.&sect;181.950, Subd. 13 (emphasis added) The Law does not address position titles or job descriptions or identify industries within which &ldquo;safety sensitive&rdquo; positions are typically or often found. It does not suggest the nature of or manner in which the health or safety of any person may be threatened.</p>
<p>The Union has failed to sustain its burden of proof. It has failed to demonstrate that this grievance was properly raised as a class action matter; that the Grievant is not properly included as an employee in a safety sensitive position; or that the random drug testing policy violates state law and is, therefore, unenforceable.</p>
<p>This Grievance was filed by and for the individual Grievant after he was directed to report for random alcohol and drug testing, 15 months after the Contract provision, and Policy provisions which followed, became effective. Due process applies to both parties. Throughout the grievance process and this hearing, the Commission was focused on the Cox Grievance as filed. Perfecting a class action grievance is not simply a matter of checking the proper box on a grievance form. It requires a clear statement of the grievance that identifies how and why the entire bargaining unit is impacted; the basis and support for the grievance as set out in the parties' CBA; and an implementable remedy to address the issues raised by the grievance.</p>
<p>It is undisputed that the plainly written Contract provision which Cox challenged was the subject of negotiation. Limited and unpersuasive detail was provided with regard to the parties' bargaining positions, and the nature of their negotiations. The parties plainly disagree, notwithstanding the Grievant's detailed job description, that his is a &ldquo;safety sensitive&rdquo; position. By all appearances, including his position description and party testimony provided at hearing, and common knowledge of the work and service provided by a public utility, there is clear support for the conclusion that Cox' highly responsible position is closely linked to the health and safety of any person with whom he works and of any person for whom the Utility provides service. He is clearly and properly subject to his employer's chosen random drug testing policy.</p>
<p>Finally, the evidence does not support a conclusion that the Commission's actions exceed what is ultimately and properly recognized as inherent managerial policy in establishing this random drug policy, including identification of <i>all</i> employees as holding &ldquo;safety sensitive&rdquo; jobs. The Union's full participation in collective bargaining and its vote approving the Contract on behalf of all of its members precludes the Grievant's challenge to the drug policy's validity or enforceability. There is no support for a conclusion that the random drug testing provision is illegal because it includes what the Union would characterize to be a fatal flaw, rendering it unenforceable as a part of the CBA.</p>
<p>There was considerable discussion at the opening of this hearing with regard to the Arbitrator's jurisdiction, created by the parties' CBA and extended by stipulation. Express authority has been provided, and it has been appropriate to review and consider provisions of Minnesota law which apply to random drug testing, and to collective bargaining in the public sector. Likewise, close review of reported court cases and relevant articles included in the hearing record which interpret the law, has been appropriate and informative in reaching this decision. The Minnesota Court of Appeals case, cited and highlighted in League of Minnesota Cities' materials, as set out above at page 11, provides analysis relevant to this case. In resolving the myriad of claims made by the Union in the <i>LELS</i> case, the Court addressed important issues raised by the facts in this case. <i>LELS</i> serves as a useful primer in labor cases raised under DATWA.</p>
<p>Significantly, DATWA distinguishes cases involving an organized workplace. The manner in which a dispute arises in a labor case directs the analysis and, as in this case, is likely to be determinative of the outcome. Threshold issues raised in <i>LELS</i> are not a part of this case. Here the Union accepted the provision in question following negotiation. With focus on the issue of the identification of &ldquo;safety sensitive positions&rdquo;, the following analysis, with citations omitted, by the <i>LELS</i> court is particularly meaningful:</p>
<blockquote><p class="continued">Because the county is a public employer, we consider the application of the Workplace Testing Act in this case under the requirements for collective bargaining imposed by PELRA. Under PELRA, public employers are not required to negotiate over &lsquo;matters of inherent managerial policy.&rsquo; Such matters include discretionary or policy matters such as an employer's functions or programs, budget, technology use, organizational structure, and selection, direction and numbers of personnel. But PELRA imposes on a public employer the &lsquo;obligation to meet and negotiate in good faith regarding grievance procedures and the terms and conditions of employment.&rsquo;</p>
<p class="continued">The Minnesota Supreme Court has recognized that in some close cases.. &lsquo;inherent managerial policy&rsquo; overlaps with &lsquo;terms and conditions of employment.&rsquo; In these cases, &lsquo;&lsqb;i&rsqb;f the policy decision is so intrinsically interwoven with its implementation that to require the public employer to negotiate its implementation would also force it to negotiate the underlying policy decision, no negotiation is required.&rsquo; In cases where there is such an overlap, a two-step process is required: first, the court must determine whether the policy has an impact on &lsquo;terms and conditions of employment,&rsquo; and second, if it does, the court must ascertain whether the policy's establishment is separate and distinct from its implementation.</p>
<p class="continued">If the establishment and the implementation are not separate and distinct, implementation is not subject to mandatory bargaining. But if establishment and implementation are separate and distinct, implementation is subject to bargaining <fill character="floating-rule" width="10"/></p>
<p class="continued">As we have noted, <i>the Workplace Testing Act authorizes an employer to &lsquo;request or require&rsquo; drug and alcohol testing, and further authorizes the employer, subject to certain limits, to request or require' random drug testing</i>. If the language authorizing testing has any meaning, in our view it must at least refer to an employer's right to establish a random drug-testing policy, or else it has no meaning.</p>
<p class="continued">In a similar vein, we note that the Union, <fill character="floating-rule" width="10"/> does acknowledge that <i>the Workplace Testing Act protects &lsquo;an employers' &lsqb;sic&rsqb; right to choose whether to test.&rsquo;</i><fill character="floating-rule" width="10"/> (emphasis added)</p>
<p class="continued">Consequently, <i>we conclude that the district court did not err in its implicit ruling that the county's decision to establish a random drug-testing policy is an inherent managerial right</i>. (emphasis added) This conclusion leads to the next step in the analysis: Does the decision have an impact on the terms and conditions of employment? On this issue we agree with the district court's finding that &lsquo;&lsqb;t&rsqb;he random drug testing policy has an impact on the union members' terms and conditions of employment, because members would be subject to a change of duties, discipline, and possible dismissal.&rsquo;</p>
<p class="continued">The final step in this analysis is to determine whether the establishment of the policy &hellip; is inseparable from the policy's implementation, so that neither the establishment nor the implementation of the policy is subject to collective bargaining. On this issue, we look first to that part of the policy designating certain categories of employees as &lsquo;safety sensitive&rsquo; and thus subject to testing. The Workplace Testing Act specifically authorizes testing of employees in &lsquo;safety-sensitive&rsquo; positions,. . &hellip; and defines those positions . . &hellip; The county's policy identifies the following categories of employees as safety sensitive:<fill character="floating-rule" width="10"/> This provision sufficiently describes the scope of positions subject to testing, and there can be no serious question that all the positions on the county's list are those with duties that implicate the public safety and health. <i>In our view, to require the county to bargain on the issue of which positions are safety sensitive would &lsquo;likely hamper the establishment of the policy.&rsquo; We conclude, therefore, that designation of which positions are safety sensitive, and thus subject to the policy, is so interwoven with the establishment of the policy that to force the county to negotiate the issue of designation would be to force the county to negotiate the underlying policy. We further conclude although designating which positions are safety sensitive may be part of implementing the policy, the county is not required to negotiate on that issue</i>. (emphasis added)</p>
<p class="continued">We disagree, however, with the district court's conclusion that, as a matter of law, none of the aspects of the policy's implementation is severable from its establishment, The plain language of (the law) permits the parties to bargain concerning a policy that &lsquo;meets or exceeds' the minimum standards for employee protection specified in the Workplace Testing Act. This is consistent with legislative policy that provision of the Workplace Testing Act were intended to provide a level of minimum mandated protection for employees affected by random drug testing<fill character="floating-rule" width="10"/></p>
<p class="continued">Although it is not the province of the courts to suggest which areas are subject to collective bargaining, we agree with the union that such areas exist. Therefore, we conclude that the district court erred in determining that the parties had no obligation to meet and negotiate concerning those areas of implementation of the county's random drug-testing policy.</p>
<p class="continued"><i>Law Enforcement Labor Services Inc. 158 et al</i> v. <i>Sherburne County, et al</i>, 695 N.W.2d 630 (Minn. Ct. App. 2005)</p></blockquote>
<p>This case was broadly cast by the Union and narrowly decided on the facts. Consequently, the foregoing analysis has been provided to illuminate the process taken in deciding this case.</p>
<h4 align="center"><b>AWARD</b></h4>
<p>Consistent with the foregoing Opinion and Findings, this Grievance is denied.</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>
