<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ruling SYSTEM "file://nastntx95001/common/config/dtd/group-xml.dtd">
<ruling content-area="HHR\ARB" num="" normval="" pub="" root="" cchwin-doctype="" node-type="document">
<ruling-text content-area="HHR\ARB">
<html>
<head><title></title></head>
<body>
<p>In the Matter of Arbitration Between City of Bridgeport And NAGE Local R1-200</p>
<p>Arbitration Case</p>
<p>Case No. 2014-A-0555</p>
<p>Award Date: December 13, 2016.</p>
<h4 align="left">ISSUE</h4>
<p>The parties agreed to let the panel frame the issue. The issue is &ldquo;what shall be the disposition of the grievance.&rdquo;</p>
<h4 align="left">RELEVANT CONTRACT LANGUAGE</h4>
<p class="continued">12.7 Employees required to work in a higher classification than their normal classification shall be paid the rate of the higher classification for that period of time.</p>
<h4 align="left">FACTS</h4>
<p>This arbitration concerns a grievance filed on behalf of custodian Troy Clemons asserting that grievant worked beyond the scope of his Custodian II duties as a Custodian IV. The city denied the grievance which led to this proceeding.</p>
<p>The time frame of this grievance is September 12, 2012 through June 14, 2016. The former date is when grievant was transferred to the city's Aquaculture school and the later date is the last day before grievant's promotion to Custodian IV and transfer to another city school. The union seeks not a promotion to Custodian IV during this time frame, but compensation as a Custodian IV.</p>
<p>Job descriptions state the duties of the four levels of custodian. The duties that are characteristic of each of the four levels are stated the same: &ldquo;Custodial and limited supervisory work of ordinary difficulty and responsibility in the cleaning, care and maintenance of a public building; related work as required; performed under general supervision.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The job descriptions also state the typical tasks and assignments of the custodian levels. Tasks of a Custodian II involve &ldquo;responsibility for custodial care and minor maintenance of a public building of such size as to require custodial help and require supervision thereof, involving one or two janitresses&hellip;or without complete custodial responsibility, assumes some minor secondary, supervisory responsibility in acting as assistant to a custodial supervisor.&rdquo; The Custodian II &ldquo;in the care of a school of this class is limited to a maximum of nineteen rooms.&rdquo; The Custodian III has the same tasks as a Custodian II except that &ldquo;in the care of a school this class of custodial worker is limited to a maximum of nineteen rooms, minimum of ten.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Custodian IV statement of tasks expands on those of Custodian III. &ldquo;Has immediate supervision of the same general level as a Custodian III except that supervision may involve one to three janitresses&hellip;and large buildings, (20 or more rooms with respect to schools) normally entailing greater knowledge and experience with respect to size and complexity of equipment and facilities.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Grievant worked at the Aquaculture school with acting Custodian IV Benny Hatchett. Grievant's work at the Aquaculture school included some duties not done at other schools such as cleaning the fish market. Grievant's duties also included opening and closing the school. Grievant complains that he was responsible for cleaning the entire school building and that Hatchett helped grievant only by cleaning the two easiest classrooms. Grievant, however, concedes that Hatchett did do his job.</p>
<p>Acting director of facilities and building operations Robert Hammond testified as to the custodial duties and work done at Aquaculture school. Hatchett as acting Custodian IV served as the liaison with the school's administrative staff including the principal and assistant principal. Grievant's duties did not include supervision. Grievant's opening and closing of the school is also done by Custodian II staff at other schools. Grievant's duties did not include the maintenance of the specialized equipment at the Aquaculture school.</p>
<p>Hammond also testified regarding the job description limitations as to the number of rooms. The Dunbar school, for example, has twenty rooms, but not all custodians there are Custodian IV. A Custodian IV at Dunbar provides supervision. Grievant at Aquaculture school was responsible on a daily basis for sixteen or seventeen rooms including twelve classrooms, two or three conference rooms, one work shop, and one hatchery. Not all rooms at Aquaculture school, unlike other schools, are used or need to be cleaned on a daily basis, although grievant's work involved all of the school's rooms.</p>
<p>Grievant was paid for part of the period of time at issue as a Custodian IV when Hatchett was absent including one period due to knee surgery. Grievant filled in for Hatchett during these times and worked alone at Aquaculture school. Grievant was paid at the Custodian IV rate for all hours worked including the overtime hours.</p>
<h4 align="left">POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES</h4>
<p>The union maintains that the quantity and nature of the work grievant performed are beyond that of a Custodian II and consistent with that of a Custodian IV. The Aquaculture school has more than nineteen rooms consistent with the Custodian IV job description.</p>
<p>The city maintains that grievant's duties and responsibilities were of a Custodian II. The Custodian II job description is consistent with grievant's work.</p>
<h4 align="left">DISCUSSION</h4>
<p>Grievant's work was consistent with that of a Custodian II by the terms of the job descriptions and the city's practice. Grievant worked under the supervision of Hatchett who acted as the custodial liaison with the school's administration. Grievant did not have supervisory responsibilities at Aquaculture school. A Custodian II works in a building that requires supervision. The Custodian II &ldquo;act&lsqb;s&rsqb; as an assistant to the custodial supervisor&rdquo; as described in the Custodian II job description. Hatchett as a Custodian IV provided that supervision. This is consistent with the city's practice at other schools.</p>
<p>The quantity of grievant's work does not support Custodian IV status. Grievant was responsible for cleaning sixteen or seventeen rooms on a daily basis consistent with the Custodian II job description. It is clear that grievant believed that he was treated unfairly by Hatchett regarding the division of work. Yet, grievant's dissatisfaction does not mean that he did the work of a Custodian IV.</p>
<p>The nature of grievant's work does not support Custodian IV status. Custodian IIs open and close other city schools. Grievant did not provide supervision. Grievant was not responsible for the maintenance of specialized equipment. The work grievant performed at Aquaculture school, while not the same as his previous assignment, was of a custodial nature consistent with the Custodian II job description.</p>
<p>Grievant's compensation at the Custodian IV level in Hatchett's absence does not support the grievance. It was reasonable both for the city to compensate grievant at Hatchett's level in Hatchett's absence and to resume grievant's compensation at the Custodian II level when Hatchett returned.</p>
<p>The union has failed to show that the contract was violated. The union has shown that grievant was unhappy with his supervisor and that some of his new duties at Aquaculture school were different from his previous assignment. This fails to show by a standard of comparison to others that the worth of grievant's work was greater than that of other Custodian IIs and equal to that of other Custodian IVs.</p>
<h4 align="left">AWARD</h4>
<p>The grievance is denied.</p>
<h4 align="left">STATE BOARD OF MEDIATION AND ARBITRATION</h4>
<p class="continued">By: <fill character="baseline-rule" width="5"/></p>
<p class="continued">Thadd A. Gnocchi, Esq.</p>
<p class="continued">Panel Chair</p>
<p class="continued">Alternate Public Member</p>
<p class="continued">By: <fill character="baseline-rule" width="5"/></p>
<p class="continued">Michael C.Culhane</p>
<p class="continued">Management Member</p>
<p class="continued">By: <fill character="baseline-rule" width="5"/></p>
<p class="continued">Richard Panagrossi</p>
<p class="continued">Alternate Labor Member</p>
</body>
</html>
</ruling-text>
</ruling>